<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="SectLabel" version="110505">
<variant no="0" confidence="0.000003">
<note confidence="0.9336">
COLING 2014
</note>
<title confidence="0.9934308">
25th International Conference on
Computational Linguistics
Proceedings of the
4th Workshop on Cognitive Aspects
of the Lexicon (CogALex-IV)
</title>
<author confidence="0.64965175">
Workshop Chairs:
Michael Zock, Reinhard Rapp, Chu-Ren Huang
August 23, 2014
Dublin, Ireland
</author>
<note confidence="0.832291666666667">
© 2014 The Authors
The papers in this volume are licensed by the authors under a
Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.
ISBN 978-1-873769-33-1
Proceedings of the 4th Workshop on Cognitive Aspects of the Lexicon
(CogALex-IV)
</note>
<author confidence="0.81086">
Michael Zock, Reinhard Rapp and Chu-Ren Huang (eds.)
</author>
<page confidence="0.603536">
ii
</page>
<note confidence="0.595019">
Introduction to the 4th Workshop on Cognitive Aspects of the Lexicon
(CogALex-IV)
1 Background1
</note>
<bodyText confidence="0.999608695652174">
Starting with a workshop devoted to electronic dictionaires at COLING, Geneva, 2004 (Enhancing and
Using Electronic Dictionaries) we have continued to do so, by keeping it associated to this conference
(2008, Manchester, 2010, Beijing , 2012, Mumbai).2 What we did change though is the name, as Co-
gALex captures better our mindset, i.e. the focus from which we look at the lexicon. CogALex stands
for Cognitive Aspects of the Lexicon. Encouraged by the enthusiasm and interest expressed by the
participants of the preceding events, it was natural to come up with a follow-up workshop.
As in the past our aim is to provide a forum for computational lexicographers, researchers in NLP,
psychologists and users of lexical resources to share their knowledge and needs concerning the con-
struction, organisation and use of a lexicon by people (lexical access) and machines (NLP, IR, data-
mining). Hence we invite again researchers with diverse backgrounds to address unsolved problems (see
below). In addition we have added two features: One is devoted to a shared Task3 where the sys-tem is
meant to learn automatically how to find a word on the basis of its associated terms, the other feature is
vocabulary learning.
While vocabulary learning is understandably not a hot topic in computational linguistics, it is never-
theless an important aspect of language learning, both in the mother tongue and in a foreign language.
Having a rich stock of vocabulary is certainly an asset, but knowing the basic words and expressions is
a must. Yet, people tend to forget some of the words they (thought to) have learned. This is not just a
question of exercise (quantity vs. quality). Traditional word lists or flash cards are clearly not the ulti-
mate answer. They are not only boring, but also rarely very effective. There is so much more we could do
these days by using corpora and computational linguistics know-how, to extract the to-be learned words
from text and to display them with their context. Hence, rather than having the user repeat sin-gle words
(or word pairs) we could display them in various contexts (e.g. sentences), thereby making sure that the
chosen ones correspond to the learners’ level and interests.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.974322" genericHeader="abstract">
2 Motivation
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999287">
The way we look at dictionaries (their creation and use) has changed dramatically over the past 30
years. While being considered as an appendix to grammar in the past, by now they have moved to
centre stage. Indeed, there is hardly any task in NLP which can be conducted without them. Also,
rather than being static entities (database view), dictionaries are now viewed as dynamic networks, i.e.
graphs, whose nodes and links (connection strengths) may change over time. Interestingly, properties
concerning topology, clustering and evolution known from other disciplines (society, economy, human
brain) also apply to dictionaries: everything is linked, hence accessible, and everything is evolving. Given
these similarities, one may wonder what we can learn from these disciplines. In this 4th edition of the
CogALex workshop we therefore also invited scientists working in these fields, with the goal to broaden
the picture, i.e. to gain a better understanding concerning the mental lexicon and to integrate these
findings into our dictionaries in order to support navigation. Given recent advances in neurosciences, it
appears timely to seek inspiration from neuroscientists studying the human brain. There is also a lot to
be learned from other fields studying graphs and networks, even if their object of study is something else
than language, for example biology, economy or society.
</bodyText>
<footnote confidence="0.9999285">
1This work is licenced under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License. Page numbers and proceedings
footer are added by the organizers. License details: http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/
2Workshop proceedings: see ACL Anthology: http://aclweb.org/anthology/
3http://pageperso.lif.univ-mrs.fr/∼michael.zock/CogALex-IV/cogalex-webpage/pst.html
</footnote>
<page confidence="0.646095">
iii
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.824707" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors">
3 Topics of Interest
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999936625">
This workshop is about possible enhancements of lexical resources and electronic dictionaries. To per-
form the groundwork for the next generation of such resources we invite researchers involved in the
building of such tools. The idea is to discuss modifications of existing resources by taking the usersí
needs and knowledge states into account, and to capitalize on the advantages of the digital media. For
this workshop we solicit papers including but not limited to the following topics, each of which can
be considered from various points of view: linguistics, neuro- or psycholinguistics (tip of the tongue
problem, associations), network related sciences (sociology, economy, biology), mathematics (vector-
based approaches, graph theory, small-world problem), etc.
</bodyText>
<listItem confidence="0.991152514285714">
I) Analysis of the conceptual input of a dictionary user
• What does a language producer start from (bag of words)?
• What is in the authors’ minds when they are generating a message and looking for a word?
• What does it take to bridge the gap between this input and the desired output (target word)?
II) The meaning of words
• Lexical representation (holistic, decomposed);
• Meaning representation (concept based, primitives);
• Revelation of hidden information (distributional semantics, latent semantics, vector-based
approaches: LSA/HAL);
• Neural models, neurosemantics, neurocomputational theories of content representation.
III) Structure of the lexicon
• Discovering structures in the lexicon: formal and semantic point of view (clustering, topical
structure);
• Creative ways of getting access to and using word associations (reading between the lines,
subliminal communication);
• Evolution, i.e. dynamic aspects of the lexicon (changes of weights);
• Neural models of the mental lexicon (distribution of information concerning words, organi-sation
of words).
IV) Methods for crafting dictionaries or Indexes
• Manual, automatic or collaborative building of dictionaries and indexes (crowd-sourcing, serious
games, etc.);
• Impact and use of social networks (Facebook, Twitter) for building dictionaries, for organizing and
indexing the data (clustering of words), and for allowing to track navigational strategies, etc.;
• (Semi-) automatic induction of the link type (e.g. synonym, hypernym, meronym, association,
collocation, ...);
• Use of corpora and patterns (datamining) for getting access to words, their uses, combinations and
associations.
V) Dictionary access (navigation and search strategies) and interface issues
• Search based on sound, meaning or associations;
iv
• Search (simple query vs multiple words);
• Context-dependent search (modification of usersí goals during search);
• Recovery;
• Navigation (frequent navigational patterns or search strategies used by people);
• Interface problems, data-visualisation.
</listItem>
<bodyText confidence="0.9998814">
We received 30 submissions, of which seven were accepted as full papers, eight were accepted for poster
presentation, and nine were accepted in the context of the shared task. While we did not get papers on all
the issues mentioned in our call, we did get a quite rich panel of topics including cognitive approaches
to lexical access, considerations on word meaning and ontologies, manual and automatic approaches for
constructing lexicons, as well as pragmatic aspects. It was also interesting to see the variety of languages
in which these issues are addressed. In sum, the community working on dictionaries is dynamic, and
there seems to be a growing awareness of the importance of some of the problems presented in our call
for papers.
We would like to thank Roberto Navigli for having accepted to be our invited speaker, Shishang Wang
for proofreading, and the COLING organizers for providing the framework and for their support. We
would also like to express our sincerest thanks to all the members of the Programme Committee whose
expertise was invaluable to assure a good selection of papers, despite the tight schedule. Their reviews
were helpful not only for us to make the decisions, but also for the authors, helping them to improve
their work. In the hope that the results will inspire you, provoke fruitful discussions and result in future
collaborations.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.92493084">
Dublin, Ireland, August 2014
Michael Zock, Reinhard Rapp, Chu-Ren Huang
v
Organizers:
Michael Zock (LIF-CNRS, Marseille, France)
Reinhard Rapp (LIF, Marseille, France and University of Mainz, Germany)
Chu-Ren Huang (The Hong Kong Polytechnic University, China)
Invited Speaker:
Roberto Navigli (Sapienza, University of Rome, Italy)
Program Committee:
Bel Enguix, Gemma (LIF Marseille, France)
Chang, Jason (National Tsing Hua University, Taiwan)
Cook, Paul (University of Melbourne, Australia)
Cristea, Dan (University A.I.Cuza, Iasi, Romania)
De Deyne, Simon (Experimental Psychology, Leuven, Belgium and Adelaide, Australia)
De Melo, Gerard (IIIS, Tsinghua University, Beijing, China)
Ferret, Olivier (CEA LIST, Gif sur Yvette, France)
Fontenelle, Thierry (CDT, Luxemburg)
Gala, Nuria (LIF-CNRS, Aix Marseille University, Marseille, France)
Granger, Sylviane (Université Catholique de Louvain, Belgium)
Grefenstette, Gregory (Inria, Saclay, France)
Hirst, Graeme (University of Toronto, Canada)
Hovy, Eduard (CMU, Pittsburgh, USA)
Hsieh, Shu-Kai (National Taiwan University, Taipei, Taiwan)
Huang, Chu-Ren (Hongkong Polytechnic University, China)
</table>
<affiliation confidence="0.9094928">
Joyce, Terry (Tama University, Kanagawa-ken, Japan)
Lapalme, Guy (RALI, University of Montreal, Canada)
Lenci, Alessandro (CNR, University of Pisa, Italy)
L’Homme, Marie Claude (University of Montreal, Canada)
Mihalcea, Rada (University of Texas, USA)
Navigli, Roberto (Sapienza, University of Rome, Italy)
Pirrelli, Vito (ILC, Pisa, Italy)
Polguère, Alain (ATILF-CNRS, Nancy, France)
Rapp, Reinhard (LIF Marseille, France and University of Mainz, Germany)
Rosso, Paolo (NLEL, Universitat Politècnica de València, Spain)
Schwab, Didier (LIG-GETALP, Grenoble, France)
Serasset, Gilles (IMAG, Grenoble, France)
Sharoff, Serge (University of Leeds, UK)
Su, Jun-Ming (University of Tainan, Taiwan)
Tiberius, Carole (Institute for Dutch Lexicology, The Netherlands)
Tokunaga, Takenobu (TITECH, Tokyo, Japan)
Tufis, Dan (RACAI, Bucharest, Romania)
Valitutti, Alessandro (Helsinki Institute of Information Technology, Finland)
Wandmacher, Tonio (IRT SystemX, Saclay, France)
Zock, Michael (LIF-CNRS, Marseille, France)
</affiliation>
<page confidence="0.92115">
vii
</page>
<tableCaption confidence="0.963319">
Table of Contents
</tableCaption>
<figure confidence="0.864321267857143">
The CogALex-IV Shared Task on the Lexical Access Problem
Reinhard Rapp and Michael Zock 1
A Two-Stage Approach for Computing Associative Responses to a Set of Stimulus Words
Urmi Ghosh, Sambhav Jain and Paul Soma 15
Deep Learning from Web-Scale Corpora for Better Dictionary Interfaces
Pavel Smrz and Lubomir Otrusina 22
Exploring the use of word embeddings and random walks on Wikipedia for the CogAlex shared task
Josu Goikoetxea, Eneko Agirre and Aitor Soroa 31
ETS Lexical Associations System for the COGALEX-4 Shared Task
Michael Flor and Beata Beigman Klebanov 35
Using Significant Word Co-occurences for the Lexical Access Problem
Rico Feist, Daniel Gerighausen, Manuel Konrad, Georg Richter, Thomas Eckart, Dirk Goldhahn
and Uwe Quasthoff 46
NaDiR: Naive Distributional Response Generation
Gabriella Lapesa and Stefan Evert 50
Retrieving Word Associations with a Simple Neighborhood Algorithm in a Graph-based Resource
Gemma Bel Enguix 60
Predicting sense convergence with distributional semantics: an application to the CogaLex 2014 shared
task
Laurianne Sitbon and Lance De Vine 64
WordFinder
Catalin Mititelu and Verginica Barbu Mititelu 68
(Digital) Goodies from the ERC Wishing Well: BabelNet, Babelfy, Video Games with a Purpose and the
Wikipedia Bitaxonomy
Roberto Navigli 75
Measuring Similarity from Word Pair Matrices with Syntagmatic and Paradigmatic Associations
Jin Matsuoka and Yves Lepage 77
Jibiki-LINKS: a tool between traditional dictionaries and lexical networks for modelling lexical re-
sources
Ying Zhang, Mathieu Mangeot, Valérie Bellynck and Christian Boitet 87
When Frequency Data Meet Dispersion Data in the Extraction of Multi-word Units from a Corpus: A
Study of Trigrams in Chinese
Chan-Chia Hsu 99
Exploring Mental Lexicon in an Efficient and Economic Way: Crowdsourcing Method for Linguistic
Experiments
Shichang Wang, Chu-Ren Huang, Yao Yao and Angel Chan 105
ix
A Computational Approach to Generate a Sensorial Lexicon
Serra Sinem Tekiroglu, Gözde Özbal and Carlo Strapparava 114
Database Design of an Online E-Learning Tool of Chinese Classifiers
Helena Gao 126
Default Physical Measurements in SUMO
Francesca Quattri, Pease Adam and John P. McCrae 138
Lexical Access Preference and Constraint Strategies for Improving Multiword Expression Association
within Semantic MT Evaluation
Dekai Wu, Chi-kiu Lo and Markus Saers 144
A Lexical Network with a Morphological Model in It
Nabil Gader, Aurore Koehl and Alain Polguère 154
Dimensions of Metaphorical Meaning
Andrew Gargett, Josef Ruppenhofer and John Barnden 166
Constructing an Ontology of Japanese Lexical Properties: Specifying its Property Structures and Lexical
Entries
Terry Joyce and Bor Hodošˇcek 174
Frames and terminology: representing predicative terms in the field of the environment
Marie-Claude L’ Homme and Benoît Robichaud 186
Modelling the Semantics of Adjectives in the Ontology-Lexicon Interface
John P. McCrae, Francesca Quattri, Christina Unger and Philipp Cimiano 198
Discovering Conceptual Metaphors using Source Domain Spaces
Samira Shaikh, Tomek Strzalkowski, Kit Cho, Ting Liu, George Aaron Broadwell, Laurie Feldman,
Sarah Taylor, Boris Yamrom, Ching-Sheng Lin, Ning Sa, Ignacio Cases, Yuliya Peshkova and
Kyle Elliot 210
Wordfinding Problems and How to Overcome them Ultimately With the Help of a Computer
Michael Zock 221
x
Workshop Program
Saturday, August 23, 2014
9:00–9:05 Opening Remarks
9:05–10:30 Session 1: Shared Task on the Lexical Access Problem
The CogALex-IV Shared Task on the Lexical Access Problem
Reinhard Rapp and Michael Zock
A Two-Stage Approach for Computing Associative Responses to a Set of Stimulus
Words
Urmi Ghosh, Sambhav Jain and Paul Soma
Deep Learning from Web-Scale Corpora for Better Dictionary Interfaces
Pavel Smrz and Lubomir Otrusina
Exploring the use of word embeddings and random walks on Wikipedia for the Co-
gAlex shared task
Josu Goikoetxea, Eneko Agirre and Aitor Soroa
ETS Lexical Associations System for the COGALEX-4 Shared Task
Michael Flor and Beata Beigman Klebanov
Using Significant Word Co-occurences for the Lexical Access Problem
Rico Feist, Daniel Gerighausen, Manuel Konrad, Georg Richter, Thomas Eckart,
Dirk Goldhahn and Uwe Quasthoff
NaDiR: Naive Distributional Response Generation
Gabriella Lapesa and Stefan Evert
Retrieving Word Associations with a Simple Neighborhood Algorithm in a Graph-
based Resource
Gemma Bel Enguix
Predicting sense convergence with distributional semantics: an application to the
CogaLex 2014 shared task
Laurianne Sitbon and Lance De Vine
WordFinder
Catalin Mititelu and Verginica Barbu Mititelu
xi
Saturday, August 23, 2014 (continued)
10:30–11:00 Coffee Break
11:00–12:00 Session 2: Invited Talk
(Digital) Goodies from the ERC Wishing Well: BabelNet, Babelfy, Video Games with a
Purpose and the Wikipedia Bitaxonomy
Roberto Navigli
12:00–12:30 Session 3a: Booster Presentations for Posters
12:03–12:06 Measuring Similarity from Word Pair Matrices with Syntagmatic and Paradigmatic Asso-
ciations
Jin Matsuoka and Yves Lepage
12:06–12:09 Jibiki-LINKS: a tool between traditional dictionaries and lexical networks for modelling
lexical resources
Ying Zhang, Mathieu Mangeot, Valérie Bellynck and Christian Boitet
12:09–12:12 When Frequency Data Meet Dispersion Data in the Extraction of Multi-word Units from
a Corpus: A Study of Trigrams in Chinese
Chan-Chia Hsu
12:12–12:15 Exploring Mental Lexicon in an Efficient and Economic Way: Crowdsourcing Method for
Linguistic Experiments
</figure>
<reference confidence="0.989882088235294">
Shichang Wang, Chu-Ren Huang, Yao Yao and Angel Chan
12:15–12:18 A Computational Approach to Generate a Sensorial Lexicon
Serra Sinem Tekiroglu, Gözde Özbal and Carlo Strapparava
12:18–12:21 Database Design of an Online E-Learning Tool of Chinese Classifiers
Helena Gao
12:21–12:24 Default Physical Measurements in SUMO
Francesca Quattri, Pease Adam and John P. McCrae
12:24–12:27 Lexical Access Preference and Constraint Strategies for Improving Multiword Expression
Association within Semantic MT Evaluation
Dekai Wu, Chi-kiu Lo and Markus Saers
12:30–14:00 Lunch Break
14:00–15:00 Session 3b: Posters
xii
Saturday, August 23, 2014 (continued)
15:00–15:30 Coffee Break
15:30–17:40 Session 4: Oral Presentations
15:30–15:50 A Lexical Network with a Morphological Model in It
Nabil Gader, Aurore Koehl and Alain Polguère
15:50–16:10 Dimensions of Metaphorical Meaning
Andrew Gargett, Josef Ruppenhofer and John Barnden
16:10–16:30 Constructing an Ontology of Japanese Lexical Properties: Specifying its Property Struc-
tures and Lexical Entries
Terry Joyce and Bor Hodošˇcek
16:30–16:50 Frames and terminology: representing predicative terms in the field of the environment
Marie-Claude L’ Homme and Benoît Robichaud
16:50–17:10 Modelling the Semantics of Adjectives in the Ontology-Lexicon Interface
John P. McCrae, Francesca Quattri, Christina Unger and Philipp Cimiano
17:10–17:30 Discovering Conceptual Metaphors using Source Domain Spaces
Samira Shaikh, Tomek Strzalkowski, Kit Cho, Ting Liu, George Aaron Broadwell, Laurie
Feldman, Sarah Taylor, Boris Yamrom, Ching-Sheng Lin, Ning Sa, Ignacio Cases, Yuliya
Peshkova and Kyle Elliot
17:30–17:50 Wordfinding Problems and How to Overcome them Ultimately With the Help of a Computer
Michael Zock
17:50–18:00 Conclusions and Closing
</reference>
<page confidence="0.55603">
xiii
</page>
</variant>
</algorithm>
<algorithm name="ParsHed" version="110505">
<variant no="0" confidence="0.000000">
<note confidence="0.97900025">COLING 2014 International Conference on Computational Linguistics Proceedings of the</note>
<title confidence="0.656547666666667">on Cognitive Aspects of the Lexicon (CogALex-IV) Workshop Chairs:</title>
<author confidence="0.88505">Michael Zock</author>
<author confidence="0.88505">Reinhard Rapp</author>
<author confidence="0.88505">Chu-Ren Huang</author>
<address confidence="0.5130445">August 23, 2014 Dublin, Ireland</address>
<note confidence="0.954029166666667">The Authors The papers in this volume are licensed by the authors under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License. ISBN 978-1-873769-33-1 Proceedings of the 4th Workshop on Cognitive Aspects of the Lexicon (CogALex-IV)</note>
<author confidence="0.693457">Michael Zock</author>
<author confidence="0.693457">Reinhard Rapp</author>
<author confidence="0.693457">Chu-Ren Huang</author>
<abstract confidence="0.993202873786408">ii to the Workshop on Cognitive Aspects of the (CogALex-IV) with a workshop devoted to electronic dictionaires at COLING, Geneva, 2004 and Electronic we have continued to do so, by keeping it associated to this conference Manchester, 2010, Beijing , 2012, What we did change though is the name, as CogALex captures better our mindset, i.e. the focus from which we look at the lexicon. CogALex stands for Cognitive Aspects of the Lexicon. Encouraged by the enthusiasm and interest expressed by the participants of the preceding events, it was natural to come up with a follow-up workshop. As in the past our aim is to provide a forum for computational lexicographers, researchers in NLP, psychologists and users of lexical resources to share their knowledge and needs concerning the construction, organisation and use of a lexicon by people (lexical access) and machines (NLP, IR, datamining). Hence we invite again researchers with diverse backgrounds to address unsolved problems (see In addition we have added two features: One is devoted to a where the sys-tem is meant to learn automatically how to find a word on the basis of its associated terms, the other feature is While vocabulary learning is understandably not a hot topic in computational linguistics, it is nevertheless an important aspect of language learning, both in the mother tongue and in a foreign language. Having a rich stock of vocabulary is certainly an asset, but knowing the basic words and expressions is a must. Yet, people tend to forget some of the words they (thought to) have learned. This is not just a question of exercise (quantity vs. quality). Traditional word lists or flash cards are clearly not the ultimate answer. They are not only boring, but also rarely very effective. There is so much more we could do these days by using corpora and computational linguistics know-how, to extract the to-be learned words from text and to display them with their context. Hence, rather than having the user repeat sin-gle words (or word pairs) we could display them in various contexts (e.g. sentences), thereby making sure that the chosen ones correspond to the learners’ level and interests. 2 Motivation The way we look at dictionaries (their creation and use) has changed dramatically over the past 30 years. While being considered as an appendix to grammar in the past, by now they have moved to centre stage. Indeed, there is hardly any task in NLP which can be conducted without them. Also, rather than being static entities (database view), dictionaries are now viewed as dynamic networks, i.e. graphs, whose nodes and links (connection strengths) may change over time. Interestingly, properties concerning topology, clustering and evolution known from other disciplines (society, economy, human brain) also apply to dictionaries: everything is linked, hence accessible, and everything is evolving. Given these similarities, one may wonder what we can learn from these disciplines. In this 4th edition of the CogALex workshop we therefore also invited scientists working in these fields, with the goal to broaden the picture, i.e. to gain a better understanding concerning the mental lexicon and to integrate these findings into our dictionaries in order to support navigation. Given recent advances in neurosciences, it appears timely to seek inspiration from neuroscientists studying the human brain. There is also a lot to be learned from other fields studying graphs and networks, even if their object of study is something else than language, for example biology, economy or society. work is licenced under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License. Page numbers and proceedings footer are added by the organizers. License details: http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/ proceedings: see ACL Anthology: http://aclweb.org/anthology/ iii 3 Topics of Interest This workshop is about possible enhancements of lexical resources and electronic dictionaries. To perform the groundwork for the next generation of such resources we invite researchers involved in the building of such tools. The idea is to discuss modifications of existing resources by taking the usersí needs and knowledge states into account, and to capitalize on the advantages of the digital media. For this workshop we solicit papers including but not limited to the following topics, each of which can be considered from various points of view: linguistics, neuroor psycholinguistics (tip of the tongue problem, associations), network related sciences (sociology, economy, biology), mathematics (vectorbased approaches, graph theory, small-world problem), etc. I) Analysis of the conceptual input of a dictionary user • What does a language producer start from (bag of words)? • What is in the authors’ minds when they are generating a message and looking for a word? • What does it take to bridge the gap between this input and the desired output (target word)? II) The meaning of words • Lexical representation (holistic, decomposed); • Meaning representation (concept based, primitives); • Revelation of hidden information (distributional semantics, latent semantics, vector-based approaches: LSA/HAL); • Neural models, neurosemantics, neurocomputational theories of content representation. III) Structure of the lexicon • Discovering structures in the lexicon: formal and semantic point of view (clustering, topical structure); • Creative ways of getting access to and using word associations (reading between the lines, subliminal communication); • Evolution, i.e. dynamic aspects of the lexicon (changes of weights); • Neural models of the mental lexicon (distribution of information concerning words, organi-sation of words). IV) Methods for crafting dictionaries or Indexes • Manual, automatic or collaborative building of dictionaries and indexes (crowd-sourcing, serious games, etc.); • Impact and use of social networks (Facebook, Twitter) for building dictionaries, for organizing and indexing the data (clustering of words), and for allowing to track navigational strategies, etc.; • (Semi-) automatic induction of the link type (e.g. synonym, hypernym, meronym, association, collocation, ...); • Use of corpora and patterns (datamining) for getting access to words, their uses, combinations and associations. V) Dictionary access (navigation and search strategies) and interface issues • Search based on sound, meaning or associations; iv • Search (simple query vs multiple words); • Context-dependent search (modification of usersí goals during search); • Recovery; • Navigation (frequent navigational patterns or search strategies used by people); • Interface problems, data-visualisation. We received 30 submissions, of which seven were accepted as full papers, eight were accepted for poster presentation, and nine were accepted in the context of the shared task. While we did not get papers on all the issues mentioned in our call, we did get a quite rich panel of topics including cognitive approaches to lexical access, considerations on word meaning and ontologies, manual and automatic approaches for constructing lexicons, as well as pragmatic aspects. It was also interesting to see the variety of languages in which these issues are addressed. In sum, the community working on dictionaries is dynamic, and there seems to be a growing awareness of the importance of some of the problems presented in our call for papers. We would like to thank Roberto Navigli for having accepted to be our invited speaker, Shishang Wang for proofreading, and the COLING organizers for providing the framework and for their support. We would also like to express our sincerest thanks to all the members of the Programme Committee whose expertise was invaluable to assure a good selection of papers, despite the tight schedule. Their reviews were helpful not only for us to make the decisions, but also for the authors, helping them to improve their work. In the hope that the results will inspire you, provoke fruitful discussions and result in future collaborations.</abstract>
<address confidence="0.579804">Dublin, Ireland, August 2014</address>
<author confidence="0.979958">Michael Zock</author>
<author confidence="0.979958">Reinhard Rapp</author>
<author confidence="0.979958">Chu-Ren Huang</author>
<email confidence="0.93236">v</email>
<note confidence="0.595708625">Organizers: Michael Zock (LIF-CNRS, Marseille, France) Reinhard Rapp (LIF, Marseille, France and University of Mainz, Germany) Chu-Ren Huang (The Hong Kong Polytechnic University, China) Invited Speaker: Roberto Navigli (Sapienza, University of Rome, Italy) Program Committee: Bel Enguix, Gemma (LIF Marseille, France)</note>
<address confidence="0.855692416666667">Chang, Jason (National Tsing Hua University, Taiwan) Cook, Paul (University of Melbourne, Australia) Cristea, Dan (University A.I.Cuza, Iasi, Romania) De Deyne, Simon (Experimental Psychology, Leuven, Belgium and Adelaide, Australia) De Melo, Gerard (IIIS, Tsinghua University, Beijing, China) Ferret, Olivier (CEA LIST, Gif sur Yvette, France) Fontenelle, Thierry (CDT, Luxemburg) Gala, Nuria (LIF-CNRS, Aix Marseille University, Marseille, France) Granger, Sylviane (Université Catholique de Louvain, Belgium) Grefenstette, Gregory (Inria, Saclay, France) Hirst, Graeme (University of Toronto, Canada) Hovy, Eduard (CMU, Pittsburgh, USA)</address>
<affiliation confidence="0.516689">Hsieh, Shu-Kai (National Taiwan University, Taipei, Taiwan) Huang, Chu-Ren (Hongkong Polytechnic University, China)</affiliation>
<address confidence="0.87267865">Joyce, Terry (Tama University, Kanagawa-ken, Japan) Lapalme, Guy (RALI, University of Montreal, Canada) Lenci, Alessandro (CNR, University of Pisa, Italy) L’Homme, Marie Claude (University of Montreal, Canada) Mihalcea, Rada (University of Texas, USA) Navigli, Roberto (Sapienza, University of Rome, Italy) Pirrelli, Vito (ILC, Pisa, Italy) Polguère, Alain (ATILF-CNRS, Nancy, France) Rapp, Reinhard (LIF Marseille, France and University of Mainz, Germany) Rosso, Paolo (NLEL, Universitat Politècnica de València, Spain) Schwab, Didier (LIG-GETALP, Grenoble, France) Serasset, Gilles (IMAG, Grenoble, France) Sharoff, Serge (University of Leeds, UK) Su, Jun-Ming (University of Tainan, Taiwan) Tiberius, Carole (Institute for Dutch Lexicology, The Netherlands) Tokunaga, Takenobu (TITECH, Tokyo, Japan) Tufis, Dan (RACAI, Bucharest, Romania) Valitutti, Alessandro (Helsinki Institute of Information Technology, Finland) Wandmacher, Tonio (IRT SystemX, Saclay, France) Zock, Michael (LIF-CNRS, Marseille, France)</address>
<email confidence="0.979439">vii</email>
<title confidence="0.861835333333333">Table of Contents The CogALex-IV Shared Task on the Lexical Access Problem Rapp and Michael Zock 1 A Two-Stage Approach for Computing Associative Responses to a Set of Stimulus Words Ghosh, Sambhav Jain and Paul Soma15 Deep Learning from Web-Scale Corpora for Better Dictionary Interfaces</title>
<author confidence="0.51283">Pavel Smrz</author>
<author confidence="0.51283">Lubomir Otrusina</author>
<title confidence="0.606398666666667">Exploring the use of word embeddings and random walks on Wikipedia for the CogAlex shared task Josu Goikoetxea, Eneko Agirre and Aitor Soroa 31 ETS Lexical Associations System for the COGALEX-4 Shared Task</title>
<author confidence="0.716583">Michael Flor</author>
<author confidence="0.716583">Beata Beigman Klebanov</author>
<title confidence="0.991389">Using Significant Word Co-occurences for the Lexical Access Problem</title>
<author confidence="0.999457">Rico Feist</author>
<author confidence="0.999457">Daniel Gerighausen</author>
<author confidence="0.999457">Manuel Konrad</author>
<author confidence="0.999457">Georg Richter</author>
<author confidence="0.999457">Thomas Eckart</author>
<author confidence="0.999457">Dirk Goldhahn</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.606589">and Uwe Quasthoff 46</affiliation>
<title confidence="0.731824">NaDiR: Naive Distributional Response Generation</title>
<note confidence="0.843289727272727">Lapesa and Stefan Evert50 Retrieving Word Associations with a Simple Neighborhood Algorithm in a Graph-based Resource Gemma Bel Enguix 60 Predicting sense convergence with distributional semantics: an application to the CogaLex 2014 shared task Sitbon and Lance De Vine64 WordFinder Mititelu and Verginica Barbu Mititelu 68 (Digital) Goodies from the ERC Wishing Well: BabelNet, Babelfy, Video Games with a Purpose and the Wikipedia Bitaxonomy Navigli 75</note>
<title confidence="0.7526122">Measuring Similarity from Word Pair Matrices with Syntagmatic and Paradigmatic Associations Matsuoka and Yves Lepage77 Jibiki-LINKS: a tool between traditional dictionaries and lexical networks for modelling lexical resources Ying Zhang, Mathieu Mangeot, Valérie Bellynck and Christian Boitet 87 When Frequency Data Meet Dispersion Data in the Extraction of Multi-word Units from a Corpus: A Study of Trigrams in Chinese Hsu99 Exploring Mental Lexicon in an Efficient and Economic Way: Crowdsourcing Method for Linguistic Experiments</title>
<author confidence="0.899968">Chu-Ren Huang Wang</author>
<author confidence="0.899968">Yao Yao</author>
<author confidence="0.899968">Angel Chan</author>
<title confidence="0.6378245">ix A Computational Approach to Generate a Sensorial Lexicon Sinem Tekiroglu, Gözde Özbal and Carlo Strapparava 114 Database Design of an Online E-Learning Tool of Chinese Classifiers</title>
<author confidence="0.671789">Helena Gao</author>
<title confidence="0.5415495">Default Physical Measurements in SUMO Quattri, Pease Adam and John P. McCrae138 Lexical Access Preference and Constraint Strategies for Improving Multiword Expression Association within Semantic MT Evaluation Wu, Chi-kiu Lo and Markus Saers144 A Lexical Network with a Morphological Model in It Nabil Gader, Aurore Koehl and Alain Polguère 154 Dimensions of Metaphorical Meaning</title>
<author confidence="0.394295">Andrew Gargett</author>
<author confidence="0.394295">Josef Ruppenhofer</author>
<author confidence="0.394295">John Barnden</author>
<title confidence="0.74757175">Constructing an Ontology of Japanese Lexical Properties: Specifying its Property Structures and Lexical Entries Joyce and Bor Hodošˇcek174 Frames and terminology: representing predicative terms in the field of the environment L’ Homme and Benoît Robichaud186 Modelling the Semantics of Adjectives in the Ontology-Lexicon Interface P. McCrae, Francesca Quattri, Christina Unger and Philipp Cimiano 198 Discovering Conceptual Metaphors using Source Domain Spaces</title>
<author confidence="0.992861">Samira Shaikh</author>
<author confidence="0.992861">Tomek Strzalkowski</author>
<author confidence="0.992861">Kit Cho</author>
<author confidence="0.992861">Ting Liu</author>
<author confidence="0.992861">George Aaron Broadwell</author>
<author confidence="0.992861">Laurie Feldman</author>
<address confidence="0.312378">Sarah Taylor, Boris Yamrom, Ching-Sheng Lin, Ning Sa, Ignacio Cases, Yuliya Peshkova and</address>
<note confidence="0.719521">Elliot210</note>
<title confidence="0.682602">Wordfinding Problems and How to Overcome them Ultimately With the Help of a Computer</title>
<author confidence="0.684435">Michael Zock</author>
<email confidence="0.644204">x</email>
<affiliation confidence="0.315135">Workshop Program</affiliation>
<address confidence="0.467102">Saturday, August 23, 2014</address>
<title confidence="0.689615666666667">Remarks 1: Shared Task on the Lexical Access Problem The CogALex-IV Shared Task on the Lexical Access Problem</title>
<author confidence="0.991719">Reinhard Rapp</author>
<author confidence="0.991719">Michael Zock</author>
<title confidence="0.977135">A Two-Stage Approach for Computing Associative Responses to a Set of Stimulus Words</title>
<author confidence="0.595062">Urmi Ghosh</author>
<author confidence="0.595062">Sambhav Jain</author>
<author confidence="0.595062">Paul Soma</author>
<title confidence="0.781721">Deep Learning from Web-Scale Corpora for Better Dictionary Interfaces Pavel Smrz and Lubomir Otrusina Exploring the use of word embeddings and random walks on Wikipedia for the CogAlex shared task Josu Goikoetxea, Eneko Agirre and Aitor Soroa ETS Lexical Associations System for the COGALEX-4 Shared Task</title>
<author confidence="0.75023">Michael Flor</author>
<author confidence="0.75023">Beata Beigman Klebanov</author>
<title confidence="0.955677">Using Significant Word Co-occurences for the Lexical Access Problem</title>
<author confidence="0.828265">Rico Feist</author>
<author confidence="0.828265">Daniel Gerighausen</author>
<author confidence="0.828265">Manuel Konrad</author>
<author confidence="0.828265">Georg Richter</author>
<author confidence="0.828265">Thomas Eckart</author>
<author confidence="0.828265">Dirk Goldhahn</author>
<author confidence="0.828265">Uwe Quasthoff</author>
<title confidence="0.964449">NaDiR: Naive Distributional Response Generation</title>
<author confidence="0.933694">Gabriella Lapesa</author>
<author confidence="0.933694">Stefan Evert</author>
<title confidence="0.885954">Retrieving Word Associations with a Simple Neighborhood Algorithm in a Graphbased Resource</title>
<author confidence="0.571274">Gemma Bel Enguix</author>
<note confidence="0.236056">Predicting sense convergence with distributional semantics: an application to the CogaLex 2014 shared task Laurianne Sitbon and Lance De Vine WordFinder Catalin Mititelu and Verginica Barbu Mititelu xi Saturday, August 23, 2014 (continued) Break 2: Invited Talk (Digital) Goodies from the ERC Wishing Well: BabelNet, Babelfy, Video Games with a</note>
<title confidence="0.979655">Purpose and the Wikipedia Bitaxonomy</title>
<author confidence="0.999143">Roberto Navigli</author>
<abstract confidence="0.7503885">3a: Booster Presentations for Posters 12:03–12:06Measuring Similarity from Word Pair Matrices with Syntagmatic and Paradigmatic Associations Jin Matsuoka and Yves Lepage 12:06–12:09Jibiki-LINKS: a tool between traditional dictionaries and lexical networks for modelling lexical resources</abstract>
<author confidence="0.51687375">When Frequency Data Meet Dispersion Data in the Extraction of Multi-word Units from a Corpus A Study of Trigrams in Chinese Chan-Chia Hsu</author>
<title confidence="0.815274">12:12–12:15Exploring Mental Lexicon in an Efficient and Economic Way: Crowdsourcing Method for Linguistic Experiments</title>
<author confidence="0.994337">Shichang Wang</author>
<author confidence="0.994337">Chu-Ren Huang</author>
<author confidence="0.994337">Yao Yao</author>
<author confidence="0.994337">Angel Chan</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.561079">12:15–12:18A Computational Approach to Generate a Sensorial Lexicon</affiliation>
<author confidence="0.751348">Serra Sinem Tekiroglu</author>
<author confidence="0.751348">Gözde Özbal</author>
<author confidence="0.751348">Carlo Strapparava</author>
<title confidence="0.871463">12:18–12:21Database Design of an Online E-Learning Tool of Chinese Classifiers</title>
<author confidence="0.956809">Helena Gao</author>
<title confidence="0.315809">12:21–12:24Default Physical Measurements in SUMO</title>
<author confidence="0.929435">Francesca Quattri</author>
<author confidence="0.929435">Pease Adam</author>
<author confidence="0.929435">John P McCrae</author>
<note confidence="0.763762636363636">12:24–12:27Lexical Access Preference and Constraint Strategies for Improving Multiword Expression Association within Semantic MT Evaluation Dekai Wu, Chi-kiu Lo and Markus Saers Break 3b: Posters xii Saturday, August 23, 2014 (continued) Break 4: Oral Presentations 15:30–15:50A Lexical Network with a Morphological Model in It Nabil Gader, Aurore Koehl and Alain Polguère</note>
<title confidence="0.544085">15:50–16:10Dimensions of Metaphorical Meaning</title>
<author confidence="0.694763">Andrew Gargett</author>
<author confidence="0.694763">Josef Ruppenhofer</author>
<author confidence="0.694763">John Barnden</author>
<title confidence="0.787149">16:10–16:30Constructing an Ontology of Japanese Lexical Properties: Specifying its Property Structures and Lexical Entries</title>
<author confidence="0.978796">Terry Joyce</author>
<author confidence="0.978796">Bor Hodošˇcek</author>
<abstract confidence="0.222964">16:30–16:50Frames and terminology: representing predicative terms in the field of the environment Marie-Claude L’ Homme and Benoît Robichaud 16:50–17:10Modelling the Semantics of Adjectives in the Ontology-Lexicon Interface</abstract>
<author confidence="0.931599">John P McCrae</author>
<author confidence="0.931599">Francesca Quattri</author>
<author confidence="0.931599">Christina Unger</author>
<author confidence="0.931599">Philipp Cimiano</author>
<title confidence="0.770826">17:10–17:30Discovering Conceptual Metaphors using Source Domain Spaces</title>
<author confidence="0.546644333333333">Samira Shaikh</author>
<author confidence="0.546644333333333">Tomek Strzalkowski</author>
<author confidence="0.546644333333333">Kit Cho</author>
<author confidence="0.546644333333333">Ting Liu</author>
<author confidence="0.546644333333333">George Aaron Broadwell</author>
<author confidence="0.546644333333333">Laurie Feldman</author>
<author confidence="0.546644333333333">Sarah Taylor</author>
<author confidence="0.546644333333333">Boris Yamrom</author>
<author confidence="0.546644333333333">Ching-Sheng Lin</author>
<author confidence="0.546644333333333">Ning Sa</author>
<author confidence="0.546644333333333">Ignacio Cases</author>
<author confidence="0.546644333333333">Yuliya Peshkova</author>
<author confidence="0.546644333333333">Kyle Elliot</author>
<title confidence="0.354873">17:30–17:50Wordfinding Problems and How to Overcome them Ultimately With the Help of a Computer</title>
<author confidence="0.996778">Michael Zock</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.509337">and Closing</affiliation>
<intro confidence="0.665024">xiii</intro>
</variant>
</algorithm>
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="false">
<title>12:15–12:18 A Computational Approach to Generate a Sensorial Lexicon Serra Sinem Tekiroglu,</title>
<booktitle>Gözde Özbal and Carlo Strapparava 12:18–12:21 Database Design of an Online E-Learning Tool of Chinese Classifiers</booktitle>
<location>Helena Gao</location>
<marker></marker>
<rawString>12:15–12:18 A Computational Approach to Generate a Sensorial Lexicon Serra Sinem Tekiroglu, Gözde Özbal and Carlo Strapparava 12:18–12:21 Database Design of an Online E-Learning Tool of Chinese Classifiers Helena Gao</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>P John</author>
</authors>
<booktitle>12:21–12:24 Default Physical Measurements in SUMO Francesca Quattri, Pease Adam and</booktitle>
<publisher>McCrae</publisher>
<marker>John, </marker>
<rawString>12:21–12:24 Default Physical Measurements in SUMO Francesca Quattri, Pease Adam and John P. McCrae</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<title>Access Preference and Constraint Strategies for Improving Multiword Expression Association within Semantic MT Evaluation Dekai Wu, Chi-kiu Lo and Markus Saers</title>
<marker></marker>
<rawString>12:24–12:27 Lexical Access Preference and Constraint Strategies for Improving Multiword Expression Association within Semantic MT Evaluation Dekai Wu, Chi-kiu Lo and Markus Saers</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<booktitle>12:30–14:00 Lunch Break 14:00–15:00 Session 3b: Posters xii</booktitle>
<marker></marker>
<rawString>12:30–14:00 Lunch Break 14:00–15:00 Session 3b: Posters xii</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Saturday</author>
</authors>
<date>2014</date>
<booktitle>(continued) 15:00–15:30 Coffee Break 15:30–17:40 Session 4: Oral Presentations</booktitle>
<marker>Saturday, 2014</marker>
<rawString>Saturday, August 23, 2014 (continued) 15:00–15:30 Coffee Break 15:30–17:40 Session 4: Oral Presentations</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<title>15:30–15:50 A Lexical Network with a Morphological Model</title>
<booktitle>in It Nabil Gader, Aurore Koehl and Alain Polguère 15:50–16:10 Dimensions of Metaphorical Meaning Andrew Gargett, Josef Ruppenhofer and John Barnden</booktitle>
<marker></marker>
<rawString>15:30–15:50 A Lexical Network with a Morphological Model in It Nabil Gader, Aurore Koehl and Alain Polguère 15:50–16:10 Dimensions of Metaphorical Meaning Andrew Gargett, Josef Ruppenhofer and John Barnden</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<booktitle>16:10–16:30 Constructing an Ontology of Japanese Lexical Properties: Specifying its Property Structures and Lexical Entries Terry Joyce and Bor Hodošˇcek</booktitle>
<marker></marker>
<rawString>16:10–16:30 Constructing an Ontology of Japanese Lexical Properties: Specifying its Property Structures and Lexical Entries Terry Joyce and Bor Hodošˇcek</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<title>terminology: representing predicative terms in the field of the environment Marie-Claude L’ Homme and Benoît Robichaud 16:50–17:10 Modelling the Semantics of Adjectives in the Ontology-Lexicon Interface</title>
<location>Tomek Strzalkowski, Kit Cho, Ting Liu, George</location>
<marker></marker>
<rawString>16:30–16:50 Frames and terminology: representing predicative terms in the field of the environment Marie-Claude L’ Homme and Benoît Robichaud 16:50–17:10 Modelling the Semantics of Adjectives in the Ontology-Lexicon Interface John P. McCrae, Francesca Quattri, Christina Unger and Philipp Cimiano 17:10–17:30 Discovering Conceptual Metaphors using Source Domain Spaces Samira Shaikh, Tomek Strzalkowski, Kit Cho, Ting Liu, George Aaron Broadwell, Laurie Feldman, Sarah Taylor, Boris Yamrom, Ching-Sheng Lin, Ning Sa, Ignacio Cases, Yuliya Peshkova and Kyle Elliot</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<title>17:30–17:50 Wordfinding Problems and How to Overcome them Ultimately With the Help of a Computer Michael Zock 17:50–18:00 Conclusions and Closing</title>
<marker></marker>
<rawString>17:30–17:50 Wordfinding Problems and How to Overcome them Ultimately With the Help of a Computer Michael Zock 17:50–18:00 Conclusions and Closing</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>