<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="SectLabel" version="110505">
<variant no="0" confidence="0.000000">
<title confidence="0.730498">
First steps towards a Predicate Matrix
</title>
<note confidence="0.583189333333333">
Maddalen L´opez de Lacalle Egoitz Laparra German Rigau
IXA group, UPV/EHU IXA group, UPV/EHU IXA group, UPV/EHU
Donostia, Spain Donostia, Spain Donostia, Spain
</note>
<email confidence="0.97844">
maddalen.lopezdelacalle@ehu.es egoitz.laparra@ehu.es german.rigau@ehu.es
</email>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.99324" genericHeader="abstract">
Abstract
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999488368421053">
This paper presents the first steps towards
building the Predicate Matrix, a new lexical re-
source resulting from the integration of multi-
ple sources of predicate information including
FrameNet (Baker et al., 1997), VerbNet (Kip-
per, 2005), PropBank (Palmer et al., 2005)
and WordNet (Fellbaum, 1998). By using
the Predicate Matrix, we expect to provide
a more robust interoperable lexicon by dis-
covering and solving inherent inconsistencies
among the resources. Moreover, we plan to
extend the coverage of current predicate re-
sources (by including from WordNet morpho-
logically related nominal and verbal concepts),
to enrich WordNet with predicate information,
and possibly to extend predicate information
to languages other than English (by exploit-
ing the local wordnets aligned to the English
WordNet).
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.998992" genericHeader="introduction">
1 Introduction
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999908679012346">
Predicate models such as FrameNet (Baker et
al., 1997), VerbNet (Kipper, 2005) or PropBank
(Palmer et al., 2005) are core resources in most
advanced NLP tasks, such as Question Answer-
ing, Textual Entailment or Information Extraction.
Most of the systems with Natural Language Un-
derstanding capabilities require a large and precise
amount of semantic knowledge at the predicate-
argument level. This type of knowledge allows
to identify the underlying typical participants of
a particular event independently of its realization
in the text. Thus, using these models, different
linguistic phenomena expressing the same event,
such as active/passive transformations, verb alter-
nations, nominalizations, implicit realizations can
be harmonized into a common semantic represen-
tation. In fact, lately, several systems have been
developed for shallow semantic parsing an explicit
and implicit semantic role labeling using these re-
sources (Erk and Pado, 2004), (Shi and Mihalcea,
2005), (Giuglea and Moschitti, 2006), (Laparra
and Rigau, 2013).
However, building large and rich enough predi-
cate models for broad–coverage semantic process-
ing takes a great deal of expensive manual effort
involving large research groups during long peri-
ods of development. In fact, the coverage of cur-
rently available predicate-argument resources is
still far from complete. For example, (Burchardt et
al., 2005) or (Shen and Lapata, 2007) indicate the
limited coverage of FrameNet as one of the main
problems of this resource. In fact, FrameNet1.5
covers around 10,000 lexical-units while for in-
stance, WordNet3.0 contains more than 150,000
words. Furthermore, the same effort should be in-
vested for each different language (Subirats and
Petruck, 2003). Moreover, most previous research
efforts on the integration of resources targeted at
knowledge about nouns and named entities rather
than predicate knowledge. Well known examples
are YAGO (Suchanek et al., 2007), Freebase (Bol-
lacker et al., 2008), DBPedia (Bizer et al., 2009),
BabelNet (Navigli and Ponzetto, 2010) or UBY
(Gurevych et al., 2012).
Following the line of previous works (Shi and
Mihalcea, 2005), (Burchardt et al., 2005), (Jo-
hansson and Nugues, 2007), (Pennacchiotti et al.,
2008), (Cao et al., 2008), (Tonelli and Pianta,
2009), (Laparra et al., 2010), we will also focus on
the integration of predicate information. We start
from the basis of SemLink (Palmer, 2009). Sem-
Link aimed to connect together different predicate
resources such as FrameNet (Baker et al., 1997),
VerbNet (Kipper, 2005), PropBank (Palmer et al.,
2005) and WordNet (Fellbaum, 1998). However,
its coverage is still far from complete.
The Predicate Matrix, the resource resulting
from the work presented in this paper, will al-
low to extend the coverage of current predicate
resources (by including from WordNet closely re-
lated nominal and verbal concepts), to discover in-
herent inconsistencies among the resources, to en-
rich WordNet with predicate information, and pos-
sibly to extend predicate information to languages
other than English (by exploiting the local word-
nets aligned to the English WordNet). Moreover,
the Predicate Matrix uses WordNet as a central re-
source. In that way, each row (or line) in the ma-
trix presents partial predicate information related
to a particular WordNet word sense.
First, as SemLink takes VerbNet as the central
resource, we present a complete study of the cov-
erage of the mappings between each resource in-
cluded in SemLink to VerbNet. We describe the
coverage and gaps of these mappings with respect
to the lexical entries and the role structures of each
resource. Second, we exploit WordNet to propose
straightforward methods to discover incosistencies
among the resources as well as to extend their cov-
erage towards a more complete and robust predi-
cate lexicon.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.57813" genericHeader="method">
2 Sources of Predicate information
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999897888888889">
As a starting point for building the Predicate Ma-
trix, we consider the sources of predicate knowl-
edge connected to SemLink.
SemLink1 (Palmer, 2009) is a project whose
aim is to link together different predicate resources
establishing a set of mappings. These mappings
make it possible to combine the different infor-
mation provided by the different lexical resources
for tasks such as inferencing, consistency check-
ing, interoperable semantic role labelling, etc.
Currently, SemLink provides partial mappings to
VerbNet (Kipper, 2005), PropBank (Palmer et al.,
2005), FrameNet (Baker et al., 1997) and Word-
Net (Fellbaum, 1998).
FrameNet 2 (Baker et al., 1997) is a very rich
semantic resource that contains descriptions and
corpus annotations of English words following the
paradigm of Frame Semantics (Fillmore, 1976). In
frame semantics, a Frame corresponds to a sce-
nario that involves the interaction of a set of typ-
ical participants, playing a particular role in the
scenario. FrameNet groups words or lexical-units
(LUs hereinafter) into coherent semantic classes
or frames, and each frame is further characterized
by a list of participants or frame-elements (FEs
hereinafter). Different senses for a word are repre-
sented in FrameNet by assigning different frames.
</bodyText>
<footnote confidence="0.9998905">
1http://verbs.colorado.edu/semlink/
2http://framenet.icsi.berkeley.edu/
</footnote>
<bodyText confidence="0.998404086956522">
PropBank 3 (Palmer et al., 2005) aims to pro-
vide a wide corpus annotated with information
about semantic propositions, including relations
between the predicates and their arguments. Prop-
Bank also contains a description of the frame
structures, called framesets, of each sense of ev-
ery verb that belong to its lexicon. Unlike other
similar resources, as FrameNet, PropBank defines
the arguments, or roles, of each verb individually.
In consecuence, it becomes a hard task obtaning
a generalization of the frame structures over the
verbs.
VerbNet 4 (Kipper, 2005) is a hierarchical
domain-independent broad-coverage verb lexicon
for English. VerbNet is organized into verb classes
extending (Levin, 1993) classes through refine-
ment and addition of subclasses to achieve syn-
tactic and semantic coherence among members
of a class. Each verb class in VerbNet is com-
pletely described by thematic-roles, selectional re-
strictions on the arguments, and frames consisting
of a syntactic description and semantic predicates.
WordNet 5 (Fellbaum, 1998) is by far the most
widely-used knowledge base. In fact, WordNet
is being used world-wide for anchoring different
types of semantic knowledge including wordnets
for languages other than English (Gonzalez-Agirre
et al., 2012a). It contains manually coded infor-
mation about English nouns, verbs, adjectives and
adverbs and is organized around the notion of a
synset. A synset is a set of words with the same
part-of-speech that can be interchanged in a cer-
tain context. For example, &lt;learn, study, read,
take&gt; form a synset because they can be used to
refer to the same concept. A synset is often fur-
ther described by a gloss, in this case: ”be a stu-
dent of a certain subject” and by explicit semantic
relations to other synsets. Each synset represents
a concept that are related with an large number
of semantic relations, including hypernymy/hy-
ponymy, meronymy/holonymy, antonymy, entail-
ment, etc.
Obviously, we can also exploit the existing
SemLink mappings to aid semi-automatic or fully
automatic extensions of the current mapping cov-
erage, in order to increase the overall overlapping.
</bodyText>
<footnote confidence="0.937601166666667">
3http://verbs.colorado.edu/-mpalmer/
projects/ace.html
4http://verbs.colorado.edu/-mpalmer/
projects/verbnet.html
5http://wordnet.princeton.edu/
3 SemLink coverage ready mapped to a WordNet sense. This is the case
</footnote>
<bodyText confidence="0.9828042">
of reveal as shown in Table 2.
As SemLink uses VerbNet as the central resource,
we present a complete study of the coverage of the
mappings between each resource included in Sem-
Link to VerbNet.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.999585">
3.1 WordNet and VerbNet aligment
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999526833333333">
Although VerbNet is one of largest verb lexicons
available it does not reach the coverage of the ver-
bal part of WordNet. While WordNet contains
25,047 different verb senses there are just 6,293
predicates in VerbNet classes. This means that the
mapping between both resources is, obviously, in-
complete. Specifically there are 18,559 senses of
WordNet, corresponding to 9,995 different lem-
mas, that have not been assigned to any VerbNet
predicate. Many of these cases appear because of
the distinct granularities of both resources. In fact
6,120 WordNet senses (corresponding to 2,099
lemmas) that are not mapped to VerbNet belong to
lemmas that have at least another WordNet sense
properly mapped to VerbNet. For instance, Table
1 shows the mapping between the verb drown in
WordNet and VerbNet. Note that only two of the
five WordNet senses are assigned to VerbNet.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.927919125">
WordNet VerbNet
sense member class
drown%2:30:00:: drown 40.7
drown%2:31:00:: drown 42.2
drown 40.7
drown%2:30:02:: - -
drown%2:35:00:: - -
drown%2:42:00:: - -
</table>
<tableCaption confidence="0.999707">
Table 1: WordNet to VerbNet aligment for drownv
</tableCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.999561625">
The rest of missing senses correspond to those
cases where the lemma does not exist in the Verb-
Net lexicon (7,320 lemmas and 11,201 senses).
For example the verb abort does not appear in
VerbNet since its three WordNet senses are not
part of SemLink. The remaining cases (1,443
WordNet senses and 576 lemmas) correspond to
lemmas that exist in both resources but there is
no sense mapping between them. For instance,
there is no mapping between the WordNet sense
harm%2:29:00:: and the VerbNet verb that be-
longs to the class 31-1.
Moreover, SemLink does not provide mappings
to WordNet senses for 1,077 VerbNet predicates.
304 of these VerbNet predicates share the same
lemma with some other VerbNet sense that is al-
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.950423285714286">
VerbNet WordNet
member class sense
reveal 29.2 reveal%2:32:00
reveal 37.7 reveal%2:32:00
reveal 37.10 reveal%2:32:00
reveal 48.1.2 -
reveal 78 -
</table>
<tableCaption confidence="0.999341">
Table 2: VerbNet to WordNet aligment for revealv
</tableCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.996223">
From the rest of missing members, 574 corre-
spond to those cases the lemma of the predicate
also exists in WordNet (like the example of harm
explained previously). Finally, there are only 199
verb senses in VerbNet whose lemmas do not exist
in WordNet. For example: africanizev, backfillv
or carbonifyv.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.999533">
3.2 PropBank and VerbNet aligment
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9995454">
The mapping between PropBank and VerbNet in-
troduces additional complexity to the comparison
of both resources. In this case, aligning the lexicon
means that the arguments of the PropBank pred-
icates must be aligned to the VerbNet thematic-
roles.
First, regarding the lexicon mapping, once
again, the differences in the coverages of the
resources impede to obtain a complete align-
ment. From the 6,181 different PropBank predi-
cates (comprising 4,552 lemmas), just 3,558 have
their corresponding VerbNet predicate in Sem-
Link. That is, 2,623 PropBank predicates have
no correspondances to VerbNet. However, all
the lemmas of PropBank are contained within the
VerbNet lexicon. This means that for each one of
the 2,623 missing predicates from PropBank there
exists at least another predicate with the same
lemma that is mapped to VerbNet. That is the case
of the PropBank predicate abandon.02, shown in
</bodyText>
<tableCaption confidence="0.8561825">
Table 3.
PropBank VerbNet
Table 3: PropBank to VerbNet aligments for
acceptv and abandonv
</tableCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.522118">
On the other hand, we found that the num-
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.968777833333333">
predicate
member class
accept 13.5.2
accept 29.2-1-1
accept 77
accept.01
</figure>
<page confidence="0.440706">
abandon.01
abandon.02
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.947399388888889">
abandon 51.2
- -
ber of VerbNet predicates that are not aligned to
PropBank is smaller than the number of Prop-
Bank predicates not aligned to VerbNet. That is,
up to 4,736 of the 6,293 VerbNet predicates are
aligned to PropBank while only 1,557 VerbNet
predicates are not aligned to PropBank. More-
over, 298 of these VerbNet predicates do not exist
in the PropBank lexicon, for instance arrogatev,
deconstructv, mewlv or sprintv. Finally, there
are 312 VerbNet predicates whose lemmas (265
in total) are actually part of the PropBank lexi-
con but there is no aligment for them. For ex-
ample, the predicate offloadv of the VerbNet class
wipe manner-10.4.1 is not connected to the Prop-
Bank predicate offload.01. Table 4 shows some
aligments from VerbNet to PropBank.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.4415">
VerbNet PropBank
member class predicate
</table>
<tableCaption confidence="0.950394">
Table 4: VerbNet to PropBank aligments for
laughv and flowv
</tableCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.998286923076923">
Regarding the PropBank arguments and the
VerbNet thematic-roles, 7,915 out of 15,871 argu-
ments from PropBank6 are mapped to a thematic-
role from VerbNet7. That is, around a half of
the total PropBank arguments, leaving out the
remaining 7,956 arguments. From the opposite
point of view, 9,682 out of 17,382 thematic-roles
from VerbNet are included in the SemLink map-
ping. This means that 7,700 thematic-roles are not
aligned to any PropBank argument. Table 5 con-
tains some examples of existing and also missing
mappings between PropBank arguments and Verb-
Net thematic-roles.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.998763">
3.3 FrameNet and VerbNet aligment
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999851833333333">
The alingment between FrameNet and VerbNet
proves to be very incomplete. For example, only
1,730 lexical-units from FrameNet8 are aligned to,
at least, one VerbNet predicate9. This number rep-
resents only 16% out of the total 10,195 lexical-
units of FrameNet. Table 6 presents some alig-
</bodyText>
<footnote confidence="0.701937571428571">
6Arguments of particular PropBank predicates. For in-
stance, Arg0 of paint.01.
7Thematic-roles of particular VerbNet predicates. For in-
stance, Agent of paint,,.
8Lexical-units of particular FrameNet frames. For in-
stance, sell„ from the frame Commerce sell.
9Predicate of a particular VerbNet class. For instance,
</footnote>
<table confidence="0.958209083333334">
sell„ from 13.1-1 VerbNet class.
VerbNet PropBank
predicate them-role predicate argument
paint 9.9 Agent paint.01 A0
paint 9.9 Destination paint.01 A1
paint 9.9 Theme paint.01 A2
plant 9.7 Agent - -
plant 9.7 Destination - -
plant 9.7 Theme - -
abandon 51.2 Theme abandon.01 A0
- - abandon.01 A1
- - abandon.01 A2
</table>
<tableCaption confidence="0.944246">
Table 5: Some aligments between VerbNet
thematic-roles and PropBank arguments
ments between VerbNet predicates and FrameNet
lexical-units.
</tableCaption>
<table confidence="0.99978925">
VerbNet FrameNet
class member frame lexical-unit
13.1-1 sell Commerce sell sell.v
13.5.1 buy Commerce buy buy.v
53.1-1 delay Hindering delay.v
53.1-1 delay Change event time -
13.5.3 employ Employing -
105 employ Using -
</table>
<tableCaption confidence="0.9817275">
Table 6: Some aligments between VerbNet predi-
cates and FrameNet lexical-units (LUs)
</tableCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.999031416666667">
SemLink also includes the alignment between
the roles of both resources. However, unlike Prop-
Bank the roles of FrameNet, that are called frame-
elements, are defined at frame-level and not at
predicate level. Therefore, the mapping of the
VerbNet thematic-roles and the frame-elements of
FrameNet is defined between VerbNet classes and
FrameNet frames. Table 7 presents an example of
the aligment of some roles from both resources for
the VerbNet class 54.1. A VerbNet predicate mem-
ber of this class has been aligned to the WordNet
sense total%2:42:00.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.9986368">
VerbNet FrameNet
class thematic-role frame frame-element
54.1 Agent Adding up Cognizer
54.1 Theme Adding up Numbers
54.1 Value Adding up Result
</table>
<tableCaption confidence="0.657847333333333">
Table 7: Some aligments between VerbNet
thematic-roles and FrameNet frame-elements
(FEs)
</tableCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.95502">
Once again, the mapping between VerbNet
and FrameNet presents significant gaps and miss-
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.580960833333333">
laugh 40.2
flow 47.2
flow 48.1.1
laugh.01
flow.01
-
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.999697888888889">
matches. For instance, just 825 of the 7,124 frame-
elements of FrameNet10 are linked to a VerbNet
thematic-role. That is, 88% of the frame-elements
from FrameNet are not aligned to any VerbNet
thematic-role. Moreover, only 262 frames out of
795 have at least one frame-element aligned to a
VerbNet thematic-role. That is, just a few frames
are used in the mapping. However, it also seems
that, at a class level, most of the VerbNet thematic-
roles appear to be aligned to at least one frame-
element. VerbNet covers 787 different thematic-
roles11. From these, 541 appear to be aligned
to a FrameNet frame-element. In other words,
it seems that just 246 thematic-roles are missing
from the mapping provided by SemLink. Table 8
presents some class level aligments between Verb-
Net thematic-roles and FrameNet frame-elements
(FEs).
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.987262263157895">
VerbNet FrameNet
class thematic-role frame frame-element
10.10 Agent - -
10.10 Attribute - -
10.10 Source - -
10.10 Theme - -
48.3 Theme Catastrophe Undesirable Event
48.3 Location Catastrophe Place
48.3 Location Catastrophe Time
- - Catastrophe Cause
- - Catastrophe Circumstances
- - Catastrophe Degree
- - Catastrophe Manner
- - Catastrophe Undergoer
- - Addiction Addict
- - Addiction Addictant
- - Addiction Compeller
- - Addiction Degree
- - Addiction State
</table>
<tableCaption confidence="0.760982666666667">
Table 8: Some aligments between VerbNet
thematic-roles and FrameNet frame-elements
(FEs)
</tableCaption>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.80008" genericHeader="method">
4 Using WordNet to cross-check
predicate information
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999418651162791">
In this section, as a proof-of-concept, we will
show a simple way to exploit WordNet for validat-
ing the predicate information appearing in Sem-
Link. We apply a very simple method to check
the consistency of VerbNet. Consider the follow-
ing WordNet synset&lt;understand, read, interpret,
10Frame-elements of a particular FrameNet frame. For in-
stance, the frame-element Cognizer for the Adding up frame
11Role of a particular VerbNet class. For instance, Agent
of VerbNet class 10.10
translate&gt; with the gloss “make sense of a lan-
guage” and the example sentences “She under-
stands French; Can you read Greek?”. As syn-
onyms, these verbs denote the same concept and
are interchangeable in many contexts. However,
in SemLink read%2:31:04 appears aligned with
the VerbNet class learn-14-112 while one of its
synonyms understand%2:31:03 appears aligned
to the VerbNet class comprehend-87.213. More-
over, the thematic-roles of both classes are differ-
ent. Learn-14-1 has the following thematic-roles
Agent (with semantic type [+animate]), Topic and
Source while comprehend-87.2 has Experiencer
(with semantic type [+animate or +organization]),
Attribute and Stimulus. Are both sets of thematic-
roles compatible? Complementary? Is one of
them incorrect? Should we joint them? Maybe
is the aligment incorrect? Is perhaps the synset
definition?
Following with this example, the VerbNet pred-
icate understand„ has no connection to FrameNet,
but its VerbNet class comprehend-87.2-1 has some
other verbal predicates aligned to FrameNet. For
instance, apprehend,,, comprehend„ and grasp„
are linked to the Grasp14 FrameNet frame. Among
the lexical-units corresponding to the Grasp frame
it appears also the verbal predicate understand,,.
This means that possibly, this verbal predicate
should also be aligned to the FrameNet frame
Grasp. The core frame-elements (roles) of this
frame are Cognizer (with semantic type Sentient),
Faculty and Phenomenon. Is this set of roles com-
patible with the previous ones?
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.83556" genericHeader="method">
5 Using WordNet to extend SemLink
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999977727272727">
As we have seen in Section 3, the mapping be-
tween the different sources of predicate informa-
tion is far from being complete. However, the
existing aligments also offer a very interesting
source of information to be systematically ex-
ploited. In fact, we are devising a number of sim-
ple automatic methods to extend SemLink by ex-
ploiting simple properties from WordNet. As a
proof-of-concept, we present in this section two
very simple approaches to extend the coverage
of the mapping between VerbNet predicates and
</bodyText>
<footnote confidence="0.949687333333333">
12http://verbs.colorado.edu/verb-index/
vn/learn-14.php#learn-14-1
13http://verbs.colorado.edu/verb-index/
vn/comprehend-87.2.php#comprehend-87.2-1
14https://framenet2.icsi.berkeley.edu/
fnReports/data/frame/Grasp.xml
</footnote>
<bodyText confidence="0.999566642857143">
WordNet senses. Moreover, we also plan to use
additional semantic resources that use WordNet
as a backbone. For instance, exploiting those
knowledge resources integrated into the Multi-
lingual Central Repository15 (MCR) (Atserias et
al., 2004; Gonzalez-Agirre et al., 2012a) to ex-
tend automatically the aligment of the different
sources of predicate information (VerbNet, Prop-
Bank, FrameNet and WordNet). Following the
line of previous works, in order to assign more
WordNet verb senses to VerbNet predicates, we
also plan to apply more sophisticated word-sense
disambiguation algorithms to semantically coher-
ent groups of predicates (Laparra et al., 2010).
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.988376">
5.1 VerbNet Monosemous predicates
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99972175">
Monosemous verbs from WordNet can be di-
rectly assigned to VerbNet predicates still with-
out a WordNet aligment. This very simple strat-
egy solves 240 aligments. In this way, VerbNet
predicates such as divulgev, exhumev, mutatev or
uploadv obtain a corresponding WordNet word
sense16. Remember that only 576 lemmas from
VerbNet were not aligned to WordNet.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.999565">
5.2 WordNet synonyms
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9992632">
A very straightforward method to extend the map-
ping between WordNet and VerbNet consists on
including synonyms of already aligned Word-
Net senses as new members of the correspond-
ing VerbNet class. Obviously, this method expects
that WordNet synomyms share the same predicate
information. For instance, the predicate desertv
member of the VerbNet class leave-51.2-1 appears
to be assigned to desert%2:31:00 WordNet verbal
sense. In WordNet, this word sense also has three
synonyms, abandonv, forsakev and desolatev. Ob-
viously, these three verbal senses can also be as-
signed to the same VerbNet class. This simple
approach can create up to 5,075 new members
of VerbNet classes (corresponding to 4,616 differ-
ent WordNet word senses). For instance, Table 9
presents two productive examples. Moreover, ap-
plying this method 103 VerbNet predicates with-
out mapping to WordNet in SemLink are aligned
to a WordNet word sense.
</bodyText>
<footnote confidence="0.875888333333333">
15http://adimen.si.ehu.es/MCR
16Obviously, these aligments can be considered just as sug-
estions to be revised later on manually.
</footnote>
<table confidence="0.890326125">
VerbNet WordNet New
abandon%2:31:00::
leave-51.2.1 desert%2:31:00 forsake%2:31:00::
desolate%2:31:00::
abjure%2:32:00::
remove-10.1 retract%2:32:00 recant%2:32:00::
forswear%2:32:00::
resile%2:32:00::
</table>
<tableCaption confidence="0.998451">
Table 9: New WordNet senses aligned to VerbNet
</tableCaption>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.959441" genericHeader="method">
6 A first version of the Predicate Matrix
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.978252916666667">
We already produced a preliminary version of the
Predicate Matrix17. The original SemLink in a
Predicate Matrix form resulted in 36,174 rows
(corresponding to 6,556 WordNet word senses).
By applying the synonyms method described in
the previous section the Predicate Matrix extended
to 69,508 rows (10,984 WordNet word senses). Fi-
nally, by applying the monosemous method, the
Predicate Matrix further extended to 70,391 rows
(11,146 WordNet word senses).
Table 10 presents a full example of the infor-
mation that is currently available in the Predi-
cate Matrix including the new mappings obtained
by the methods described in the previous section.
Each row of this Table represents the mapping of
a role over the different resources and includes
all the aligned knowledge about its correspond-
ing verb. The Table presents the cases obtained
originally from SemLink, denoted as SEMLINK,
and the cases inferred following the methods ex-
plained previously, identified as SYNONYMS or
MONOSEMIC depending on the case. The Ta-
ble also includes the following fields: the lemma
and the class in VerbNet, the sense of the verb in
WordNet, the thematic-role in VerbNet, the Frame
of FrameNet, the corresponding lexical-entry and
frame-element of FrameNet, the predicate in Prop-
Bank and its argument, the offset of the sense in
WordNet and the knowledge associated with that
sense in the MCR, such as the Adimen-SUMO
( ´Alvez et al., 2012) and the new WordNet domain
aligned to WordNet 3.0 (Gonz´alez-Agirre et al.,
2012b) features as well as the Base Level Concept
(Izquierdo et al., 2007) of the sense. Finaly, each
line also includes the frequency and the number of
relations of the WordNet word sense.
</bodyText>
<footnote confidence="0.9558455">
17http://adimen.si.ehu.es/web/
PredicateMatrix
</footnote>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.707691" genericHeader="conclusions">
7 Conclusions and future work
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999988210526316">
We are now producing and studying initial ver-
sions of the Predicate Matrix by exploiting Sem-
Link and applying very simple methods to extend
and validate its content. By developping more ad-
vanced versions of the Predicate Matrix, we ex-
pect to provide a more robust and interoperable
predicate lexicon. We plan to discover and solve
inherent inconsistencies among the integrated re-
sources. Moreover, we plan to extend the cover-
age of current predicate resources (by including
from WordNet morphologically related nominal
and verbal concepts, by exploiting also FrameNet
information, etc.), to enrich WordNet with pred-
icate information, and possibly to extend predi-
cate information to languages other than English
(by exploiting the local wordnets aligned to the
English WordNet) and predicate information from
other languages. For instance, the Ancora Spanish
corpus and lexicon (Taul´e et al., 2008).
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.945443" genericHeader="acknowledgments">
Acknowledgment
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9989862">
We are grateful to the anonymous reviewers
for their insightful comments. This work has
been partially funded by SKaTer (TIN2012-
38584-C06-02), OpeNER (FP7-ICT-2011-SME-
DCL-296451) and NewsReader (FP7-ICT-2011-
8-316404), as well as the READERS project
with the financial support of MINECO, ANR
(convention ANR-12-CHRI-0004-03) and EPSRC
(EP/K017845/1) in the framework of ERA-NET
CHIST-ERA (UE FP7/2007-2013).
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.998515" genericHeader="references">
References
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.975204449275363">
Javier ´Alvez, Paqui Lucio, and German Rigau. 2012.
Adimen-sumo: Reengineering an ontology for first-
order reasoning. International Journal on Seman-
tic Web and Information Systems (IJSWIS), 8(4):80–
116.
Jordi Atserias, Luis Villarejo, German Rigau, Eneko
Agirre, John Carroll, Bernardo Magnini, and Piek
Vossen. 2004. The meaning multilingual central
repository. In Proceedings of GWC, Brno, Czech
Republic.
Collin F. Baker, Charles J. Fillmore, and John B. Lowe.
1997. The berkeley framenet project. In COL-
ING/ACL’98, Montreal, Canada.
Christian Bizer, Jens Lehmann, Georgi Kobilarov,
S¨oren Auer, Christian Becker, Richard Cyganiak,
and Sebastian Hellmann. 2009. Dbpedia-a crys-
tallization point for the web of data. Web Seman-
tics: Science, Services and Agents on the World Wide
Web, 7(3):154–165.
Kurt Bollacker, Colin Evans, Praveen Paritosh, Tim
Sturge, and Jamie Taylor. 2008. Freebase: a col-
laboratively created graph database for structuring
human knowledge. In Proceedings of the 2008 ACM
SIGMOD international conference on Management
of data, pages 1247–1250. ACM.
Aljoscha Burchardt, Katrin Erk, and Anette Frank.
2005. A WordNet Detour to FrameNet. In Pro-
ceedings of the GLDV 2005 GermaNet II Workshop,
pages 408–421, Bonn, Germany.
Diego De Cao, Danilo Croce, Marco Pennacchiotti,
and Roberto Basili. 2008. Combining word sense
and usage for modeling frame semantics. In Pro-
ceedings of The Symposium on Semantics in Systems
for Text Processing (STEP 2008), Venice, Italy.
Katrin Erk and Sebastian Pado. 2004. A powerful and
versatile xml format for representing role-semantic
annotation. In Proceedings of LREC-2004, Lisbon.
Christiane Fellbaum, editor. 1998. WordNet. An Elec-
tronic Lexical Database. The MIT Press.
Charles J. Fillmore. 1976. Frame semantics and the
nature of language. In Annals of the New York
Academy of Sciences: Conference on the Origin and
Development of Language and Speech, volume 280,
pages 20–32, New York.
Ana-Maria Giuglea and Alessandro Moschitti. 2006.
Semantic role labeling via framenet, verbnet and
propbank. In Proceedings of COLING-ACL 2006,
pages 929–936, Morristown, NJ, USA. ACL.
Aitor Gonzalez-Agirre, Egoitz Laparra, and German
Rigau. 2012a. Multilingual central repository ver-
sion 3.0. In LREC, pages 2525–2529.
Aitor Gonz´alez-Agirre, German Rigau, and Mauro
Castillo. 2012b. A graph-based method to im-
prove wordnet domains. In CICLING, pages 17–28.
Springer.
Iryna Gurevych, Judith Eckle-Kohler, Silvana Hart-
mann, Michael Matuschek, Christian M Meyer, and
Christian Wirth. 2012. Uby: A large-scale unified
lexical-semantic resource based on lmf. In Proceed-
ings of EACL, pages 580–590.
Rub´en Izquierdo, Armando Su´arez, and German Rigau.
2007. Exploring the automatic selection of basic
level concepts. In Proceedings of RANLP, volume 7.
Citeseer.
Richard Johansson and Pierre Nugues. 2007. Using
WordNet to extend FrameNet coverage. In Proceed-
ings of the Workshop on Building Frame-semantic
Resources for Scandinavian and Baltic Languages,
at NODALIDA, Tartu, Estonia, May 24.
</reference>
<table confidence="0.999465983333333">
VERSION VN LEMA VN CLASS WN SENSE VN THEMROLE FN FRAME FN LEXENT FN ROLE PB ROLESET PB ARG MCR iliOffset MCR SUMO MCR Domain WN BLC WN SENSEFREC WN SYNSET REL NUM SEMLINK stutter 37.3 stutter%2:32:00 Agent Communication manner 565 Speaker stutter.01 0 ili-30-00981544-v Communication factotum speak%2:32:00 2 006 Table 10: Partial view of the current content of the Predicate Matrix
SEMLINK stutter 37.3 stutter%2:32:00 Recipient Communication manner 565 Addressee stutter.01 2 ili-30-00981544-v Communication factotum speak%2:32:00 2 006
SEMLINK stutter 37.3 stutter%2:32:00 Topic Communication manner 565 Message stutter.01 1 ili-30-00981544-v Communication factotum speak%2:32:00 2 006
SEMLINK stutter 37.3 stutter%2:32:00 Topic Communication manner 565 Topic stutter.01 1 ili-30-00981544-v Communication factotum speak%2:32:00 2 006
SEMLINK stammer 37.3 stammer%2:32:00 Agent Communication manner 564 Speaker NULL NULL ili-30-00981544-v Communication factotum speak%2:32:00 6 006
SEMLINK stammer 37.3 stammer%2:32:00 Recipient Communication manner 564 Addressee NULL NULL ili-30-00981544-v Communication factotum speak%2:32:00 6 006
SEMLINK stammer 37.3 stammer%2:32:00 Topic Communication manner 564 Message NULL NULL ili-30-00981544-v Communication factotum speak%2:32:00 6 006
SEMLINK stammer 37.3 stammer%2:32:00 Topic Communication manner 564 Topic NULL NULL ili-30-00981544-v Communication factotum speak%2:32:00 6 006
SYNONYMS bumble 37.3 bumble%2:32:00 Agent Communication manner 565 Speaker stutter.01 0 ili-30-00981544-v Communication factotum speak%2:32:00 2 006
SYNONYMS bumble 37.3 bumble%2:32:00 Recipient Communication manner 565 Addressee stutter.01 2 ili-30-00981544-v Communication factotum speak%2:32:00 2 006
SYNONYMS bumble 37.3 bumble%2:32:00 Topic Communication manner 565 Message stutter.01 1 ili-30-00981544-v Communication factotum speak%2:32:00 2 006
SYNONYMS bumble 37.3 bumble%2:32:00 Topic Communication manner 565 Topic stutter.01 1 ili-30-00981544-v Communication factotum speak%2:32:00 2 006
SYNONYMS bumble 37.3 bumble%2:32:00 Agent Communication manner 564 Speaker NULL NULL ili-30-00981544-v Communication factotum speak%2:32:00 6 006
SYNONYMS bumble 37.3 bumble%2:32:00 Recipient Communication manner 564 Addressee NULL NULL ili-30-00981544-v Communication factotum speak%2:32:00 6 006
SYNONYMS bumble 37.3 bumble%2:32:00 Topic Communication manner 564 Message NULL NULL ili-30-00981544-v Communication factotum speak%2:32:00 6 006
SYNONYMS bumble 37.3 bumble%2:32:00 Topic Communication manner 564 Topic NULL NULL ili-30-00981544-v Communication factotum speak%2:32:00 6 006
SYNONYMS falter 37.3 falter%2:32:00 Agent Communication manner 565 Speaker stutter.01 0 ili-30-00981544-v Communication factotum speak%2:32:00 2 006
SYNONYMS falter 37.3 falter%2:32:00 Recipient Communication manner 565 Addressee stutter.01 2 ili-30-00981544-v Communication factotum speak%2:32:00 2 006
SYNONYMS falter 37.3 falter%2:32:00 Topic Communication manner 565 Message stutter.01 1 ili-30-00981544-v Communication factotum speak%2:32:00 2 006
SYNONYMS falter 37.3 falter%2:32:00 Topic Communication manner 565 Topic stutter.01 1 ili-30-00981544-v Communication factotum speak%2:32:00 2 006
SYNONYMS falter 37.3 falter%2:32:00 Agent Communication manner 564 Speaker NULL NULL ili-30-00981544-v Communication factotum speak%2:32:00 6 006
SYNONYMS falter 37.3 falter%2:32:00 Recipient Communication manner 564 Addressee NULL NULL ili-30-00981544-v Communication factotum speak%2:32:00 6 006
SYNONYMS falter 37.3 falter%2:32:00 Topic Communication manner 564 Message NULL NULL ili-30-00981544-v Communication factotum speak%2:32:00 6 006
SYNONYMS falter 37.3 falter%2:32:00 Topic Communication manner 564 Topic NULL NULL ili-30-00981544-v Communication factotum speak%2:32:00 6 006
SEMLINK squeak 37.3 squeak%2:39:00 Agent Communication noise 612 Speaker squeak.01 0 ili-30-02171664-v SoundAttribute factotum sound%2:39:00 3 007
SEMLINK squeak 37.3 squeak%2:39:00 Recipient Communication noise 612 Addressee squeak.01 NULL ili-30-02171664-v SoundAttribute factotum sound%2:39:00 3 007
SEMLINK squeak 37.3 squeak%2:39:00 Topic Communication noise 612 Message squeak.01 1 ili-30-02171664-v SoundAttribute factotum sound%2:39:00 3 007
SEMLINK squeak 37.3 squeak%2:39:00 Topic Communication noise 612 Topic squeak.01 1 ili-30-02171664-v SoundAttribute factotum sound%2:39:00 3 007
SEMLINK screech 37.3 screech%2:39:00 Agent Communication noise 604 Speaker screech.03 0 ili-30-02171664-v SoundAttribute factotum sound%2:39:00 5 007
SEMLINK screech 37.3 screech%2:39:00 Recipient Communication noise 604 Addressee screech.03 2 ili-30-02171664-v SoundAttribute factotum sound%2:39:00 5 007
SEMLINK screech 37.3 screech%2:39:00 Topic Communication noise 604 Message screech.03 1 ili-30-02171664-v SoundAttribute factotum sound%2:39:00 5 007
SEMLINK screech 37.3 screech%2:39:00 Topic Communication noise 604 Topic screech.03 1 ili-30-02171664-v SoundAttribute factotum sound%2:39:00 5 007
SYNONYMS screak 37.3 screak%2:39:00 Agent Communication noise 612 Speaker squeak.01 0 ili-30-02171664-v SoundAttribute factotum sound%2:39:00 3 007
SYNONYMS screak 37.3 screak%2:39:00 Recipient Communication noise 612 Addressee squeak.01 NULL ili-30-02171664-v SoundAttribute factotum sound%2:39:00 3 007
SYNONYMS screak 37.3 screak%2:39:00 Topic Communication noise 612 Message squeak.01 1 ili-30-02171664-v SoundAttribute factotum sound%2:39:00 3 007
SYNONYMS screak 37.3 screak%2:39:00 Topic Communication noise 612 Topic squeak.01 1 ili-30-02171664-v SoundAttribute factotum sound%2:39:00 3 007
SYNONYMS screak 37.3 screak%2:39:00 Recipient Communication noise 604 Addressee screech.03 2 ili-30-02171664-v SoundAttribute factotum sound%2:39:00 5 007
SYNONYMS screak 37.3 screak%2:39:00 Topic Communication noise 604 Message screech.03 1 ili-30-02171664-v SoundAttribute factotum sound%2:39:00 5 007
SYNONYMS screak 37.3 screak%2:39:00 Topic Communication noise 604 Topic screech.03 1 ili-30-02171664-v SoundAttribute factotum sound%2:39:00 5 007
SYNONYMS screak 37.3 screak%2:39:00 Agent Communication noise 604 Speaker screech.03 0 ili-30-02171664-v SoundAttribute factotum sound%2:39:00 5 007
SYNONYMS whine 37.3 whine%2:39:00 Agent Communication noise 612 Speaker squeak.01 0 ili-30-02171664-v SoundAttribute factotum sound%2:39:00 3 007
SYNONYMS whine 37.3 whine%2:39:00 Recipient Communication noise 612 Addressee squeak.01 NULL ili-30-02171664-v SoundAttribute factotum sound%2:39:00 3 007
SYNONYMS whine 37.3 whine%2:39:00 Topic Communication noise 612 Message squeak.01 1 ili-30-02171664-v SoundAttribute factotum sound%2:39:00 3 007
SYNONYMS whine 37.3 whine%2:39:00 Topic Communication noise 612 Topic squeak.01 1 ili-30-02171664-v SoundAttribute factotum sound%2:39:00 3 007
SYNONYMS whine 37.3 whine%2:39:00 Agent Communication noise 604 Speaker screech.03 0 ili-30-02171664-v SoundAttribute factotum sound%2:39:00 5 007
SYNONYMS whine 37.3 whine%2:39:00 Recipient Communication noise 604 Addressee screech.03 2 ili-30-02171664-v SoundAttribute factotum sound%2:39:00 5 007
SYNONYMS whine 37.3 whine%2:39:00 Topic Communication noise 604 Message screech.03 1 ili-30-02171664-v SoundAttribute factotum sound%2:39:00 5 007
SYNONYMS whine 37.3 whine%2:39:00 Topic Communication noise 604 Topic screech.03 1 ili-30-02171664-v SoundAttribute factotum sound%2:39:00 5 007
MONOSEMIC natter 37.3 natter%2:32:00 Agent Communication manner 547 Speaker chatter.01 0 ili-30-01038666-v Communication factotum communicate%2:32:00 1 011
MONOSEMIC natter 37.3 natter%2:32:00 Topic Communication manner 547 Message chatter.01 1 ili-30-01038666-v Communication factotum communicate%2:32:00 1 011
MONOSEMIC natter 37.3 natter%2:32:00 Topic Communication manner 547 Topic chatter.01 1 ili-30-01038666-v Communication factotum communicate%2:32:00 1 011
MONOSEMIC natter 37.3 natter%2:32:00 Recipient Communication manner 547 Addressee chatter.01 NULL ili-30-01038666-v Communication factotum communicate%2:32:00 1 011
MONOSEMIC prattle 37.3 prattle%2:32:00 Agent Communication manner 547 Speaker chatter.01 0 ili-30-01036804-v Communication factotum speak%2:32:00 1 015
MONOSEMIC prattle 37.3 prattle%2:32:00 Topic Communication manner 547 Message chatter.01 1 ili-30-01036804-v Communication factotum speak%2:32:00 1 015
MONOSEMIC prattle 37.3 prattle%2:32:00 Topic Communication manner 547 Topic chatter.01 1 ili-30-01036804-v Communication factotum speak%2:32:00 1 015
MONOSEMIC prattle 37.3 prattle%2:32:00 Recipient Communication manner 547 Addressee chatter.01 NULL ili-30-01036804-v Communication factotum speak%2:32:00 1 015
MONOSEMIC rant 37.3 rant%2:32:00 Agent Communication manner 551 Speaker jabber.01 0 ili-30-01051956-v Communication factotum speak%2:32:00 2 011
MONOSEMIC rant 37.3 rant%2:32:00 Topic Communication manner 551 Message jabber.01 1 ili-30-01051956-v Communication factotum speak%2:32:00 2 011
MONOSEMIC rant 37.3 rant%2:32:00 Topic Communication manner 551 Topic jabber.01 1 ili-30-01051956-v Communication factotum speak%2:32:00 2 011
MONOSEMIC rant 37.3 rant%2:32:00 Recipient Communication manner 551 Addressee jabber.01 2 ili-30-01051956-v Communication factotum speak%2:32:00 2 011
</table>
<reference confidence="0.999613557692308">
Karen Kipper. 2005. VerbNet: A broad-coverage,
comprehensive verb lexicon. Ph.D. thesis, Univer-
sity of Pennsylvania.
Egoitz Laparra and German Rigau. 2013. Impar: A
deterministic algorithm for implicit semantic role la-
belling. In Proceedings of the 51st Annual Meet-
ing of the Association for Computational Linguistics
(ACL 2013), pages 33–41.
Egoitz Laparra, German Rigau, and Montse Cuadros.
2010. Exploring the integration of wordnet and
framenet. In Proceedings of the 5th Global Word-
Net Conference (GWC 2010), Mumbai, India.
Beth Levin. 1993. English verb classes and alter-
nations: A preliminary investigation, volume 348.
University of Chicago press Chicago.
Roberto Navigli and Simone Paolo Ponzetto. 2010.
Babelnet: Building a very large multilingual seman-
tic network. In Proceedings of the 48th annual meet-
ing of ACL, pages 216–225.
Martha Palmer, Daniel Gildea, and Paul Kingsbury.
2005. The proposition bank: An annotated cor-
pus of semantic roles. Computational Linguistics,
31(1):71–106, March.
Martha Palmer. 2009. Semlink: Linking propbank,
verbnet and framenet. In Proceedings of the Gener-
ative Lexicon Conference, pages 9–15.
Marco Pennacchiotti, Diego De Cao, Roberto Basili,
Danilo Croce, and Michael Roth. 2008. Automatic
induction of FrameNet lexical units. In Proceedings
of EMNLP.
Dan Shen and Mirella Lapata. 2007. Using semantic
roles to improve question answering. In Proceed-
ings of the Joint Conference on (EMNLP-CoNLL),
pages 12–21.
Lei Shi and Rada Mihalcea. 2005. Putting pieces to-
gether: Combining framenet, verbnet and wordnet
for robust semantic parsing. In Proceedings of CI-
CLing, Mexico.
Carlos Subirats and Miriam R.L. Petruck. 2003. Sur-
prise: Spanish framenet! In Proceedings of the In-
ternational Congress of Linguists, Praga.
Fabian M. Suchanek, Gjergji Kasneci, and Gerhard
Weikum. 2007. Yago: A Core of Semantic Knowl-
edge. In WWW conference, New York, NY, USA.
ACM Press.
Mariona Taul´e, Maria Ant`onia Mart´ı, and Marta Re-
casens. 2008. Ancora: Multilevel annotated corpora
for catalan and spanish. In LREC.
Sara Tonelli and Emanuele Pianta. 2009. A novel ap-
proach to mapping framenet lexical units to word-
net synsets. In Proceedings of IWCS-8, Tilburg, The
Netherlands.
</reference>
</variant>
</algorithm>
<algorithm name="ParsHed" version="110505">
<variant no="0" confidence="0.256960">
<title confidence="0.994148">First steps towards a Predicate Matrix</title>
<author confidence="0.989202">Maddalen L´opez de_Lacalle Egoitz Laparra German Rigau</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.951094">IXA group, UPV/EHU IXA group, UPV/EHU IXA group, UPV/EHU</affiliation>
<address confidence="0.67017">Donostia, Spain Donostia, Spain Donostia, Spain</address>
<email confidence="0.669718">maddalen.lopezdelacalle@ehu.esegoitz.laparra@ehu.esgerman.rigau@ehu.es</email>
<abstract confidence="0.995944894736842">This paper presents the first steps towards building the Predicate Matrix, a new lexical resource resulting from the integration of multiple sources of predicate information including FrameNet (Baker et al., 1997), VerbNet (Kipper, 2005), PropBank (Palmer et al., 2005) and WordNet (Fellbaum, 1998). By using the Predicate Matrix, we expect to provide a more robust interoperable lexicon by discovering and solving inherent inconsistencies among the resources. Moreover, we plan to extend the coverage of current predicate resources (by including from WordNet morphologically related nominal and verbal concepts), to enrich WordNet with predicate information, and possibly to extend predicate information to languages other than English (by exploiting the local wordnets aligned to the English</abstract>
<intro confidence="0.569638">WordNet).</intro>
</variant>
</algorithm>
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Javier ´Alvez</author>
<author>Paqui Lucio</author>
<author>German Rigau</author>
</authors>
<title>Adimen-sumo: Reengineering an ontology for firstorder reasoning.</title>
<date>2012</date>
<booktitle>International Journal on Semantic Web and Information Systems (IJSWIS),</booktitle>
<volume>8</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<pages>116</pages>
<marker>´Alvez, Lucio, Rigau, 2012</marker>
<rawString>Javier ´Alvez, Paqui Lucio, and German Rigau. 2012. Adimen-sumo: Reengineering an ontology for firstorder reasoning. International Journal on Semantic Web and Information Systems (IJSWIS), 8(4):80– 116.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Jordi Atserias</author>
<author>Luis Villarejo</author>
<author>German Rigau</author>
<author>Eneko Agirre</author>
<author>John Carroll</author>
<author>Bernardo Magnini</author>
<author>Piek Vossen</author>
</authors>
<title>The meaning multilingual central repository.</title>
<date>2004</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of GWC,</booktitle>
<location>Brno, Czech Republic.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="20469" citStr="Atserias et al., 2004" startWordPosition="3131" endWordPosition="3134">s from WordNet. As a proof-of-concept, we present in this section two very simple approaches to extend the coverage of the mapping between VerbNet predicates and 12http://verbs.colorado.edu/verb-index/ vn/learn-14.php#learn-14-1 13http://verbs.colorado.edu/verb-index/ vn/comprehend-87.2.php#comprehend-87.2-1 14https://framenet2.icsi.berkeley.edu/ fnReports/data/frame/Grasp.xml WordNet senses. Moreover, we also plan to use additional semantic resources that use WordNet as a backbone. For instance, exploiting those knowledge resources integrated into the Multilingual Central Repository15 (MCR) (Atserias et al., 2004; Gonzalez-Agirre et al., 2012a) to extend automatically the aligment of the different sources of predicate information (VerbNet, PropBank, FrameNet and WordNet). Following the line of previous works, in order to assign more WordNet verb senses to VerbNet predicates, we also plan to apply more sophisticated word-sense disambiguation algorithms to semantically coherent groups of predicates (Laparra et al., 2010). 5.1 VerbNet Monosemous predicates Monosemous verbs from WordNet can be directly assigned to VerbNet predicates still without a WordNet aligment. This very simple strategy solves 240 al</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Atserias, Villarejo, Rigau, Agirre, Carroll, Magnini, Vossen, 2004</marker>
<rawString>Jordi Atserias, Luis Villarejo, German Rigau, Eneko Agirre, John Carroll, Bernardo Magnini, and Piek Vossen. 2004. The meaning multilingual central repository. In Proceedings of GWC, Brno, Czech Republic.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Collin F Baker</author>
<author>Charles J Fillmore</author>
<author>John B Lowe</author>
</authors>
<title>The berkeley framenet project.</title>
<date>1997</date>
<booktitle>In COLING/ACL’98,</booktitle>
<location>Montreal, Canada.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="1154" citStr="Baker et al., 1997" startWordPosition="161" endWordPosition="164">r et al., 2005) and WordNet (Fellbaum, 1998). By using the Predicate Matrix, we expect to provide a more robust interoperable lexicon by discovering and solving inherent inconsistencies among the resources. Moreover, we plan to extend the coverage of current predicate resources (by including from WordNet morphologically related nominal and verbal concepts), to enrich WordNet with predicate information, and possibly to extend predicate information to languages other than English (by exploiting the local wordnets aligned to the English WordNet). 1 Introduction Predicate models such as FrameNet (Baker et al., 1997), VerbNet (Kipper, 2005) or PropBank (Palmer et al., 2005) are core resources in most advanced NLP tasks, such as Question Answering, Textual Entailment or Information Extraction. Most of the systems with Natural Language Understanding capabilities require a large and precise amount of semantic knowledge at the predicateargument level. This type of knowledge allows to identify the underlying typical participants of a particular event independently of its realization in the text. Thus, using these models, different linguistic phenomena expressing the same event, such as active/passive transform</context>
<context position="3612" citStr="Baker et al., 1997" startWordPosition="532" endWordPosition="535">own examples are YAGO (Suchanek et al., 2007), Freebase (Bollacker et al., 2008), DBPedia (Bizer et al., 2009), BabelNet (Navigli and Ponzetto, 2010) or UBY (Gurevych et al., 2012). Following the line of previous works (Shi and Mihalcea, 2005), (Burchardt et al., 2005), (Johansson and Nugues, 2007), (Pennacchiotti et al., 2008), (Cao et al., 2008), (Tonelli and Pianta, 2009), (Laparra et al., 2010), we will also focus on the integration of predicate information. We start from the basis of SemLink (Palmer, 2009). SemLink aimed to connect together different predicate resources such as FrameNet (Baker et al., 1997), VerbNet (Kipper, 2005), PropBank (Palmer et al., 2005) and WordNet (Fellbaum, 1998). However, its coverage is still far from complete. The Predicate Matrix, the resource resulting from the work presented in this paper, will allow to extend the coverage of current predicate resources (by including from WordNet closely related nominal and verbal concepts), to discover inherent inconsistencies among the resources, to enrich WordNet with predicate information, and possibly to extend predicate information to languages other than English (by exploiting the local wordnets aligned to the English Wor</context>
<context position="5546" citStr="Baker et al., 1997" startWordPosition="836" endWordPosition="839"> Predicate information As a starting point for building the Predicate Matrix, we consider the sources of predicate knowledge connected to SemLink. SemLink1 (Palmer, 2009) is a project whose aim is to link together different predicate resources establishing a set of mappings. These mappings make it possible to combine the different information provided by the different lexical resources for tasks such as inferencing, consistency checking, interoperable semantic role labelling, etc. Currently, SemLink provides partial mappings to VerbNet (Kipper, 2005), PropBank (Palmer et al., 2005), FrameNet (Baker et al., 1997) and WordNet (Fellbaum, 1998). FrameNet 2 (Baker et al., 1997) is a very rich semantic resource that contains descriptions and corpus annotations of English words following the paradigm of Frame Semantics (Fillmore, 1976). In frame semantics, a Frame corresponds to a scenario that involves the interaction of a set of typical participants, playing a particular role in the scenario. FrameNet groups words or lexical-units (LUs hereinafter) into coherent semantic classes or frames, and each frame is further characterized by a list of participants or frame-elements (FEs hereinafter). Different sens</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Baker, Fillmore, Lowe, 1997</marker>
<rawString>Collin F. Baker, Charles J. Fillmore, and John B. Lowe. 1997. The berkeley framenet project. In COLING/ACL’98, Montreal, Canada.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Christian Bizer</author>
<author>Jens Lehmann</author>
<author>Georgi Kobilarov</author>
<author>S¨oren Auer</author>
<author>Christian Becker</author>
<author>Richard Cyganiak</author>
<author>Sebastian Hellmann</author>
</authors>
<title>Dbpedia-a crystallization point for the web of data. Web Semantics: Science, Services and Agents on the World Wide Web,</title>
<date>2009</date>
<volume>7</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<contexts>
<context position="3103" citStr="Bizer et al., 2009" startWordPosition="451" endWordPosition="454"> or (Shen and Lapata, 2007) indicate the limited coverage of FrameNet as one of the main problems of this resource. In fact, FrameNet1.5 covers around 10,000 lexical-units while for instance, WordNet3.0 contains more than 150,000 words. Furthermore, the same effort should be invested for each different language (Subirats and Petruck, 2003). Moreover, most previous research efforts on the integration of resources targeted at knowledge about nouns and named entities rather than predicate knowledge. Well known examples are YAGO (Suchanek et al., 2007), Freebase (Bollacker et al., 2008), DBPedia (Bizer et al., 2009), BabelNet (Navigli and Ponzetto, 2010) or UBY (Gurevych et al., 2012). Following the line of previous works (Shi and Mihalcea, 2005), (Burchardt et al., 2005), (Johansson and Nugues, 2007), (Pennacchiotti et al., 2008), (Cao et al., 2008), (Tonelli and Pianta, 2009), (Laparra et al., 2010), we will also focus on the integration of predicate information. We start from the basis of SemLink (Palmer, 2009). SemLink aimed to connect together different predicate resources such as FrameNet (Baker et al., 1997), VerbNet (Kipper, 2005), PropBank (Palmer et al., 2005) and WordNet (Fellbaum, 1998). Howe</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Bizer, Lehmann, Kobilarov, Auer, Becker, Cyganiak, Hellmann, 2009</marker>
<rawString>Christian Bizer, Jens Lehmann, Georgi Kobilarov, S¨oren Auer, Christian Becker, Richard Cyganiak, and Sebastian Hellmann. 2009. Dbpedia-a crystallization point for the web of data. Web Semantics: Science, Services and Agents on the World Wide Web, 7(3):154–165.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Kurt Bollacker</author>
<author>Colin Evans</author>
<author>Praveen Paritosh</author>
<author>Tim Sturge</author>
<author>Jamie Taylor</author>
</authors>
<title>Freebase: a collaboratively created graph database for structuring human knowledge.</title>
<date>2008</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 2008 ACM SIGMOD international conference on Management of data,</booktitle>
<pages>1247--1250</pages>
<publisher>ACM.</publisher>
<contexts>
<context position="3073" citStr="Bollacker et al., 2008" startWordPosition="445" endWordPosition="449"> example, (Burchardt et al., 2005) or (Shen and Lapata, 2007) indicate the limited coverage of FrameNet as one of the main problems of this resource. In fact, FrameNet1.5 covers around 10,000 lexical-units while for instance, WordNet3.0 contains more than 150,000 words. Furthermore, the same effort should be invested for each different language (Subirats and Petruck, 2003). Moreover, most previous research efforts on the integration of resources targeted at knowledge about nouns and named entities rather than predicate knowledge. Well known examples are YAGO (Suchanek et al., 2007), Freebase (Bollacker et al., 2008), DBPedia (Bizer et al., 2009), BabelNet (Navigli and Ponzetto, 2010) or UBY (Gurevych et al., 2012). Following the line of previous works (Shi and Mihalcea, 2005), (Burchardt et al., 2005), (Johansson and Nugues, 2007), (Pennacchiotti et al., 2008), (Cao et al., 2008), (Tonelli and Pianta, 2009), (Laparra et al., 2010), we will also focus on the integration of predicate information. We start from the basis of SemLink (Palmer, 2009). SemLink aimed to connect together different predicate resources such as FrameNet (Baker et al., 1997), VerbNet (Kipper, 2005), PropBank (Palmer et al., 2005) and </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Bollacker, Evans, Paritosh, Sturge, Taylor, 2008</marker>
<rawString>Kurt Bollacker, Colin Evans, Praveen Paritosh, Tim Sturge, and Jamie Taylor. 2008. Freebase: a collaboratively created graph database for structuring human knowledge. In Proceedings of the 2008 ACM SIGMOD international conference on Management of data, pages 1247–1250. ACM.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Aljoscha Burchardt</author>
<author>Katrin Erk</author>
<author>Anette Frank</author>
</authors>
<title>A WordNet Detour to FrameNet.</title>
<date>2005</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the GLDV 2005 GermaNet II Workshop,</booktitle>
<pages>408--421</pages>
<location>Bonn, Germany.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="2484" citStr="Burchardt et al., 2005" startWordPosition="356" endWordPosition="359">representation. In fact, lately, several systems have been developed for shallow semantic parsing an explicit and implicit semantic role labeling using these resources (Erk and Pado, 2004), (Shi and Mihalcea, 2005), (Giuglea and Moschitti, 2006), (Laparra and Rigau, 2013). However, building large and rich enough predicate models for broad–coverage semantic processing takes a great deal of expensive manual effort involving large research groups during long periods of development. In fact, the coverage of currently available predicate-argument resources is still far from complete. For example, (Burchardt et al., 2005) or (Shen and Lapata, 2007) indicate the limited coverage of FrameNet as one of the main problems of this resource. In fact, FrameNet1.5 covers around 10,000 lexical-units while for instance, WordNet3.0 contains more than 150,000 words. Furthermore, the same effort should be invested for each different language (Subirats and Petruck, 2003). Moreover, most previous research efforts on the integration of resources targeted at knowledge about nouns and named entities rather than predicate knowledge. Well known examples are YAGO (Suchanek et al., 2007), Freebase (Bollacker et al., 2008), DBPedia (</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Burchardt, Erk, Frank, 2005</marker>
<rawString>Aljoscha Burchardt, Katrin Erk, and Anette Frank. 2005. A WordNet Detour to FrameNet. In Proceedings of the GLDV 2005 GermaNet II Workshop, pages 408–421, Bonn, Germany.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Diego De Cao</author>
<author>Danilo Croce</author>
<author>Marco Pennacchiotti</author>
<author>Roberto Basili</author>
</authors>
<title>Combining word sense and usage for modeling frame semantics.</title>
<date>2008</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of The Symposium on Semantics in Systems for Text Processing (STEP 2008),</booktitle>
<location>Venice, Italy.</location>
<marker>De Cao, Croce, Pennacchiotti, Basili, 2008</marker>
<rawString>Diego De Cao, Danilo Croce, Marco Pennacchiotti, and Roberto Basili. 2008. Combining word sense and usage for modeling frame semantics. In Proceedings of The Symposium on Semantics in Systems for Text Processing (STEP 2008), Venice, Italy.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Katrin Erk</author>
<author>Sebastian Pado</author>
</authors>
<title>A powerful and versatile xml format for representing role-semantic annotation.</title>
<date>2004</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of LREC-2004,</booktitle>
<location>Lisbon.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="2049" citStr="Erk and Pado, 2004" startWordPosition="291" endWordPosition="294"> amount of semantic knowledge at the predicateargument level. This type of knowledge allows to identify the underlying typical participants of a particular event independently of its realization in the text. Thus, using these models, different linguistic phenomena expressing the same event, such as active/passive transformations, verb alternations, nominalizations, implicit realizations can be harmonized into a common semantic representation. In fact, lately, several systems have been developed for shallow semantic parsing an explicit and implicit semantic role labeling using these resources (Erk and Pado, 2004), (Shi and Mihalcea, 2005), (Giuglea and Moschitti, 2006), (Laparra and Rigau, 2013). However, building large and rich enough predicate models for broad–coverage semantic processing takes a great deal of expensive manual effort involving large research groups during long periods of development. In fact, the coverage of currently available predicate-argument resources is still far from complete. For example, (Burchardt et al., 2005) or (Shen and Lapata, 2007) indicate the limited coverage of FrameNet as one of the main problems of this resource. In fact, FrameNet1.5 covers around 10,000 lexical</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Erk, Pado, 2004</marker>
<rawString>Katrin Erk and Sebastian Pado. 2004. A powerful and versatile xml format for representing role-semantic annotation. In Proceedings of LREC-2004, Lisbon.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<title>WordNet. An Electronic Lexical Database.</title>
<date>1998</date>
<editor>Christiane Fellbaum, editor.</editor>
<publisher>The MIT Press.</publisher>
<marker>1998</marker>
<rawString>Christiane Fellbaum, editor. 1998. WordNet. An Electronic Lexical Database. The MIT Press.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Charles J Fillmore</author>
</authors>
<title>Frame semantics and the nature of language.</title>
<date>1976</date>
<booktitle>In Annals of the New York Academy of Sciences: Conference on the Origin and Development of Language and Speech,</booktitle>
<volume>280</volume>
<pages>20--32</pages>
<location>New York.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="5767" citStr="Fillmore, 1976" startWordPosition="872" endWordPosition="873">redicate resources establishing a set of mappings. These mappings make it possible to combine the different information provided by the different lexical resources for tasks such as inferencing, consistency checking, interoperable semantic role labelling, etc. Currently, SemLink provides partial mappings to VerbNet (Kipper, 2005), PropBank (Palmer et al., 2005), FrameNet (Baker et al., 1997) and WordNet (Fellbaum, 1998). FrameNet 2 (Baker et al., 1997) is a very rich semantic resource that contains descriptions and corpus annotations of English words following the paradigm of Frame Semantics (Fillmore, 1976). In frame semantics, a Frame corresponds to a scenario that involves the interaction of a set of typical participants, playing a particular role in the scenario. FrameNet groups words or lexical-units (LUs hereinafter) into coherent semantic classes or frames, and each frame is further characterized by a list of participants or frame-elements (FEs hereinafter). Different senses for a word are represented in FrameNet by assigning different frames. 1http://verbs.colorado.edu/semlink/ 2http://framenet.icsi.berkeley.edu/ PropBank 3 (Palmer et al., 2005) aims to provide a wide corpus annotated wit</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Fillmore, 1976</marker>
<rawString>Charles J. Fillmore. 1976. Frame semantics and the nature of language. In Annals of the New York Academy of Sciences: Conference on the Origin and Development of Language and Speech, volume 280, pages 20–32, New York.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Ana-Maria Giuglea</author>
<author>Alessandro Moschitti</author>
</authors>
<title>Semantic role labeling via framenet, verbnet and propbank.</title>
<date>2006</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of COLING-ACL 2006,</booktitle>
<pages>929--936</pages>
<publisher>ACL.</publisher>
<location>Morristown, NJ, USA.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="2106" citStr="Giuglea and Moschitti, 2006" startWordPosition="299" endWordPosition="302">gument level. This type of knowledge allows to identify the underlying typical participants of a particular event independently of its realization in the text. Thus, using these models, different linguistic phenomena expressing the same event, such as active/passive transformations, verb alternations, nominalizations, implicit realizations can be harmonized into a common semantic representation. In fact, lately, several systems have been developed for shallow semantic parsing an explicit and implicit semantic role labeling using these resources (Erk and Pado, 2004), (Shi and Mihalcea, 2005), (Giuglea and Moschitti, 2006), (Laparra and Rigau, 2013). However, building large and rich enough predicate models for broad–coverage semantic processing takes a great deal of expensive manual effort involving large research groups during long periods of development. In fact, the coverage of currently available predicate-argument resources is still far from complete. For example, (Burchardt et al., 2005) or (Shen and Lapata, 2007) indicate the limited coverage of FrameNet as one of the main problems of this resource. In fact, FrameNet1.5 covers around 10,000 lexical-units while for instance, WordNet3.0 contains more than </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Giuglea, Moschitti, 2006</marker>
<rawString>Ana-Maria Giuglea and Alessandro Moschitti. 2006. Semantic role labeling via framenet, verbnet and propbank. In Proceedings of COLING-ACL 2006, pages 929–936, Morristown, NJ, USA. ACL.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Aitor Gonzalez-Agirre</author>
<author>Egoitz Laparra</author>
<author>German Rigau</author>
</authors>
<title>Multilingual central repository version 3.0. In</title>
<date>2012</date>
<booktitle>LREC,</booktitle>
<pages>2525--2529</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="7555" citStr="Gonzalez-Agirre et al., 2012" startWordPosition="1132" endWordPosition="1135">ish. VerbNet is organized into verb classes extending (Levin, 1993) classes through refinement and addition of subclasses to achieve syntactic and semantic coherence among members of a class. Each verb class in VerbNet is completely described by thematic-roles, selectional restrictions on the arguments, and frames consisting of a syntactic description and semantic predicates. WordNet 5 (Fellbaum, 1998) is by far the most widely-used knowledge base. In fact, WordNet is being used world-wide for anchoring different types of semantic knowledge including wordnets for languages other than English (Gonzalez-Agirre et al., 2012a). It contains manually coded information about English nouns, verbs, adjectives and adverbs and is organized around the notion of a synset. A synset is a set of words with the same part-of-speech that can be interchanged in a certain context. For example, &lt;learn, study, read, take&gt; form a synset because they can be used to refer to the same concept. A synset is often further described by a gloss, in this case: ”be a student of a certain subject” and by explicit semantic relations to other synsets. Each synset represents a concept that are related with an large number of semantic relations, i</context>
<context position="20499" citStr="Gonzalez-Agirre et al., 2012" startWordPosition="3135" endWordPosition="3138">oof-of-concept, we present in this section two very simple approaches to extend the coverage of the mapping between VerbNet predicates and 12http://verbs.colorado.edu/verb-index/ vn/learn-14.php#learn-14-1 13http://verbs.colorado.edu/verb-index/ vn/comprehend-87.2.php#comprehend-87.2-1 14https://framenet2.icsi.berkeley.edu/ fnReports/data/frame/Grasp.xml WordNet senses. Moreover, we also plan to use additional semantic resources that use WordNet as a backbone. For instance, exploiting those knowledge resources integrated into the Multilingual Central Repository15 (MCR) (Atserias et al., 2004; Gonzalez-Agirre et al., 2012a) to extend automatically the aligment of the different sources of predicate information (VerbNet, PropBank, FrameNet and WordNet). Following the line of previous works, in order to assign more WordNet verb senses to VerbNet predicates, we also plan to apply more sophisticated word-sense disambiguation algorithms to semantically coherent groups of predicates (Laparra et al., 2010). 5.1 VerbNet Monosemous predicates Monosemous verbs from WordNet can be directly assigned to VerbNet predicates still without a WordNet aligment. This very simple strategy solves 240 aligments. In this way, VerbNet </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Gonzalez-Agirre, Laparra, Rigau, 2012</marker>
<rawString>Aitor Gonzalez-Agirre, Egoitz Laparra, and German Rigau. 2012a. Multilingual central repository version 3.0. In LREC, pages 2525–2529.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Aitor Gonz´alez-Agirre</author>
<author>German Rigau</author>
<author>Mauro Castillo</author>
</authors>
<title>A graph-based method to improve wordnet domains. In</title>
<date>2012</date>
<booktitle>CICLING,</booktitle>
<pages>17--28</pages>
<publisher>Springer.</publisher>
<marker>Gonz´alez-Agirre, Rigau, Castillo, 2012</marker>
<rawString>Aitor Gonz´alez-Agirre, German Rigau, and Mauro Castillo. 2012b. A graph-based method to improve wordnet domains. In CICLING, pages 17–28. Springer.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Iryna Gurevych</author>
<author>Judith Eckle-Kohler</author>
<author>Silvana Hartmann</author>
<author>Michael Matuschek</author>
<author>Christian M Meyer</author>
<author>Christian Wirth</author>
</authors>
<title>Uby: A large-scale unified lexical-semantic resource based on lmf.</title>
<date>2012</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of EACL,</booktitle>
<pages>580--590</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="3173" citStr="Gurevych et al., 2012" startWordPosition="462" endWordPosition="465">et as one of the main problems of this resource. In fact, FrameNet1.5 covers around 10,000 lexical-units while for instance, WordNet3.0 contains more than 150,000 words. Furthermore, the same effort should be invested for each different language (Subirats and Petruck, 2003). Moreover, most previous research efforts on the integration of resources targeted at knowledge about nouns and named entities rather than predicate knowledge. Well known examples are YAGO (Suchanek et al., 2007), Freebase (Bollacker et al., 2008), DBPedia (Bizer et al., 2009), BabelNet (Navigli and Ponzetto, 2010) or UBY (Gurevych et al., 2012). Following the line of previous works (Shi and Mihalcea, 2005), (Burchardt et al., 2005), (Johansson and Nugues, 2007), (Pennacchiotti et al., 2008), (Cao et al., 2008), (Tonelli and Pianta, 2009), (Laparra et al., 2010), we will also focus on the integration of predicate information. We start from the basis of SemLink (Palmer, 2009). SemLink aimed to connect together different predicate resources such as FrameNet (Baker et al., 1997), VerbNet (Kipper, 2005), PropBank (Palmer et al., 2005) and WordNet (Fellbaum, 1998). However, its coverage is still far from complete. The Predicate Matrix, th</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Gurevych, Eckle-Kohler, Hartmann, Matuschek, Meyer, Wirth, 2012</marker>
<rawString>Iryna Gurevych, Judith Eckle-Kohler, Silvana Hartmann, Michael Matuschek, Christian M Meyer, and Christian Wirth. 2012. Uby: A large-scale unified lexical-semantic resource based on lmf. In Proceedings of EACL, pages 580–590.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Rub´en Izquierdo</author>
<author>Armando Su´arez</author>
<author>German Rigau</author>
</authors>
<title>Exploring the automatic selection of basic level concepts.</title>
<date>2007</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of RANLP,</booktitle>
<volume>7</volume>
<publisher>Citeseer.</publisher>
<marker>Izquierdo, Su´arez, Rigau, 2007</marker>
<rawString>Rub´en Izquierdo, Armando Su´arez, and German Rigau. 2007. Exploring the automatic selection of basic level concepts. In Proceedings of RANLP, volume 7. Citeseer.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Richard Johansson</author>
<author>Pierre Nugues</author>
</authors>
<title>Using WordNet to extend FrameNet coverage.</title>
<date>2007</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the Workshop on Building Frame-semantic Resources for Scandinavian and Baltic Languages, at NODALIDA,</booktitle>
<location>Tartu, Estonia,</location>
<contexts>
<context position="3292" citStr="Johansson and Nugues, 2007" startWordPosition="480" endWordPosition="484"> instance, WordNet3.0 contains more than 150,000 words. Furthermore, the same effort should be invested for each different language (Subirats and Petruck, 2003). Moreover, most previous research efforts on the integration of resources targeted at knowledge about nouns and named entities rather than predicate knowledge. Well known examples are YAGO (Suchanek et al., 2007), Freebase (Bollacker et al., 2008), DBPedia (Bizer et al., 2009), BabelNet (Navigli and Ponzetto, 2010) or UBY (Gurevych et al., 2012). Following the line of previous works (Shi and Mihalcea, 2005), (Burchardt et al., 2005), (Johansson and Nugues, 2007), (Pennacchiotti et al., 2008), (Cao et al., 2008), (Tonelli and Pianta, 2009), (Laparra et al., 2010), we will also focus on the integration of predicate information. We start from the basis of SemLink (Palmer, 2009). SemLink aimed to connect together different predicate resources such as FrameNet (Baker et al., 1997), VerbNet (Kipper, 2005), PropBank (Palmer et al., 2005) and WordNet (Fellbaum, 1998). However, its coverage is still far from complete. The Predicate Matrix, the resource resulting from the work presented in this paper, will allow to extend the coverage of current predicate reso</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Johansson, Nugues, 2007</marker>
<rawString>Richard Johansson and Pierre Nugues. 2007. Using WordNet to extend FrameNet coverage. In Proceedings of the Workshop on Building Frame-semantic Resources for Scandinavian and Baltic Languages, at NODALIDA, Tartu, Estonia, May 24.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Karen Kipper</author>
</authors>
<title>VerbNet: A broad-coverage, comprehensive verb lexicon.</title>
<date>2005</date>
<tech>Ph.D. thesis,</tech>
<institution>University of Pennsylvania.</institution>
<contexts>
<context position="1178" citStr="Kipper, 2005" startWordPosition="166" endWordPosition="167">ellbaum, 1998). By using the Predicate Matrix, we expect to provide a more robust interoperable lexicon by discovering and solving inherent inconsistencies among the resources. Moreover, we plan to extend the coverage of current predicate resources (by including from WordNet morphologically related nominal and verbal concepts), to enrich WordNet with predicate information, and possibly to extend predicate information to languages other than English (by exploiting the local wordnets aligned to the English WordNet). 1 Introduction Predicate models such as FrameNet (Baker et al., 1997), VerbNet (Kipper, 2005) or PropBank (Palmer et al., 2005) are core resources in most advanced NLP tasks, such as Question Answering, Textual Entailment or Information Extraction. Most of the systems with Natural Language Understanding capabilities require a large and precise amount of semantic knowledge at the predicateargument level. This type of knowledge allows to identify the underlying typical participants of a particular event independently of its realization in the text. Thus, using these models, different linguistic phenomena expressing the same event, such as active/passive transformations, verb alternation</context>
<context position="3636" citStr="Kipper, 2005" startWordPosition="537" endWordPosition="538">k et al., 2007), Freebase (Bollacker et al., 2008), DBPedia (Bizer et al., 2009), BabelNet (Navigli and Ponzetto, 2010) or UBY (Gurevych et al., 2012). Following the line of previous works (Shi and Mihalcea, 2005), (Burchardt et al., 2005), (Johansson and Nugues, 2007), (Pennacchiotti et al., 2008), (Cao et al., 2008), (Tonelli and Pianta, 2009), (Laparra et al., 2010), we will also focus on the integration of predicate information. We start from the basis of SemLink (Palmer, 2009). SemLink aimed to connect together different predicate resources such as FrameNet (Baker et al., 1997), VerbNet (Kipper, 2005), PropBank (Palmer et al., 2005) and WordNet (Fellbaum, 1998). However, its coverage is still far from complete. The Predicate Matrix, the resource resulting from the work presented in this paper, will allow to extend the coverage of current predicate resources (by including from WordNet closely related nominal and verbal concepts), to discover inherent inconsistencies among the resources, to enrich WordNet with predicate information, and possibly to extend predicate information to languages other than English (by exploiting the local wordnets aligned to the English WordNet). Moreover, the Pre</context>
<context position="5483" citStr="Kipper, 2005" startWordPosition="828" endWordPosition="829"> more complete and robust predicate lexicon. 2 Sources of Predicate information As a starting point for building the Predicate Matrix, we consider the sources of predicate knowledge connected to SemLink. SemLink1 (Palmer, 2009) is a project whose aim is to link together different predicate resources establishing a set of mappings. These mappings make it possible to combine the different information provided by the different lexical resources for tasks such as inferencing, consistency checking, interoperable semantic role labelling, etc. Currently, SemLink provides partial mappings to VerbNet (Kipper, 2005), PropBank (Palmer et al., 2005), FrameNet (Baker et al., 1997) and WordNet (Fellbaum, 1998). FrameNet 2 (Baker et al., 1997) is a very rich semantic resource that contains descriptions and corpus annotations of English words following the paradigm of Frame Semantics (Fillmore, 1976). In frame semantics, a Frame corresponds to a scenario that involves the interaction of a set of typical participants, playing a particular role in the scenario. FrameNet groups words or lexical-units (LUs hereinafter) into coherent semantic classes or frames, and each frame is further characterized by a list of p</context>
<context position="6853" citStr="Kipper, 2005" startWordPosition="1032" endWordPosition="1033">o.edu/semlink/ 2http://framenet.icsi.berkeley.edu/ PropBank 3 (Palmer et al., 2005) aims to provide a wide corpus annotated with information about semantic propositions, including relations between the predicates and their arguments. PropBank also contains a description of the frame structures, called framesets, of each sense of every verb that belong to its lexicon. Unlike other similar resources, as FrameNet, PropBank defines the arguments, or roles, of each verb individually. In consecuence, it becomes a hard task obtaning a generalization of the frame structures over the verbs. VerbNet 4 (Kipper, 2005) is a hierarchical domain-independent broad-coverage verb lexicon for English. VerbNet is organized into verb classes extending (Levin, 1993) classes through refinement and addition of subclasses to achieve syntactic and semantic coherence among members of a class. Each verb class in VerbNet is completely described by thematic-roles, selectional restrictions on the arguments, and frames consisting of a syntactic description and semantic predicates. WordNet 5 (Fellbaum, 1998) is by far the most widely-used knowledge base. In fact, WordNet is being used world-wide for anchoring different types o</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Kipper, 2005</marker>
<rawString>Karen Kipper. 2005. VerbNet: A broad-coverage, comprehensive verb lexicon. Ph.D. thesis, University of Pennsylvania.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Egoitz Laparra</author>
<author>German Rigau</author>
</authors>
<title>Impar: A deterministic algorithm for implicit semantic role labelling.</title>
<date>2013</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 51st Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL</booktitle>
<pages>33--41</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="2133" citStr="Laparra and Rigau, 2013" startWordPosition="303" endWordPosition="306">ledge allows to identify the underlying typical participants of a particular event independently of its realization in the text. Thus, using these models, different linguistic phenomena expressing the same event, such as active/passive transformations, verb alternations, nominalizations, implicit realizations can be harmonized into a common semantic representation. In fact, lately, several systems have been developed for shallow semantic parsing an explicit and implicit semantic role labeling using these resources (Erk and Pado, 2004), (Shi and Mihalcea, 2005), (Giuglea and Moschitti, 2006), (Laparra and Rigau, 2013). However, building large and rich enough predicate models for broad–coverage semantic processing takes a great deal of expensive manual effort involving large research groups during long periods of development. In fact, the coverage of currently available predicate-argument resources is still far from complete. For example, (Burchardt et al., 2005) or (Shen and Lapata, 2007) indicate the limited coverage of FrameNet as one of the main problems of this resource. In fact, FrameNet1.5 covers around 10,000 lexical-units while for instance, WordNet3.0 contains more than 150,000 words. Furthermore,</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Laparra, Rigau, 2013</marker>
<rawString>Egoitz Laparra and German Rigau. 2013. Impar: A deterministic algorithm for implicit semantic role labelling. In Proceedings of the 51st Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL 2013), pages 33–41.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Egoitz Laparra</author>
<author>German Rigau</author>
<author>Montse Cuadros</author>
</authors>
<title>Exploring the integration of wordnet and framenet.</title>
<date>2010</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 5th Global WordNet Conference (GWC 2010),</booktitle>
<location>Mumbai, India.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="3394" citStr="Laparra et al., 2010" startWordPosition="497" endWordPosition="500">each different language (Subirats and Petruck, 2003). Moreover, most previous research efforts on the integration of resources targeted at knowledge about nouns and named entities rather than predicate knowledge. Well known examples are YAGO (Suchanek et al., 2007), Freebase (Bollacker et al., 2008), DBPedia (Bizer et al., 2009), BabelNet (Navigli and Ponzetto, 2010) or UBY (Gurevych et al., 2012). Following the line of previous works (Shi and Mihalcea, 2005), (Burchardt et al., 2005), (Johansson and Nugues, 2007), (Pennacchiotti et al., 2008), (Cao et al., 2008), (Tonelli and Pianta, 2009), (Laparra et al., 2010), we will also focus on the integration of predicate information. We start from the basis of SemLink (Palmer, 2009). SemLink aimed to connect together different predicate resources such as FrameNet (Baker et al., 1997), VerbNet (Kipper, 2005), PropBank (Palmer et al., 2005) and WordNet (Fellbaum, 1998). However, its coverage is still far from complete. The Predicate Matrix, the resource resulting from the work presented in this paper, will allow to extend the coverage of current predicate resources (by including from WordNet closely related nominal and verbal concepts), to discover inherent in</context>
<context position="20883" citStr="Laparra et al., 2010" startWordPosition="3192" endWordPosition="3195">plan to use additional semantic resources that use WordNet as a backbone. For instance, exploiting those knowledge resources integrated into the Multilingual Central Repository15 (MCR) (Atserias et al., 2004; Gonzalez-Agirre et al., 2012a) to extend automatically the aligment of the different sources of predicate information (VerbNet, PropBank, FrameNet and WordNet). Following the line of previous works, in order to assign more WordNet verb senses to VerbNet predicates, we also plan to apply more sophisticated word-sense disambiguation algorithms to semantically coherent groups of predicates (Laparra et al., 2010). 5.1 VerbNet Monosemous predicates Monosemous verbs from WordNet can be directly assigned to VerbNet predicates still without a WordNet aligment. This very simple strategy solves 240 aligments. In this way, VerbNet predicates such as divulgev, exhumev, mutatev or uploadv obtain a corresponding WordNet word sense16. Remember that only 576 lemmas from VerbNet were not aligned to WordNet. 5.2 WordNet synonyms A very straightforward method to extend the mapping between WordNet and VerbNet consists on including synonyms of already aligned WordNet senses as new members of the corresponding VerbNet </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Laparra, Rigau, Cuadros, 2010</marker>
<rawString>Egoitz Laparra, German Rigau, and Montse Cuadros. 2010. Exploring the integration of wordnet and framenet. In Proceedings of the 5th Global WordNet Conference (GWC 2010), Mumbai, India.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Beth Levin</author>
</authors>
<title>English verb classes and alternations: A preliminary investigation, volume 348.</title>
<date>1993</date>
<institution>University of Chicago press Chicago.</institution>
<contexts>
<context position="6994" citStr="Levin, 1993" startWordPosition="1050" endWordPosition="1051">bout semantic propositions, including relations between the predicates and their arguments. PropBank also contains a description of the frame structures, called framesets, of each sense of every verb that belong to its lexicon. Unlike other similar resources, as FrameNet, PropBank defines the arguments, or roles, of each verb individually. In consecuence, it becomes a hard task obtaning a generalization of the frame structures over the verbs. VerbNet 4 (Kipper, 2005) is a hierarchical domain-independent broad-coverage verb lexicon for English. VerbNet is organized into verb classes extending (Levin, 1993) classes through refinement and addition of subclasses to achieve syntactic and semantic coherence among members of a class. Each verb class in VerbNet is completely described by thematic-roles, selectional restrictions on the arguments, and frames consisting of a syntactic description and semantic predicates. WordNet 5 (Fellbaum, 1998) is by far the most widely-used knowledge base. In fact, WordNet is being used world-wide for anchoring different types of semantic knowledge including wordnets for languages other than English (Gonzalez-Agirre et al., 2012a). It contains manually coded informat</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Levin, 1993</marker>
<rawString>Beth Levin. 1993. English verb classes and alternations: A preliminary investigation, volume 348. University of Chicago press Chicago.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Roberto Navigli</author>
<author>Simone Paolo Ponzetto</author>
</authors>
<title>Babelnet: Building a very large multilingual semantic network.</title>
<date>2010</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 48th annual meeting of ACL,</booktitle>
<pages>216--225</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="3142" citStr="Navigli and Ponzetto, 2010" startWordPosition="456" endWordPosition="459">icate the limited coverage of FrameNet as one of the main problems of this resource. In fact, FrameNet1.5 covers around 10,000 lexical-units while for instance, WordNet3.0 contains more than 150,000 words. Furthermore, the same effort should be invested for each different language (Subirats and Petruck, 2003). Moreover, most previous research efforts on the integration of resources targeted at knowledge about nouns and named entities rather than predicate knowledge. Well known examples are YAGO (Suchanek et al., 2007), Freebase (Bollacker et al., 2008), DBPedia (Bizer et al., 2009), BabelNet (Navigli and Ponzetto, 2010) or UBY (Gurevych et al., 2012). Following the line of previous works (Shi and Mihalcea, 2005), (Burchardt et al., 2005), (Johansson and Nugues, 2007), (Pennacchiotti et al., 2008), (Cao et al., 2008), (Tonelli and Pianta, 2009), (Laparra et al., 2010), we will also focus on the integration of predicate information. We start from the basis of SemLink (Palmer, 2009). SemLink aimed to connect together different predicate resources such as FrameNet (Baker et al., 1997), VerbNet (Kipper, 2005), PropBank (Palmer et al., 2005) and WordNet (Fellbaum, 1998). However, its coverage is still far from com</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Navigli, Ponzetto, 2010</marker>
<rawString>Roberto Navigli and Simone Paolo Ponzetto. 2010. Babelnet: Building a very large multilingual semantic network. In Proceedings of the 48th annual meeting of ACL, pages 216–225.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Martha Palmer</author>
<author>Daniel Gildea</author>
<author>Paul Kingsbury</author>
</authors>
<title>The proposition bank: An annotated corpus of semantic roles.</title>
<date>2005</date>
<journal>Computational Linguistics,</journal>
<volume>31</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<contexts>
<context position="1212" citStr="Palmer et al., 2005" startWordPosition="170" endWordPosition="173">e Predicate Matrix, we expect to provide a more robust interoperable lexicon by discovering and solving inherent inconsistencies among the resources. Moreover, we plan to extend the coverage of current predicate resources (by including from WordNet morphologically related nominal and verbal concepts), to enrich WordNet with predicate information, and possibly to extend predicate information to languages other than English (by exploiting the local wordnets aligned to the English WordNet). 1 Introduction Predicate models such as FrameNet (Baker et al., 1997), VerbNet (Kipper, 2005) or PropBank (Palmer et al., 2005) are core resources in most advanced NLP tasks, such as Question Answering, Textual Entailment or Information Extraction. Most of the systems with Natural Language Understanding capabilities require a large and precise amount of semantic knowledge at the predicateargument level. This type of knowledge allows to identify the underlying typical participants of a particular event independently of its realization in the text. Thus, using these models, different linguistic phenomena expressing the same event, such as active/passive transformations, verb alternations, nominalizations, implicit reali</context>
<context position="3668" citStr="Palmer et al., 2005" startWordPosition="540" endWordPosition="543"> (Bollacker et al., 2008), DBPedia (Bizer et al., 2009), BabelNet (Navigli and Ponzetto, 2010) or UBY (Gurevych et al., 2012). Following the line of previous works (Shi and Mihalcea, 2005), (Burchardt et al., 2005), (Johansson and Nugues, 2007), (Pennacchiotti et al., 2008), (Cao et al., 2008), (Tonelli and Pianta, 2009), (Laparra et al., 2010), we will also focus on the integration of predicate information. We start from the basis of SemLink (Palmer, 2009). SemLink aimed to connect together different predicate resources such as FrameNet (Baker et al., 1997), VerbNet (Kipper, 2005), PropBank (Palmer et al., 2005) and WordNet (Fellbaum, 1998). However, its coverage is still far from complete. The Predicate Matrix, the resource resulting from the work presented in this paper, will allow to extend the coverage of current predicate resources (by including from WordNet closely related nominal and verbal concepts), to discover inherent inconsistencies among the resources, to enrich WordNet with predicate information, and possibly to extend predicate information to languages other than English (by exploiting the local wordnets aligned to the English WordNet). Moreover, the Predicate Matrix uses WordNet as a </context>
<context position="5515" citStr="Palmer et al., 2005" startWordPosition="831" endWordPosition="834"> predicate lexicon. 2 Sources of Predicate information As a starting point for building the Predicate Matrix, we consider the sources of predicate knowledge connected to SemLink. SemLink1 (Palmer, 2009) is a project whose aim is to link together different predicate resources establishing a set of mappings. These mappings make it possible to combine the different information provided by the different lexical resources for tasks such as inferencing, consistency checking, interoperable semantic role labelling, etc. Currently, SemLink provides partial mappings to VerbNet (Kipper, 2005), PropBank (Palmer et al., 2005), FrameNet (Baker et al., 1997) and WordNet (Fellbaum, 1998). FrameNet 2 (Baker et al., 1997) is a very rich semantic resource that contains descriptions and corpus annotations of English words following the paradigm of Frame Semantics (Fillmore, 1976). In frame semantics, a Frame corresponds to a scenario that involves the interaction of a set of typical participants, playing a particular role in the scenario. FrameNet groups words or lexical-units (LUs hereinafter) into coherent semantic classes or frames, and each frame is further characterized by a list of participants or frame-elements (F</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Palmer, Gildea, Kingsbury, 2005</marker>
<rawString>Martha Palmer, Daniel Gildea, and Paul Kingsbury. 2005. The proposition bank: An annotated corpus of semantic roles. Computational Linguistics, 31(1):71–106, March.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Martha Palmer</author>
</authors>
<title>Semlink: Linking propbank, verbnet and framenet.</title>
<date>2009</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the Generative Lexicon Conference,</booktitle>
<pages>9--15</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="3509" citStr="Palmer, 2009" startWordPosition="518" endWordPosition="519">ces targeted at knowledge about nouns and named entities rather than predicate knowledge. Well known examples are YAGO (Suchanek et al., 2007), Freebase (Bollacker et al., 2008), DBPedia (Bizer et al., 2009), BabelNet (Navigli and Ponzetto, 2010) or UBY (Gurevych et al., 2012). Following the line of previous works (Shi and Mihalcea, 2005), (Burchardt et al., 2005), (Johansson and Nugues, 2007), (Pennacchiotti et al., 2008), (Cao et al., 2008), (Tonelli and Pianta, 2009), (Laparra et al., 2010), we will also focus on the integration of predicate information. We start from the basis of SemLink (Palmer, 2009). SemLink aimed to connect together different predicate resources such as FrameNet (Baker et al., 1997), VerbNet (Kipper, 2005), PropBank (Palmer et al., 2005) and WordNet (Fellbaum, 1998). However, its coverage is still far from complete. The Predicate Matrix, the resource resulting from the work presented in this paper, will allow to extend the coverage of current predicate resources (by including from WordNet closely related nominal and verbal concepts), to discover inherent inconsistencies among the resources, to enrich WordNet with predicate information, and possibly to extend predicate i</context>
<context position="5097" citStr="Palmer, 2009" startWordPosition="772" endWordPosition="773"> complete study of the coverage of the mappings between each resource included in SemLink to VerbNet. We describe the coverage and gaps of these mappings with respect to the lexical entries and the role structures of each resource. Second, we exploit WordNet to propose straightforward methods to discover incosistencies among the resources as well as to extend their coverage towards a more complete and robust predicate lexicon. 2 Sources of Predicate information As a starting point for building the Predicate Matrix, we consider the sources of predicate knowledge connected to SemLink. SemLink1 (Palmer, 2009) is a project whose aim is to link together different predicate resources establishing a set of mappings. These mappings make it possible to combine the different information provided by the different lexical resources for tasks such as inferencing, consistency checking, interoperable semantic role labelling, etc. Currently, SemLink provides partial mappings to VerbNet (Kipper, 2005), PropBank (Palmer et al., 2005), FrameNet (Baker et al., 1997) and WordNet (Fellbaum, 1998). FrameNet 2 (Baker et al., 1997) is a very rich semantic resource that contains descriptions and corpus annotations of En</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Palmer, 2009</marker>
<rawString>Martha Palmer. 2009. Semlink: Linking propbank, verbnet and framenet. In Proceedings of the Generative Lexicon Conference, pages 9–15.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Marco Pennacchiotti</author>
<author>Diego De Cao</author>
<author>Roberto Basili</author>
<author>Danilo Croce</author>
<author>Michael Roth</author>
</authors>
<title>Automatic induction of FrameNet lexical units.</title>
<date>2008</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of EMNLP.</booktitle>
<marker>Pennacchiotti, De Cao, Basili, Croce, Roth, 2008</marker>
<rawString>Marco Pennacchiotti, Diego De Cao, Roberto Basili, Danilo Croce, and Michael Roth. 2008. Automatic induction of FrameNet lexical units. In Proceedings of EMNLP.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Dan Shen</author>
<author>Mirella Lapata</author>
</authors>
<title>Using semantic roles to improve question answering.</title>
<date>2007</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the Joint Conference on (EMNLP-CoNLL),</booktitle>
<pages>12--21</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="2511" citStr="Shen and Lapata, 2007" startWordPosition="361" endWordPosition="364">ely, several systems have been developed for shallow semantic parsing an explicit and implicit semantic role labeling using these resources (Erk and Pado, 2004), (Shi and Mihalcea, 2005), (Giuglea and Moschitti, 2006), (Laparra and Rigau, 2013). However, building large and rich enough predicate models for broad–coverage semantic processing takes a great deal of expensive manual effort involving large research groups during long periods of development. In fact, the coverage of currently available predicate-argument resources is still far from complete. For example, (Burchardt et al., 2005) or (Shen and Lapata, 2007) indicate the limited coverage of FrameNet as one of the main problems of this resource. In fact, FrameNet1.5 covers around 10,000 lexical-units while for instance, WordNet3.0 contains more than 150,000 words. Furthermore, the same effort should be invested for each different language (Subirats and Petruck, 2003). Moreover, most previous research efforts on the integration of resources targeted at knowledge about nouns and named entities rather than predicate knowledge. Well known examples are YAGO (Suchanek et al., 2007), Freebase (Bollacker et al., 2008), DBPedia (Bizer et al., 2009), BabelN</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Shen, Lapata, 2007</marker>
<rawString>Dan Shen and Mirella Lapata. 2007. Using semantic roles to improve question answering. In Proceedings of the Joint Conference on (EMNLP-CoNLL), pages 12–21.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Lei Shi</author>
<author>Rada Mihalcea</author>
</authors>
<title>Putting pieces together: Combining framenet, verbnet and wordnet for robust semantic parsing.</title>
<date>2005</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of CICLing,</booktitle>
<location>Mexico.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="2075" citStr="Shi and Mihalcea, 2005" startWordPosition="295" endWordPosition="298">owledge at the predicateargument level. This type of knowledge allows to identify the underlying typical participants of a particular event independently of its realization in the text. Thus, using these models, different linguistic phenomena expressing the same event, such as active/passive transformations, verb alternations, nominalizations, implicit realizations can be harmonized into a common semantic representation. In fact, lately, several systems have been developed for shallow semantic parsing an explicit and implicit semantic role labeling using these resources (Erk and Pado, 2004), (Shi and Mihalcea, 2005), (Giuglea and Moschitti, 2006), (Laparra and Rigau, 2013). However, building large and rich enough predicate models for broad–coverage semantic processing takes a great deal of expensive manual effort involving large research groups during long periods of development. In fact, the coverage of currently available predicate-argument resources is still far from complete. For example, (Burchardt et al., 2005) or (Shen and Lapata, 2007) indicate the limited coverage of FrameNet as one of the main problems of this resource. In fact, FrameNet1.5 covers around 10,000 lexical-units while for instance,</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Shi, Mihalcea, 2005</marker>
<rawString>Lei Shi and Rada Mihalcea. 2005. Putting pieces together: Combining framenet, verbnet and wordnet for robust semantic parsing. In Proceedings of CICLing, Mexico.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Carlos Subirats</author>
<author>Miriam R L Petruck</author>
</authors>
<title>Surprise: Spanish framenet!</title>
<date>2003</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the International Congress of Linguists, Praga.</booktitle>
<contexts>
<context position="2825" citStr="Subirats and Petruck, 2003" startWordPosition="409" endWordPosition="412">oad–coverage semantic processing takes a great deal of expensive manual effort involving large research groups during long periods of development. In fact, the coverage of currently available predicate-argument resources is still far from complete. For example, (Burchardt et al., 2005) or (Shen and Lapata, 2007) indicate the limited coverage of FrameNet as one of the main problems of this resource. In fact, FrameNet1.5 covers around 10,000 lexical-units while for instance, WordNet3.0 contains more than 150,000 words. Furthermore, the same effort should be invested for each different language (Subirats and Petruck, 2003). Moreover, most previous research efforts on the integration of resources targeted at knowledge about nouns and named entities rather than predicate knowledge. Well known examples are YAGO (Suchanek et al., 2007), Freebase (Bollacker et al., 2008), DBPedia (Bizer et al., 2009), BabelNet (Navigli and Ponzetto, 2010) or UBY (Gurevych et al., 2012). Following the line of previous works (Shi and Mihalcea, 2005), (Burchardt et al., 2005), (Johansson and Nugues, 2007), (Pennacchiotti et al., 2008), (Cao et al., 2008), (Tonelli and Pianta, 2009), (Laparra et al., 2010), we will also focus on the int</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Subirats, Petruck, 2003</marker>
<rawString>Carlos Subirats and Miriam R.L. Petruck. 2003. Surprise: Spanish framenet! In Proceedings of the International Congress of Linguists, Praga.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Fabian M Suchanek</author>
<author>Gjergji Kasneci</author>
<author>Gerhard Weikum</author>
</authors>
<title>Yago: A Core of Semantic Knowledge.</title>
<date>2007</date>
<booktitle>In WWW conference,</booktitle>
<publisher>ACM Press.</publisher>
<location>New York, NY, USA.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="3038" citStr="Suchanek et al., 2007" startWordPosition="440" endWordPosition="443">es is still far from complete. For example, (Burchardt et al., 2005) or (Shen and Lapata, 2007) indicate the limited coverage of FrameNet as one of the main problems of this resource. In fact, FrameNet1.5 covers around 10,000 lexical-units while for instance, WordNet3.0 contains more than 150,000 words. Furthermore, the same effort should be invested for each different language (Subirats and Petruck, 2003). Moreover, most previous research efforts on the integration of resources targeted at knowledge about nouns and named entities rather than predicate knowledge. Well known examples are YAGO (Suchanek et al., 2007), Freebase (Bollacker et al., 2008), DBPedia (Bizer et al., 2009), BabelNet (Navigli and Ponzetto, 2010) or UBY (Gurevych et al., 2012). Following the line of previous works (Shi and Mihalcea, 2005), (Burchardt et al., 2005), (Johansson and Nugues, 2007), (Pennacchiotti et al., 2008), (Cao et al., 2008), (Tonelli and Pianta, 2009), (Laparra et al., 2010), we will also focus on the integration of predicate information. We start from the basis of SemLink (Palmer, 2009). SemLink aimed to connect together different predicate resources such as FrameNet (Baker et al., 1997), VerbNet (Kipper, 2005), </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Suchanek, Kasneci, Weikum, 2007</marker>
<rawString>Fabian M. Suchanek, Gjergji Kasneci, and Gerhard Weikum. 2007. Yago: A Core of Semantic Knowledge. In WWW conference, New York, NY, USA. ACM Press.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Mariona Taul´e</author>
<author>Maria Ant`onia Mart´ı</author>
<author>Marta Recasens</author>
</authors>
<title>Ancora: Multilevel annotated corpora for catalan and spanish.</title>
<date>2008</date>
<booktitle>In LREC.</booktitle>
<marker>Taul´e, Mart´ı, Recasens, 2008</marker>
<rawString>Mariona Taul´e, Maria Ant`onia Mart´ı, and Marta Recasens. 2008. Ancora: Multilevel annotated corpora for catalan and spanish. In LREC.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Sara Tonelli</author>
<author>Emanuele Pianta</author>
</authors>
<title>A novel approach to mapping framenet lexical units to wordnet synsets.</title>
<date>2009</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of IWCS-8,</booktitle>
<location>Tilburg, The Netherlands.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="3370" citStr="Tonelli and Pianta, 2009" startWordPosition="493" endWordPosition="496">fort should be invested for each different language (Subirats and Petruck, 2003). Moreover, most previous research efforts on the integration of resources targeted at knowledge about nouns and named entities rather than predicate knowledge. Well known examples are YAGO (Suchanek et al., 2007), Freebase (Bollacker et al., 2008), DBPedia (Bizer et al., 2009), BabelNet (Navigli and Ponzetto, 2010) or UBY (Gurevych et al., 2012). Following the line of previous works (Shi and Mihalcea, 2005), (Burchardt et al., 2005), (Johansson and Nugues, 2007), (Pennacchiotti et al., 2008), (Cao et al., 2008), (Tonelli and Pianta, 2009), (Laparra et al., 2010), we will also focus on the integration of predicate information. We start from the basis of SemLink (Palmer, 2009). SemLink aimed to connect together different predicate resources such as FrameNet (Baker et al., 1997), VerbNet (Kipper, 2005), PropBank (Palmer et al., 2005) and WordNet (Fellbaum, 1998). However, its coverage is still far from complete. The Predicate Matrix, the resource resulting from the work presented in this paper, will allow to extend the coverage of current predicate resources (by including from WordNet closely related nominal and verbal concepts),</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Tonelli, Pianta, 2009</marker>
<rawString>Sara Tonelli and Emanuele Pianta. 2009. A novel approach to mapping framenet lexical units to wordnet synsets. In Proceedings of IWCS-8, Tilburg, The Netherlands.</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>