<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="SectLabel" version="110505">
<variant no="0" confidence="0.085103">
<title confidence="0.9843405">
Improving the Precision of Synset Links Between Cornetto and Princeton
WordNet
</title>
<author confidence="0.988851">
Leen Sevens Vincent Vandeghinste Frank Van Eynde
</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.985656">
Centre for Computational Linguistics
</affiliation>
<address confidence="0.710481">
KU Leuven
</address>
<email confidence="0.988161">
firstname@ccl.kuleuven.be
</email>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.993552" genericHeader="abstract">
Abstract
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999875416666667">
Knowledge-based multilingual language processing benefits from having access to correctly es-
tablished relations between semantic lexicons, such as the links between different WordNets.
WordNet linking is a process that can be sped up by the use of computational techniques. Manual
evaluations of the partly automatically established synonym set (synset) relations between Dutch
and English in Cornetto, a Dutch lexical-semantic database associated with the EuroWordNet
grid, have confronted us with a worrisome amount of erroneous links. By extracting transla-
tions from various bilingual resources and automatically assigning a confidence score to every
pre-established link, we reduce the error rate of the existing equivalence relations between both
languages’ synsets (section 2). We will apply this technique to reuse the connection of Sclera
and Beta pictograph sets and Cornetto synsets to Princeton WordNet and other WordNets, allow-
ing us to further extend an existing Dutch text-to-pictograph translation tool to other languages
(section 3).
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.9988" genericHeader="introduction">
1 Introduction
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999904210526316">
The connections between WordNets, large semantic databases grouping lexical units into synonym
sets or synsets, are an important resource in knowledge-based multilingual language processing.
EuroWordNet (Vossen, 1997) aims to build language-specific WordNets among the same lines as the
original WordNet1 (Miller et al., 1990), using Inter-Lingual-Indexes to weave a web of equivalence re-
lations between the synsets contained within the databases. Cornetto2 (Vossen et al., 2007), a Dutch
lexical-semantic collection of data associated with the Dutch EuroWordNet3, consists of more than 118
000 synsets. The equivalence relations establish connections between Dutch and English synsets in
Princeton WordNet version 1.5 and 2.0. We update these links to Princeton WordNet version 3.0 by the
mappings among WordNet versions made available by TALP-UPC 4. The equivalence relations between
Cornetto and Princeton have been established semi-automatically by Vossen et al. (1999). Manual cod-
ing was carried out for the 14 749 most important concepts in the database. These include the most
frequent concepts, the concepts having a large amount of semantic relations and the concepts occupying
a high position in the lexical hierarchy. Automatic linkage was done by mapping the bilingual Van Dale
database5 to WordNet 1.5. For every WordNet synset containing a dictionary’s translation for a particular
Dutch word, all its members were proposed as alternative translations. In the case of only one transla-
tion, the synset relation was instantly assumed correct, while multiple translations were weighted using
several heuristics, such as measuring the conceptual distance in the WordNet hierarchy. We decided to
verify the quality of these links and noticed that they were highly erroneous, making them not yet very
reliable for multilingual processing.
</bodyText>
<footnote confidence="0.949416714285714">
This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International Licence. Page numbers and proceedings footer
are added by the organisers. Licence details:http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/
1http://wordnet.princeton.edu
2http://tst-centrale.org/producten/lexica/cornetto/7-56
3http://www.illc.uva.nl/EuroWordNet
4http://www.talp.upc.edu
5http://www.vandale.be
</footnote>
<page confidence="0.764901">
120
</page>
<note confidence="0.7672535">
Proceedings of the Workshop on Lexical and Grammatical Resources for Language Processing, pages 120–126,
Coling 2014, Dublin, Ireland, August 24 2014.
</note>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.673681" genericHeader="method">
2 Improving the equivalence relations between Cornetto and Princeton WordNet
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999808772727273">
We manually evaluated the quality of the links between 300 randomly selected Cornetto synsets and
their supposedly related Princeton synsets. A Cornetto synset is often linked to more than one Princeton
synset. We found an erroneous link in 35.27% of the 998 equivalence relations we evaluated.
Each Cornetto synset has about 3.3 automatically derived English equivalents, allowing to roughly
compare our evaluation to an initial quality check of the equivalence relations performed by Vossen et
al. (1999). They note that, in the case of synsets with three to nine translations, the percentages of
correct automatically derived equivalents went down to 65% and 49% for nouns and verbs respectively.
Our manual evaluations are in line with these results, showing that only 64.73% of all the connections
in our sample are correct. An example of where it goes wrong is the Cornetto synset for the animal tor
”beetle”, which is not only appropriately linked to correct synsets (such as beetle and bug), but also
mistakenly to the Princeton synset for the computational glitch. This flaw is most probably caused by
the presence of the synonym bug, which is a commonly used word for errors in computer programs.
Examples like these are omnipresent in our data6 and led us to conclude that the synset links between
Cornetto and Princeton WordNet definitely could be improved.
We build a bilingual dictionary for Dutch and English and use these translations as an automatic
indicator of the quality of equivalence relations. In order to create a huge list of translations we merge
several translation word lists, removing double entries. Some are manually compiled dictionaries, while
others are automatically derived word lists from parallel corpora: we extracted the 1-word phrases from
the phrase tables built with Moses (Koehn et al., 2007) based on the GIZA++ word alignments (Och and
Ney, 2003). Table 1 gives an overview.
This resulted in a coverage of 52.18% (43 970 out of 84 264) of the equivalence relations for which
translation information was available in order to possibly confirm the relation.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.9993665">
Translation dictionary Reference Method of compilation Nr of word pairs
Wiktionary www.wiktionary.org Manual 23,575
FreeDict www.freedict.com Manual 49,493
Europarl (Koehn, 2005) Automatic 2,970,501
Opus (Tiedemann, 2009) Automatic 6,223,539
Sclera translations www.pictoselector.eu Manual 12,381
</table>
<tableCaption confidence="0.999951">
Table 1: The used translation sources
</tableCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.997081285714286">
Figure 1 visualizes how we used the bilingual dictionaries to automatically evaluate the quality of the
pre-established links between Cornetto and Princeton WordNet. We retrieve all the lemmas of the lexical
units that were contained within a synset Si (in our example, snoepgoed ”confectionary” and snoep
”candy” extracted from S1). Each of these lemmas is looked up in the bilingual dictionary, resulting
in a dictionary words list of English translations.7 This list is used to estimate the correctness of the
equivalence relation between the Cornetto and the Princeton synset.
We retrieve the lexical units list from the English synset Tj (in our example candy and confect extracted
from Ti). We count the number of words in the lexical units list also appearing in the dictionary words
list (the overlap being represented as the multiset Q). Translations appearing more than once are given
more importance. For example, candy occurs twice, putting our overlap counter on 2. This overlap is
normalized. In the example it is divided by 3 (confect + candy + candy, as the double count is taken into
account), leaving us with a score of 66.67%. For the gloss words list we remove the stop words8 and
make an analogous calculation. In our example, sweet is counted twice (the overlap being represented
as the multiset R) and this number is divided by the total number of gloss words available (again taking
</bodyText>
<footnote confidence="0.988047">
6Other examples: nederig ”humble” was linked to the synset for flexible (as a synonym for elastic), waterachtig ”aquatic”
was linked to the synsets for grey and mousy, rocker (hardrocker) was linked to the synset for rocking chair, etc.
7Note that this list can contain doubles (such as candy and delicacy), as these translations would provide additional evidence
to our scoring algorithm. It is therefore not the case that the dictionary words list represents a set. It represents a multiset.
8http://norm.al/2009/04/14/list-of-english-stop-words
</footnote>
<page confidence="0.988891">
121
</page>
<figureCaption confidence="0.999948">
Figure 1: The scoring mechanism with examples
</figureCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.999912454545455">
into account the double count). Averaging this score of 25% with our first result, we obtain a confidence
score of 45.83% for this equivalence relation. We calculated this confidence score for every equivalence
relation in Cornetto.
We checked whether the automatic scoring algorithm (section 2) (dis)agreed with the manual judge-
ments in order to determine a satisfactory threshold value for the acceptance of synset links. Evaluation
results are shown in figure 2. While the precision (the proportion of accurate links that the system got
right) went slightly up as our criterium for link acceptance became stricter, the recall (the proportion of
correct links that the system retrieved) quickly made a rather deep dive. The F-score reveals that the best
trade-off is reached when synset links getting a score of 0% are rejected, retaining any link with a higher
confidence score. The results in Table 3 shows that we were able to reduce the error rate to 21.09%,
which is a relative improvement of 40.20% over the baseline.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.974159" genericHeader="method">
3 Improving the equivalence relations in the context of text-to-pictograph translation
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999843">
Being able to use the currently available technological tools is becoming an increasingly important factor
in today’s society. Augmentative and Alternative Communication (AAC) refers to the whole of commu-
nication methods which aim to assist people that are suffering from cognitive disabilities, helping them to
become more socially active in various domains of daily life. Text-to-pictograph translation is a particular
form of AAC technology that enables linguistically-impaired people to use the Internet independently.
Filtering away erroneous synset links in Cornetto has proven to be a useful way to improve the quality
of a text-to-pictograph translation tool. Vandeghinste and Schuurman (2014) have connected pictograph
sets to Cornetto synsets to enable text-to-pictograph translation. Equivalence relations are important to
allow reusing these connections in order to link pictographs to synsets for other languages than Dutch.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.991359">
122
</page>
<figureCaption confidence="0.991638">
Figure 2: Precision (top line), recall (bottom line) and F-score (middle line) for different threshold values
of link acceptance.
</figureCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.986179461538461">
Vandeghinste and Schuurman (2014) released Sclera2Cornetto, a resource linking Sclera9 pictographs
to Cornetto synsets. Currently, over 13 000 Sclera pictographs are made available online, 5 710 of which
have been manually linked to Cornetto synsets. We want to build a text-to-pictograph conversion with
English and Spanish as source languages, reusing the Sclera2Cornetto data.
By improving Cornetto’s pre-established equivalence relations with Princeton synsets, we can connect
the Sclera pictographs with Princeton WordNet for English. The latter, in turn, will then be used as the
intermediate step in our process of assigning pictographs to Spanish synsets.
Manual evaluations were made for a randomly generated subset of the synsets that were previously
used by Vandeghinste and Schuurman (2014) for assigning Sclera and Beta10 pictographs to Cornetto.
Beta pictographs are another pictograph set for which a link between the pictographs and Cornetto was
provided by Vandeghinste (2014).
Table 2 presents the coverage of our bilingual dictionary for synsets being connected to Sclera and
Beta pictographs, which is clearly higher than the coverage over all synsets.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.999685">
Covered Total Difference with All synsets
All synsets 43 970 (52.18%) 84 264 -
Sclera baseline 5 294 (88.80%) 5 962 36.62%
Beta synsets 3 409 (88.94%) 3 833 36.76%
</table>
<tableCaption confidence="0.997288">
Table 2: Dictionary Coverage for different sets of synsets
</tableCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.987757692307692">
Table 3 shows that the error rate of Cornetto’s equivalence relations on the Sclera and Beta subsets
is much lower than the error rate on the whole set (section 2). We attribute this difference to the fact
that Vossen et al. (1999) carried out manual coding for the most important concepts in the database (see
section 1), as the Sclera and Beta pictographs tend to belong to this category. In these cases, every
synset has between one and two automatically derived English equivalents on the average, allowing us
to roughly compare with the initial quality check of the equivalence relations performed by Vossen et al.
(1999) showing that, in the event of a Dutch synset having only one English equivalent, 86% of the nouns
and 78% of the verbs were correctly linked, while the ones having two equivalents were appropriate in
68% and 71% of the cases respectively.
The F-score in Figure 3 reveals that the best trade-off between precision and recall is reached at the
&gt; 0% threshold value, improving the baseline precision for both Sclera and Beta. We now retrieve all
English synsets for which a non-zero score was obtained in order to assign Sclera and Beta pictographs
to Princeton WordNet.
</bodyText>
<footnote confidence="0.9997645">
9http://www.sclera.be
10http://www.betavzw.be
</footnote>
<page confidence="0.996565">
123
</page>
<figureCaption confidence="0.7491575">
Figure 3: Precision (top line), recall (bottom line) and F-score (middle line) for Sclera and Beta synsets
respectively, for different threshold values of link acceptance.
</figureCaption>
<table confidence="0.9997795">
Baseline Current Relative improvement
All 35.27% 21.09% 40.20%
Sclera 14.50% 9.95% 31.38%
Beta 15.77% 13.47% 14.58%
</table>
<tableCaption confidence="0.999749">
Table 3: The reduction in error rates of Cornetto’s equivalence relations.
</tableCaption>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.999344" genericHeader="method">
4 Related work
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9999764">
Using bilingual dictionaries to initiate or improve WordNet linkage has been applied elsewhere. Linking
Chinese lemmata to English synsets (Huang et al., 2003) to create the Chinese WordNet is one such
example. The 200 most frequent Chinese words and the 10 most frequent adjectives were taken as
a starting set and found as translation equivalences for 496 English lemmata, making each Chinese
lemma corresponding to 2.13 English synsets on average. Evaluations showed that 77% of the 496
equivalent pairs were synonymous. This accuracy rate dropped to 62.7% when the list of equivalence
pairs was extended by including all WordNet synonyms. Sornlertlamvanich et al. (2008) assign synsets
to bilingual dictionaries for Asian languages by considering English equivalents and lexical synonyms,
listing all English translations and scoring synsets according to the amount of matching translations
found, yielding an average accuracy rate of 49.4% for synset assignment to a Thai-English dictionary
and an accuracy rate of 93.3% for synsets that are attributed the highest confidence score. Joshi et
al. (2012) generate candidate synsets in English, starting with synsets in Hindi. For each Hindi synset, a
bag of words is obtained by parsing its gloss, examples and synonyms. Using a bilingual dictionary, these
Hindi words are translated to English. Various heuristics are used to calculate the intersection between
the translated bag of words and the synset words, concepts or relations of the target language, such as
finding the closest hyperonym synset (accuracy rate of 79.76%), the closest common synset word bag
(accuracy rate of 74.48%) and the closest common concept word bag (accuracy rate of 55.20%). Finally,
Soria et al. (2009) develop a mechanism for enriching monolingual lexicons with new semantic relations
by relying on the use of Inter-Lingual-Indexes to link WordNets of different languages. However, the
quality of these links is not evaluated.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.980148" genericHeader="conclusions">
5 Conclusions and future work
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999921857142857">
We have shown that a rather large reduction in error rates (a relative improvement of 40.20% on the
whole set) concerning the equivalence relations between Cornetto and Princeton WordNet can be ac-
quired by applying a scoring algorithm based on bilingual dictionaries. The method can be used to create
new equivalence relations as well. Contrasting our results with related work shows that we reach at least
the same level of correctness, although results are hard to compare because of conceptual differences
between languages. An accuracy rate of 78.91% was obtained for the general set of Cornetto’s equiva-
lence relations, while its subset of Sclera and Beta synsets (denoting frequent concepts) acquired final
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.995032">
124
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.99942">
precision rates of 90.05% and 86.53% respectively (compare with section 4).
One advantage of our method is that it could easily be reused to automatically build reliable links
between Princeton WordNet and brand-new WordNets. Unsupervised clustering methods can provide us
with synonym sets in the source language, after which the bilingual dictionary technique and the scoring
algorithm can be applied in order to provide us with satisfactory equivalence relations between both
languages. Semantic relations between synsets can then also be transferred from Princeton to the source
language’s WordNet.
Our improved links will be integrated in the next version of Cornetto. Future work will consist of
scaling to other languages through other relations between WordNets.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.998956" genericHeader="acknowledgments">
6 Acknowledgements
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999540833333333">
We would like to thank Tom Vanallemeersch for providing us with the EuroParl and Opus alignment
tables. We are also grateful to Martijn van der Kooij for sending us the mappings between the Dutch and
English Sclera pictograph file names made in the Picto-selector project.
The research in this paper was partly funded by the support fund M.M. Delacroix under the Picto
project, by the EU-CIP project Able-To-Include, and by the Program Advisory Committee of the Ad-
vanced Master of Artificial Intelligence of the University of Leuven.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.998929" genericHeader="references">
References
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.999662">
Chu-Ren Huang, Elanna Tseng, Dylan Tsai and Brian Murphy. 2003. Cross-lingual Portability of Semantic
relations: Bootstrapping Chinese WordNet with English WordNet Relations. Languages and Linguistics, 4(3):
509–532. Academia Sinica, Taipei.
Salil Joshi, Arindam Chatterjee, Arun Karthikeyan Karra and Pushpak Bhattacharyya. 2012. Eating Your Own
Cooking: Automatically Linking Wordnet Synsets of Two Languages. COLING (Demos): 239–246.
Philip Koehn. 2005. Europarl: A Parallel Corpus for Statistical Machine Translation. Conference Proceedings:
the tenth Machine Translation Summit: 79–86. Phuket, Thailand.
Philip Koehn, Hieu Hoang, Alexandra Birch, Chris Callison-Burch, Marcello Federico, Nicola Bertoldi, Brooke
Cowan, Wade Shen, Christine Moran, Richard Zens, Chris Dyer, Ondrej Bojar, Alexandra Constantin and
Evan Herbst. 2007. Moses: Open Source Toolkit for Statistical Machine Translation Annual Meeting of the
Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL), demonstration session. Prague, Czech Republic.
George A. Miller, Richard Beckwidth, Christiane Fellbaum, Derek Gross and Katherine Miller. 1990. Introduction
to WordNet: An On-line Lexical Database. International Journal of Lexicography, 3(4): 235–244.
Franz Josef Och and Hermann Ney. 2003. A Systematic Comparison of Various Statistical Alignment Models.
Computational Linguistics, 29(1): 19–51.
Claudia Soria, Monica Monachini, Francesca Bertagna, Nicoletta Calzolari, Chu-Ren Huang, Shu-Kai Hsieh,
Andrea Marchetti and Maurizio Tesconi. 2009. Exploring Interoperability of Language Resources: the Case of
Cross-lingual Semi-automatic Enrichment of Wordnets. In A. Witt, U. Heid, F. Sasaki and G. S´erasset (eds).
Special Issue on Interoperability of Multilingual Language Processing. Language Resources and Evaluation.,
43(1): 87–96.
Virach Sornlertlamvanich, Thatsanee Charoenporn, Chumpol Mokarat, Hitoshi Isahara, Hammam Riza and Purev
Jaimai. 2008. Synset Assignment for Bi-lingual Dictionary with Limited Resource. Proceedings of the Third
International Joint Conference on Natural Language Processing: 673–678.
Jrg Tiedemann. 2009. News from OPUS – A Collection of Multilingual Parallel Corpora with Tools and Interfaces.
In N. Nicolov and K. Bontcheva and G. Angelova and R. Mitkov (eds). Recent Advances in Natural Language
Processing, Volume V. John Benjamins: Amsterdam/Philadelphia.
Vincent Vandeghinste. Linking Pictographs to Synsets: Beta2Cornetto. Technical report.
Vincent Vandeghinste and Ineke Schuurman. 2014. Linking Pictographs to Synsets: Sclera2Cornetto. LREC
2014. In press.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.981284">
125
</page>
<reference confidence="0.995887428571429">
Piek Vossen. 1997. EuroWordNet: a multilingual database for information retrieval. Proceedings of the DELOS
workshop on Cross-language Information Retrieval. Zurich.
Piek Vossen, Laura Bloksma, and Paul Boersma. 1999. The Dutch Wordnet. EuroWordNet Paper. University of
Amsterdam, Amsterdam.
Piek Vossen, Katja Hofman, Maarten de Rijke, Erik Tjong Kim Sang and Koen Deschacht. 2007 The Cornetto
Database: Architecture and User-Scenarios. Proceedings of 7th Dutch-Belgian Information Retrieval Workshop
DIR2007. University of Leuven, Leuven.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.99854">
126
</page>
</variant>
</algorithm>
<algorithm name="ParsHed" version="110505">
<variant no="0" confidence="0.408906">
<title confidence="0.9877465">Improving the Precision of Synset Links Between Cornetto and Princeton WordNet</title>
<author confidence="0.983492">Leen Sevens Vincent Vandeghinste Frank Van_Eynde</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.964437">Centre for Computational</affiliation>
<address confidence="0.453883">KU Leuven</address>
<email confidence="0.992452">firstname@ccl.kuleuven.be</email>
<abstract confidence="0.994515384615385">Knowledge-based multilingual language processing benefits from having access to correctly established relations between semantic lexicons, such as the links between different WordNets. WordNet linking is a process that can be sped up by the use of computational techniques. Manual evaluations of the partly automatically established synonym set (synset) relations between Dutch and English in Cornetto, a Dutch lexical-semantic database associated with the EuroWordNet grid, have confronted us with a worrisome amount of erroneous links. By extracting translations from various bilingual resources and automatically assigning a confidence score to every pre-established link, we reduce the error rate of the existing equivalence relations between both languages’ synsets (section 2). We will apply this technique to reuse the connection of Sclera and Beta pictograph sets and Cornetto synsets to Princeton WordNet and other WordNets, allowing us to further extend an existing Dutch text-to-pictograph translation tool to other languages (section 3).</abstract>
</variant>
</algorithm>
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Chu-Ren Huang</author>
<author>Elanna Tseng</author>
<author>Dylan Tsai</author>
<author>Brian Murphy</author>
</authors>
<title>Cross-lingual Portability of Semantic relations: Bootstrapping Chinese WordNet with English WordNet Relations.</title>
<date>2003</date>
<journal>Languages and Linguistics,</journal>
<booktitle>Academia Sinica,</booktitle>
<volume>4</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<pages>509--532</pages>
<location>Taipei.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="13541" citStr="Huang et al., 2003" startWordPosition="2028" endWordPosition="2031">ctographs to Princeton WordNet. 9http://www.sclera.be 10http://www.betavzw.be 123 Figure 3: Precision (top line), recall (bottom line) and F-score (middle line) for Sclera and Beta synsets respectively, for different threshold values of link acceptance. Baseline Current Relative improvement All 35.27% 21.09% 40.20% Sclera 14.50% 9.95% 31.38% Beta 15.77% 13.47% 14.58% Table 3: The reduction in error rates of Cornetto’s equivalence relations. 4 Related work Using bilingual dictionaries to initiate or improve WordNet linkage has been applied elsewhere. Linking Chinese lemmata to English synsets (Huang et al., 2003) to create the Chinese WordNet is one such example. The 200 most frequent Chinese words and the 10 most frequent adjectives were taken as a starting set and found as translation equivalences for 496 English lemmata, making each Chinese lemma corresponding to 2.13 English synsets on average. Evaluations showed that 77% of the 496 equivalent pairs were synonymous. This accuracy rate dropped to 62.7% when the list of equivalence pairs was extended by including all WordNet synonyms. Sornlertlamvanich et al. (2008) assign synsets to bilingual dictionaries for Asian languages by considering English </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Huang, Tseng, Tsai, Murphy, 2003</marker>
<rawString>Chu-Ren Huang, Elanna Tseng, Dylan Tsai and Brian Murphy. 2003. Cross-lingual Portability of Semantic relations: Bootstrapping Chinese WordNet with English WordNet Relations. Languages and Linguistics, 4(3): 509–532. Academia Sinica, Taipei.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Salil Joshi</author>
</authors>
<title>Arindam Chatterjee, Arun Karthikeyan Karra and Pushpak Bhattacharyya.</title>
<date>2012</date>
<pages>239--246</pages>
<publisher>COLING (Demos):</publisher>
<marker>Joshi, 2012</marker>
<rawString>Salil Joshi, Arindam Chatterjee, Arun Karthikeyan Karra and Pushpak Bhattacharyya. 2012. Eating Your Own Cooking: Automatically Linking Wordnet Synsets of Two Languages. COLING (Demos): 239–246.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Philip Koehn</author>
</authors>
<title>Europarl: A Parallel Corpus for</title>
<date>2005</date>
<booktitle>Statistical Machine Translation. Conference Proceedings: the tenth Machine Translation Summit:</booktitle>
<pages>79--86</pages>
<location>Phuket, Thailand.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="6016" citStr="Koehn, 2005" startWordPosition="868" endWordPosition="869">s, while others are automatically derived word lists from parallel corpora: we extracted the 1-word phrases from the phrase tables built with Moses (Koehn et al., 2007) based on the GIZA++ word alignments (Och and Ney, 2003). Table 1 gives an overview. This resulted in a coverage of 52.18% (43 970 out of 84 264) of the equivalence relations for which translation information was available in order to possibly confirm the relation. Translation dictionary Reference Method of compilation Nr of word pairs Wiktionary www.wiktionary.org Manual 23,575 FreeDict www.freedict.com Manual 49,493 Europarl (Koehn, 2005) Automatic 2,970,501 Opus (Tiedemann, 2009) Automatic 6,223,539 Sclera translations www.pictoselector.eu Manual 12,381 Table 1: The used translation sources Figure 1 visualizes how we used the bilingual dictionaries to automatically evaluate the quality of the pre-established links between Cornetto and Princeton WordNet. We retrieve all the lemmas of the lexical units that were contained within a synset Si (in our example, snoepgoed ”confectionary” and snoep ”candy” extracted from S1). Each of these lemmas is looked up in the bilingual dictionary, resulting in a dictionary words list of Englis</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Koehn, 2005</marker>
<rawString>Philip Koehn. 2005. Europarl: A Parallel Corpus for Statistical Machine Translation. Conference Proceedings: the tenth Machine Translation Summit: 79–86. Phuket, Thailand.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>Philip Koehn</author>
<author>Hieu Hoang</author>
<author>Alexandra Birch</author>
<author>Chris Callison-Burch</author>
<author>Marcello Federico</author>
<author>Nicola Bertoldi</author>
<author>Brooke Cowan</author>
<author>Wade Shen</author>
<author>Christine Moran</author>
<author>Richard Zens</author>
</authors>
<title>Chris Dyer, Ondrej Bojar, Alexandra Constantin and Evan Herbst.</title>
<date>2007</date>
<location>Prague, Czech Republic.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="5572" citStr="Koehn et al., 2007" startWordPosition="800" endWordPosition="803">ke these are omnipresent in our data6 and led us to conclude that the synset links between Cornetto and Princeton WordNet definitely could be improved. We build a bilingual dictionary for Dutch and English and use these translations as an automatic indicator of the quality of equivalence relations. In order to create a huge list of translations we merge several translation word lists, removing double entries. Some are manually compiled dictionaries, while others are automatically derived word lists from parallel corpora: we extracted the 1-word phrases from the phrase tables built with Moses (Koehn et al., 2007) based on the GIZA++ word alignments (Och and Ney, 2003). Table 1 gives an overview. This resulted in a coverage of 52.18% (43 970 out of 84 264) of the equivalence relations for which translation information was available in order to possibly confirm the relation. Translation dictionary Reference Method of compilation Nr of word pairs Wiktionary www.wiktionary.org Manual 23,575 FreeDict www.freedict.com Manual 49,493 Europarl (Koehn, 2005) Automatic 2,970,501 Opus (Tiedemann, 2009) Automatic 6,223,539 Sclera translations www.pictoselector.eu Manual 12,381 Table 1: The used translation sources</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Koehn, Hoang, Birch, Callison-Burch, Federico, Bertoldi, Cowan, Shen, Moran, Zens, 2007</marker>
<rawString>Philip Koehn, Hieu Hoang, Alexandra Birch, Chris Callison-Burch, Marcello Federico, Nicola Bertoldi, Brooke Cowan, Wade Shen, Christine Moran, Richard Zens, Chris Dyer, Ondrej Bojar, Alexandra Constantin and Evan Herbst. 2007. Moses: Open Source Toolkit for Statistical Machine Translation Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL), demonstration session. Prague, Czech Republic.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>George A Miller</author>
<author>Richard Beckwidth</author>
<author>Christiane Fellbaum</author>
<author>Derek Gross</author>
<author>Katherine Miller</author>
</authors>
<title>Introduction to WordNet: An On-line Lexical Database.</title>
<date>1990</date>
<journal>International Journal of Lexicography,</journal>
<volume>3</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<pages>235--244</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="1601" citStr="Miller et al., 1990" startWordPosition="218" endWordPosition="221">(section 2). We will apply this technique to reuse the connection of Sclera and Beta pictograph sets and Cornetto synsets to Princeton WordNet and other WordNets, allowing us to further extend an existing Dutch text-to-pictograph translation tool to other languages (section 3). 1 Introduction The connections between WordNets, large semantic databases grouping lexical units into synonym sets or synsets, are an important resource in knowledge-based multilingual language processing. EuroWordNet (Vossen, 1997) aims to build language-specific WordNets among the same lines as the original WordNet1 (Miller et al., 1990), using Inter-Lingual-Indexes to weave a web of equivalence relations between the synsets contained within the databases. Cornetto2 (Vossen et al., 2007), a Dutch lexical-semantic collection of data associated with the Dutch EuroWordNet3, consists of more than 118 000 synsets. The equivalence relations establish connections between Dutch and English synsets in Princeton WordNet version 1.5 and 2.0. We update these links to Princeton WordNet version 3.0 by the mappings among WordNet versions made available by TALP-UPC 4. The equivalence relations between Cornetto and Princeton have been establi</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Miller, Beckwidth, Fellbaum, Gross, Miller, 1990</marker>
<rawString>George A. Miller, Richard Beckwidth, Christiane Fellbaum, Derek Gross and Katherine Miller. 1990. Introduction to WordNet: An On-line Lexical Database. International Journal of Lexicography, 3(4): 235–244.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Franz Josef Och</author>
<author>Hermann Ney</author>
</authors>
<title>A Systematic Comparison of Various Statistical Alignment Models.</title>
<date>2003</date>
<journal>Computational Linguistics,</journal>
<volume>29</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<contexts>
<context position="5628" citStr="Och and Ney, 2003" startWordPosition="810" endWordPosition="813">ude that the synset links between Cornetto and Princeton WordNet definitely could be improved. We build a bilingual dictionary for Dutch and English and use these translations as an automatic indicator of the quality of equivalence relations. In order to create a huge list of translations we merge several translation word lists, removing double entries. Some are manually compiled dictionaries, while others are automatically derived word lists from parallel corpora: we extracted the 1-word phrases from the phrase tables built with Moses (Koehn et al., 2007) based on the GIZA++ word alignments (Och and Ney, 2003). Table 1 gives an overview. This resulted in a coverage of 52.18% (43 970 out of 84 264) of the equivalence relations for which translation information was available in order to possibly confirm the relation. Translation dictionary Reference Method of compilation Nr of word pairs Wiktionary www.wiktionary.org Manual 23,575 FreeDict www.freedict.com Manual 49,493 Europarl (Koehn, 2005) Automatic 2,970,501 Opus (Tiedemann, 2009) Automatic 6,223,539 Sclera translations www.pictoselector.eu Manual 12,381 Table 1: The used translation sources Figure 1 visualizes how we used the bilingual dictionar</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Och, Ney, 2003</marker>
<rawString>Franz Josef Och and Hermann Ney. 2003. A Systematic Comparison of Various Statistical Alignment Models. Computational Linguistics, 29(1): 19–51.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>Claudia Soria</author>
<author>Monica Monachini</author>
<author>Francesca Bertagna</author>
<author>Nicoletta Calzolari</author>
<author>Chu-Ren Huang</author>
<author>Shu-Kai Hsieh</author>
<author>Andrea Marchetti</author>
<author>Maurizio Tesconi</author>
</authors>
<title>Exploring Interoperability of Language Resources: the Case of Cross-lingual Semi-automatic Enrichment of Wordnets. In</title>
<date>2009</date>
<booktitle>Special Issue on Interoperability of Multilingual Language Processing. Language Resources and Evaluation.,</booktitle>
<volume>43</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<pages>87--96</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="15121" citStr="Soria et al. (2009)" startWordPosition="2272" endWordPosition="2275">didate synsets in English, starting with synsets in Hindi. For each Hindi synset, a bag of words is obtained by parsing its gloss, examples and synonyms. Using a bilingual dictionary, these Hindi words are translated to English. Various heuristics are used to calculate the intersection between the translated bag of words and the synset words, concepts or relations of the target language, such as finding the closest hyperonym synset (accuracy rate of 79.76%), the closest common synset word bag (accuracy rate of 74.48%) and the closest common concept word bag (accuracy rate of 55.20%). Finally, Soria et al. (2009) develop a mechanism for enriching monolingual lexicons with new semantic relations by relying on the use of Inter-Lingual-Indexes to link WordNets of different languages. However, the quality of these links is not evaluated. 5 Conclusions and future work We have shown that a rather large reduction in error rates (a relative improvement of 40.20% on the whole set) concerning the equivalence relations between Cornetto and Princeton WordNet can be acquired by applying a scoring algorithm based on bilingual dictionaries. The method can be used to create new equivalence relations as well. Contrast</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Soria, Monachini, Bertagna, Calzolari, Huang, Hsieh, Marchetti, Tesconi, 2009</marker>
<rawString>Claudia Soria, Monica Monachini, Francesca Bertagna, Nicoletta Calzolari, Chu-Ren Huang, Shu-Kai Hsieh, Andrea Marchetti and Maurizio Tesconi. 2009. Exploring Interoperability of Language Resources: the Case of Cross-lingual Semi-automatic Enrichment of Wordnets. In A. Witt, U. Heid, F. Sasaki and G. S´erasset (eds). Special Issue on Interoperability of Multilingual Language Processing. Language Resources and Evaluation., 43(1): 87–96.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Virach Sornlertlamvanich</author>
</authors>
<title>Thatsanee Charoenporn, Chumpol Mokarat, Hitoshi Isahara, Hammam Riza and Purev Jaimai.</title>
<date>2008</date>
<booktitle>Proceedings of the Third International Joint Conference on Natural Language Processing:</booktitle>
<pages>673--678</pages>
<marker>Sornlertlamvanich, 2008</marker>
<rawString>Virach Sornlertlamvanich, Thatsanee Charoenporn, Chumpol Mokarat, Hitoshi Isahara, Hammam Riza and Purev Jaimai. 2008. Synset Assignment for Bi-lingual Dictionary with Limited Resource. Proceedings of the Third International Joint Conference on Natural Language Processing: 673–678.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Jrg Tiedemann</author>
</authors>
<title>News from OPUS – A Collection of Multilingual Parallel Corpora with Tools and Interfaces. In</title>
<date>2009</date>
<booktitle>Recent Advances in Natural Language Processing, Volume</booktitle>
<tech>Technical report.</tech>
<contexts>
<context position="6059" citStr="Tiedemann, 2009" startWordPosition="873" endWordPosition="874">ed word lists from parallel corpora: we extracted the 1-word phrases from the phrase tables built with Moses (Koehn et al., 2007) based on the GIZA++ word alignments (Och and Ney, 2003). Table 1 gives an overview. This resulted in a coverage of 52.18% (43 970 out of 84 264) of the equivalence relations for which translation information was available in order to possibly confirm the relation. Translation dictionary Reference Method of compilation Nr of word pairs Wiktionary www.wiktionary.org Manual 23,575 FreeDict www.freedict.com Manual 49,493 Europarl (Koehn, 2005) Automatic 2,970,501 Opus (Tiedemann, 2009) Automatic 6,223,539 Sclera translations www.pictoselector.eu Manual 12,381 Table 1: The used translation sources Figure 1 visualizes how we used the bilingual dictionaries to automatically evaluate the quality of the pre-established links between Cornetto and Princeton WordNet. We retrieve all the lemmas of the lexical units that were contained within a synset Si (in our example, snoepgoed ”confectionary” and snoep ”candy” extracted from S1). Each of these lemmas is looked up in the bilingual dictionary, resulting in a dictionary words list of English translations.7 This list is used to estim</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Tiedemann, 2009</marker>
<rawString>Jrg Tiedemann. 2009. News from OPUS – A Collection of Multilingual Parallel Corpora with Tools and Interfaces. In N. Nicolov and K. Bontcheva and G. Angelova and R. Mitkov (eds). Recent Advances in Natural Language Processing, Volume V. John Benjamins: Amsterdam/Philadelphia. Vincent Vandeghinste. Linking Pictographs to Synsets: Beta2Cornetto. Technical report.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Vincent Vandeghinste</author>
<author>Ineke Schuurman</author>
</authors>
<date>2014</date>
<booktitle>Linking Pictographs to Synsets: Sclera2Cornetto. LREC</booktitle>
<note>In press.</note>
<contexts>
<context position="9992" citStr="Vandeghinste and Schuurman (2014)" startWordPosition="1482" endWordPosition="1485">oming an increasingly important factor in today’s society. Augmentative and Alternative Communication (AAC) refers to the whole of communication methods which aim to assist people that are suffering from cognitive disabilities, helping them to become more socially active in various domains of daily life. Text-to-pictograph translation is a particular form of AAC technology that enables linguistically-impaired people to use the Internet independently. Filtering away erroneous synset links in Cornetto has proven to be a useful way to improve the quality of a text-to-pictograph translation tool. Vandeghinste and Schuurman (2014) have connected pictograph sets to Cornetto synsets to enable text-to-pictograph translation. Equivalence relations are important to allow reusing these connections in order to link pictographs to synsets for other languages than Dutch. 122 Figure 2: Precision (top line), recall (bottom line) and F-score (middle line) for different threshold values of link acceptance. Vandeghinste and Schuurman (2014) released Sclera2Cornetto, a resource linking Sclera9 pictographs to Cornetto synsets. Currently, over 13 000 Sclera pictographs are made available online, 5 710 of which have been manually linked</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Vandeghinste, Schuurman, 2014</marker>
<rawString>Vincent Vandeghinste and Ineke Schuurman. 2014. Linking Pictographs to Synsets: Sclera2Cornetto. LREC 2014. In press.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Piek Vossen</author>
</authors>
<title>EuroWordNet: a multilingual database for information retrieval.</title>
<date>1997</date>
<booktitle>Proceedings of the DELOS workshop on Cross-language Information Retrieval.</booktitle>
<location>Zurich.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="1492" citStr="Vossen, 1997" startWordPosition="203" endWordPosition="204"> link, we reduce the error rate of the existing equivalence relations between both languages’ synsets (section 2). We will apply this technique to reuse the connection of Sclera and Beta pictograph sets and Cornetto synsets to Princeton WordNet and other WordNets, allowing us to further extend an existing Dutch text-to-pictograph translation tool to other languages (section 3). 1 Introduction The connections between WordNets, large semantic databases grouping lexical units into synonym sets or synsets, are an important resource in knowledge-based multilingual language processing. EuroWordNet (Vossen, 1997) aims to build language-specific WordNets among the same lines as the original WordNet1 (Miller et al., 1990), using Inter-Lingual-Indexes to weave a web of equivalence relations between the synsets contained within the databases. Cornetto2 (Vossen et al., 2007), a Dutch lexical-semantic collection of data associated with the Dutch EuroWordNet3, consists of more than 118 000 synsets. The equivalence relations establish connections between Dutch and English synsets in Princeton WordNet version 1.5 and 2.0. We update these links to Princeton WordNet version 3.0 by the mappings among WordNet vers</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Vossen, 1997</marker>
<rawString>Piek Vossen. 1997. EuroWordNet: a multilingual database for information retrieval. Proceedings of the DELOS workshop on Cross-language Information Retrieval. Zurich.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Piek Vossen</author>
<author>Laura Bloksma</author>
<author>Paul Boersma</author>
</authors>
<date>1999</date>
<institution>The Dutch Wordnet. EuroWordNet Paper. University of Amsterdam,</institution>
<location>Amsterdam.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="2248" citStr="Vossen et al. (1999)" startWordPosition="311" endWordPosition="314">es to weave a web of equivalence relations between the synsets contained within the databases. Cornetto2 (Vossen et al., 2007), a Dutch lexical-semantic collection of data associated with the Dutch EuroWordNet3, consists of more than 118 000 synsets. The equivalence relations establish connections between Dutch and English synsets in Princeton WordNet version 1.5 and 2.0. We update these links to Princeton WordNet version 3.0 by the mappings among WordNet versions made available by TALP-UPC 4. The equivalence relations between Cornetto and Princeton have been established semi-automatically by Vossen et al. (1999). Manual coding was carried out for the 14 749 most important concepts in the database. These include the most frequent concepts, the concepts having a large amount of semantic relations and the concepts occupying a high position in the lexical hierarchy. Automatic linkage was done by mapping the bilingual Van Dale database5 to WordNet 1.5. For every WordNet synset containing a dictionary’s translation for a particular Dutch word, all its members were proposed as alternative translations. In the case of only one translation, the synset relation was instantly assumed correct, while multiple tra</context>
<context position="4241" citStr="Vossen et al. (1999)" startWordPosition="584" endWordPosition="587">14, Dublin, Ireland, August 24 2014. 2 Improving the equivalence relations between Cornetto and Princeton WordNet We manually evaluated the quality of the links between 300 randomly selected Cornetto synsets and their supposedly related Princeton synsets. A Cornetto synset is often linked to more than one Princeton synset. We found an erroneous link in 35.27% of the 998 equivalence relations we evaluated. Each Cornetto synset has about 3.3 automatically derived English equivalents, allowing to roughly compare our evaluation to an initial quality check of the equivalence relations performed by Vossen et al. (1999). They note that, in the case of synsets with three to nine translations, the percentages of correct automatically derived equivalents went down to 65% and 49% for nouns and verbs respectively. Our manual evaluations are in line with these results, showing that only 64.73% of all the connections in our sample are correct. An example of where it goes wrong is the Cornetto synset for the animal tor ”beetle”, which is not only appropriately linked to correct synsets (such as beetle and bug), but also mistakenly to the Princeton synset for the computational glitch. This flaw is most probably cause</context>
<context position="11990" citStr="Vossen et al. (1999)" startWordPosition="1786" endWordPosition="1789">ents the coverage of our bilingual dictionary for synsets being connected to Sclera and Beta pictographs, which is clearly higher than the coverage over all synsets. Covered Total Difference with All synsets All synsets 43 970 (52.18%) 84 264 - Sclera baseline 5 294 (88.80%) 5 962 36.62% Beta synsets 3 409 (88.94%) 3 833 36.76% Table 2: Dictionary Coverage for different sets of synsets Table 3 shows that the error rate of Cornetto’s equivalence relations on the Sclera and Beta subsets is much lower than the error rate on the whole set (section 2). We attribute this difference to the fact that Vossen et al. (1999) carried out manual coding for the most important concepts in the database (see section 1), as the Sclera and Beta pictographs tend to belong to this category. In these cases, every synset has between one and two automatically derived English equivalents on the average, allowing us to roughly compare with the initial quality check of the equivalence relations performed by Vossen et al. (1999) showing that, in the event of a Dutch synset having only one English equivalent, 86% of the nouns and 78% of the verbs were correctly linked, while the ones having two equivalents were appropriate in 68% </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Vossen, Bloksma, Boersma, 1999</marker>
<rawString>Piek Vossen, Laura Bloksma, and Paul Boersma. 1999. The Dutch Wordnet. EuroWordNet Paper. University of Amsterdam, Amsterdam.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Piek Vossen</author>
</authors>
<title>Katja Hofman, Maarten de Rijke, Erik Tjong Kim Sang and Koen Deschacht.</title>
<date>2007</date>
<booktitle>Proceedings of 7th Dutch-Belgian Information Retrieval Workshop DIR2007.</booktitle>
<institution>University of Leuven,</institution>
<location>Leuven.</location>
<marker>Vossen, 2007</marker>
<rawString>Piek Vossen, Katja Hofman, Maarten de Rijke, Erik Tjong Kim Sang and Koen Deschacht. 2007 The Cornetto Database: Architecture and User-Scenarios. Proceedings of 7th Dutch-Belgian Information Retrieval Workshop DIR2007. University of Leuven, Leuven.</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>