<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="SectLabel" version="110505">
<variant no="0" confidence="0.010095">
<title confidence="0.99287">
Language Technologies for Suicide Prevention in Social Media
</title>
<author confidence="0.997709">
Jose M. Gomez
</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.989643">
Department of Software and Computing Systems, University of Alicante
</affiliation>
<email confidence="0.976183">
jmgomez@ua.es
</email>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.995205" genericHeader="abstract">
Abstract
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999967612903226">
At present, the suicide phenomenon is
raising, having a relevant impact on our
society. Each year about one million
people die as a result of suicidal behavior
becoming an economic, social and
human problem. On the other hand, the
use of Social Media as a means of
communication is becoming extremely
popular, through which their emotional
states and impressions are exchanged.
Therefore, it is no surprise that more and
more people with depression publish
their suicide notes in these
communication channels. In this context,
Information Technologies and
Communications and, more specifically,
Language Technologies play an
important role in the early detection of
the depression, their causes and their
terrible consequences. Based on these
considerations, it is mandatory to provide
societal, environmentally approaches and
solutions to tackle these societal
challenges. This work pretends to be an
exhaustive survey of the different
researches in this scope, in order to
explain which methodologies,
technologies and resources are used in
the detection of mental problems by
means of the Social Media analysis as
well as to re-veal their deficiencies.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.997736" genericHeader="keywords">
1 Introduction
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9999515">
In Europe, suicide has become the leading cause
of violent death (WHO, 2014). Each year
804.000 people die in the world as a result of
suicidal behavior and the number of attempts is
about 20 times higher (WHO, 2012; WHO,
2014). It is estimated that in 2020, about 1.53
million people will die as a result of suicidal acts.
Preventing suicide is one of the five areas of
priority of the European Pact for Mental Health
and Well- Being1, which was launched by the
European Commission in 2008. Suicide is the
third leading cause of violent death among
people aged 15 to 44, followed by accidents and
homicides (Holmes et al., 2007), and it would be
the second reason that would explain the deaths
in the group of people aged 15 to 19 years
(WHO, 2014). Suicidal behaviors can be defined
as a complex process that can range from suicidal
ideation (communicated through verbal or non-
verbal means) to planning of suicide, attempting
suicide, and in the worst case, the suicide itself.
These behaviors are influenced by interacting
biological, genetic, psychological, social,
environmental and situational factors
(Wasserman et al., 2004).
Suicide has also been strong linked to inequity,
social exclusion and socio-economic deprivation
(Berk and Dodd, 2006). It is an enormous
problem that causing unnecessary human
suffering and immeasurable costs for society.
According to Josee Van Remoortel, advisor to
the European organization Mental Health
Europe2 (MHE), the financial crisis is affecting
“all areas of life”, not just economies, and its
impact on mental health is creating a “deep
chasm in our society”.
</bodyText>
<footnote confidence="0.986395333333333">
1http://ec.europa.eu/health/ph_determinants/life_style/menta
l/docs/pact_en.pdf
2http://www.mhe-sme.org/
</footnote>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.338972" genericHeader="introduction">
2 Internet and Social Media Penetration
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999925458333333">
In the other hand, studies reveal that between
90.1% and 97.8% of young people between 10
and 15 years, access the Internet3; and, around
88.5% of youth aged 16 to 24 choose social
networks as a way to communicate. Therefore,
the use of this type of technology can be up to
90.2%, in the case of students (García-Rabagó et
al., 2010). Forums, chats, social networks, blogs,
microblogs or e-mails are virtual spaces where
Internet users can interact freely and even
fantasize, using anonymous identities. This
implies that people with suicidal tendencies, tend
to express their thoughts, desires and intentions
in pro-suicide forums and share with other
people, feelings and intentions (Moreno Gea and
Blanco Sanchez, 2012). They also warn their
suicidal intentions through the Web in real time,
before and while committing the act (Sarno,
2008). The study conducted in (Mingote et al.,
2004) also proves that the younger are one of the
population segments where prevention is
particularly necessary, finding that 20% of
suicides occur among adolescents and young
adults.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.891851" genericHeader="method">
3 Suicide Prevention in Social Media
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999970920634921">
It is important to raise awareness on that most
self-inflicted deaths are potentially preventable.
Well-known studies concerning research on
suicide (Owen et al., 2012; Isometsa, 2001;
Cantor, 2000; Rudestam, 1971) show that a high
number of people who decide to end with their
lives. Through suicide had no prior contact with
mental health services, but had communicated
their suicidal plans or thoughts directly or
indirectly through different means to members of
their family, friends, colleagues, or through their
social networks. Improve the staff skills in early
recognition of suicide warning signs, is an
essential issue to prevent suicidal mortality.
There is an increasing tendency (Ruder et al.,
2011) where suicide notes are posted on the
social media (e.g., Facebook, Twitter), where
Internet users (and not necessarily teenagers)
announce their suicidal thoughts before
committing suicide. This poses new challenges
for human language technologies since,
traditional existing automatic tools are not able to
process the new language employed in the social
media (abbreviations, slang, smiles and, more
generally, a low unstructured and highly informal
language).
The Internet, and specifically the Web 2.0, is
an important source of information for learning
about suicidal behaviors (Dunlop et al., 2011).
The way individuals respond to help request
from people at high risk of suicide or interact
with them can lead to the fact that the potential
suicidal may reconsider his/her final decision, or,
on the contrary, encourage and accelerate the
process of ending with his/her life (Wasserman et
al., 2004).
During the recent years, some popular social
networks, such as Facebook have become the
most important means of social communication,
with nearly 1,230 million of registered users
world-wide4, 70% of whom are young people
who make frequent use of this type of media,
through which the emotional states and
impressions are exchanged (Dunlop et al., 2011;
Lenhart et al., 2010). These social networks are
also a way to find comfort and welfare and its
usage promotes contact and positive support
among young people, especially among those
with mental disorders (Ellison et al., 2007). In
addition, the Web offers possibilities for early
detection on suicidal behaviors and it may
constitute a cost-effective means of intervention
based on a first step care approach. Their use
may be of help for identifying pro-suicide
messages, detecting group patterns, analyzing
exposure to the warning signs and intervening in
a personalized manner with people at risk who
are willing to accept professional help. In order
to raise awareness of the ways people could get
help when showing a suicidal behavior,
Facebook and the Samaritans5 association
developed a joint initiative consisting in adding a
new feature to Facebook, where anyone worried
</bodyText>
<footnote confidence="0.986730666666667">
4http://investor.fb.com/releasedetail.
3http://ec.europa.eu/eurostat/product? cfm?ReleaseID=821954
code=isoc_pibi_use&amp;mode=view 5http://www.samaritans.org/
</footnote>
<bodyText confidence="0.994051358407081">
about a friend could fill out a form, related to
suicide prevention. With the development of
Web 2.0 new forms of communication arise that
allow to interactively disseminate information
through forums, blogs, micro-blogs, mobile apps,
etc. These technologies provide new
opportunities to define and develop suicide
prevention strategies. The use of e-health
technologies has many beneficial applications for
society. Every day millions of people access the
Web to find, provide and share information about
opinions, feelings and even plans and intentions.
Recognizing suicidal warning signs will be the
first necessary step to help and offer support to
these people. A study that examines the warning
signs of suicide on the Internet (Mandrusiak et
al., 2006) found that the searches with the terms
“warning signals” and “suicide” produced
approximately 183,000 outcomes. Warning signs
could be categorized in terms of cognitive
content, behavioral, situational or other
indicators concerning psychological
characteristics or interpersonal problems. They
could identify suicidal groups that need urgent
intervention. Internet searches for suicide may
provide a faster way of monitoring possible
trends in suicide.
Some clinical studies observed that depressed
patients frequently speech slow, uniform,
monotonous and with a low voice (Kuny and
Stassen, 1993) or to have psychomotor
symptoms and this is reflected in the speech
(Sobin and Sackeim, 1997). Moreover, emotions
and mood can influence the speaking behavior of
a person and the characteristics of the sound in
speech (Kuny and Stassen, 1993; Bachorowski
and Owren, 1995; Sobin and Alpert, 1999;
Scherer, 2003; Goudbeek and Scherer, 2010).
The speech of depressed patients is characterized
by a longer pause duration, that is, an increased
amount of time between speech utterances as
well as by a reduced variability in mean vocal
pitch (Lamers et al., 2014). For these reasons, the
acoustic speech features can be used to build
models and algorithms for automated depression
detection in clinical scenarios.
But these acoustic features are not the only
ones that can be used, Internet usage itself
(Katikala-pudi et al., 2012), social networking
behaviors (Moreno et al., 2011; Choudhury et al.,
2012) or location sharing (Park et al., 2013) can
vary as a function of being depressed. (Quercia et
al., 2012) found correlations between sentiment
and levels of popularity, influence and general
well-being using the network relations among
users and (O’Connor et al., 2010) used a measure
of public opinion. All these methods can be
applied to analyze emotion in suicide notes
(Liakata et al., 2012).
5 Human Language Technologies and
Suicide Prevention
In order to resolve this social issue, Language
Technologies (LT) could help with the early
identification of “suicide warning signs” that will
be useful to detect individuals with suicidal
ideation, as well as virtual environments where
pro-suicide information is being shared or
suicidal attempts are being encouraged. In
particular, LT can analyze language structures
and their meaning (Navigli, 2009) on different
textual genres. Tasks such as information
retrieval (Salton and McGill, 1986), information
extraction (Cowie and Lehnert, 1996), text
classification and clustering (Sebastiani, 2002),
or sentiment analysis (Pang and Lee, 2008) are
basic pillars of these technologies that allow the
construction of more complex automatic
processes for discovering knowledge from oral
and/or written text.
Recent research in LT has been proved great
potential in the area of healthcare. From the
development of applications to assist medical
practitioners in the access and management of
information about patients, e.g. (Iakovidis and
Smailis, 2012; Vest, 2012), to the creation of
computer programs to support and/or facilitate
reading comprehension for language-impaired
children during communication (Dietz et al.,
2011; Wang and Paul, 2011). So far, and to the
best of our knowledge, very little effort has been
made to apply LT for the benefit of suicide
prevention.
The linguistic analysis of suicide notes has a
long history and already started as early as 1956
with the work of (Shneidman and Farberow,
1956), followed by several others (Osgood and
Walker, 1959; Gleser et al., 1961; Edelman and
Renshaw, 1982). The basis of most of this
research was a corpus of 66 suicides notes, half
genuine and half simulated, collected by
Schneidman and the task was to identify those
textual features which could differentiate
between genuine and fake notes. Whereas the
earlier work mostly focused on the manual
analysis and detection of these differentiating
features, e.g. by relying on techniques from
discourse analysis (Shneidman and Farberow,
1956) or by focusing on shallow text
characteristics such as the usage of modals and
auxiliaries (Osgood and Walker, 1959), the
choice of verbs and adverbs (Gleser et al., 1961),
etc. We can observe a recent tendency to also
rely on automatic corpus analysis techniques for
the automatic detection of suicide messages.
(Shapero, 2011), for example, studied two
corpora of suicide notes in an attempt to define
the typical suicide note. For doing so, she
automatically calculated word usage and
semantic concepts in the notes. (Pennebaker and
Chung, 2011) used the frequency of verbal
elements in a narrative that express a certain
mood or sentiment which show that there is also
ample evidence that text mining techniques
based on the frequency of certain terms can be
applied to narratives from patients in order to
monitor changes in mood. As far as we know,
(Pestian et al., 2010) were the first to experiment
with the use machine learning techniques for the
automatic classification of suicide notes. In
experiments on the earlier described data set of
66 notes, they investigated whether a machine
learning system was able to classify suicide notes
with a higher accuracy than mental health
professionals. They showed that the best machine
learners were indeed able to outperform the
human experts. More recent studies confirm this
fact (Janssen et al., 2013), underlining once again
the added value of automated speech analysis.
(Howes et al., 2014) present an initial
investigation into the application of
computational linguistic techniques, such as
topic and sentiment modelling, to online therapy
for depression and anxiety using Latent Dirichlet
Allocation (Blei et al., 2003). However, early
works tried to detect specific emotions such as
anger, surprise, fear, etc. using dictionary-based
or machine-learning-based approaches (Chuang
and Wu, 2004; Seol et al., 2008) and more
recently (Purver and Battersby, 2012; Choudhury
et al., 2012; Neuman et al., 2012; Howes et al.,
2014).
Although interesting research was conducted
on the Schneidman data set, the focus should not
be on distinguishing between genuine and
elicited suicide notes. Instead, it is of key
importance to determine what exactly makes a
note a real suicide note, independently of the
features of the elicited notes or the distinguishing
characteristics between both types of notes. Such
a suicide note corpus of positive-only data,
annotated with fine-grained emotions, was
released in the framework of the 2011 i2b2
Natural Language Processing Challenge (Pestian
et al., 2012) on emotion classification in suicide
notes. Although the scope of the challenge
(differentiating between emotions in positive-
only data) was different, it led to the creation of a
permanently available resource facilitating future
research in emotion detection in suicide notes.
The corpus contains the notes written by 1319
people, before they committed suicide. The notes
were collected between 1950 and 2011. Spelling
and grammar errors were kept in the data. All
notes were anonymized by replacing all names
with other values and by randomly shifting dates
within the same year. The data set of the
challenge consisted of a training set of 600
suicide notes, and a test set of 300 notes. The
challenge itself revealed that not only shallow
lexical, but also semantic features contributed to
classification performance. However, many
challenges remain to be investigated: the
sensitivity of the current systems to spelling and
other errors -especially in online data-, the lack
of deep understanding of the data through the use
of mainly shallow features, etc. The release of
this data set has made it possible to accurately
detect and differentiate between different
emotions, which might be indicative of suicidal
behavior.
For the automatic detection and classification
of emotions in suicidal content, we can rely on
the recent advances in the domain of LT
(Jurafsky and Martin, 2008) and machine
learning (Mitchell, 1997). Whereas the
international LT research community until
recently mainly focused on the “factual” aspects
of content analysis, we can observe an additional
growing interest in the analysis of attitude and
affect in textual sources, especially in online
content such as blogs, tweets, social network
data, etc. The extraction of affective contents
does not only imply the detection of opinions,
evaluations, beliefs and speculations in text
(topics which have a high application potential in
customer intelligence applications and the like),
but also the identification of certain emotions.
For example, how do people express their intent
to commit suicide? The use of machine learning
techniques and sentiment analysis techniques for
the automatic analysis of suicide notes is not
new. (Huang et al., 2007), for example,
experimented with lexicon-based sentiment
analysis for the automatic detection of suicidal
blogs. (Pestian et al., 2010) combined shallow
text characteristics, such as part-of-speech
information, readability scores and parse
information with the machine learning software
as available in the Weka package.
Until we know, the most complete research
about suicide prevention in the social networks,
specifically Facebook, is the work of (Schwartz
et al., 2014). However, instead of trying to detect
suicide notes or to differentiate people with or
without mental disorders, they measure the
changes across time of the degree of depression.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.998217" genericHeader="conclusions">
6 Conclusions
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999974666666667">
The magnitude of the suicide in the EU member
states and the rest of the world make suicide
prevention not exclusively a problem of Mental
Health. This is a problem that must be addressed
from a multidisciplinary perspective, involving
different areas. Internet Technologies and
Communication and, more specifically, the
Human Language Technologies can help to
resolve part of these problems through the early
detection of suicidal thoughts and/or behavior
expressed through the Social Media. The words
and the way people use to communicate in their
blogs, social networks, etc. provide information
about the psychological state and personality of
individuals. The processing and analysis of
natural language texts shared via Internet helps
record and detect changes in cognitive and
emotional state of the people. Unfortunately,
although there are available resources and tools
for sentiment analysis and opinion mining, even
in the field of the depression detection and using
different approaches and features, there is neither
system nor platform that deal with the full process
of suicide prevention.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.980878" genericHeader="acknowledgments">
Acknowledgements
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.997209">
This research work has been partially funded by the
Spanish Government and the European
Commission through the project, ATTOS (TIN2012-
38536-C03- 03), LEGOLANG (TIN2012-31224),
SAM (FP7- 611312) and FIRST (FP7-287607).
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.971934" genericHeader="references">
References
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.947192915194347">
Jo-Anne Bachorowski and Michael J. Owren. 1995.
VOCAL EXPRESSION OF EMOTION: Acoustic
Properties of Speech Are Associated With Emo-
tional Intensity and Context. Psychological
Science, 6(4):219–224, July.
Barr, D. Taylor-Robinson, A. Scott-Samuel, M. Mc-
Kee, and D Stuckler. 2012. Suicides associated
with the 2008-10 economic recession in England:
time trend analysis. British Medical Journal,
345:1–7.
M. Berk and Henry S. Dodd. 2006. The effect of
macroeconomic variables on suicide. Psychol Med,
36(2):181–189.
David M. Blei, Andrew Y. Ng, and Michael I. Jordan.
2003. Latent dirichlet allocation. The Journal of
Machine Learning Research, 3:993–1022, March.
Christopher H. Cantor. 2000. The International
Handbook of Suicide and Attempted Suicide. In
Keith Hawton and Kees van Heeringen, editors,
The Inter-national Handbook of Suicide and
Attempted Suicide. John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd, West
Sussex, Enland, January.
Munmun De Choudhury, Michael Gamon, and Scott
Counts. 2012. Happy, Nervous or Surprised?
Classification of Human Affective States in Social
Me-dia. In ICWSM, Dublin, Ireland.
Ze-Jing Chuang and Chung-Hsien Wu. 2004. Multi-
Modal Emotion Recognition from Speech and
Text.
International Journal of Computational Linguistics &amp;
Chinese Language Processing, Volume 9, Number
2, August 2004: Special Issue on New Trends of
Speech and Language Processing, 9(2):45–62.
Jim Cowie and Wendy Lehnert. 1996. Information
extraction. Communications of the ACM,
39(1):80–91, January.
A Dietz, A Ball, and J Griffith. 2011. Reading and
writing with aphasia in the 21st century:
technological applications of supported reading
comprehension and written expression. Top Stroke
Rehabil, 18(6):758–769.
S.M. Dunlop, E. More, and D. Romer. 2011. Where
do youth learn about suicide on the internet, and
what influence does this have on suicidal ideation?
The Journal of Child Psychology and Psychiatry,
52(10):1073–1080.
A.M. Edelman and S L Renshaw. 1982. Genuine
versus simulated suicide notes: an issue revisited
through discourse analysis. Suicide &amp; life-
threatening behavior, 12(2):103–13, January.
N.B. Ellison, C. Steinfield, and C. Lampe. 2007. The
benefits of Facebbok friend’s: Social capital and
college students’ use of online social network sites.
Journal of Computer-Mediated Communication,
12:1143–1168.
Horacio Garcıa-Rabago, Jose E Sahagun-Flores,
Alfonso Ruiz-Gomez, Gustavo M Sanchez Urena,
Juan C Tirado-Vargas, and Jaime G Gonzalez-
Gamez. 2010. Comparing high- and low-lethality
factors regarding attempted suicide-associated risk
factors. Revista de salud publica (Bogota,
Colombia), 12(5):713–21, October.
G. C. Gleser, L. A. Gottschalk, and K. J. Springer.
1961. An anxiety scale applicable to verbal
samples.
Archives of general psychiatry, 5:593–605, Decem-
ber.
Martijn Goudbeek and Klaus Scherer. 2010. Beyond
arousal: valence and potency/control cues in the
vocal expression of emotion. The Journal of the
Acoustical Society of America, 128(3):1322–36,
September.
Emily A. Holmes, Catherine Crane, Melanie J. V.
Fennell, and J.Mark G. Williams. 2007. Imagery
about suicide in depression-“flash-forwards”?
Journal of Behavior Therapy and Experimental
Psychiatry, 38:423–434.
Christine Howes, Matthew Purver, and Rose McCabe.
2014. Linguistic Indicators of Severity and
Progress in Online Text-based Therapy for
Depression. In
Proceedings of the Workshop on Computational Lin-
guistics and Clinical Psychology: From Linguistic
Signal to Clinical Reality, pages 7–16, Baltimore.
Association for Computational Linguistics.
Yen-Pei Huang, Tiong Goh, and Chern Li Liew.
2007. Hunting Suicide Notes in Web 2.0 -
Preliminary Findings. In Ninth IEEE International
Symposium on Multimedia Workshops (ISMW
2007), pages 517– 521. IEEE, December.
D Iakovidis and C Smailis. 2012. A semantic model
for multimodal data mining in healthcare informa-
tion systems. Stud Health Technol Inform,
180:574– 578.
E T Isometsa.¨ 2001. Psychological autopsy studies– a
review. European psychiatry : the journal of the
Association of European Psychiatrists, 16(7):379–
85, November.
Joris H. Janssen, Paul Tacken, J.J.G. (Gert-Jan) de
Vries, Egon L. van den Broek, Joyce H.D.M.
Westerink, Pim Haselager, and Wijnand A. IJssel-
steijn. 2013. Machines Outperform Laypersons in
Recognizing Emotions Elicited by Autobiograph-
ical Recollection. Human–Computer Interaction,
28(6):479–517, November.
Daniel Jurafsky and James H. Martin. 2008. Speech
and Language Processing, 2nd Edition.
Raghavendra Katikalapudi, Sriram Chellappan,
Frances Montgomery, Donald Wunsch, and Karl
Lutzen. 2012. Associating Internet Usage with De-
pressive Behavior Among College Students. IEEE
Technology and Society Magazine, 31(4):73–80.
S Kuny and H H Stassen. 1993. Speaking behav-ior
and voice sound characteristics in depressive pa-
tients during recovery. Journal of psychiatric re-
search, 27(3):289–307.
Sanne M.A. Lamers, Khiet P. Truong, Bas Steunen-
berg, Franciska de Jong, and Gerben J. Westerhof.
2014. Applying prosodic speech features in mental
health care: An exploratory study in a life-review
intervention for depression. In Proceedings of the
Workshop on Computational Linguistics and Clin-
ical Psychology: From Linguistic Signal to Clini-
cal Reality, pages 61–68, Baltimore. Association
for Computational Linguistics.
Amanda Lenhart, Kristen Purcell, Aaron Smith, and
Kathryn Zickuhr. 2010. Social Media &amp; Mobile In-
ternet Use Among Teens and Young Adults.
Techni-cal report, Pew Research Center,
Washington, D.C.
Maria Liakata, Jee-Hyub Kim, Shyamasree Saha,
Janna Hastings, and Dietrich Rebholz-Schuhmann.
2012. Three hybrid classifiers for the detection of
emotions in suicide notes. Biomedical informatics
insights, 5(Suppl. 1):175–84, January.
Michael Mandrusiak, M David Rudd, Thomas E
Joiner, Alan L Berman, Kimberly A Van Orden,
and Tracy Witte. 2006. Warning signs for suicide
on the Inter-net: a descriptive study. Suicide &amp; life-
threatening behavior, 36(3):263–71, June.
J.C Mingote, M.A Jimenez,´ R Osorio, and T.
Palomo. 2004. Suicidio. Asistencia Cl´ınica. In
Gu´ıa de practica´ medica´, chapter 4, pages 19–30.
D´ıaz San-tos.
Thomas M. Mitchell. 1997. Machine Learning.
McGraw-Hill, Inc., New York, NY, USA, March.
Megan A Moreno, Lauren A Jelenchick, Katie G
Egan, Elizabeth Cox, Henry Young, Kerry E
Gannon, and Tara Becker. 2011. Feeling bad on
Face-book: depression disclosures by college
students on a social networking site. Depression
and anxiety, 28(6):447–55, June.
Pedro Moreno Gea and Carmen Blanco Sanchez´.
2012. Suicidio e Internet. Medidas preventivas y de
ac-tuacion´. Psiquiatria.com, 16.
Navigli. 2009. Word Sense Disambiguation: A Sur-
vey. ACM Computing Surveys, 41(2).
Yair Neuman, Yohai Cohen, Dan Assaf, and Gabbi
Kedma. 2012. Proactive screening for depres-sion
through metaphorical and automatic text analy-sis.
Artificial intelligence in medicine, 56(1):19–25,
September.
Brendan O’Connor, Ramnath Balasubramanyan,
Bryan R. Routledge, and Noah A. Smith. 2010.
From Tweets to Polls: Linking Text Sentiment to
Public Opinion Time Series. In Fourth International
AAAI Conference on Weblogs and Social Media.
C. E. Osgood and E. G. Walker. 1959. Motivation and
language behavior: a content analysis of suicide
notes. Journal of abnormal psychology, 59(1):58–
67, July.
Gareth Owen, Judith Belam, Helen Lambert, Jenny
Donovan, Frances Rapport, and Christabel Owens.
2012. Suicide communication events: lay inter-
pretation of the communication of suicidal ideation
and intent. Social science &amp; medicine (1982),
75(2):419–28, July.
Bo Pang and Lillian Lee. 2008. Opinion Mining and
Sentiment Analysis. Foundations and Trends R in
Information Retrieval, 2(1–2):1–135, January.
Sungkyu Park, Sang Won Lee, Jinah Kwak,
Meeyoung Cha, and Bumseok Jeong. 2013.
Activities on Face-book reveal the depressive state
of users. Journal of medical Internet research,
15(10):e217, January.
James W. Pennebaker and Cindy K. Chung. 2011. Ex-
pressive Writing, Emotional Upheavals, and
Health. In Howard S. Friedman, editor, Expressive
Writing, Emotional Upheavals, and Health, chapter
18, page
936. Oxford University Press.
J. Pestian, H. Nasrallah, Matykiewicz, A. Bennett, and
A. Leenaars. 2010. Suicide Note Classification Us-
ing Natural Language Processing. Biomed Inform
Insights, 3:19–28.
John P Pestian, Pawel Matykiewicz, Michelle Linn-
Gust, Brett South, Ozlem Uzuner, Jan Wiebe, K
Bretonnel Cohen, John Hurdle, and Christopher
Brew. 2012. Sentiment Analysis of Suicide Notes:
A Shared Task. Biomedical informatics insights,
5(Suppl 1):3–16, January.
Matthew Purver and Stuart Battersby. 2012. Experi-
menting with distant supervision for emotion
classi-fication. In 13th Conference of the European
Chap-ter of the Association for Computational
Linguistics (EACL), pages 482–491. Association
for Computa-tional Linguistics, Stroudsburg, PA,
USA, April.
Daniele Quercia, Jonathan Ellis, Licia Capra, and Jon
Crowcroft. 2012. Tracking ”gross community
happiness” from tweets. In Proceedings of the
ACM 2012 conference on Computer Supported
Coopera-tive Work - CSCW ’12, page 965, New
York, New York, USA, February. ACM Press.
Thomas D Ruder, Gary M Hatch, Garyfalia
Ampanozi, Michael J Thali, and Nadja Fischer.
2011. Suicide announcement on Facebook. Crisis,
32(5):280–2, January.
Kjell E. Rudestam. 1971. Stockholm and Los
Angeles: A cross-cultural study of the
communication of suicidal intent. Journal of
Consulting and Clinical Psychology, 36(1):82–90.
Gerard Salton and Michael J. McGill. 1986. Intro-
duction to Modern Information Retrieval.
McGraw-Hill, Inc., New York, NY, USA.
David Sarno. 2008. Rise and fall of the Googled
swastika.
K Scherer. 2003. Vocal communication of emotion: A
review of research paradigms. Speech Communica-
tion, 40(1-2):227–256, April.
Andrew Schwartz, Johannes Eichstaedt, Margaret L.
Kern, Gregory Park, Maarten Sap, David Stillwell,
Michal Kosinski, and Lyle Ungar. 2014. Towards
Assessing Changes in Degree of Depression
through Facebook. In Proceedings of the Workshop
on Computational Linguistics and Clinical
Psychology: From Linguistic Signal to Clinical
Reality, pages 118–125, Baltimore. Association for
Computational Linguistics.
Fabrizio Sebastiani. 2002. Machine learning in au-
tomated text categorization. ACM Computing Sur-
veys, 34(1):1–47, March.
Young-Soo Seol, Dong-Joo Kim, and Han-Woo Kim.
2008. Emotion Recognition from Text Using
Knowledge-based ANN. Proceedings of ITC-
CSCC, 9(2).
Jess Jann Shapero. 2011. The language of suicide
notes, July.
E. S. Shneidman and N. L. Farberow. 1956. Clues to
suicide. Public health reports, 71(2):109–14, Febru-
ary.
C Sobin and M Alpert. 1999. Emotion in speech: the
acoustic attributes of fear, anger, sadness, and joy.
Journal of psycholinguistic research, 28(4):347–65,
July.
C Sobin and H A Sackeim. 1997. Psychomotor symp-
toms of depression. The American journal of psy-
chiatry, 154(1):4–17, January.
P Sobocki, I Lekander, and F Borgstrom¨. 2007. The
economic burden of depression in Sweden from
1997 to 2005. Eur Psychiatry, 22(3):146–152.
David Stuckler, Sanjay BasuMarc, Adam Coutts
Suhrcke, and McKee. Martin. 2011. Effects of the
2008 recession on health: a first look at European
data. The Lancet, 378(9786):124 – 125.
JR Vest. 2012. Health information exchange: national
and international approaches. Adv Health Care
Manag, 12:3–24.
Y Wang and P.V. Paul. 2011. Integrating technology
and reading instruction with children who are deaf
or hard of hearing: the effectiveness of the
Cornerstones project. Am Ann Deaf, 156(1):56–68.
Danuta Wasserman, Ellenor Mittendorfer Rutz,
Wolfgang Rutz, and Armin Schmidtke. 2004.
Suicide Prevention In Europe. Technical report,
National and Stockholm County Council’s Centre
for Suicide Research and Prevention of Mental Ill
Health.
WHO. 2012. Public health action for the prevention of
suicide: a framework. Technical report, World
Health Organization.
WHO. 2014. Preventing suicide: A global imperative.
Technical report, World Health Organization.
</reference>
</variant>
</algorithm>
<algorithm name="ParsHed" version="110505">
<variant no="0" confidence="0.930902">
<title confidence="0.997484">Language Technologies for Suicide Prevention in Social Media</title>
<author confidence="0.999995">Jose M Gomez</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.999485">Department of Software and Computing Systems, University of Alicante</affiliation>
<email confidence="0.981313">jmgomez@ua.es</email>
<abstract confidence="0.99818615625">At present, the suicide phenomenon is raising, having a relevant impact on our society. Each year about one million people die as a result of suicidal behavior becoming an economic, social and human problem. On the other hand, the use of Social Media as a means of communication is becoming extremely popular, through which their emotional states and impressions are exchanged. Therefore, it is no surprise that more and more people with depression publish their suicide notes in these communication channels. In this context, Information Technologies Communications and, more specifically, Language Technologies play an important role in the early detection of the depression, their causes and their terrible consequences. Based on these considerations, it is mandatory to provide societal, environmentally approaches and solutions to tackle these societal challenges. This work pretends to be an exhaustive survey of the different researches in this scope, in order to explain which technologies and resources are used in the detection of mental problems by means of the Social Media analysis as well as to re-veal their deficiencies.</abstract>
</variant>
</algorithm>
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Jo-Anne Bachorowski</author>
<author>Michael J Owren</author>
</authors>
<date>1995</date>
<journal>VOCAL EXPRESSION OF EMOTION: Acoustic Properties of Speech Are Associated With Emotional Intensity and Context. Psychological Science,</journal>
<volume>6</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<contexts>
<context position="8840" citStr="Bachorowski and Owren, 1995" startWordPosition="1327" endWordPosition="1330">ical characteristics or interpersonal problems. They could identify suicidal groups that need urgent intervention. Internet searches for suicide may provide a faster way of monitoring possible trends in suicide. Some clinical studies observed that depressed patients frequently speech slow, uniform, monotonous and with a low voice (Kuny and Stassen, 1993) or to have psychomotor symptoms and this is reflected in the speech (Sobin and Sackeim, 1997). Moreover, emotions and mood can influence the speaking behavior of a person and the characteristics of the sound in speech (Kuny and Stassen, 1993; Bachorowski and Owren, 1995; Sobin and Alpert, 1999; Scherer, 2003; Goudbeek and Scherer, 2010). The speech of depressed patients is characterized by a longer pause duration, that is, an increased amount of time between speech utterances as well as by a reduced variability in mean vocal pitch (Lamers et al., 2014). For these reasons, the acoustic speech features can be used to build models and algorithms for automated depression detection in clinical scenarios. But these acoustic features are not the only ones that can be used, Internet usage itself (Katikala-pudi et al., 2012), social networking behaviors (Moreno et al</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Bachorowski, Owren, 1995</marker>
<rawString>Jo-Anne Bachorowski and Michael J. Owren. 1995. VOCAL EXPRESSION OF EMOTION: Acoustic Properties of Speech Are Associated With Emotional Intensity and Context. Psychological Science, 6(4):219–224, July.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>D Taylor-Robinson Barr</author>
<author>A Scott-Samuel</author>
<author>M McKee</author>
<author>D Stuckler</author>
</authors>
<title>Suicides associated with the 2008-10 economic recession in England: time trend analysis.</title>
<date>2012</date>
<journal>British Medical Journal,</journal>
<pages>345--1</pages>
<marker>Barr, Scott-Samuel, McKee, Stuckler, 2012</marker>
<rawString>Barr, D. Taylor-Robinson, A. Scott-Samuel, M. McKee, and D Stuckler. 2012. Suicides associated with the 2008-10 economic recession in England: time trend analysis. British Medical Journal, 345:1–7.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M Berk</author>
<author>Henry S Dodd</author>
</authors>
<title>The effect of macroeconomic variables on suicide.</title>
<date>2006</date>
<journal>Psychol Med,</journal>
<volume>36</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<contexts>
<context position="2590" citStr="Berk and Dodd, 2006" startWordPosition="402" endWordPosition="405">nd it would be the second reason that would explain the deaths in the group of people aged 15 to 19 years (WHO, 2014). Suicidal behaviors can be defined as a complex process that can range from suicidal ideation (communicated through verbal or nonverbal means) to planning of suicide, attempting suicide, and in the worst case, the suicide itself. These behaviors are influenced by interacting biological, genetic, psychological, social, environmental and situational factors (Wasserman et al., 2004). Suicide has also been strong linked to inequity, social exclusion and socio-economic deprivation (Berk and Dodd, 2006). It is an enormous problem that causing unnecessary human suffering and immeasurable costs for society. According to Josee Van Remoortel, advisor to the European organization Mental Health Europe2 (MHE), the financial crisis is affecting “all areas of life”, not just economies, and its impact on mental health is creating a “deep chasm in our society”. 1http://ec.europa.eu/health/ph_determinants/life_style/menta l/docs/pact_en.pdf 2http://www.mhe-sme.org/ 2 Internet and Social Media Penetration In the other hand, studies reveal that between 90.1% and 97.8% of young people between 10 and 15 yea</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Berk, Dodd, 2006</marker>
<rawString>M. Berk and Henry S. Dodd. 2006. The effect of macroeconomic variables on suicide. Psychol Med, 36(2):181–189.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>David M Blei</author>
<author>Andrew Y Ng</author>
<author>Michael I Jordan</author>
</authors>
<title>Latent dirichlet allocation.</title>
<date>2003</date>
<journal>The Journal of Machine Learning Research,</journal>
<pages>3--993</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="13659" citStr="Blei et al., 2003" startWordPosition="2075" endWordPosition="2078">ey investigated whether a machine learning system was able to classify suicide notes with a higher accuracy than mental health professionals. They showed that the best machine learners were indeed able to outperform the human experts. More recent studies confirm this fact (Janssen et al., 2013), underlining once again the added value of automated speech analysis. (Howes et al., 2014) present an initial investigation into the application of computational linguistic techniques, such as topic and sentiment modelling, to online therapy for depression and anxiety using Latent Dirichlet Allocation (Blei et al., 2003). However, early works tried to detect specific emotions such as anger, surprise, fear, etc. using dictionary-based or machine-learning-based approaches (Chuang and Wu, 2004; Seol et al., 2008) and more recently (Purver and Battersby, 2012; Choudhury et al., 2012; Neuman et al., 2012; Howes et al., 2014). Although interesting research was conducted on the Schneidman data set, the focus should not be on distinguishing between genuine and elicited suicide notes. Instead, it is of key importance to determine what exactly makes a note a real suicide note, independently of the features of the elici</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Blei, Ng, Jordan, 2003</marker>
<rawString>David M. Blei, Andrew Y. Ng, and Michael I. Jordan. 2003. Latent dirichlet allocation. The Journal of Machine Learning Research, 3:993–1022, March.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Christopher H Cantor</author>
</authors>
<date>2000</date>
<booktitle>The International Handbook of Suicide and Attempted Suicide. In Keith Hawton and Kees</booktitle>
<editor>van Heeringen, editors,</editor>
<publisher>John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd, West</publisher>
<location>Sussex, Enland,</location>
<contexts>
<context position="4395" citStr="Cantor, 2000" startWordPosition="673" endWordPosition="674">Gea and Blanco Sanchez, 2012). They also warn their suicidal intentions through the Web in real time, before and while committing the act (Sarno, 2008). The study conducted in (Mingote et al., 2004) also proves that the younger are one of the population segments where prevention is particularly necessary, finding that 20% of suicides occur among adolescents and young adults. 3 Suicide Prevention in Social Media It is important to raise awareness on that most self-inflicted deaths are potentially preventable. Well-known studies concerning research on suicide (Owen et al., 2012; Isometsa, 2001; Cantor, 2000; Rudestam, 1971) show that a high number of people who decide to end with their lives. Through suicide had no prior contact with mental health services, but had communicated their suicidal plans or thoughts directly or indirectly through different means to members of their family, friends, colleagues, or through their social networks. Improve the staff skills in early recognition of suicide warning signs, is an essential issue to prevent suicidal mortality. There is an increasing tendency (Ruder et al., 2011) where suicide notes are posted on the social media (e.g., Facebook, Twitter), where </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Cantor, 2000</marker>
<rawString>Christopher H. Cantor. 2000. The International Handbook of Suicide and Attempted Suicide. In Keith Hawton and Kees van Heeringen, editors, The Inter-national Handbook of Suicide and Attempted Suicide. John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd, West Sussex, Enland, January.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Munmun De Choudhury</author>
<author>Michael Gamon</author>
<author>Scott Counts</author>
</authors>
<title>Happy, Nervous or Surprised? Classification of Human Affective States in Social Me-dia. In ICWSM,</title>
<date>2012</date>
<location>Dublin, Ireland.</location>
<marker>De Choudhury, Gamon, Counts, 2012</marker>
<rawString>Munmun De Choudhury, Michael Gamon, and Scott Counts. 2012. Happy, Nervous or Surprised? Classification of Human Affective States in Social Me-dia. In ICWSM, Dublin, Ireland.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Ze-Jing Chuang</author>
<author>Chung-Hsien Wu</author>
</authors>
<title>MultiModal Emotion Recognition from Speech and Text.</title>
<date>2004</date>
<contexts>
<context position="13832" citStr="Chuang and Wu, 2004" startWordPosition="2098" endWordPosition="2101">ine learners were indeed able to outperform the human experts. More recent studies confirm this fact (Janssen et al., 2013), underlining once again the added value of automated speech analysis. (Howes et al., 2014) present an initial investigation into the application of computational linguistic techniques, such as topic and sentiment modelling, to online therapy for depression and anxiety using Latent Dirichlet Allocation (Blei et al., 2003). However, early works tried to detect specific emotions such as anger, surprise, fear, etc. using dictionary-based or machine-learning-based approaches (Chuang and Wu, 2004; Seol et al., 2008) and more recently (Purver and Battersby, 2012; Choudhury et al., 2012; Neuman et al., 2012; Howes et al., 2014). Although interesting research was conducted on the Schneidman data set, the focus should not be on distinguishing between genuine and elicited suicide notes. Instead, it is of key importance to determine what exactly makes a note a real suicide note, independently of the features of the elicited notes or the distinguishing characteristics between both types of notes. Such a suicide note corpus of positive-only data, annotated with fine-grained emotions, was rele</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Chuang, Wu, 2004</marker>
<rawString>Ze-Jing Chuang and Chung-Hsien Wu. 2004. MultiModal Emotion Recognition from Speech and Text.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<date>2004</date>
<journal>International Journal of Computational Linguistics &amp; Chinese Language Processing, Volume 9, Number</journal>
<booktitle>Special Issue on New Trends of Speech and Language Processing,</booktitle>
<volume>2</volume>
<pages>9--2</pages>
<marker>2004</marker>
<rawString>International Journal of Computational Linguistics &amp; Chinese Language Processing, Volume 9, Number 2, August 2004: Special Issue on New Trends of Speech and Language Processing, 9(2):45–62.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Jim Cowie</author>
<author>Wendy Lehnert</author>
</authors>
<title>Information extraction.</title>
<date>1996</date>
<journal>Communications of the ACM,</journal>
<volume>39</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<contexts>
<context position="10468" citStr="Cowie and Lehnert, 1996" startWordPosition="1576" endWordPosition="1579">s (Liakata et al., 2012). 5 Human Language Technologies and Suicide Prevention In order to resolve this social issue, Language Technologies (LT) could help with the early identification of “suicide warning signs” that will be useful to detect individuals with suicidal ideation, as well as virtual environments where pro-suicide information is being shared or suicidal attempts are being encouraged. In particular, LT can analyze language structures and their meaning (Navigli, 2009) on different textual genres. Tasks such as information retrieval (Salton and McGill, 1986), information extraction (Cowie and Lehnert, 1996), text classification and clustering (Sebastiani, 2002), or sentiment analysis (Pang and Lee, 2008) are basic pillars of these technologies that allow the construction of more complex automatic processes for discovering knowledge from oral and/or written text. Recent research in LT has been proved great potential in the area of healthcare. From the development of applications to assist medical practitioners in the access and management of information about patients, e.g. (Iakovidis and Smailis, 2012; Vest, 2012), to the creation of computer programs to support and/or facilitate reading compreh</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Cowie, Lehnert, 1996</marker>
<rawString>Jim Cowie and Wendy Lehnert. 1996. Information extraction. Communications of the ACM, 39(1):80–91, January.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>A Dietz</author>
<author>A Ball</author>
<author>J Griffith</author>
</authors>
<title>Reading and writing with aphasia in the 21st century: technological applications of supported reading comprehension and written expression. Top Stroke Rehabil,</title>
<date>2011</date>
<contexts>
<context position="11146" citStr="Dietz et al., 2011" startWordPosition="1672" endWordPosition="1675">sentiment analysis (Pang and Lee, 2008) are basic pillars of these technologies that allow the construction of more complex automatic processes for discovering knowledge from oral and/or written text. Recent research in LT has been proved great potential in the area of healthcare. From the development of applications to assist medical practitioners in the access and management of information about patients, e.g. (Iakovidis and Smailis, 2012; Vest, 2012), to the creation of computer programs to support and/or facilitate reading comprehension for language-impaired children during communication (Dietz et al., 2011; Wang and Paul, 2011). So far, and to the best of our knowledge, very little effort has been made to apply LT for the benefit of suicide prevention. The linguistic analysis of suicide notes has a long history and already started as early as 1956 with the work of (Shneidman and Farberow, 1956), followed by several others (Osgood and Walker, 1959; Gleser et al., 1961; Edelman and Renshaw, 1982). The basis of most of this research was a corpus of 66 suicides notes, half genuine and half simulated, collected by Schneidman and the task was to identify those textual features which could differentia</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Dietz, Ball, Griffith, 2011</marker>
<rawString>A Dietz, A Ball, and J Griffith. 2011. Reading and writing with aphasia in the 21st century: technological applications of supported reading comprehension and written expression. Top Stroke Rehabil, 18(6):758–769.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S M Dunlop</author>
<author>E More</author>
<author>D Romer</author>
</authors>
<title>Where do youth learn about suicide on the internet, and what influence does this have on suicidal ideation?</title>
<date>2011</date>
<journal>The Journal of Child Psychology and Psychiatry,</journal>
<volume>52</volume>
<issue>10</issue>
<contexts>
<context position="5516" citStr="Dunlop et al., 2011" startWordPosition="838" endWordPosition="841"> et al., 2011) where suicide notes are posted on the social media (e.g., Facebook, Twitter), where Internet users (and not necessarily teenagers) announce their suicidal thoughts before committing suicide. This poses new challenges for human language technologies since, traditional existing automatic tools are not able to process the new language employed in the social media (abbreviations, slang, smiles and, more generally, a low unstructured and highly informal language). The Internet, and specifically the Web 2.0, is an important source of information for learning about suicidal behaviors (Dunlop et al., 2011). The way individuals respond to help request from people at high risk of suicide or interact with them can lead to the fact that the potential suicidal may reconsider his/her final decision, or, on the contrary, encourage and accelerate the process of ending with his/her life (Wasserman et al., 2004). During the recent years, some popular social networks, such as Facebook have become the most important means of social communication, with nearly 1,230 million of registered users world-wide4, 70% of whom are young people who make frequent use of this type of media, through which the emotional s</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Dunlop, More, Romer, 2011</marker>
<rawString>S.M. Dunlop, E. More, and D. Romer. 2011. Where do youth learn about suicide on the internet, and what influence does this have on suicidal ideation? The Journal of Child Psychology and Psychiatry, 52(10):1073–1080.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>A M Edelman</author>
<author>S L Renshaw</author>
</authors>
<title>Genuine versus simulated suicide notes: an issue revisited through discourse analysis. Suicide &amp; lifethreatening behavior,</title>
<date>1982</date>
<pages>12--2</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="11542" citStr="Edelman and Renshaw, 1982" startWordPosition="1741" endWordPosition="1744">mation about patients, e.g. (Iakovidis and Smailis, 2012; Vest, 2012), to the creation of computer programs to support and/or facilitate reading comprehension for language-impaired children during communication (Dietz et al., 2011; Wang and Paul, 2011). So far, and to the best of our knowledge, very little effort has been made to apply LT for the benefit of suicide prevention. The linguistic analysis of suicide notes has a long history and already started as early as 1956 with the work of (Shneidman and Farberow, 1956), followed by several others (Osgood and Walker, 1959; Gleser et al., 1961; Edelman and Renshaw, 1982). The basis of most of this research was a corpus of 66 suicides notes, half genuine and half simulated, collected by Schneidman and the task was to identify those textual features which could differentiate between genuine and fake notes. Whereas the earlier work mostly focused on the manual analysis and detection of these differentiating features, e.g. by relying on techniques from discourse analysis (Shneidman and Farberow, 1956) or by focusing on shallow text characteristics such as the usage of modals and auxiliaries (Osgood and Walker, 1959), the choice of verbs and adverbs (Gleser et al.</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Edelman, Renshaw, 1982</marker>
<rawString>A.M. Edelman and S L Renshaw. 1982. Genuine versus simulated suicide notes: an issue revisited through discourse analysis. Suicide &amp; lifethreatening behavior, 12(2):103–13, January.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>N B Ellison</author>
<author>C Steinfield</author>
<author>C Lampe</author>
</authors>
<title>The benefits of Facebbok friend’s: Social capital and college students’ use of online social network sites.</title>
<date>2007</date>
<journal>Journal of Computer-Mediated Communication,</journal>
<pages>12--1143</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="6401" citStr="Ellison et al., 2007" startWordPosition="981" endWordPosition="984"> his/her life (Wasserman et al., 2004). During the recent years, some popular social networks, such as Facebook have become the most important means of social communication, with nearly 1,230 million of registered users world-wide4, 70% of whom are young people who make frequent use of this type of media, through which the emotional states and impressions are exchanged (Dunlop et al., 2011; Lenhart et al., 2010). These social networks are also a way to find comfort and welfare and its usage promotes contact and positive support among young people, especially among those with mental disorders (Ellison et al., 2007). In addition, the Web offers possibilities for early detection on suicidal behaviors and it may constitute a cost-effective means of intervention based on a first step care approach. Their use may be of help for identifying pro-suicide messages, detecting group patterns, analyzing exposure to the warning signs and intervening in a personalized manner with people at risk who are willing to accept professional help. In order to raise awareness of the ways people could get help when showing a suicidal behavior, Facebook and the Samaritans5 association developed a joint initiative consisting in a</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Ellison, Steinfield, Lampe, 2007</marker>
<rawString>N.B. Ellison, C. Steinfield, and C. Lampe. 2007. The benefits of Facebbok friend’s: Social capital and college students’ use of online social network sites. Journal of Computer-Mediated Communication, 12:1143–1168.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Horacio Garcıa-Rabago</author>
<author>Jose E Sahagun-Flores</author>
<author>Alfonso Ruiz-Gomez</author>
<author>Gustavo M Sanchez Urena</author>
<author>Juan C Tirado-Vargas</author>
<author>Jaime G GonzalezGamez</author>
</authors>
<title>Comparing high- and low-lethality factors regarding attempted suicide-associated risk factors. Revista de salud publica</title>
<date>2010</date>
<location>Bogota,</location>
<marker>Garcıa-Rabago, Sahagun-Flores, Ruiz-Gomez, Urena, Tirado-Vargas, GonzalezGamez, 2010</marker>
<rawString>Horacio Garcıa-Rabago, Jose E Sahagun-Flores, Alfonso Ruiz-Gomez, Gustavo M Sanchez Urena, Juan C Tirado-Vargas, and Jaime G GonzalezGamez. 2010. Comparing high- and low-lethality factors regarding attempted suicide-associated risk factors. Revista de salud publica (Bogota, Colombia), 12(5):713–21, October.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>G C Gleser</author>
<author>L A Gottschalk</author>
<author>K J Springer</author>
</authors>
<title>An anxiety scale applicable to verbal samples. Archives of general psychiatry,</title>
<date>1961</date>
<pages>5--593</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="11514" citStr="Gleser et al., 1961" startWordPosition="1737" endWordPosition="1740">d management of information about patients, e.g. (Iakovidis and Smailis, 2012; Vest, 2012), to the creation of computer programs to support and/or facilitate reading comprehension for language-impaired children during communication (Dietz et al., 2011; Wang and Paul, 2011). So far, and to the best of our knowledge, very little effort has been made to apply LT for the benefit of suicide prevention. The linguistic analysis of suicide notes has a long history and already started as early as 1956 with the work of (Shneidman and Farberow, 1956), followed by several others (Osgood and Walker, 1959; Gleser et al., 1961; Edelman and Renshaw, 1982). The basis of most of this research was a corpus of 66 suicides notes, half genuine and half simulated, collected by Schneidman and the task was to identify those textual features which could differentiate between genuine and fake notes. Whereas the earlier work mostly focused on the manual analysis and detection of these differentiating features, e.g. by relying on techniques from discourse analysis (Shneidman and Farberow, 1956) or by focusing on shallow text characteristics such as the usage of modals and auxiliaries (Osgood and Walker, 1959), the choice of verb</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Gleser, Gottschalk, Springer, 1961</marker>
<rawString>G. C. Gleser, L. A. Gottschalk, and K. J. Springer. 1961. An anxiety scale applicable to verbal samples. Archives of general psychiatry, 5:593–605, December.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Martijn Goudbeek</author>
<author>Klaus Scherer</author>
</authors>
<title>Beyond arousal: valence and potency/control cues in the vocal expression of emotion.</title>
<date>2010</date>
<journal>The Journal of the Acoustical Society of America,</journal>
<volume>128</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<contexts>
<context position="8908" citStr="Goudbeek and Scherer, 2010" startWordPosition="1337" endWordPosition="1340">suicidal groups that need urgent intervention. Internet searches for suicide may provide a faster way of monitoring possible trends in suicide. Some clinical studies observed that depressed patients frequently speech slow, uniform, monotonous and with a low voice (Kuny and Stassen, 1993) or to have psychomotor symptoms and this is reflected in the speech (Sobin and Sackeim, 1997). Moreover, emotions and mood can influence the speaking behavior of a person and the characteristics of the sound in speech (Kuny and Stassen, 1993; Bachorowski and Owren, 1995; Sobin and Alpert, 1999; Scherer, 2003; Goudbeek and Scherer, 2010). The speech of depressed patients is characterized by a longer pause duration, that is, an increased amount of time between speech utterances as well as by a reduced variability in mean vocal pitch (Lamers et al., 2014). For these reasons, the acoustic speech features can be used to build models and algorithms for automated depression detection in clinical scenarios. But these acoustic features are not the only ones that can be used, Internet usage itself (Katikala-pudi et al., 2012), social networking behaviors (Moreno et al., 2011; Choudhury et al., 2012) or location sharing (Park et al., 2</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Goudbeek, Scherer, 2010</marker>
<rawString>Martijn Goudbeek and Klaus Scherer. 2010. Beyond arousal: valence and potency/control cues in the vocal expression of emotion. The Journal of the Acoustical Society of America, 128(3):1322–36, September.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Emily A Holmes</author>
<author>Catherine Crane</author>
<author>Melanie J V Fennell</author>
<author>J Mark G Williams</author>
</authors>
<title>Imagery about suicide in depression-“flash-forwards”?</title>
<date>2007</date>
<journal>Journal of Behavior Therapy and Experimental Psychiatry,</journal>
<pages>38--423</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="1967" citStr="Holmes et al., 2007" startWordPosition="307" endWordPosition="310">, suicide has become the leading cause of violent death (WHO, 2014). Each year 804.000 people die in the world as a result of suicidal behavior and the number of attempts is about 20 times higher (WHO, 2012; WHO, 2014). It is estimated that in 2020, about 1.53 million people will die as a result of suicidal acts. Preventing suicide is one of the five areas of priority of the European Pact for Mental Health and Well- Being1, which was launched by the European Commission in 2008. Suicide is the third leading cause of violent death among people aged 15 to 44, followed by accidents and homicides (Holmes et al., 2007), and it would be the second reason that would explain the deaths in the group of people aged 15 to 19 years (WHO, 2014). Suicidal behaviors can be defined as a complex process that can range from suicidal ideation (communicated through verbal or nonverbal means) to planning of suicide, attempting suicide, and in the worst case, the suicide itself. These behaviors are influenced by interacting biological, genetic, psychological, social, environmental and situational factors (Wasserman et al., 2004). Suicide has also been strong linked to inequity, social exclusion and socio-economic deprivatio</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Holmes, Crane, Fennell, Williams, 2007</marker>
<rawString>Emily A. Holmes, Catherine Crane, Melanie J. V. Fennell, and J.Mark G. Williams. 2007. Imagery about suicide in depression-“flash-forwards”? Journal of Behavior Therapy and Experimental Psychiatry, 38:423–434.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Christine Howes</author>
<author>Matthew Purver</author>
<author>Rose McCabe</author>
</authors>
<title>Linguistic Indicators of Severity and Progress in Online Text-based Therapy for Depression. In</title>
<date>2014</date>
<contexts>
<context position="13427" citStr="Howes et al., 2014" startWordPosition="2043" endWordPosition="2046">mood. As far as we know, (Pestian et al., 2010) were the first to experiment with the use machine learning techniques for the automatic classification of suicide notes. In experiments on the earlier described data set of 66 notes, they investigated whether a machine learning system was able to classify suicide notes with a higher accuracy than mental health professionals. They showed that the best machine learners were indeed able to outperform the human experts. More recent studies confirm this fact (Janssen et al., 2013), underlining once again the added value of automated speech analysis. (Howes et al., 2014) present an initial investigation into the application of computational linguistic techniques, such as topic and sentiment modelling, to online therapy for depression and anxiety using Latent Dirichlet Allocation (Blei et al., 2003). However, early works tried to detect specific emotions such as anger, surprise, fear, etc. using dictionary-based or machine-learning-based approaches (Chuang and Wu, 2004; Seol et al., 2008) and more recently (Purver and Battersby, 2012; Choudhury et al., 2012; Neuman et al., 2012; Howes et al., 2014). Although interesting research was conducted on the Schneidman</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Howes, Purver, McCabe, 2014</marker>
<rawString>Christine Howes, Matthew Purver, and Rose McCabe. 2014. Linguistic Indicators of Severity and Progress in Online Text-based Therapy for Depression. In</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<booktitle>Proceedings of the Workshop on Computational Linguistics and Clinical Psychology: From Linguistic Signal to Clinical Reality,</booktitle>
<pages>7--16</pages>
<institution>Baltimore. Association for Computational Linguistics.</institution>
<marker></marker>
<rawString>Proceedings of the Workshop on Computational Linguistics and Clinical Psychology: From Linguistic Signal to Clinical Reality, pages 7–16, Baltimore. Association for Computational Linguistics.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Yen-Pei Huang</author>
<author>Tiong Goh</author>
<author>Chern Li Liew</author>
</authors>
<title>Hunting Suicide Notes in Web 2.0 -Preliminary Findings.</title>
<date>2007</date>
<booktitle>In Ninth IEEE International Symposium on Multimedia Workshops (ISMW</booktitle>
<pages>517--521</pages>
<publisher>IEEE,</publisher>
<contexts>
<context position="16765" citStr="Huang et al., 2007" startWordPosition="2552" endWordPosition="2555">s of attitude and affect in textual sources, especially in online content such as blogs, tweets, social network data, etc. The extraction of affective contents does not only imply the detection of opinions, evaluations, beliefs and speculations in text (topics which have a high application potential in customer intelligence applications and the like), but also the identification of certain emotions. For example, how do people express their intent to commit suicide? The use of machine learning techniques and sentiment analysis techniques for the automatic analysis of suicide notes is not new. (Huang et al., 2007), for example, experimented with lexicon-based sentiment analysis for the automatic detection of suicidal blogs. (Pestian et al., 2010) combined shallow text characteristics, such as part-of-speech information, readability scores and parse information with the machine learning software as available in the Weka package. Until we know, the most complete research about suicide prevention in the social networks, specifically Facebook, is the work of (Schwartz et al., 2014). However, instead of trying to detect suicide notes or to differentiate people with or without mental disorders, they measure </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Huang, Goh, Liew, 2007</marker>
<rawString>Yen-Pei Huang, Tiong Goh, and Chern Li Liew. 2007. Hunting Suicide Notes in Web 2.0 -Preliminary Findings. In Ninth IEEE International Symposium on Multimedia Workshops (ISMW 2007), pages 517– 521. IEEE, December.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>D Iakovidis</author>
<author>C Smailis</author>
</authors>
<title>A semantic model for multimodal data mining in healthcare information systems.</title>
<date>2012</date>
<journal>Stud Health Technol Inform,</journal>
<volume>180</volume>
<pages>578</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="10972" citStr="Iakovidis and Smailis, 2012" startWordPosition="1649" endWordPosition="1652">ual genres. Tasks such as information retrieval (Salton and McGill, 1986), information extraction (Cowie and Lehnert, 1996), text classification and clustering (Sebastiani, 2002), or sentiment analysis (Pang and Lee, 2008) are basic pillars of these technologies that allow the construction of more complex automatic processes for discovering knowledge from oral and/or written text. Recent research in LT has been proved great potential in the area of healthcare. From the development of applications to assist medical practitioners in the access and management of information about patients, e.g. (Iakovidis and Smailis, 2012; Vest, 2012), to the creation of computer programs to support and/or facilitate reading comprehension for language-impaired children during communication (Dietz et al., 2011; Wang and Paul, 2011). So far, and to the best of our knowledge, very little effort has been made to apply LT for the benefit of suicide prevention. The linguistic analysis of suicide notes has a long history and already started as early as 1956 with the work of (Shneidman and Farberow, 1956), followed by several others (Osgood and Walker, 1959; Gleser et al., 1961; Edelman and Renshaw, 1982). The basis of most of this re</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Iakovidis, Smailis, 2012</marker>
<rawString>D Iakovidis and C Smailis. 2012. A semantic model for multimodal data mining in healthcare information systems. Stud Health Technol Inform, 180:574– 578.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>E T Isometsa ¨</author>
</authors>
<title>Psychological autopsy studies– a review. European psychiatry :</title>
<date>2001</date>
<journal>the journal of the Association of European Psychiatrists,</journal>
<volume>16</volume>
<issue>7</issue>
<pages>85</pages>
<marker>¨, 2001</marker>
<rawString>E T Isometsa.¨ 2001. Psychological autopsy studies– a review. European psychiatry : the journal of the Association of European Psychiatrists, 16(7):379– 85, November.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Joris H Janssen</author>
<author>Paul Tacken</author>
<author>J J G de Vries</author>
<author>Egon L van den Broek</author>
<author>Joyce H D M Westerink</author>
<author>Pim Haselager</author>
<author>Wijnand A IJsselsteijn</author>
</authors>
<title>Machines Outperform Laypersons in Recognizing Emotions Elicited by Autobiographical Recollection.</title>
<date>2013</date>
<journal>Human–Computer Interaction,</journal>
<volume>28</volume>
<issue>6</issue>
<marker>Janssen, Tacken, de Vries, van den Broek, Westerink, Haselager, IJsselsteijn, 2013</marker>
<rawString>Joris H. Janssen, Paul Tacken, J.J.G. (Gert-Jan) de Vries, Egon L. van den Broek, Joyce H.D.M. Westerink, Pim Haselager, and Wijnand A. IJsselsteijn. 2013. Machines Outperform Laypersons in Recognizing Emotions Elicited by Autobiographical Recollection. Human–Computer Interaction, 28(6):479–517, November.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Daniel Jurafsky</author>
<author>James H Martin</author>
</authors>
<date>2008</date>
<booktitle>Speech and Language Processing, 2nd Edition.</booktitle>
<contexts>
<context position="15922" citStr="Jurafsky and Martin, 2008" startWordPosition="2426" endWordPosition="2429">antic features contributed to classification performance. However, many challenges remain to be investigated: the sensitivity of the current systems to spelling and other errors -especially in online data-, the lack of deep understanding of the data through the use of mainly shallow features, etc. The release of this data set has made it possible to accurately detect and differentiate between different emotions, which might be indicative of suicidal behavior. For the automatic detection and classification of emotions in suicidal content, we can rely on the recent advances in the domain of LT (Jurafsky and Martin, 2008) and machine learning (Mitchell, 1997). Whereas the international LT research community until recently mainly focused on the “factual” aspects of content analysis, we can observe an additional growing interest in the analysis of attitude and affect in textual sources, especially in online content such as blogs, tweets, social network data, etc. The extraction of affective contents does not only imply the detection of opinions, evaluations, beliefs and speculations in text (topics which have a high application potential in customer intelligence applications and the like), but also the identific</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Jurafsky, Martin, 2008</marker>
<rawString>Daniel Jurafsky and James H. Martin. 2008. Speech and Language Processing, 2nd Edition.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Raghavendra Katikalapudi</author>
<author>Sriram Chellappan</author>
<author>Frances Montgomery</author>
<author>Donald Wunsch</author>
<author>Karl Lutzen</author>
</authors>
<title>Associating Internet Usage with Depressive Behavior Among College Students.</title>
<date>2012</date>
<journal>IEEE Technology and Society Magazine,</journal>
<volume>31</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<marker>Katikalapudi, Chellappan, Montgomery, Wunsch, Lutzen, 2012</marker>
<rawString>Raghavendra Katikalapudi, Sriram Chellappan, Frances Montgomery, Donald Wunsch, and Karl Lutzen. 2012. Associating Internet Usage with Depressive Behavior Among College Students. IEEE Technology and Society Magazine, 31(4):73–80.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S Kuny</author>
<author>H H Stassen</author>
</authors>
<title>Speaking behav-ior and voice sound characteristics in depressive patients during recovery.</title>
<date>1993</date>
<journal>Journal of psychiatric research,</journal>
<pages>27--3</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="8569" citStr="Kuny and Stassen, 1993" startWordPosition="1283" endWordPosition="1286">Mandrusiak et al., 2006) found that the searches with the terms “warning signals” and “suicide” produced approximately 183,000 outcomes. Warning signs could be categorized in terms of cognitive content, behavioral, situational or other indicators concerning psychological characteristics or interpersonal problems. They could identify suicidal groups that need urgent intervention. Internet searches for suicide may provide a faster way of monitoring possible trends in suicide. Some clinical studies observed that depressed patients frequently speech slow, uniform, monotonous and with a low voice (Kuny and Stassen, 1993) or to have psychomotor symptoms and this is reflected in the speech (Sobin and Sackeim, 1997). Moreover, emotions and mood can influence the speaking behavior of a person and the characteristics of the sound in speech (Kuny and Stassen, 1993; Bachorowski and Owren, 1995; Sobin and Alpert, 1999; Scherer, 2003; Goudbeek and Scherer, 2010). The speech of depressed patients is characterized by a longer pause duration, that is, an increased amount of time between speech utterances as well as by a reduced variability in mean vocal pitch (Lamers et al., 2014). For these reasons, the acoustic speech </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Kuny, Stassen, 1993</marker>
<rawString>S Kuny and H H Stassen. 1993. Speaking behav-ior and voice sound characteristics in depressive patients during recovery. Journal of psychiatric research, 27(3):289–307.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>Sanne M A Lamers</author>
<author>Khiet P Truong</author>
<author>Bas Steunenberg</author>
<author>Franciska de Jong</author>
<author>Gerben J Westerhof</author>
</authors>
<title>Applying prosodic speech features in mental health care: An exploratory study in a life-review intervention for depression.</title>
<date>2014</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the Workshop on Computational Linguistics and Clinical Psychology: From Linguistic Signal to Clinical Reality,</booktitle>
<pages>61--68</pages>
<institution>Baltimore. Association for Computational Linguistics.</institution>
<marker>Lamers, Truong, Steunenberg, de Jong, Westerhof, 2014</marker>
<rawString>Sanne M.A. Lamers, Khiet P. Truong, Bas Steunenberg, Franciska de Jong, and Gerben J. Westerhof. 2014. Applying prosodic speech features in mental health care: An exploratory study in a life-review intervention for depression. In Proceedings of the Workshop on Computational Linguistics and Clinical Psychology: From Linguistic Signal to Clinical Reality, pages 61–68, Baltimore. Association for Computational Linguistics.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Amanda Lenhart</author>
<author>Kristen Purcell</author>
<author>Aaron Smith</author>
<author>Kathryn Zickuhr</author>
</authors>
<title>Social Media &amp; Mobile Internet Use Among Teens and Young Adults.</title>
<date>2010</date>
<tech>Techni-cal report,</tech>
<institution>Pew Research Center,</institution>
<location>Washington, D.C.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="6195" citStr="Lenhart et al., 2010" startWordPosition="948" endWordPosition="951">at high risk of suicide or interact with them can lead to the fact that the potential suicidal may reconsider his/her final decision, or, on the contrary, encourage and accelerate the process of ending with his/her life (Wasserman et al., 2004). During the recent years, some popular social networks, such as Facebook have become the most important means of social communication, with nearly 1,230 million of registered users world-wide4, 70% of whom are young people who make frequent use of this type of media, through which the emotional states and impressions are exchanged (Dunlop et al., 2011; Lenhart et al., 2010). These social networks are also a way to find comfort and welfare and its usage promotes contact and positive support among young people, especially among those with mental disorders (Ellison et al., 2007). In addition, the Web offers possibilities for early detection on suicidal behaviors and it may constitute a cost-effective means of intervention based on a first step care approach. Their use may be of help for identifying pro-suicide messages, detecting group patterns, analyzing exposure to the warning signs and intervening in a personalized manner with people at risk who are willing to a</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Lenhart, Purcell, Smith, Zickuhr, 2010</marker>
<rawString>Amanda Lenhart, Kristen Purcell, Aaron Smith, and Kathryn Zickuhr. 2010. Social Media &amp; Mobile Internet Use Among Teens and Young Adults. Techni-cal report, Pew Research Center, Washington, D.C.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Maria Liakata</author>
<author>Jee-Hyub Kim</author>
<author>Shyamasree Saha</author>
<author>Janna Hastings</author>
<author>Dietrich Rebholz-Schuhmann</author>
</authors>
<title>Three hybrid classifiers for the detection of emotions in suicide notes. Biomedical informatics insights,</title>
<date>2012</date>
<pages>5--1</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="9868" citStr="Liakata et al., 2012" startWordPosition="1491" endWordPosition="1494">etection in clinical scenarios. But these acoustic features are not the only ones that can be used, Internet usage itself (Katikala-pudi et al., 2012), social networking behaviors (Moreno et al., 2011; Choudhury et al., 2012) or location sharing (Park et al., 2013) can vary as a function of being depressed. (Quercia et al., 2012) found correlations between sentiment and levels of popularity, influence and general well-being using the network relations among users and (O’Connor et al., 2010) used a measure of public opinion. All these methods can be applied to analyze emotion in suicide notes (Liakata et al., 2012). 5 Human Language Technologies and Suicide Prevention In order to resolve this social issue, Language Technologies (LT) could help with the early identification of “suicide warning signs” that will be useful to detect individuals with suicidal ideation, as well as virtual environments where pro-suicide information is being shared or suicidal attempts are being encouraged. In particular, LT can analyze language structures and their meaning (Navigli, 2009) on different textual genres. Tasks such as information retrieval (Salton and McGill, 1986), information extraction (Cowie and Lehnert, 1996)</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Liakata, Kim, Saha, Hastings, Rebholz-Schuhmann, 2012</marker>
<rawString>Maria Liakata, Jee-Hyub Kim, Shyamasree Saha, Janna Hastings, and Dietrich Rebholz-Schuhmann. 2012. Three hybrid classifiers for the detection of emotions in suicide notes. Biomedical informatics insights, 5(Suppl. 1):175–84, January.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Michael Mandrusiak</author>
<author>M David Rudd</author>
<author>Thomas E Joiner</author>
<author>Alan L Berman</author>
<author>Kimberly A Van Orden</author>
<author>Tracy Witte</author>
</authors>
<title>Warning signs for suicide on the Inter-net: a descriptive study. Suicide &amp; lifethreatening behavior,</title>
<date>2006</date>
<volume>36</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<marker>Mandrusiak, Rudd, Joiner, Berman, Van Orden, Witte, 2006</marker>
<rawString>Michael Mandrusiak, M David Rudd, Thomas E Joiner, Alan L Berman, Kimberly A Van Orden, and Tracy Witte. 2006. Warning signs for suicide on the Inter-net: a descriptive study. Suicide &amp; lifethreatening behavior, 36(3):263–71, June.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>R Osorio</author>
<author>T Palomo</author>
</authors>
<title>Suicidio. Asistencia Cl´ınica.</title>
<date>2004</date>
<booktitle>In Gu´ıa de practica´ medica´, chapter 4,</booktitle>
<pages>pages</pages>
<location>D´ıaz San-tos.</location>
<marker>Osorio, Palomo, 2004</marker>
<rawString>J.C Mingote, M.A Jimenez,´ R Osorio, and T. Palomo. 2004. Suicidio. Asistencia Cl´ınica. In Gu´ıa de practica´ medica´, chapter 4, pages 19–30. D´ıaz San-tos.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Thomas M Mitchell</author>
</authors>
<date>1997</date>
<booktitle>Machine Learning.</booktitle>
<publisher>McGraw-Hill, Inc.,</publisher>
<location>New York, NY, USA,</location>
<contexts>
<context position="15960" citStr="Mitchell, 1997" startWordPosition="2433" endWordPosition="2434">ormance. However, many challenges remain to be investigated: the sensitivity of the current systems to spelling and other errors -especially in online data-, the lack of deep understanding of the data through the use of mainly shallow features, etc. The release of this data set has made it possible to accurately detect and differentiate between different emotions, which might be indicative of suicidal behavior. For the automatic detection and classification of emotions in suicidal content, we can rely on the recent advances in the domain of LT (Jurafsky and Martin, 2008) and machine learning (Mitchell, 1997). Whereas the international LT research community until recently mainly focused on the “factual” aspects of content analysis, we can observe an additional growing interest in the analysis of attitude and affect in textual sources, especially in online content such as blogs, tweets, social network data, etc. The extraction of affective contents does not only imply the detection of opinions, evaluations, beliefs and speculations in text (topics which have a high application potential in customer intelligence applications and the like), but also the identification of certain emotions. For example</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Mitchell, 1997</marker>
<rawString>Thomas M. Mitchell. 1997. Machine Learning. McGraw-Hill, Inc., New York, NY, USA, March.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Megan A Moreno</author>
<author>Lauren A Jelenchick</author>
<author>Katie G Egan</author>
<author>Elizabeth Cox</author>
<author>Henry Young</author>
<author>Kerry E Gannon</author>
<author>Tara Becker</author>
</authors>
<title>Feeling bad on Face-book: depression disclosures by college students on a social networking site. Depression and anxiety,</title>
<date>2011</date>
<pages>28--6</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="9447" citStr="Moreno et al., 2011" startWordPosition="1423" endWordPosition="1426"> Owren, 1995; Sobin and Alpert, 1999; Scherer, 2003; Goudbeek and Scherer, 2010). The speech of depressed patients is characterized by a longer pause duration, that is, an increased amount of time between speech utterances as well as by a reduced variability in mean vocal pitch (Lamers et al., 2014). For these reasons, the acoustic speech features can be used to build models and algorithms for automated depression detection in clinical scenarios. But these acoustic features are not the only ones that can be used, Internet usage itself (Katikala-pudi et al., 2012), social networking behaviors (Moreno et al., 2011; Choudhury et al., 2012) or location sharing (Park et al., 2013) can vary as a function of being depressed. (Quercia et al., 2012) found correlations between sentiment and levels of popularity, influence and general well-being using the network relations among users and (O’Connor et al., 2010) used a measure of public opinion. All these methods can be applied to analyze emotion in suicide notes (Liakata et al., 2012). 5 Human Language Technologies and Suicide Prevention In order to resolve this social issue, Language Technologies (LT) could help with the early identification of “suicide warni</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Moreno, Jelenchick, Egan, Cox, Young, Gannon, Becker, 2011</marker>
<rawString>Megan A Moreno, Lauren A Jelenchick, Katie G Egan, Elizabeth Cox, Henry Young, Kerry E Gannon, and Tara Becker. 2011. Feeling bad on Face-book: depression disclosures by college students on a social networking site. Depression and anxiety, 28(6):447–55, June.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Pedro Moreno Gea</author>
<author>Carmen Blanco Sanchez´</author>
</authors>
<title>Suicidio e Internet. Medidas preventivas y de ac-tuacion´.</title>
<date>2012</date>
<journal>Psiquiatria.com,</journal>
<volume>16</volume>
<marker>Gea, Sanchez´, 2012</marker>
<rawString>Pedro Moreno Gea and Carmen Blanco Sanchez´. 2012. Suicidio e Internet. Medidas preventivas y de ac-tuacion´. Psiquiatria.com, 16.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Navigli</author>
</authors>
<title>Word Sense Disambiguation: A Survey.</title>
<date>2009</date>
<journal>ACM Computing Surveys,</journal>
<volume>41</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<contexts>
<context position="10327" citStr="Navigli, 2009" startWordPosition="1559" endWordPosition="1560">s and (O’Connor et al., 2010) used a measure of public opinion. All these methods can be applied to analyze emotion in suicide notes (Liakata et al., 2012). 5 Human Language Technologies and Suicide Prevention In order to resolve this social issue, Language Technologies (LT) could help with the early identification of “suicide warning signs” that will be useful to detect individuals with suicidal ideation, as well as virtual environments where pro-suicide information is being shared or suicidal attempts are being encouraged. In particular, LT can analyze language structures and their meaning (Navigli, 2009) on different textual genres. Tasks such as information retrieval (Salton and McGill, 1986), information extraction (Cowie and Lehnert, 1996), text classification and clustering (Sebastiani, 2002), or sentiment analysis (Pang and Lee, 2008) are basic pillars of these technologies that allow the construction of more complex automatic processes for discovering knowledge from oral and/or written text. Recent research in LT has been proved great potential in the area of healthcare. From the development of applications to assist medical practitioners in the access and management of information abou</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Navigli, 2009</marker>
<rawString>Navigli. 2009. Word Sense Disambiguation: A Survey. ACM Computing Surveys, 41(2).</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Yair Neuman</author>
<author>Yohai Cohen</author>
<author>Dan Assaf</author>
<author>Gabbi Kedma</author>
</authors>
<title>Proactive screening for depres-sion through metaphorical and automatic text analy-sis.</title>
<date>2012</date>
<journal>Artificial intelligence in medicine,</journal>
<volume>56</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<contexts>
<context position="13943" citStr="Neuman et al., 2012" startWordPosition="2117" endWordPosition="2120">t al., 2013), underlining once again the added value of automated speech analysis. (Howes et al., 2014) present an initial investigation into the application of computational linguistic techniques, such as topic and sentiment modelling, to online therapy for depression and anxiety using Latent Dirichlet Allocation (Blei et al., 2003). However, early works tried to detect specific emotions such as anger, surprise, fear, etc. using dictionary-based or machine-learning-based approaches (Chuang and Wu, 2004; Seol et al., 2008) and more recently (Purver and Battersby, 2012; Choudhury et al., 2012; Neuman et al., 2012; Howes et al., 2014). Although interesting research was conducted on the Schneidman data set, the focus should not be on distinguishing between genuine and elicited suicide notes. Instead, it is of key importance to determine what exactly makes a note a real suicide note, independently of the features of the elicited notes or the distinguishing characteristics between both types of notes. Such a suicide note corpus of positive-only data, annotated with fine-grained emotions, was released in the framework of the 2011 i2b2 Natural Language Processing Challenge (Pestian et al., 2012) on emotion </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Neuman, Cohen, Assaf, Kedma, 2012</marker>
<rawString>Yair Neuman, Yohai Cohen, Dan Assaf, and Gabbi Kedma. 2012. Proactive screening for depres-sion through metaphorical and automatic text analy-sis. Artificial intelligence in medicine, 56(1):19–25, September.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Brendan O’Connor</author>
<author>Ramnath Balasubramanyan</author>
<author>Bryan R Routledge</author>
<author>Noah A Smith</author>
</authors>
<title>From Tweets to Polls: Linking Text Sentiment to Public Opinion Time Series.</title>
<date>2010</date>
<booktitle>In Fourth International AAAI Conference on Weblogs and Social Media.</booktitle>
<marker>O’Connor, Balasubramanyan, Routledge, Smith, 2010</marker>
<rawString>Brendan O’Connor, Ramnath Balasubramanyan, Bryan R. Routledge, and Noah A. Smith. 2010. From Tweets to Polls: Linking Text Sentiment to Public Opinion Time Series. In Fourth International AAAI Conference on Weblogs and Social Media.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>C E Osgood</author>
<author>E G Walker</author>
</authors>
<title>Motivation and language behavior: a content analysis of suicide notes.</title>
<date>1959</date>
<journal>Journal of abnormal psychology,</journal>
<volume>59</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<pages>67</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="11493" citStr="Osgood and Walker, 1959" startWordPosition="1733" endWordPosition="1736">itioners in the access and management of information about patients, e.g. (Iakovidis and Smailis, 2012; Vest, 2012), to the creation of computer programs to support and/or facilitate reading comprehension for language-impaired children during communication (Dietz et al., 2011; Wang and Paul, 2011). So far, and to the best of our knowledge, very little effort has been made to apply LT for the benefit of suicide prevention. The linguistic analysis of suicide notes has a long history and already started as early as 1956 with the work of (Shneidman and Farberow, 1956), followed by several others (Osgood and Walker, 1959; Gleser et al., 1961; Edelman and Renshaw, 1982). The basis of most of this research was a corpus of 66 suicides notes, half genuine and half simulated, collected by Schneidman and the task was to identify those textual features which could differentiate between genuine and fake notes. Whereas the earlier work mostly focused on the manual analysis and detection of these differentiating features, e.g. by relying on techniques from discourse analysis (Shneidman and Farberow, 1956) or by focusing on shallow text characteristics such as the usage of modals and auxiliaries (Osgood and Walker, 1959</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Osgood, Walker, 1959</marker>
<rawString>C. E. Osgood and E. G. Walker. 1959. Motivation and language behavior: a content analysis of suicide notes. Journal of abnormal psychology, 59(1):58– 67, July.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Gareth Owen</author>
<author>Judith Belam</author>
<author>Helen Lambert</author>
<author>Jenny Donovan</author>
<author>Frances Rapport</author>
<author>Christabel Owens</author>
</authors>
<title>Suicide communication events: lay interpretation of the communication of suicidal ideation and intent.</title>
<date>2012</date>
<booktitle>Social science &amp; medicine</booktitle>
<pages>75--2</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="4365" citStr="Owen et al., 2012" startWordPosition="667" endWordPosition="670">e, feelings and intentions (Moreno Gea and Blanco Sanchez, 2012). They also warn their suicidal intentions through the Web in real time, before and while committing the act (Sarno, 2008). The study conducted in (Mingote et al., 2004) also proves that the younger are one of the population segments where prevention is particularly necessary, finding that 20% of suicides occur among adolescents and young adults. 3 Suicide Prevention in Social Media It is important to raise awareness on that most self-inflicted deaths are potentially preventable. Well-known studies concerning research on suicide (Owen et al., 2012; Isometsa, 2001; Cantor, 2000; Rudestam, 1971) show that a high number of people who decide to end with their lives. Through suicide had no prior contact with mental health services, but had communicated their suicidal plans or thoughts directly or indirectly through different means to members of their family, friends, colleagues, or through their social networks. Improve the staff skills in early recognition of suicide warning signs, is an essential issue to prevent suicidal mortality. There is an increasing tendency (Ruder et al., 2011) where suicide notes are posted on the social media (e.</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Owen, Belam, Lambert, Donovan, Rapport, Owens, 2012</marker>
<rawString>Gareth Owen, Judith Belam, Helen Lambert, Jenny Donovan, Frances Rapport, and Christabel Owens. 2012. Suicide communication events: lay interpretation of the communication of suicidal ideation and intent. Social science &amp; medicine (1982), 75(2):419–28, July.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Bo Pang</author>
<author>Lillian Lee</author>
</authors>
<title>Opinion Mining and Sentiment Analysis. Foundations and Trends R in Information Retrieval,</title>
<date>2008</date>
<pages>2--1</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="10567" citStr="Pang and Lee, 2008" startWordPosition="1589" endWordPosition="1592">social issue, Language Technologies (LT) could help with the early identification of “suicide warning signs” that will be useful to detect individuals with suicidal ideation, as well as virtual environments where pro-suicide information is being shared or suicidal attempts are being encouraged. In particular, LT can analyze language structures and their meaning (Navigli, 2009) on different textual genres. Tasks such as information retrieval (Salton and McGill, 1986), information extraction (Cowie and Lehnert, 1996), text classification and clustering (Sebastiani, 2002), or sentiment analysis (Pang and Lee, 2008) are basic pillars of these technologies that allow the construction of more complex automatic processes for discovering knowledge from oral and/or written text. Recent research in LT has been proved great potential in the area of healthcare. From the development of applications to assist medical practitioners in the access and management of information about patients, e.g. (Iakovidis and Smailis, 2012; Vest, 2012), to the creation of computer programs to support and/or facilitate reading comprehension for language-impaired children during communication (Dietz et al., 2011; Wang and Paul, 2011</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Pang, Lee, 2008</marker>
<rawString>Bo Pang and Lillian Lee. 2008. Opinion Mining and Sentiment Analysis. Foundations and Trends R in Information Retrieval, 2(1–2):1–135, January.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>Sungkyu Park</author>
</authors>
<location>Sang Won Lee, Jinah Kwak,</location>
<marker>Park, </marker>
<rawString>Sungkyu Park, Sang Won Lee, Jinah Kwak,</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Meeyoung Cha</author>
<author>Bumseok Jeong</author>
</authors>
<title>Activities on Face-book reveal the depressive state of users.</title>
<date>2013</date>
<journal>Journal of medical Internet research,</journal>
<volume>15</volume>
<issue>10</issue>
<marker>Cha, Jeong, 2013</marker>
<rawString>Meeyoung Cha, and Bumseok Jeong. 2013. Activities on Face-book reveal the depressive state of users. Journal of medical Internet research, 15(10):e217, January.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>James W Pennebaker</author>
<author>Cindy K Chung</author>
</authors>
<title>Expressive Writing, Emotional Upheavals, and Health. In</title>
<date>2011</date>
<booktitle>Expressive Writing, Emotional Upheavals, and Health, chapter 18,</booktitle>
<pages>936</pages>
<editor>Howard S. Friedman, editor,</editor>
<publisher>Oxford University Press.</publisher>
<contexts>
<context position="12526" citStr="Pennebaker and Chung, 2011" startWordPosition="1896" endWordPosition="1899">y relying on techniques from discourse analysis (Shneidman and Farberow, 1956) or by focusing on shallow text characteristics such as the usage of modals and auxiliaries (Osgood and Walker, 1959), the choice of verbs and adverbs (Gleser et al., 1961), etc. We can observe a recent tendency to also rely on automatic corpus analysis techniques for the automatic detection of suicide messages. (Shapero, 2011), for example, studied two corpora of suicide notes in an attempt to define the typical suicide note. For doing so, she automatically calculated word usage and semantic concepts in the notes. (Pennebaker and Chung, 2011) used the frequency of verbal elements in a narrative that express a certain mood or sentiment which show that there is also ample evidence that text mining techniques based on the frequency of certain terms can be applied to narratives from patients in order to monitor changes in mood. As far as we know, (Pestian et al., 2010) were the first to experiment with the use machine learning techniques for the automatic classification of suicide notes. In experiments on the earlier described data set of 66 notes, they investigated whether a machine learning system was able to classify suicide notes </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Pennebaker, Chung, 2011</marker>
<rawString>James W. Pennebaker and Cindy K. Chung. 2011. Expressive Writing, Emotional Upheavals, and Health. In Howard S. Friedman, editor, Expressive Writing, Emotional Upheavals, and Health, chapter 18, page 936. Oxford University Press.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>J Pestian</author>
<author>H Nasrallah</author>
<author>A Bennett Matykiewicz</author>
<author>A Leenaars</author>
</authors>
<title>Suicide Note Classification Using Natural Language Processing. Biomed Inform Insights,</title>
<date>2010</date>
<pages>3--19</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="12855" citStr="Pestian et al., 2010" startWordPosition="1954" endWordPosition="1957">hniques for the automatic detection of suicide messages. (Shapero, 2011), for example, studied two corpora of suicide notes in an attempt to define the typical suicide note. For doing so, she automatically calculated word usage and semantic concepts in the notes. (Pennebaker and Chung, 2011) used the frequency of verbal elements in a narrative that express a certain mood or sentiment which show that there is also ample evidence that text mining techniques based on the frequency of certain terms can be applied to narratives from patients in order to monitor changes in mood. As far as we know, (Pestian et al., 2010) were the first to experiment with the use machine learning techniques for the automatic classification of suicide notes. In experiments on the earlier described data set of 66 notes, they investigated whether a machine learning system was able to classify suicide notes with a higher accuracy than mental health professionals. They showed that the best machine learners were indeed able to outperform the human experts. More recent studies confirm this fact (Janssen et al., 2013), underlining once again the added value of automated speech analysis. (Howes et al., 2014) present an initial investig</context>
<context position="16900" citStr="Pestian et al., 2010" startWordPosition="2570" endWordPosition="2573">tion of affective contents does not only imply the detection of opinions, evaluations, beliefs and speculations in text (topics which have a high application potential in customer intelligence applications and the like), but also the identification of certain emotions. For example, how do people express their intent to commit suicide? The use of machine learning techniques and sentiment analysis techniques for the automatic analysis of suicide notes is not new. (Huang et al., 2007), for example, experimented with lexicon-based sentiment analysis for the automatic detection of suicidal blogs. (Pestian et al., 2010) combined shallow text characteristics, such as part-of-speech information, readability scores and parse information with the machine learning software as available in the Weka package. Until we know, the most complete research about suicide prevention in the social networks, specifically Facebook, is the work of (Schwartz et al., 2014). However, instead of trying to detect suicide notes or to differentiate people with or without mental disorders, they measure the changes across time of the degree of depression. 6 Conclusions The magnitude of the suicide in the EU member states and the rest of</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Pestian, Nasrallah, Matykiewicz, Leenaars, 2010</marker>
<rawString>J. Pestian, H. Nasrallah, Matykiewicz, A. Bennett, and A. Leenaars. 2010. Suicide Note Classification Using Natural Language Processing. Biomed Inform Insights, 3:19–28.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>John P Pestian</author>
<author>Pawel Matykiewicz</author>
<author>Michelle LinnGust</author>
<author>Brett South</author>
<author>Ozlem Uzuner</author>
<author>Jan Wiebe</author>
<author>K Bretonnel Cohen</author>
<author>John Hurdle</author>
<author>Christopher Brew</author>
</authors>
<title>Sentiment Analysis of Suicide Notes: A Shared Task. Biomedical informatics insights, 5(Suppl 1):3–16,</title>
<date>2012</date>
<contexts>
<context position="14531" citStr="Pestian et al., 2012" startWordPosition="2207" endWordPosition="2210">et al., 2012; Neuman et al., 2012; Howes et al., 2014). Although interesting research was conducted on the Schneidman data set, the focus should not be on distinguishing between genuine and elicited suicide notes. Instead, it is of key importance to determine what exactly makes a note a real suicide note, independently of the features of the elicited notes or the distinguishing characteristics between both types of notes. Such a suicide note corpus of positive-only data, annotated with fine-grained emotions, was released in the framework of the 2011 i2b2 Natural Language Processing Challenge (Pestian et al., 2012) on emotion classification in suicide notes. Although the scope of the challenge (differentiating between emotions in positiveonly data) was different, it led to the creation of a permanently available resource facilitating future research in emotion detection in suicide notes. The corpus contains the notes written by 1319 people, before they committed suicide. The notes were collected between 1950 and 2011. Spelling and grammar errors were kept in the data. All notes were anonymized by replacing all names with other values and by randomly shifting dates within the same year. The data set of t</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Pestian, Matykiewicz, LinnGust, South, Uzuner, Wiebe, Cohen, Hurdle, Brew, 2012</marker>
<rawString>John P Pestian, Pawel Matykiewicz, Michelle LinnGust, Brett South, Ozlem Uzuner, Jan Wiebe, K Bretonnel Cohen, John Hurdle, and Christopher Brew. 2012. Sentiment Analysis of Suicide Notes: A Shared Task. Biomedical informatics insights, 5(Suppl 1):3–16, January.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Matthew Purver</author>
<author>Stuart Battersby</author>
</authors>
<title>Experimenting with distant supervision for emotion classi-fication.</title>
<date>2012</date>
<booktitle>In 13th Conference of the European Chap-ter of the Association for Computational Linguistics (EACL),</booktitle>
<pages>482--491</pages>
<location>Stroudsburg, PA, USA,</location>
<contexts>
<context position="13898" citStr="Purver and Battersby, 2012" startWordPosition="2109" endWordPosition="2112">ts. More recent studies confirm this fact (Janssen et al., 2013), underlining once again the added value of automated speech analysis. (Howes et al., 2014) present an initial investigation into the application of computational linguistic techniques, such as topic and sentiment modelling, to online therapy for depression and anxiety using Latent Dirichlet Allocation (Blei et al., 2003). However, early works tried to detect specific emotions such as anger, surprise, fear, etc. using dictionary-based or machine-learning-based approaches (Chuang and Wu, 2004; Seol et al., 2008) and more recently (Purver and Battersby, 2012; Choudhury et al., 2012; Neuman et al., 2012; Howes et al., 2014). Although interesting research was conducted on the Schneidman data set, the focus should not be on distinguishing between genuine and elicited suicide notes. Instead, it is of key importance to determine what exactly makes a note a real suicide note, independently of the features of the elicited notes or the distinguishing characteristics between both types of notes. Such a suicide note corpus of positive-only data, annotated with fine-grained emotions, was released in the framework of the 2011 i2b2 Natural Language Processing</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Purver, Battersby, 2012</marker>
<rawString>Matthew Purver and Stuart Battersby. 2012. Experimenting with distant supervision for emotion classi-fication. In 13th Conference of the European Chap-ter of the Association for Computational Linguistics (EACL), pages 482–491. Association for Computa-tional Linguistics, Stroudsburg, PA, USA, April.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Daniele Quercia</author>
<author>Jonathan Ellis</author>
<author>Licia Capra</author>
<author>Jon Crowcroft</author>
</authors>
<title>Tracking ”gross community happiness” from tweets.</title>
<date>2012</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the ACM 2012 conference on Computer Supported Coopera-tive Work - CSCW ’12,</booktitle>
<pages>965</pages>
<publisher>ACM Press.</publisher>
<location>New York, New York, USA,</location>
<contexts>
<context position="9578" citStr="Quercia et al., 2012" startWordPosition="1446" endWordPosition="1449">ed by a longer pause duration, that is, an increased amount of time between speech utterances as well as by a reduced variability in mean vocal pitch (Lamers et al., 2014). For these reasons, the acoustic speech features can be used to build models and algorithms for automated depression detection in clinical scenarios. But these acoustic features are not the only ones that can be used, Internet usage itself (Katikala-pudi et al., 2012), social networking behaviors (Moreno et al., 2011; Choudhury et al., 2012) or location sharing (Park et al., 2013) can vary as a function of being depressed. (Quercia et al., 2012) found correlations between sentiment and levels of popularity, influence and general well-being using the network relations among users and (O’Connor et al., 2010) used a measure of public opinion. All these methods can be applied to analyze emotion in suicide notes (Liakata et al., 2012). 5 Human Language Technologies and Suicide Prevention In order to resolve this social issue, Language Technologies (LT) could help with the early identification of “suicide warning signs” that will be useful to detect individuals with suicidal ideation, as well as virtual environments where pro-suicide infor</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Quercia, Ellis, Capra, Crowcroft, 2012</marker>
<rawString>Daniele Quercia, Jonathan Ellis, Licia Capra, and Jon Crowcroft. 2012. Tracking ”gross community happiness” from tweets. In Proceedings of the ACM 2012 conference on Computer Supported Coopera-tive Work - CSCW ’12, page 965, New York, New York, USA, February. ACM Press.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Thomas D Ruder</author>
<author>Gary M Hatch</author>
<author>Garyfalia Ampanozi</author>
<author>Michael J Thali</author>
<author>Nadja Fischer</author>
</authors>
<title>Suicide announcement on Facebook.</title>
<date>2011</date>
<journal>Crisis,</journal>
<volume>32</volume>
<issue>5</issue>
<contexts>
<context position="4910" citStr="Ruder et al., 2011" startWordPosition="751" endWordPosition="754">able. Well-known studies concerning research on suicide (Owen et al., 2012; Isometsa, 2001; Cantor, 2000; Rudestam, 1971) show that a high number of people who decide to end with their lives. Through suicide had no prior contact with mental health services, but had communicated their suicidal plans or thoughts directly or indirectly through different means to members of their family, friends, colleagues, or through their social networks. Improve the staff skills in early recognition of suicide warning signs, is an essential issue to prevent suicidal mortality. There is an increasing tendency (Ruder et al., 2011) where suicide notes are posted on the social media (e.g., Facebook, Twitter), where Internet users (and not necessarily teenagers) announce their suicidal thoughts before committing suicide. This poses new challenges for human language technologies since, traditional existing automatic tools are not able to process the new language employed in the social media (abbreviations, slang, smiles and, more generally, a low unstructured and highly informal language). The Internet, and specifically the Web 2.0, is an important source of information for learning about suicidal behaviors (Dunlop et al.,</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Ruder, Hatch, Ampanozi, Thali, Fischer, 2011</marker>
<rawString>Thomas D Ruder, Gary M Hatch, Garyfalia Ampanozi, Michael J Thali, and Nadja Fischer. 2011. Suicide announcement on Facebook. Crisis, 32(5):280–2, January.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Kjell E Rudestam</author>
</authors>
<title>Stockholm and Los Angeles: A cross-cultural study of the communication of suicidal intent.</title>
<date>1971</date>
<journal>Journal of Consulting and Clinical Psychology,</journal>
<volume>36</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<contexts>
<context position="4412" citStr="Rudestam, 1971" startWordPosition="675" endWordPosition="676"> Sanchez, 2012). They also warn their suicidal intentions through the Web in real time, before and while committing the act (Sarno, 2008). The study conducted in (Mingote et al., 2004) also proves that the younger are one of the population segments where prevention is particularly necessary, finding that 20% of suicides occur among adolescents and young adults. 3 Suicide Prevention in Social Media It is important to raise awareness on that most self-inflicted deaths are potentially preventable. Well-known studies concerning research on suicide (Owen et al., 2012; Isometsa, 2001; Cantor, 2000; Rudestam, 1971) show that a high number of people who decide to end with their lives. Through suicide had no prior contact with mental health services, but had communicated their suicidal plans or thoughts directly or indirectly through different means to members of their family, friends, colleagues, or through their social networks. Improve the staff skills in early recognition of suicide warning signs, is an essential issue to prevent suicidal mortality. There is an increasing tendency (Ruder et al., 2011) where suicide notes are posted on the social media (e.g., Facebook, Twitter), where Internet users (a</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Rudestam, 1971</marker>
<rawString>Kjell E. Rudestam. 1971. Stockholm and Los Angeles: A cross-cultural study of the communication of suicidal intent. Journal of Consulting and Clinical Psychology, 36(1):82–90.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Gerard Salton</author>
<author>Michael J McGill</author>
</authors>
<title>Introduction to Modern Information Retrieval.</title>
<date>1986</date>
<publisher>McGraw-Hill, Inc.,</publisher>
<location>New York, NY, USA.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="10418" citStr="Salton and McGill, 1986" startWordPosition="1570" endWordPosition="1573"> can be applied to analyze emotion in suicide notes (Liakata et al., 2012). 5 Human Language Technologies and Suicide Prevention In order to resolve this social issue, Language Technologies (LT) could help with the early identification of “suicide warning signs” that will be useful to detect individuals with suicidal ideation, as well as virtual environments where pro-suicide information is being shared or suicidal attempts are being encouraged. In particular, LT can analyze language structures and their meaning (Navigli, 2009) on different textual genres. Tasks such as information retrieval (Salton and McGill, 1986), information extraction (Cowie and Lehnert, 1996), text classification and clustering (Sebastiani, 2002), or sentiment analysis (Pang and Lee, 2008) are basic pillars of these technologies that allow the construction of more complex automatic processes for discovering knowledge from oral and/or written text. Recent research in LT has been proved great potential in the area of healthcare. From the development of applications to assist medical practitioners in the access and management of information about patients, e.g. (Iakovidis and Smailis, 2012; Vest, 2012), to the creation of computer pro</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Salton, McGill, 1986</marker>
<rawString>Gerard Salton and Michael J. McGill. 1986. Introduction to Modern Information Retrieval. McGraw-Hill, Inc., New York, NY, USA.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>David Sarno</author>
</authors>
<date>2008</date>
<note>Rise and fall of the Googled swastika.</note>
<contexts>
<context position="3934" citStr="Sarno, 2008" startWordPosition="604" endWordPosition="605">e of this type of technology can be up to 90.2%, in the case of students (García-Rabagó et al., 2010). Forums, chats, social networks, blogs, microblogs or e-mails are virtual spaces where Internet users can interact freely and even fantasize, using anonymous identities. This implies that people with suicidal tendencies, tend to express their thoughts, desires and intentions in pro-suicide forums and share with other people, feelings and intentions (Moreno Gea and Blanco Sanchez, 2012). They also warn their suicidal intentions through the Web in real time, before and while committing the act (Sarno, 2008). The study conducted in (Mingote et al., 2004) also proves that the younger are one of the population segments where prevention is particularly necessary, finding that 20% of suicides occur among adolescents and young adults. 3 Suicide Prevention in Social Media It is important to raise awareness on that most self-inflicted deaths are potentially preventable. Well-known studies concerning research on suicide (Owen et al., 2012; Isometsa, 2001; Cantor, 2000; Rudestam, 1971) show that a high number of people who decide to end with their lives. Through suicide had no prior contact with mental he</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Sarno, 2008</marker>
<rawString>David Sarno. 2008. Rise and fall of the Googled swastika.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>K Scherer</author>
</authors>
<title>Vocal communication of emotion: A review of research paradigms.</title>
<date>2003</date>
<journal>Speech Communication,</journal>
<pages>40--1</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="8879" citStr="Scherer, 2003" startWordPosition="1335" endWordPosition="1336">could identify suicidal groups that need urgent intervention. Internet searches for suicide may provide a faster way of monitoring possible trends in suicide. Some clinical studies observed that depressed patients frequently speech slow, uniform, monotonous and with a low voice (Kuny and Stassen, 1993) or to have psychomotor symptoms and this is reflected in the speech (Sobin and Sackeim, 1997). Moreover, emotions and mood can influence the speaking behavior of a person and the characteristics of the sound in speech (Kuny and Stassen, 1993; Bachorowski and Owren, 1995; Sobin and Alpert, 1999; Scherer, 2003; Goudbeek and Scherer, 2010). The speech of depressed patients is characterized by a longer pause duration, that is, an increased amount of time between speech utterances as well as by a reduced variability in mean vocal pitch (Lamers et al., 2014). For these reasons, the acoustic speech features can be used to build models and algorithms for automated depression detection in clinical scenarios. But these acoustic features are not the only ones that can be used, Internet usage itself (Katikala-pudi et al., 2012), social networking behaviors (Moreno et al., 2011; Choudhury et al., 2012) or loc</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Scherer, 2003</marker>
<rawString>K Scherer. 2003. Vocal communication of emotion: A review of research paradigms. Speech Communication, 40(1-2):227–256, April.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>Andrew Schwartz</author>
<author>Johannes Eichstaedt</author>
<author>Margaret L Kern</author>
<author>Gregory Park</author>
<author>Maarten Sap</author>
<author>David Stillwell</author>
<author>Michal Kosinski</author>
<author>Lyle Ungar</author>
</authors>
<title>Towards Assessing Changes in Degree of Depression through Facebook.</title>
<date>2014</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the Workshop on Computational Linguistics and Clinical Psychology: From Linguistic Signal to Clinical Reality,</booktitle>
<pages>118--125</pages>
<institution>Baltimore. Association for Computational Linguistics.</institution>
<contexts>
<context position="17238" citStr="Schwartz et al., 2014" startWordPosition="2618" endWordPosition="2621">The use of machine learning techniques and sentiment analysis techniques for the automatic analysis of suicide notes is not new. (Huang et al., 2007), for example, experimented with lexicon-based sentiment analysis for the automatic detection of suicidal blogs. (Pestian et al., 2010) combined shallow text characteristics, such as part-of-speech information, readability scores and parse information with the machine learning software as available in the Weka package. Until we know, the most complete research about suicide prevention in the social networks, specifically Facebook, is the work of (Schwartz et al., 2014). However, instead of trying to detect suicide notes or to differentiate people with or without mental disorders, they measure the changes across time of the degree of depression. 6 Conclusions The magnitude of the suicide in the EU member states and the rest of the world make suicide prevention not exclusively a problem of Mental Health. This is a problem that must be addressed from a multidisciplinary perspective, involving different areas. Internet Technologies and Communication and, more specifically, the Human Language Technologies can help to resolve part of these problems through the ea</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Schwartz, Eichstaedt, Kern, Park, Sap, Stillwell, Kosinski, Ungar, 2014</marker>
<rawString>Andrew Schwartz, Johannes Eichstaedt, Margaret L. Kern, Gregory Park, Maarten Sap, David Stillwell, Michal Kosinski, and Lyle Ungar. 2014. Towards Assessing Changes in Degree of Depression through Facebook. In Proceedings of the Workshop on Computational Linguistics and Clinical Psychology: From Linguistic Signal to Clinical Reality, pages 118–125, Baltimore. Association for Computational Linguistics.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Fabrizio Sebastiani</author>
</authors>
<title>Machine learning in automated text categorization.</title>
<date>2002</date>
<journal>ACM Computing Surveys,</journal>
<volume>34</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<contexts>
<context position="10523" citStr="Sebastiani, 2002" startWordPosition="1584" endWordPosition="1585">icide Prevention In order to resolve this social issue, Language Technologies (LT) could help with the early identification of “suicide warning signs” that will be useful to detect individuals with suicidal ideation, as well as virtual environments where pro-suicide information is being shared or suicidal attempts are being encouraged. In particular, LT can analyze language structures and their meaning (Navigli, 2009) on different textual genres. Tasks such as information retrieval (Salton and McGill, 1986), information extraction (Cowie and Lehnert, 1996), text classification and clustering (Sebastiani, 2002), or sentiment analysis (Pang and Lee, 2008) are basic pillars of these technologies that allow the construction of more complex automatic processes for discovering knowledge from oral and/or written text. Recent research in LT has been proved great potential in the area of healthcare. From the development of applications to assist medical practitioners in the access and management of information about patients, e.g. (Iakovidis and Smailis, 2012; Vest, 2012), to the creation of computer programs to support and/or facilitate reading comprehension for language-impaired children during communicat</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Sebastiani, 2002</marker>
<rawString>Fabrizio Sebastiani. 2002. Machine learning in automated text categorization. ACM Computing Surveys, 34(1):1–47, March.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Young-Soo Seol</author>
<author>Dong-Joo Kim</author>
<author>Han-Woo Kim</author>
</authors>
<title>Emotion Recognition from Text Using Knowledge-based ANN.</title>
<date>2008</date>
<booktitle>Proceedings of ITCCSCC,</booktitle>
<pages>9--2</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="13852" citStr="Seol et al., 2008" startWordPosition="2102" endWordPosition="2105">eed able to outperform the human experts. More recent studies confirm this fact (Janssen et al., 2013), underlining once again the added value of automated speech analysis. (Howes et al., 2014) present an initial investigation into the application of computational linguistic techniques, such as topic and sentiment modelling, to online therapy for depression and anxiety using Latent Dirichlet Allocation (Blei et al., 2003). However, early works tried to detect specific emotions such as anger, surprise, fear, etc. using dictionary-based or machine-learning-based approaches (Chuang and Wu, 2004; Seol et al., 2008) and more recently (Purver and Battersby, 2012; Choudhury et al., 2012; Neuman et al., 2012; Howes et al., 2014). Although interesting research was conducted on the Schneidman data set, the focus should not be on distinguishing between genuine and elicited suicide notes. Instead, it is of key importance to determine what exactly makes a note a real suicide note, independently of the features of the elicited notes or the distinguishing characteristics between both types of notes. Such a suicide note corpus of positive-only data, annotated with fine-grained emotions, was released in the framewor</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Seol, Kim, Kim, 2008</marker>
<rawString>Young-Soo Seol, Dong-Joo Kim, and Han-Woo Kim. 2008. Emotion Recognition from Text Using Knowledge-based ANN. Proceedings of ITCCSCC, 9(2).</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Jess Jann Shapero</author>
</authors>
<title>The language of suicide notes,</title>
<date>2011</date>
<contexts>
<context position="12306" citStr="Shapero, 2011" startWordPosition="1863" endWordPosition="1864">dentify those textual features which could differentiate between genuine and fake notes. Whereas the earlier work mostly focused on the manual analysis and detection of these differentiating features, e.g. by relying on techniques from discourse analysis (Shneidman and Farberow, 1956) or by focusing on shallow text characteristics such as the usage of modals and auxiliaries (Osgood and Walker, 1959), the choice of verbs and adverbs (Gleser et al., 1961), etc. We can observe a recent tendency to also rely on automatic corpus analysis techniques for the automatic detection of suicide messages. (Shapero, 2011), for example, studied two corpora of suicide notes in an attempt to define the typical suicide note. For doing so, she automatically calculated word usage and semantic concepts in the notes. (Pennebaker and Chung, 2011) used the frequency of verbal elements in a narrative that express a certain mood or sentiment which show that there is also ample evidence that text mining techniques based on the frequency of certain terms can be applied to narratives from patients in order to monitor changes in mood. As far as we know, (Pestian et al., 2010) were the first to experiment with the use machine </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Shapero, 2011</marker>
<rawString>Jess Jann Shapero. 2011. The language of suicide notes, July.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>E S Shneidman</author>
<author>N L Farberow</author>
</authors>
<title>Clues to suicide. Public health reports,</title>
<date>1956</date>
<pages>71--2</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="11440" citStr="Shneidman and Farberow, 1956" startWordPosition="1725" endWordPosition="1728">rom the development of applications to assist medical practitioners in the access and management of information about patients, e.g. (Iakovidis and Smailis, 2012; Vest, 2012), to the creation of computer programs to support and/or facilitate reading comprehension for language-impaired children during communication (Dietz et al., 2011; Wang and Paul, 2011). So far, and to the best of our knowledge, very little effort has been made to apply LT for the benefit of suicide prevention. The linguistic analysis of suicide notes has a long history and already started as early as 1956 with the work of (Shneidman and Farberow, 1956), followed by several others (Osgood and Walker, 1959; Gleser et al., 1961; Edelman and Renshaw, 1982). The basis of most of this research was a corpus of 66 suicides notes, half genuine and half simulated, collected by Schneidman and the task was to identify those textual features which could differentiate between genuine and fake notes. Whereas the earlier work mostly focused on the manual analysis and detection of these differentiating features, e.g. by relying on techniques from discourse analysis (Shneidman and Farberow, 1956) or by focusing on shallow text characteristics such as the usa</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Shneidman, Farberow, 1956</marker>
<rawString>E. S. Shneidman and N. L. Farberow. 1956. Clues to suicide. Public health reports, 71(2):109–14, February.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>C Sobin</author>
<author>M Alpert</author>
</authors>
<title>Emotion in speech: the acoustic attributes of fear, anger, sadness, and joy.</title>
<date>1999</date>
<journal>Journal of psycholinguistic research,</journal>
<volume>28</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<contexts>
<context position="8864" citStr="Sobin and Alpert, 1999" startWordPosition="1331" endWordPosition="1334">personal problems. They could identify suicidal groups that need urgent intervention. Internet searches for suicide may provide a faster way of monitoring possible trends in suicide. Some clinical studies observed that depressed patients frequently speech slow, uniform, monotonous and with a low voice (Kuny and Stassen, 1993) or to have psychomotor symptoms and this is reflected in the speech (Sobin and Sackeim, 1997). Moreover, emotions and mood can influence the speaking behavior of a person and the characteristics of the sound in speech (Kuny and Stassen, 1993; Bachorowski and Owren, 1995; Sobin and Alpert, 1999; Scherer, 2003; Goudbeek and Scherer, 2010). The speech of depressed patients is characterized by a longer pause duration, that is, an increased amount of time between speech utterances as well as by a reduced variability in mean vocal pitch (Lamers et al., 2014). For these reasons, the acoustic speech features can be used to build models and algorithms for automated depression detection in clinical scenarios. But these acoustic features are not the only ones that can be used, Internet usage itself (Katikala-pudi et al., 2012), social networking behaviors (Moreno et al., 2011; Choudhury et al</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Sobin, Alpert, 1999</marker>
<rawString>C Sobin and M Alpert. 1999. Emotion in speech: the acoustic attributes of fear, anger, sadness, and joy. Journal of psycholinguistic research, 28(4):347–65, July.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>C Sobin</author>
<author>H A Sackeim</author>
</authors>
<title>Psychomotor symptoms of depression.</title>
<date>1997</date>
<journal>The American journal of psychiatry,</journal>
<volume>154</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<contexts>
<context position="8663" citStr="Sobin and Sackeim, 1997" startWordPosition="1299" endWordPosition="1302">e” produced approximately 183,000 outcomes. Warning signs could be categorized in terms of cognitive content, behavioral, situational or other indicators concerning psychological characteristics or interpersonal problems. They could identify suicidal groups that need urgent intervention. Internet searches for suicide may provide a faster way of monitoring possible trends in suicide. Some clinical studies observed that depressed patients frequently speech slow, uniform, monotonous and with a low voice (Kuny and Stassen, 1993) or to have psychomotor symptoms and this is reflected in the speech (Sobin and Sackeim, 1997). Moreover, emotions and mood can influence the speaking behavior of a person and the characteristics of the sound in speech (Kuny and Stassen, 1993; Bachorowski and Owren, 1995; Sobin and Alpert, 1999; Scherer, 2003; Goudbeek and Scherer, 2010). The speech of depressed patients is characterized by a longer pause duration, that is, an increased amount of time between speech utterances as well as by a reduced variability in mean vocal pitch (Lamers et al., 2014). For these reasons, the acoustic speech features can be used to build models and algorithms for automated depression detection in clin</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Sobin, Sackeim, 1997</marker>
<rawString>C Sobin and H A Sackeim. 1997. Psychomotor symptoms of depression. The American journal of psychiatry, 154(1):4–17, January.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>P Sobocki</author>
<author>I Lekander</author>
<author>F Borgstrom¨</author>
</authors>
<title>The economic burden of depression in Sweden from</title>
<date>2007</date>
<journal>Eur Psychiatry,</journal>
<volume>22</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<note>to</note>
<marker>Sobocki, Lekander, Borgstrom¨, 2007</marker>
<rawString>P Sobocki, I Lekander, and F Borgstrom¨. 2007. The economic burden of depression in Sweden from 1997 to 2005. Eur Psychiatry, 22(3):146–152.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Martin</author>
</authors>
<title>Effects of the 2008 recession on health: a first look at European data.</title>
<date>2011</date>
<journal>The Lancet,</journal>
<volume>378</volume>
<issue>9786</issue>
<pages>125</pages>
<marker>Martin, 2011</marker>
<rawString>David Stuckler, Sanjay BasuMarc, Adam Coutts Suhrcke, and McKee. Martin. 2011. Effects of the 2008 recession on health: a first look at European data. The Lancet, 378(9786):124 – 125.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>JR Vest</author>
</authors>
<title>Health information exchange: national and international approaches. Adv Health Care Manag,</title>
<date>2012</date>
<pages>12--3</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="10985" citStr="Vest, 2012" startWordPosition="1653" endWordPosition="1654">ormation retrieval (Salton and McGill, 1986), information extraction (Cowie and Lehnert, 1996), text classification and clustering (Sebastiani, 2002), or sentiment analysis (Pang and Lee, 2008) are basic pillars of these technologies that allow the construction of more complex automatic processes for discovering knowledge from oral and/or written text. Recent research in LT has been proved great potential in the area of healthcare. From the development of applications to assist medical practitioners in the access and management of information about patients, e.g. (Iakovidis and Smailis, 2012; Vest, 2012), to the creation of computer programs to support and/or facilitate reading comprehension for language-impaired children during communication (Dietz et al., 2011; Wang and Paul, 2011). So far, and to the best of our knowledge, very little effort has been made to apply LT for the benefit of suicide prevention. The linguistic analysis of suicide notes has a long history and already started as early as 1956 with the work of (Shneidman and Farberow, 1956), followed by several others (Osgood and Walker, 1959; Gleser et al., 1961; Edelman and Renshaw, 1982). The basis of most of this research was a </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Vest, 2012</marker>
<rawString>JR Vest. 2012. Health information exchange: national and international approaches. Adv Health Care Manag, 12:3–24.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Y Wang</author>
<author>P V Paul</author>
</authors>
<title>Integrating technology and reading instruction with children who are deaf or hard of hearing: the effectiveness of the Cornerstones project.</title>
<date>2011</date>
<journal>Am Ann Deaf,</journal>
<volume>156</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<contexts>
<context position="11168" citStr="Wang and Paul, 2011" startWordPosition="1676" endWordPosition="1679">Pang and Lee, 2008) are basic pillars of these technologies that allow the construction of more complex automatic processes for discovering knowledge from oral and/or written text. Recent research in LT has been proved great potential in the area of healthcare. From the development of applications to assist medical practitioners in the access and management of information about patients, e.g. (Iakovidis and Smailis, 2012; Vest, 2012), to the creation of computer programs to support and/or facilitate reading comprehension for language-impaired children during communication (Dietz et al., 2011; Wang and Paul, 2011). So far, and to the best of our knowledge, very little effort has been made to apply LT for the benefit of suicide prevention. The linguistic analysis of suicide notes has a long history and already started as early as 1956 with the work of (Shneidman and Farberow, 1956), followed by several others (Osgood and Walker, 1959; Gleser et al., 1961; Edelman and Renshaw, 1982). The basis of most of this research was a corpus of 66 suicides notes, half genuine and half simulated, collected by Schneidman and the task was to identify those textual features which could differentiate between genuine and</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Wang, Paul, 2011</marker>
<rawString>Y Wang and P.V. Paul. 2011. Integrating technology and reading instruction with children who are deaf or hard of hearing: the effectiveness of the Cornerstones project. Am Ann Deaf, 156(1):56–68.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Danuta Wasserman</author>
<author>Ellenor Mittendorfer Rutz</author>
<author>Wolfgang Rutz</author>
<author>Armin Schmidtke</author>
</authors>
<title>Suicide Prevention In</title>
<date>2004</date>
<booktitle>Europe. Technical report, National and Stockholm County Council’s Centre for Suicide Research and Prevention of Mental Ill Health.</booktitle>
<contexts>
<context position="2470" citStr="Wasserman et al., 2004" startWordPosition="385" endWordPosition="388">ird leading cause of violent death among people aged 15 to 44, followed by accidents and homicides (Holmes et al., 2007), and it would be the second reason that would explain the deaths in the group of people aged 15 to 19 years (WHO, 2014). Suicidal behaviors can be defined as a complex process that can range from suicidal ideation (communicated through verbal or nonverbal means) to planning of suicide, attempting suicide, and in the worst case, the suicide itself. These behaviors are influenced by interacting biological, genetic, psychological, social, environmental and situational factors (Wasserman et al., 2004). Suicide has also been strong linked to inequity, social exclusion and socio-economic deprivation (Berk and Dodd, 2006). It is an enormous problem that causing unnecessary human suffering and immeasurable costs for society. According to Josee Van Remoortel, advisor to the European organization Mental Health Europe2 (MHE), the financial crisis is affecting “all areas of life”, not just economies, and its impact on mental health is creating a “deep chasm in our society”. 1http://ec.europa.eu/health/ph_determinants/life_style/menta l/docs/pact_en.pdf 2http://www.mhe-sme.org/ 2 Internet and Socia</context>
<context position="5818" citStr="Wasserman et al., 2004" startWordPosition="888" endWordPosition="891">ic tools are not able to process the new language employed in the social media (abbreviations, slang, smiles and, more generally, a low unstructured and highly informal language). The Internet, and specifically the Web 2.0, is an important source of information for learning about suicidal behaviors (Dunlop et al., 2011). The way individuals respond to help request from people at high risk of suicide or interact with them can lead to the fact that the potential suicidal may reconsider his/her final decision, or, on the contrary, encourage and accelerate the process of ending with his/her life (Wasserman et al., 2004). During the recent years, some popular social networks, such as Facebook have become the most important means of social communication, with nearly 1,230 million of registered users world-wide4, 70% of whom are young people who make frequent use of this type of media, through which the emotional states and impressions are exchanged (Dunlop et al., 2011; Lenhart et al., 2010). These social networks are also a way to find comfort and welfare and its usage promotes contact and positive support among young people, especially among those with mental disorders (Ellison et al., 2007). In addition, th</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Wasserman, Rutz, Rutz, Schmidtke, 2004</marker>
<rawString>Danuta Wasserman, Ellenor Mittendorfer Rutz, Wolfgang Rutz, and Armin Schmidtke. 2004. Suicide Prevention In Europe. Technical report, National and Stockholm County Council’s Centre for Suicide Research and Prevention of Mental Ill Health.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>WHO</author>
</authors>
<title>Public health action for the prevention of suicide: a framework. Technical report, World Health Organization.</title>
<date>2012</date>
<contexts>
<context position="1553" citStr="WHO, 2012" startWordPosition="236" endWordPosition="237"> provide societal, environmentally approaches and solutions to tackle these societal challenges. This work pretends to be an exhaustive survey of the different researches in this scope, in order to explain which methodologies, technologies and resources are used in the detection of mental problems by means of the Social Media analysis as well as to re-veal their deficiencies. 1 Introduction In Europe, suicide has become the leading cause of violent death (WHO, 2014). Each year 804.000 people die in the world as a result of suicidal behavior and the number of attempts is about 20 times higher (WHO, 2012; WHO, 2014). It is estimated that in 2020, about 1.53 million people will die as a result of suicidal acts. Preventing suicide is one of the five areas of priority of the European Pact for Mental Health and Well- Being1, which was launched by the European Commission in 2008. Suicide is the third leading cause of violent death among people aged 15 to 44, followed by accidents and homicides (Holmes et al., 2007), and it would be the second reason that would explain the deaths in the group of people aged 15 to 19 years (WHO, 2014). Suicidal behaviors can be defined as a complex process that can </context>
</contexts>
<marker>WHO, 2012</marker>
<rawString>WHO. 2012. Public health action for the prevention of suicide: a framework. Technical report, World Health Organization.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>WHO</author>
</authors>
<title>Preventing suicide: A global imperative.</title>
<date>2014</date>
<tech>Technical report, World Health Organization.</tech>
<contexts>
<context position="1414" citStr="WHO, 2014" startWordPosition="210" endWordPosition="211">le in the early detection of the depression, their causes and their terrible consequences. Based on these considerations, it is mandatory to provide societal, environmentally approaches and solutions to tackle these societal challenges. This work pretends to be an exhaustive survey of the different researches in this scope, in order to explain which methodologies, technologies and resources are used in the detection of mental problems by means of the Social Media analysis as well as to re-veal their deficiencies. 1 Introduction In Europe, suicide has become the leading cause of violent death (WHO, 2014). Each year 804.000 people die in the world as a result of suicidal behavior and the number of attempts is about 20 times higher (WHO, 2012; WHO, 2014). It is estimated that in 2020, about 1.53 million people will die as a result of suicidal acts. Preventing suicide is one of the five areas of priority of the European Pact for Mental Health and Well- Being1, which was launched by the European Commission in 2008. Suicide is the third leading cause of violent death among people aged 15 to 44, followed by accidents and homicides (Holmes et al., 2007), and it would be the second reason that would </context>
</contexts>
<marker>WHO, 2014</marker>
<rawString>WHO. 2014. Preventing suicide: A global imperative. Technical report, World Health Organization.</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>