<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="SectLabel" version="110505">
<variant no="0" confidence="0.000151">
<note confidence="0.937535">
COLING 2014
</note>
<title confidence="0.99831275">
The 25th International Conference
on Computational Linguistics
Proceedings of the Workshop on Open Infrastructures and
Analysis Frameworks for HLT
</title>
<author confidence="0.3908275">
August 23rd, 2014
Dublin, Ireland
</author>
<note confidence="0.918796833333333">
U1, 2014 The Authors
The papers in this volume are licensed by the authors under a
Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.
ISBN 978-1-873769-38-6
Proceedings of the Workshop on Open Infrastructures and Analysis Frameworks for HLT
(OIAF4HLT)
</note>
<author confidence="0.604129">
Nancy Ide and Jens Grivolla (eds.)
</author>
<page confidence="0.636934">
ii
</page>
<note confidence="0.617418">
Preface
</note>
<bodyText confidence="0.994306431818182">
The Workshop on Open Infrastructures and Analysis Frameworks for Human Language Technology
(HLT) provides a forum for discussion of requirements for an envisaged open “global laboratory&amp;quot; for
HLT research and development. Recent advances in digital storage and networking, coupled with the
extension of HLT into ever broader areas and the persistence of difficulties in software portability,
have led to an increased focus on development and deployment of web-based infrastructures that allow
users to access tools and other resources and combine them to create novel solutions that can be
efficiently composed, tuned, evaluated, disseminated and consumed. This in turn engenders collaborative
development and deployment among individuals and teams across the globe. It also increases the need
for robust, widely available evaluation methods and tools, means to achieve interoperability of software
and data from diverse sources, means to handle licensing for limited access resources distributed over
the web, and, perhaps crucially, the need to develop strategies for multi-site collaborative work.
For many decades, NLP has suffered from low software engineering standards, resulting in a limited
degree of re-usability of code and interoperability of different modules within larger NLP systems.
While this did not really hamper success in limited task areas, it caused serious problems for building
complex integrated software systems, e.g., for information extraction or machine translation. This lack of
integration has led to duplicated software development, work-arounds for programs written in different
(versions of) programming languages, and ad-hoc tweaking of interfaces between modules developed at
different sites.
In recent years, several efforts have been devoted to the development of frameworks to to allow the easy
integration of varied tools through common type systems and standardized communication methods
for components analyzing unstructured textual information. These include two frameworks, UIMA
and GATE, which have been widely adopted within the HLT community to facilitate the creation of
reusable HLT components that can be assembled to address different HLT tasks depending on their
order, combination and configuration. At the same time, major projects in the US, EU, and Asia have
recently undertaken the development of web service platforms for HLT, in order to exploit the growing
number of web-based tools and services available for HLT-related tasks including corpus annotation,
configuration and execution of tool pipelines, and evaluation of results and automatic parameter tuning.
These platforms may also integrate modules and pipelines from existing frameworks such as UIMA and
GATE, in order to achieve interoperability with a wide variety of modules from different sources.
Many of the issues and challenges surrounding these developments have been addressed individually in
particular projects and workshops, but there are ramifications that cut across all of them. This workshop
brings together participants representing the range of interests that comprise the comprehensive
picture for community-driven, distributed, collaborative, web-based development and use for language
processing software and resources, including developers of HLT infrastructures as well as those who
will use these services and infrastructures, especially for multi-site collaborative work. The program
includes presentations describing approaches to the range of challenges posed by such development,
including legal issues concerning licensing of components and tools; the technical aspects of packaging
and distribution of components; means to assemble complex processing pipelines and manage large
bodies of data; means to visualize, explore, and further deploy analysis results; and issues surrounding
the preservation of analysis results, provenance documentation, and evaluation and reproducibility. The
overall goal is to work toward eliminating the fragmentation and duplication of effort that currently
characterizes the field by establishing the basis of a community effort to develop and support the global
laboratory for HLT development and research.
iii
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.729195">
Workshop Committee
Program Co-Chairs
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.6039535">
Jens Grivolla, Universitat Pompeu Fabra (Spain)
Nancy Ide, Vassar College (USA)
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.314534">
General Organizers
</subsectionHeader>
<table confidence="0.8973805">
Kalina Bontcheva, University of Sheffield (UK)
Christopher Cieri, Linguistic Data Consortium (USA)
Eric Nyberg, Carnegie Mellon University (USA)
James Pustejovsky, Brandeis University (USA)
Jonathan Wright, Linguistic Data Consortium (USA)
Program Committee:
Al Asswad, Mohammad, Cornell University
Nuria Bel, Universitat Pompeu Fabra
Steven Bethard, University of Alabama at Birmingham
Philipp Cimiano, Universität Bielefeld
Joan Codina, Universitat Pompeu Fabra
Kevin Cohen, University of Colorado School of Medicine
Azad Dehghan, University of Manchester
Leon Derczynski, University of Sheffield
Richard Eckart de Castilho, TU Darmstadt
Nicolai Erbs, TU Darmstadt
Thilo Götz, IBM Deutschland
Mark A. Greenwood, University of Sheffield
Nicolas Hernandez, University of Nantes
Yoshinobu Kano, Japan Science and Technology Agency
Peter Klügl, University of Würzburg
Marie-Jean Meurs, Concordia University
Yohei Murakama, Kyoto University
Kamel Nebhi, University of Geneva
Renaud Richardet, École Polytechnique Fédérale De Lausanne
Carlos Rodríguez-Penagos, Barcelona Media
Horacio Saggion, Universitat Pompeu Fabra
Bahar Sateli, Concordia University
Chunqi Shi, Brandeis University
Keith Suderman, Vassar College
Michael Tanenblatt, Thomas J. Watson Research Center
Martin Toepfer, Universität Würzburg
Katrin Tomanek, VigLink Inc.
Marc Verhagen, Brandeis University
</table>
<affiliation confidence="0.99738275">
Karin Verspoor, University of Melbourne
Graham Wilcock, University of Helsinki
René Witte, Concordia University
Torsten Zesch, University of Duisburg-Essen
</affiliation>
<page confidence="0.956288">
v
</page>
<tableCaption confidence="0.95454">
Table of Contents
</tableCaption>
<figure confidence="0.95891687804878">
A broad-coverage collection ofportable NLP components for building shareable analysis pipelines
Richard Eckart de Castilho and Iryna Gurevych 1
Integrating UIMA with Alveo, a human communication science virtual laboratory
Dominique Estival, Steve Cassidy, Karin Verspoor, Andrew MacKinlay and Denis Burnham ... 12
Towards Model Driven Architectures for Human Language Technologies
Alessandro di Bari, Guido Vetere and Kateryna Tymoshenko 23
The Language Application Grid Web Service Exchange Vocabulary
Nancy Ide, James Pustejovsky, Keith Suderman and Marc Verhagen 34
Significance of Bridging Real-world Documents and NLP Technologies
Tadayoshi Hara, Goran Topic, Yusuke Miyao and Akiko Aizawa 44
A Conceptual Framework of Online Natural Language Processing Pipeline Application
Chunqi Shi, James Pustejovsky and Marc Verhagen 53
Command-line utilities for managing and exploring annotated corpora
Joel Nothman, Tim Dawborn and James R. Curran 60
SSF. A Common Representation Scheme for Language Analysis for Language Technology Infrastructure
Development
Akshar Bharati, Rajeev Sangal, Dipti Misra Sharma and Anil Kumar Singh 66
Quo Vadis UIMA?
Thilo Götz, Jörn Kottmann and Alexander Lang 77
Integrated Tools for Query-driven Development of Light-weight Ontologies and Information Extraction
Components
Martin Toepfer, Georg Fette, Philip-Daniel Beck, Peter Kluegl and Frank Puppe 83
Intellectual Property Rights Management with Web Service Grids
Christopher Cieri and Denise DiPersio 93
EUMSSI. a Platform for Multimodal Analysis and Recommendation using UIMA
Jens Grivolla, Maite Melero, Toni Badia, Cosmin Cabulea, Yannick Estève, Eelco Herder, Jean-
Marc Odobez, Susanne Preuß and Raúl Marín 101
vii
Conference Program
Saturday, August 23, 2014
8:45–9:00 Opening Remarks
9:00–9:30 A broad-coverage collection of portable NLP components for building shareable
analysis pipelines
Richard Eckart de Castilho and Iryna Gurevych
9:30–10:00 Integrating UIMA with Alveo, a human communication science virtual laboratory
Dominique Estival, Steve Cassidy, Karin Verspoor, Andrew MacKinlay and Denis
Burnham
10:00–10:30 Towards Model Driven Architectures for Human Language Technologies
Alessandro di Bari, Guido Vetere and Kateryna Tymoshenko
10:30–11:00 Coffee break
11:00–11:30 The Language Application Grid Web Service Exchange Vocabulary
</figure>
<reference confidence="0.969950115384615">
Nancy Ide, James Pustejovsky, Keith Suderman and Marc Verhagen
11:30–12:00 Significance of Bridging Real-world Documents and NLP Technologies
Tadayoshi Hara, Goran Topic, Yusuke Miyao and Akiko Aizawa
12:00–12:30 A Conceptual Framework of Online Natural Language Processing Pipeline Appli-
cation
Chunqi Shi, James Pustejovsky and Marc Verhagen
12:30–14:00 Lunch
14:00–14:30 Command-line utilities for managing and exploring annotated corpora
Joel Nothman, Tim Dawborn and James R. Curran
14:30–15:00 SSF: A Common Representation Scheme for Language Analysis for Language Tech-
nology Infrastructure Development
Akshar Bharati, Rajeev Sangal, Dipti Misra Sharma and Anil Kumar Singh
15:00–15:30 Coffee break
15:30–16:00 Quo Vadis UIMA?
Thilo Götz, Jörn Kottmann and Alexander Lang
ix
Saturday, August 23, 2014 (continued)
16:00–16:30 Integrated Tools for Query-driven Development of Light-weight Ontologies and Informa-
tion Extraction Components
Martin Toepfer, Georg Fette, Philip-Daniel Beck, Peter Kluegl and Frank Puppe
16:30–17:00 Intellectual Property Rights Management with Web Service Grids
Christopher Cieri and Denise DiPersio
17:00–17:30 EUMSSI: a Platform for Multimodal Analysis and Recommendation using UIMA
Jens Grivolla, Maite Melero, Toni Badia, Cosmin Cabulea, Yannick Estève, Eelco Herder,
Jean-Marc Odobez, Susanne Preuß and Raúl Marín
17:30–18:00 Discussion: How to build a global community
</reference>
<page confidence="0.792611">
x
</page>
</variant>
</algorithm>
<algorithm name="ParsHed" version="110505">
<variant no="0" confidence="0.000000">
<note confidence="0.880705933333333">COLING 2014 The 25th International on Computational Linguistics Proceedings of the Workshop on Open Infrastructures and Analysis Frameworks for HLT August 23rd, Dublin, Ireland 2014 The Authors The papers in this volume are licensed by the authors under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License. ISBN 978-1-873769-38-6 Proceedings of the Workshop on Open Infrastructures and Analysis Frameworks for HLT (OIAF4HLT) Nancy Ide and Jens Grivolla (eds.) ii</note>
<title confidence="0.4775835">Preface The Workshop on Open Infrastructures and Analysis Frameworks for Human Language Technology</title>
<abstract confidence="0.986427906976744">(HLT) provides a forum for discussion of requirements for an envisaged open “global laboratory&amp;quot; for HLT research and development. Recent advances in digital storage and networking, coupled with the extension of HLT into ever broader areas and the persistence of difficulties in software portability, have led to an increased focus on development and deployment of web-based infrastructures that allow users to access tools and other resources and combine them to create novel solutions that can be efficiently composed, tuned, evaluated, disseminated and consumed. This in turn engenders collaborative development and deployment among individuals and teams across the globe. It also increases the need for robust, widely available evaluation methods and tools, means to achieve interoperability of software and data from diverse sources, means to handle licensing for limited access resources distributed over the web, and, perhaps crucially, the need to develop strategies for multi-site collaborative work. For many decades, NLP has suffered from low software engineering standards, resulting in a limited degree of re-usability of code and interoperability of different modules within larger NLP systems. While this did not really hamper success in limited task areas, it caused serious problems for building complex integrated software systems, e.g., for information extraction or machine translation. This lack of integration has led to duplicated software development, work-arounds for programs written in different (versions of) programming languages, and ad-hoc tweaking of interfaces between modules developed at different sites. In recent years, several efforts have been devoted to the development of frameworks to to allow the easy integration of varied tools through common type systems and standardized communication methods for components analyzing unstructured textual information. These include two frameworks, UIMA and GATE, which have been widely adopted within the HLT community to facilitate the creation of reusable HLT components that can be assembled to address different HLT tasks depending on their order, combination and configuration. At the same time, major projects in the US, EU, and Asia have recently undertaken the development of web service platforms for HLT, in order to exploit the growing number of web-based tools and services available for HLT-related tasks including corpus annotation, configuration and execution of tool pipelines, and evaluation of results and automatic parameter tuning. These platforms may also integrate modules and pipelines from existing frameworks such as UIMA and GATE, in order to achieve interoperability with a wide variety of modules from different sources. Many of the issues and challenges surrounding these developments have been addressed individually in particular projects and workshops, but there are ramifications that cut across all of them. This workshop brings together participants representing the range of interests that comprise the comprehensive picture for community-driven, distributed, collaborative, web-based development and use for language processing software and resources, including developers of HLT infrastructures as well as those who will use these services and infrastructures, especially for multi-site collaborative work. The program includes presentations describing approaches to the range of challenges posed by such development, including legal issues concerning licensing of components and tools; the technical aspects of packaging and distribution of components; means to assemble complex processing pipelines and manage large bodies of data; means to visualize, explore, and further deploy analysis results; and issues surrounding the preservation of analysis results, provenance documentation, and evaluation and reproducibility. The overall goal is to work toward eliminating the fragmentation and duplication of effort that currently characterizes the field by establishing the basis of a community effort to develop and support the global laboratory for HLT development and research. iii</abstract>
<title confidence="0.9388515">Workshop Committee Program Co-Chairs</title>
<author confidence="0.948995">Jens Grivolla</author>
<author confidence="0.948995">Universitat Pompeu Fabra</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.860477">Nancy Ide, Vassar College (USA)</affiliation>
<title confidence="0.927752">General Organizers</title>
<author confidence="0.787276">Kalina Bontcheva</author>
<author confidence="0.787276">University of Sheffield</author>
<degree confidence="0.65692515">Christopher Cieri, Linguistic Data Consortium (USA) Eric Nyberg, Carnegie Mellon University (USA) James Pustejovsky, Brandeis University (USA) Jonathan Wright, Linguistic Data Consortium (USA) Program Committee: Al Asswad, Mohammad, Cornell University Nuria Bel, Universitat Pompeu Fabra Steven Bethard, University of Alabama at Birmingham Philipp Cimiano, Universität Bielefeld Joan Codina, Universitat Pompeu Fabra Kevin Cohen, University of Colorado School of Medicine Azad Dehghan, University of Manchester Leon Derczynski, University of Sheffield Richard Eckart de Castilho, TU Darmstadt Nicolai Erbs, TU Darmstadt Thilo Götz, IBM Deutschland Mark A. Greenwood, University of Sheffield Nicolas Hernandez, University of Nantes Yoshinobu Kano, Japan Science and Technology Agency Peter Klügl, University of Würzburg</degree>
<affiliation confidence="0.9798245">Marie-Jean Meurs, Concordia University Yohei Murakama, Kyoto University</affiliation>
<address confidence="0.366071">Kamel Nebhi, University of Geneva</address>
<author confidence="0.819957">Renaud Richardet</author>
<author confidence="0.819957">École Polytechnique Fédérale De_Lausanne Carlos Rodríguez-Penagos</author>
<author confidence="0.819957">Barcelona Media Horacio Saggion</author>
<author confidence="0.819957">Universitat Pompeu Fabra</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.8136421">Bahar Sateli, Concordia University Chunqi Shi, Brandeis University Keith Suderman, Vassar College Michael Tanenblatt, Thomas J. Watson Research Center Martin Toepfer, Universität Würzburg Katrin Tomanek, VigLink Inc. Marc Verhagen, Brandeis University Karin Verspoor, University of Melbourne Graham Wilcock, University of Helsinki René Witte, Concordia University</affiliation>
<author confidence="0.39247">Torsten Zesch</author>
<author confidence="0.39247">University of Duisburg-Essen</author>
<email confidence="0.710773">v</email>
<title confidence="0.975677">Table of Contents A broad-coverage collection ofportable NLP components for building shareable analysis pipelines</title>
<author confidence="0.87524">Eckart de_Castilho</author>
<author confidence="0.87524">Iryna Gurevych</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.88515">Integrating UIMA with Alveo, a human communication science virtual laboratory</affiliation>
<address confidence="0.716514">Estival, Steve Cassidy, Karin Verspoor, Andrew MacKinlay and Denis Burnham ...12</address>
<title confidence="0.996732">Towards Model Driven Architectures for Human Language Technologies</title>
<author confidence="0.977819">Alessandro di_Bari</author>
<author confidence="0.977819">Guido Vetere</author>
<author confidence="0.977819">Kateryna Tymoshenko</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.866576">The Language Application Grid Web Service Exchange Vocabulary</affiliation>
<address confidence="0.839246">Ide, James Pustejovsky, Keith Suderman and Marc Verhagen34</address>
<affiliation confidence="0.849067">Significance of Bridging Real-world Documents and NLP Technologies</affiliation>
<address confidence="0.84639">Hara, Goran Topic, Yusuke Miyao and Akiko Aizawa44</address>
<title confidence="0.680601">A Conceptual Framework of Online Natural Language Processing Pipeline Application</title>
<note confidence="0.897059454545455">Chunqi Shi, James Pustejovsky and Marc Verhagen 53 Command-line utilities for managing and exploring annotated corpora Nothman, Tim Dawborn and James R. Curran60 SSF. A Common Representation Scheme for Language Analysis for Language Technology Infrastructure Development Akshar Bharati, Rajeev Sangal, Dipti Misra Sharma and Anil Kumar Singh 66 Quo Vadis UIMA? Götz, Jörn Kottmann and Alexander Lang77 Integrated Tools for Query-driven Development of Light-weight Ontologies and Information Extraction Components Toepfer, Georg Fette, Philip-Daniel Beck, Peter Kluegl and Frank Puppe83</note>
<title confidence="0.903075">Intellectual Property Rights Management with Web Service Grids</title>
<author confidence="0.89557">Christopher Cieri</author>
<author confidence="0.89557">Denise DiPersio</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.745466">EUMSSI. a Platform for Multimodal Analysis and Recommendation using UIMA Grivolla, Maite Melero, Toni Badia, Cosmin Cabulea, Yannick Estève, Eelco Herder, Jean-</affiliation>
<address confidence="0.855022">Odobez, Susanne Preuß and Raúl Marín101</address>
<email confidence="0.969592">vii</email>
<affiliation confidence="0.95509">Conference Program</affiliation>
<address confidence="0.796099">Saturday, August 23, 2014 8:45–9:00 Opening Remarks</address>
<abstract confidence="0.8652995">9:00–9:30A broad-coverage collection of portable NLP components for building shareable analysis pipelines</abstract>
<author confidence="0.955954">Richard Eckart de_Castilho</author>
<author confidence="0.955954">Iryna Gurevych</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.715014">9:30–10:00Integrating UIMA with Alveo, a human communication science virtual laboratory Dominique Estival, Steve Cassidy, Karin Verspoor, Andrew MacKinlay and Denis Burnham</affiliation>
<title confidence="0.686034">10:00–10:30Towards Model Driven Architectures for Human Language Technologies</title>
<author confidence="0.917447">Alessandro di_Bari</author>
<author confidence="0.917447">Guido Vetere</author>
<author confidence="0.917447">Kateryna Tymoshenko</author>
<address confidence="0.42387">10:30–11:00 Coffee break</address>
<title confidence="0.613767">11:00–11:30The Language Application Grid Web Service Exchange Vocabulary</title>
<author confidence="0.998414">Nancy Ide</author>
<author confidence="0.998414">James Pustejovsky</author>
<author confidence="0.998414">Keith Suderman</author>
<author confidence="0.998414">Marc Verhagen</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.894189">11:30–12:00Significance of Bridging Real-world Documents and NLP Technologies</affiliation>
<address confidence="0.7152965">Tadayoshi Hara, Goran Topic, Yusuke Miyao and Akiko Aizawa 12:00–12:30A Conceptual Framework of Online Natural Language Processing Pipeline Appli-</address>
<email confidence="0.6965">cation</email>
<author confidence="0.970848">Chunqi Shi</author>
<author confidence="0.970848">James Pustejovsky</author>
<author confidence="0.970848">Marc Verhagen</author>
<abstract confidence="0.231711">12:30–14:00 Lunch 14:00–14:30Command-line utilities for managing and exploring annotated corpora</abstract>
<author confidence="0.903555">Joel Nothman</author>
<author confidence="0.903555">Tim Dawborn</author>
<author confidence="0.903555">James R Curran</author>
<title confidence="0.540879">14:30–15:00SSF: A Common Representation Scheme for Language Analysis for Language Technology Infrastructure Development</title>
<author confidence="0.67955">Akshar Bharati</author>
<author confidence="0.67955">Rajeev Sangal</author>
<author confidence="0.67955">Dipti Misra Sharma</author>
<author confidence="0.67955">Anil Kumar Singh</author>
<note confidence="0.765518666666667">15:00–15:30 Coffee break 15:30–16:00Quo Vadis UIMA? Thilo Götz, Jörn Kottmann and Alexander Lang ix Saturday, August 23, 2014 (continued) 16:00–16:30Integrated Tools for Query-driven Development of Light-weight Ontologies and Informa-</note>
<title confidence="0.983507">tion Extraction Components</title>
<author confidence="0.99306">Martin Toepfer</author>
<author confidence="0.99306">Georg Fette</author>
<author confidence="0.99306">Philip-Daniel Beck</author>
<author confidence="0.99306">Peter Kluegl</author>
<author confidence="0.99306">Frank Puppe</author>
<title confidence="0.502262">16:30–17:00Intellectual Property Rights Management with Web Service Grids</title>
<author confidence="0.853546">Christopher Cieri</author>
<author confidence="0.853546">Denise DiPersio</author>
<title confidence="0.459753">17:00–17:30EUMSSI: a Platform for Multimodal Analysis and Recommendation using UIMA</title>
<author confidence="0.964611">Jens Grivolla</author>
<author confidence="0.964611">Maite Melero</author>
<author confidence="0.964611">Toni Badia</author>
<author confidence="0.964611">Cosmin Cabulea</author>
<author confidence="0.964611">Yannick Estève</author>
<author confidence="0.964611">Eelco Herder</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.807406">Jean-Marc Odobez, Susanne Preuß and Raúl Marín</affiliation>
<address confidence="0.592745">17:30–18:00 Discussion: How to build a global community</address>
<intro confidence="0.693214">x</intro>
</variant>
</algorithm>
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>Nancy Ide</author>
<author>James Pustejovsky</author>
</authors>
<title>Keith Suderman and Marc Verhagen 11:30–12:00 Significance of Bridging Real-world Documents and NLP Technologies Tadayoshi Hara, Goran Topic, Yusuke Miyao and Akiko Aizawa</title>
<marker>Ide, Pustejovsky, </marker>
<rawString>Nancy Ide, James Pustejovsky, Keith Suderman and Marc Verhagen 11:30–12:00 Significance of Bridging Real-world Documents and NLP Technologies Tadayoshi Hara, Goran Topic, Yusuke Miyao and Akiko Aizawa</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<booktitle>12:00–12:30 A Conceptual Framework of Online Natural Language Processing Pipeline Application</booktitle>
<marker></marker>
<rawString>12:00–12:30 A Conceptual Framework of Online Natural Language Processing Pipeline Application</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>Chunqi Shi</author>
<author>James Pustejovsky</author>
<author>Marc Verhagen Joel Nothman</author>
<author>Tim Dawborn</author>
<author>R James</author>
</authors>
<publisher>Curran</publisher>
<marker>Shi, Pustejovsky, Nothman, Dawborn, James, </marker>
<rawString>Chunqi Shi, James Pustejovsky and Marc Verhagen Joel Nothman, Tim Dawborn and James R. Curran</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<title>A Common Representation Scheme for Language Analysis for Language Technology Infrastructure Development Akshar Bharati, Rajeev Sangal,</title>
<booktitle>Dipti Misra Sharma and Anil Kumar Singh 15:00–15:30 Coffee break 15:30–16:00 Quo Vadis UIMA? Thilo Götz, Jörn Kottmann and Alexander Lang ix</booktitle>
<marker></marker>
<rawString>14:30–15:00 SSF: A Common Representation Scheme for Language Analysis for Language Technology Infrastructure Development Akshar Bharati, Rajeev Sangal, Dipti Misra Sharma and Anil Kumar Singh 15:00–15:30 Coffee break 15:30–16:00 Quo Vadis UIMA? Thilo Götz, Jörn Kottmann and Alexander Lang ix</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Saturday</author>
</authors>
<title>(continued) 16:00–16:30 Integrated Tools for Query-driven Development of Light-weight Ontologies and Information Extraction Components</title>
<date>2014</date>
<marker>Saturday, 2014</marker>
<rawString>Saturday, August 23, 2014 (continued) 16:00–16:30 Integrated Tools for Query-driven Development of Light-weight Ontologies and Information Extraction Components</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>Martin Toepfer</author>
<author>Georg Fette</author>
<author>Philip-Daniel Beck</author>
</authors>
<title>Peter Kluegl and Frank Puppe 16:30–17:00 Intellectual Property Rights Management with Web Service Grids Christopher Cieri and Denise DiPersio 17:00–17:30 EUMSSI: a Platform for Multimodal Analysis and Recommendation using UIMA Jens Grivolla, Maite Melero, Toni Badia, Cosmin Cabulea, Yannick Estève, Eelco Herder, Jean-Marc Odobez, Susanne Preuß and Raúl Marín 17:30–18:00 Discussion: How to build a global community</title>
<marker>Toepfer, Fette, Beck, </marker>
<rawString>Martin Toepfer, Georg Fette, Philip-Daniel Beck, Peter Kluegl and Frank Puppe 16:30–17:00 Intellectual Property Rights Management with Web Service Grids Christopher Cieri and Denise DiPersio 17:00–17:30 EUMSSI: a Platform for Multimodal Analysis and Recommendation using UIMA Jens Grivolla, Maite Melero, Toni Badia, Cosmin Cabulea, Yannick Estève, Eelco Herder, Jean-Marc Odobez, Susanne Preuß and Raúl Marín 17:30–18:00 Discussion: How to build a global community</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>