<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="SectLabel" version="110505">
<variant no="0" confidence="0.000001">
<title confidence="0.973466">
The Lexicon-Grammar of Italian Idioms
</title>
<author confidence="0.982338">
Simonetta Vietri
</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.77053">
Department of Political,
Social and Communication
</affiliation>
<author confidence="0.294226">
Sciences
</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.930281">
University of Salerno, Italy
</affiliation>
<email confidence="0.997074">
vietri@unisa.it
</email>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.993837" genericHeader="abstract">
Abstract
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999468818181818">
This paper presents the Lexicon-Grammar classification of Italian idioms that has been constructed on
formal principles and, as such, can be exploited in information extraction. Among MWEs, idioms are
those fixed constructions which are hard to automatically detect, given their syntactic flexibility and
lexical variation. The syntactic properties of idioms have been formally represented and coded in bi-
nary matrixes according to the Lexicon-Grammar framework. The research takes into account idioms
with ordinary verbs as well as support verb idiomatic constructions. The overall classification counts
7,000+ Italian idioms. In particular, two binary matrixes of two classes of idioms will be presented.
The class C1 refers to the Verb + Object constructions, whereas the class EPC refers to the preposi-
tional constructions with the support verb essere. Pre-constructed lexical resources facilitate idioms
retrieval both in the case of &amp;quot;hybrid&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;knowledge-based&amp;quot; approaches to Natural Language Pro-
cessing.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.998798" genericHeader="introduction">
1 Introduction
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.97193">
Idioms, and multi-word expressions in general, have always been &amp;quot;a pain in the neck&amp;quot;, as Sag et al.
(2001) state in the title of their paper. The formal representation and the construction of a computa-
tional linguistic model of idioms is not an easy task as shown by Gazdar et al. (1985), Pulman (1993),
Abeillé (1995), Villavicencio et al. (2004), Muzny and Zettlemoyer (2013) to name a few of the many
(computational) linguists who have carried out research on this topic.
It has always been pointed out that the main problem concerning the automatic analysis of idioms
is the difficulty to disambiguate such constructions which are ambiguous by definition (Fothergill and
Baldwin 2012, Li and Sporlender 2009, Fazly et al. 2009, McShane and Nirenburg 2014). However,
given the flexibility of idioms, a more basic and still unsolved problem has to be taken into account:
that is, the extraction and annotation of such constructions (Fellbaum 2011).
As Fazly et al. (2009, p. 61) point out &amp;quot;despite a great deal of research on the properties of idioms in
the linguistics literature, there is not much agreement on which properties are characteristics of these
expressions&amp;quot;. The distinction drawn by Nunberg et al. (1994) between idiomatic phrases and idiomati-
cally combining expressions has been adopted by most of the research on idioms. However, many
problems still remain and they are due to two basic reasons. On one hand, idioms can be considered
lexical units, given the fact that their &amp;quot;special meaning&amp;quot; is associated to a particular verb and one or
more particular complements. On the other hand, idioms syntactically behave as non-idiomatic con-
structions. Passive is the syntactic construction more frequently analyzed by the linguistic research on
idioms since it involves the occurrence of the fixed object to the left of the verb. However, idioms
show a great deal of other syntactic constructions where the fixed object may not necessarily occur in
postverbal position (see Vietri 2014, forthcoming).
It is for these peculiarities that idioms have also aroused the interest of the psycholinguistic re-
searchers who have advanced several hypothesis on the processing of idioms (Swinney and Cutler,
This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International Licence. Page numbers and proceedings footer
are added by the organisers. Licence details: http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.942661">
137
</page>
<note confidence="0.9859905">
Proceedings of the Workshop on Lexical and Grammatical Resources for Language Processing, pages 137–146,
Coling 2014, Dublin, Ireland, August 24 2014.
</note>
<bodyText confidence="0.990719238095238">
1979; Gibbs, 1995; Cacciari and Tabossi, 1988; Cutting and Bock, 1997; Sprenger et al., 2006).
The systematic description of French idiomatic and non-idiomatic constructions has been carried
out by Gross (1982, 1988) and his colleagues (Leclère, 2002) on the basis of the formal principles of
the Lexicon-Grammar methodology, as developed by Gross (1975, 1979). According to Gross, the
basic syntactic unit is not the word but the simple or elementary sentence, and the Lexicon-Grammar
of a language is organized into three main components: free sentences, frozen sentences (or idioms),
support verbs sentences (Gross 1981, 1998). For each component, Gross and his colleagues built ex-
haustive classifications, systematically organized and represented by binary matrixes (named Lexicon-
Grammar tables), where each syntactic and/or distributional property is marked &amp;quot;+&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;-&amp;quot; if accepted
or not by a certain lexical unit. In the Lexicon-Grammar methodology, idiomatic and non-idiomatic
constructions are built according to the same formal principles. The difference between these two
types of constructions mainly concerns the distribution: idioms show a higher level of restricted distri-
bution than non-idioms. The French Lexicon-Grammars are available at http://infolingu.univ-
mlv.fr/english/.
A classification of English idioms and phrasal verbs has been carried out according to the same
formal principles and criteria, respectively, by Freckleton (1985) and Machonis (1985). A Lexicon-
Grammar of European Portuguese idioms has been built by Baptista (2005a, 2005b).
The Lexicon-Grammar classification of Italian idioms has been implemented on the basis of Gross&apos;
methodology. It includes more than 30 Lexicon-Grammar classes of idioms with ordinary verbs (sec.
2) and support verbs (sec. 3), for a total of more than 7,000 lexical entries1. The binary matrixes are
created in Excel format.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.768527" genericHeader="method">
2 The Lexicon-Grammar of Italian Idioms with Ordinary Verbs
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999434181818182">
The Lexicon-Grammar of idioms using ordinary verbs includes 12 classes for a total of 3,990 entries
(sec. 2.1, Table 1). Each class of idioms contains those constructions which share the same definitional
structure. In the Lexicon-Grammar framework, the definitional structure is identified on the basis of
the arguments required by the operators (see Harris 1982). In the case of idioms, the operator consists
of the Verb and the Fixed element(s), while the argument may be the subject and/or a free comple-
ment. This section shows only the main differences between the idioms&apos; classes C1 and CAN.
For example, idioms in (1) and (2) have two different definitional structures. On one hand, an idiom
such as tagliare la corda in (1) is an operator that requires only one argument, i.e. the subject. On the
other hand, an idiom such as rompere le balle in (2) is an operator that requires two arguments, the
subject and the noun Amy within the prepositional complement. The prepositions a and di alternate
and can be considered fixed:
</bodyText>
<listItem confidence="0.9228675">
1. Amy ha tagliato la corda &amp;quot;to sneak off&amp;quot;
Amy-has-cut-the-rope
2. Joe ha rotto le balle (a + di) Amy &amp;quot;to annoy sb.&amp;quot;
Joe-has-broken-the-balls-(to + of)-Amy
</listItem>
<bodyText confidence="0.844723538461538">
Idioms such as (1) have been listed and analyzed in a class named C1, that counts about 1,200 entries.
Furthermore, C indicates the &amp;quot;constrained&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;fixed&amp;quot; noun and 1 refers to its position in the sentence,
in this case, the object position. These idioms have only one argument, that is the (non-fixed noun) in
subject position. The definitional structure of the class C1 is N0 V C1 where N indicates the free noun,
V the verb and C, as previously stated, the fixed element. The subscripts 0 and 1 indicate the position
of the noun within the sentence in a linear order, in this case, the subject and the object position.
Idioms such as (2) have been listed and analyzed in the class named CAN, that counts 320 entries.
The definitional structure of this class is N0 V C1 (a + di) N2, since these idioms have two arguments,
1 Vietri (1984) includes the very first classification of Italian idioms. Since then, the classification has been widely en-
riched, updated and completely re-examined. For a semantic study of Italian idioms, see Casadei (1996). A Lexicon-
Grammar classification of Verb-particle constructions has been developed by Guglielmo (2013). From a different per-
spective, Masini (2005) provides a synchronic and diacronic analysis of Italian verb-particle constructions found in a
corpus.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997109">
138
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.9999557">
i.e. the subject N0 and the noun N2. The alternation of the prepositions a and di is represented between
brackets, and the &amp;quot;+&amp;quot; sign indicates &amp;quot;either/or&amp;quot;.
Each class, formally represented by a table in the form of a binary matrix, contains a specific num-
ber of idiomatic entries associated with a specific number of distributional and syntactic properties. In
particular, each row of the matrix corresponds to an idiom, and each column to a property (or a con-
struction). If the idiom accepts that particular property, a &amp;quot;+&amp;quot; sign is placed at the intersection between
the row and the column; otherwise a &amp;quot;-&amp;quot; sign occurs.
As a sample of this type of lexical resource, I will give an excerpt of the class C1 in Figure 1. The
central non-numbered columns indicate the &amp;quot;part of speech&amp;quot; assigned to each lexical element that con-
stitutes the idiomatic construction. In an idiom like non alzare un dito (lit. not lift a finger), the nega-
tion non is obligatory. On the other hand, the si-pronominal form is obligatory in idioms like leccarsi i
baffi (lit. lick-si the moustaches). The determiner can be Definite (Def), Indefinite (Ind), or null (Zero).
As previously pointed out, V refers to the verb and C to the fixed noun.
The properties from [1] to [3] indicate the distribution of N0, i.e. the subject. It can be expressed by
[± human] noun or a by a sentence [Ch F].
The distributional property [4] indicates if C1 is expressed by a body-part noun, whereas the mor-
phological property [5] indicates if C1 can be in the plural form. Property [4] showed that 1,700+ idi-
oms involve a body-part noun, at least the 24% of the overall classification. Property [5] is a useful
piece of information because it refers to the possible variation of the fixed noun and, consequently, of
the determiner.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.95358975">
Neg Pro V Def Ind Zero C1 [4] 5] 6] 7] [8]
+ - - - - allungare il - - muso + - - - + - - -
+ - - non - alzare - un - dito + - - - - - - + - - - - alzare la - - testa + - - - + - + [11
-
+ - - - - chiudere il - - capitolo - - + + - + - -
+ - - - - dipanare la una - matassa - - + + - + - -
+ - - - - incrociare le - - braccia + - - + + - - -
+ - - - - ingoiare il un - rospo - + - - - + - -
+ - - - si leccare i - - baffi + + -
+ - - - si mangiare il - - fegato + - - - - - - + - - - si mangiare la - - lingua + - - - - - -
[1] N0 = + hum
[2] N0 = - hum
</equation>
<figure confidence="0.9438643">
[3] N0 = Ch F
[4] C1= body-part
[5] C1= plural
[6] Unaccusative DET C1 si V
[7] DET C1 essere (V-PP + Adj)
[8] N0 avere Det C1 (V-PP + Adj)
[9] N0 avere C da V-Inf
[10] Nominal = V-n di (Det+0) C1
[10
[11] VC Compound
</figure>
<equation confidence="0.998673666666667">
+ + + - - mostrare la - - corda
+ - - - - perdere il - + tempo
+ - - - - rizzare gli - - orecchi
+ - - - - rompere il - - ghiaccio
+ - - - - scoprire l&apos; - - acqua calda
+ - - - - scoprire le - - carte
+ - - - - scoprire l&apos; - - America
+ - - - - tappare il un - buco
+ - - - - vendere - - - fumo
</equation>
<figureCaption confidence="0.998529">
Figure 1. The Class C1
</figureCaption>
<listItem confidence="0.638267">
- - - - - - - perditempo
+ +
+ - - + + - - -
- - + + - - - -
+ -
- - - + + + - -
+ -
- + - - - + - tappabuchi
+ vendifumo
</listItem>
<page confidence="0.993664">
139
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.985890666666667">
The syntactic properties are numbered from [6] to [10]. In particular, [6] and [7] refer, respectively, to
the unaccusative (3b) and the adjectival passive (3c) constructs in which some idioms may occur, as in
the following:
</bodyText>
<listItem confidence="0.785637">
3a. Liv ha dipanato la matassa &amp;quot;to solve a problem&amp;quot;
Liv-has-unraveled-the-skein
3b. La matassa si è dipanata
The skein-si-is-unraveled
3c. La matassa è dipanata
The-skein-is-unraveled
</listItem>
<bodyText confidence="0.958079705882353">
Properties [8] and [9] indicate two more sentence structures in which idioms may occur. In particular,
[8] refers to a sentence structure involving the verb avere (&apos;to have&apos;) as in (4b):
4a. Gli operai incrociano le braccia &amp;quot;to go on strike&amp;quot;
The-workers-cross-the-arms
4b. Gli operai hanno le braccia incrociate
The-workers-have-the-arms-crossed
The syntactic property [9] indicates a particular structure where the verb is in the infinitive form and
introduced by the preposition da, as in (5b):
5a. Joe ingoiò un rospo &amp;quot;to swallow a bitter pill&amp;quot;
Joe-swalled-a-toad
5b. Joe ha un rospo da ingoiare
Joe-has-a-toad-to-swallow
Notice that, in the constructions defined by properties [6]-[9], C1 does not occur in its canonical posi-
tion but to the left of the verb.
Property [10] concerns the possibility of having a nominalization, as in (6b). Finally, the morpho-
syntactic property [11] shows the formation of a VC compound, as in (7b). The VC compound is ex-
plicitly indicated in the corresponding column.
</bodyText>
<listItem confidence="0.945705125">
6a. Joe ha alzato la testa &amp;quot;to rebel&amp;quot;
Joe-has-raised-the-head
6b. L&apos;alzata di testa (di + che ha fatto) Joe
The-raising-of-the-head (of + that-has-made)-Joe
7a. Joe vende fumo &amp;quot;to be a snake oil salesman&amp;quot;
Joe-sells-smoke
7b. Joe è un vendifumo
Joe-is-a-sell.smoke
</listItem>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.978389">
2.1 The Classes of Idioms with Ordinary Verbs
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9997751">
Table 1 contains all the classes of idioms with ordinary verbs. The first column indicates the name of
the Lexicon Grammar class, while the second column refers to the definitional structure of the idioms
belonging to the corresponding class. The third column contains an idiomatic example for each class.
Finally, the fourth column refers to the number of idioms listed in each class. The last class of Table 1,
i.e. PVCO, contains those idioms where the fixed verb is followed by a comparative clause introduced
by come2.
The figures in the fourth column are to be taken as an approximate quantity, since this is an ongo-
ing research. Therefore, the classes are subject to updating. Although approximate, the figures are an
important piece of information because they show the idioms&apos; distribution throughout the syntactic
patterns.
</bodyText>
<footnote confidence="0.708698">
2 See also De Gioia (2001).
</footnote>
<page confidence="0.929498">
140
</page>
<table confidence="0.999759285714286">
LG-class Sentence structure Example I.
C0 C0 V S2 il piatto piange 80
C1 N0 V C1 tirare le cuoia 1,200
CAI N0 V C1 (a + di) N2 rompere le scatole (a + di) I 320
CDI N0 V C1 di N2 non vedere l&apos;ora di I 90
CPI N0 V C1 Prep N2 attaccare bottone con I 550
CPC N0 V C1 Prep C2 prendere lucciole per lanterne 450
CPCPI N0 V C1 Prep C2 Prep N3 dire pane al pane a I 20
IPC N0 V N1 Prep C2 piantare I in asso 350
PCPI N0 V Prep C1 Prep N2 dare alla testa a I 100
PC1 N0 V Prep C1 parlare al muro 600
PCPC N0 V Prep C1 Prep C2 durare da Iatale a Santo Stefano 30
PVCO N0 V come C1 fumare come un turco 200
3,990
</table>
<tableCaption confidence="0.999919">
Table 1. Idioms with Ordinary Verbs
</tableCaption>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.957261" genericHeader="method">
3 The Lexicon-Grammar of the Italian Idiomatic Support Verb Constructions
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9979395">
Idioms may be not only formed by an ordinary verb but also by support verbs, the most common of
which are, in Italian, avere (&apos;to have&apos;), essere (&apos;to be&apos;), fare (&apos;to make&apos;). The main difference between
support verbs (hereafter SV) and ordinary verbs constructions is linked to their meaning. That is, sup-
port verbs are semantically empty, while ordinary verbs are not. Therefore, support verbs are not pred-
icates.
The idiomatic constructions formed by such verbs show a high degree of lexical and syntactic flex-
ibility due to the semantic &amp;quot;emptiness&amp;quot; of the support verb. Such a flexibility of SV idioms is shown
by (a) the alternation of support verbs with aspectual variants, (b) the production of causative con-
structions, (c) the deletion of the support verb itself that can trigger the formation of complex nominal
groups and adverbials.
The Lexicon-Grammar of SV idioms (sec. 3.1, Table 2) includes 16 classes for a total of about
3,300 entries. I will present one of the classes defined by the general structure I0 essere Prep C S2,
where it is the prepositional complement that is fixed and necessary to sub-categorize a possible fur-
ther argument S2, as in the following3:
</bodyText>
<listItem confidence="0.653524">
8. Ielly è al settimo cielo &amp;quot;to be in seventh heaven&amp;quot;
Nelly-is-at-the-seventh-sky
9. Joe è ai ferri corti con Ielly &amp;quot;to be at loggerheads with sb.&amp;quot;
Joe-is-at-the-short-irons-with-Nelly
</listItem>
<bodyText confidence="0.8386715">
In example (8), the fixed prepositional complement PC does not require a further argument besides the
subject, whereas a free prepositional complement PI is required in the case of (9). Therefore, idioms
like (8) and (9) have been listed in two different classes, respectively, EPC and EPCPI, where E in-
dicates the verb essere (&apos;to be&apos;), P the preposition, C indicates the constrained noun, and I the free
noun. Figure 2 is an excerpt of the class EPC which includes 500+ entries.
3 The Lexicon-grammar of the French être Prep constructions has been built by Danlos (1988). The Portuguese con-
structions were analyzed by Ranchod (1983). A first classification of the Italian essere Prep constructions has been built
by Vietri (1996). This early classification has been completely revised.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.989783">
141
</page>
<figure confidence="0.991337066666667">
[1] N0 = + hum
[2] N0 = - hum
[3] N0 = Che F
[4] C1 = body-part
[5] Vsup = Stare
[6] Vsup = Restare-Rimanere
[7] Vsup = Diventare
[8] Vmt = Andare
[9] Vcaus = Mandare
[10] Vcaus = Mettere
[11] Vcaus = Ridurre
[12] Vop = Avere
[9]
[1
[1
</figure>
<table confidence="0.948433">
V Prep Prep-Det C1
+ + - essere in - ballo - + + - - - + - -
+ - - essere in - bestia - + + - + + - - -
- + - essere sotto - chiave - + + - - - + - -
+ - - essere - sulla corda - + + - - - + - -
+ - - essere - alle corde - + + - - - + - -
- + - essere - al dente + - + - - - - - -
+ - - essere in - erba [4]
- - + + - - - - -
+ + - essere - con i fiocchi - - + + - - - - -
+ - - essere - fuori dai gangheri - + + - + + - - -
+ - - essere - sul lastrico - + + - + + + + -
+ + + essere fuori - luogo - - + - - - - - -
+ - - essere fuori - mano + + + - - - - - -
+ + - essere a - nudo - - + - - - + - -
+ + - essere sott&apos; - occhio + + + - - - - - +
- + - essere - alle porte - + + - - - - - -
+ - - essere - sulle spine - + + - - - + - -
+ - - essere - al tappeto - + + - + + + - -
- + - essere - sul tappeto - + + - - - + - -[1
+ - - essere in - gamba + - + + - - - - -
+ - - essere
</table>
<figureCaption confidence="0.999866">
Figure 2. The class EPC
</figureCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.997124857142857">
The distributional properties [1]-[4] have been previously illustrated (sec. 2, Figure 1). The properties
from [5] to [8] indicate the possibility for the EPC constructions to occur with verbs other than essere.
The verbs considered are stare4, in [5], restare and rimanere (&apos;remain&apos;), in [6], diventare (&apos;become,
get&apos;) in [7]. The property [8] indicates that a construction with the verb of motion andare (&apos;to go&apos;) may
be acceptable.
However, the acceptability of all these constructions is lexically dependant, as in the following ex-
amples:
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.820945">
10. Nelly (sta+ resta + *diventa + va) al settimo cielo &amp;quot;to be in seventh heaven&amp;quot;
Nelly-(stays + remains + *becomes + goes)-at-the-seventh-sky
11. Joe (*sta + resta + diventa + *va) in gamba &amp;quot;to be smart&amp;quot;
Joe-(*stays + remains + becomes + *goes)-in-leg
EPC constructions can also enter complex sentence structures with causative verbs (see properties [9]-
-[10]) such as mandare (&apos;send&apos;), mettere (&apos;to put&apos;), ridurre (&apos;make&apos;), as in the following:
</figure>
<footnote confidence="0.855365">
4 I will literally translate this verb as &amp;quot;to stay&amp;quot;. However, there is no equivalent in English since this verb is to be found
in Romance languages like Italian, Portuguese and Spanish.
</footnote>
<note confidence="0.248509">
- al verde - + + - - - + + -
</note>
<page confidence="0.805037">
142
</page>
<figure confidence="0.99382075">
12. Joe (mandò + *mise + *ridusse) Ielly al settimo cielo &amp;quot;to be in seventh heaven&amp;quot;
Joe-(sent + *put + *reduced)-Nelly-at-the-seventh-sky
13. Joe (mandò + mise + ridusse) Ielly sul lastrico &amp;quot;to be on the skids&amp;quot;
Joe-(sent + put + reduced)-Nelly-on-the-pavement
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.663290833333333">
Finally, property [12] indicates that the link operator (see Gross 1981) avere (&apos;to have&apos;) may produce
an acceptable sentence, as in (14b):
14a. La situazione in Ukraina è sott&apos;occhio &amp;quot;to monitor N&amp;quot;
The-situation-in-Ukraine-is-under-eye
14b. Obama ha sott&apos;occhio la situazione in Ukraina
Obama-has-under-eye-the-situation-in-Ukraine
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.999079">
3.1 The Classes of Idioms with Support Verbs
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999348">
Table 2 lists only those classes of SV idioms containing at least 50 idiomatic entries5. As a general
rule, the classes of idioms with the verb essere start with E, those ones with the verb avere start
with A, and finally, those classes involving the verb fare start with F. The only exception is the
class PECO which refers to the idioms of comparison where the verb essere is followed by a
clause introduced by come6.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.999769636363636">
LG class Sentence structure Example N.
EPC N0 essere Prep C1 essere sulle spine 530
EPCModif N0 essere Prep Adj C1 essere di vecchio stampo 130
N0 essere Prep C1 Adj essere in mani sicure
EPCPN N0 essere Prep C1 Prep N2 essere all&apos;oscuro di I 140
essere ai ferri corti con I
EPCPC N0 essere Prep (C Prep C)1 essere nelle mani di Dio 115
essere al passo con i tempi
EAPC N0 essere Adj Prep C1 non essere dolce di sale 100
PECO N0 essere Adj come C1 essere sordo come una campana 360
AC N avere C1 avere polso, avere (buon) occhio 80
ACA N avere C1 Adj avere la memoria corta 400
ACXC N0 avere C1 Prep C2 avere i nervi a fior di pelle 180
&lt;=&gt; C1 di N1 essere Prep C2 &lt;=&gt; i nervi di I sono a fior di pelle
ACPN N0 avere C1 Prep N2 non avere la testa di I 50
ACPC N0 avere C1 Prep C2 avere il cervello tra le nuvole 200
FC N0 fare C1 fare melina, fare lo gnorri 300
FCPN N0 fare C1 Prep N2 fare le bucce a, fare man bassa di I 300
FCDC N0 fare (C di C)1 fare l&apos;arte dei pazzi 80
FCPC N0 fare C1 Prep C2 fare un buco nell&apos; acqua 220
FPC(PN) N0 fare Prep C1 (E + Prep N2) fare sul serio, farsi in quattro per I 50
Total 3,235
</table>
<tableCaption confidence="0.99995">
Table 2. Idioms with Support Verbs
</tableCaption>
<footnote confidence="0.486308">
5 See Vietri (2014, forthcoming) for the complete classification.
6 For the French classification of idiomatic comparisons see Gross (1984).
</footnote>
<page confidence="0.998648">
143
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.911457" genericHeader="evaluation">
4 Annotating and Parsing Idioms
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9999086875">
The Lexicon-Grammar classes of idioms can be exploited by the hybrid as well as the symbolic ap-
proach to Natural Language Processing. Some experimentation in this direction has already been car-
ried out by Machonis (2011), who used NooJ to retrieve and disambiguate English phrasal verbs. NooJ
is an NLP application developed by Silberztein (2003) that relies heavily on linguistic resources.
NooJ has been used to carry out experimentation on some of the Lexicon-Grammar classes of Ital-
ian idioms. The experimentation, still in progress, concerns the annotation and parsing of idioms. This
application allows the construction of lexicons/dictionaries whose entries contain information such as
the distributional and syntactic properties indicated in the Lexicon-Grammar classes. The Lexicon-
Grammar classes of idioms can be converted in a NooJ dictionary of idioms. This dictionary, which
contains thousands of entries, has to be linked to a grammar that describes the syntactic behaviour of
idioms. By applying to a text such a dictionary/grammar pair, NooJ successfully annotates and parses
idioms, also in case the constituents Verb + Fixed element(s) are discontinuous. An example of this is
the sentence John ha vuotato subito il sacco (lit. John-has-immediately-emptied-the bag, &amp;quot;to spill the
beans&amp;quot;), where the underlined adverb occurs between the verb and the fixed object.
However, the current NooJ version does not yet handle easily the syntactic flexibility and the lexi-
cal variation of idioms 7.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.999299" genericHeader="conclusions">
5 Conclusion
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99998025">
The Lexicon-Grammar classes of idioms are a manually-built linguistic resource that provides infor-
mation about variation and flexibility of idioms. These classes, being formally coded, constitute an
invaluable linguistic resource that can be used for research in (psycho)linguistics, and computational
linguistics. The overall classification, as illustrated in Tables 1 and 2, outlines the syntactic patterns of
the idiomatic constructions. This is a piece of information that can be regarded as the syntactic map of
Italian idioms8. Furthermore, the lexico-syntactic information provided by the idioms&apos; classes can also
integrate the automatic Machine Translation evaluation methods9.
The Lexicon-Grammar classes of idioms can be exploited by the hybrid as well as the symbolic ap-
proach to Natural Language Processing. Some experimentation in this direction has already been car-
ried out by Machonis (2011) and by Vietri (2014, forthcoming). Both authors used the knowledge-
based system NooJ. On the other hand, Baptista et al. (2014) used the Lexicon-Grammar classes of
Portuguese idioms to test the hybrid system STRING.
Further experimentation will be conducted to evaluate the benefit of using the LG distributional
and syntactic information in order to extract idioms from corpora. However, very huge corpora (con-
sisting of documents in an informal language style) are needed, together with powerful tools able to
perform complex searches on massive textual data.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.99861" genericHeader="references">
References
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.999076909090909">
Anne Abeillé. 1995. The Flexibility of French Idioms: a Representation with Lexicalized Tree Adjoining
Grammar. In M. Everaert, E-J. van der Linden, A. Schenk, &amp; R. Schreuder (Eds.), Idioms: structural and
psychological perspectives. Hillsdale, NJ: Lawrence Erlbaum Associates: 15-41.
Jorge Baptista, Anabela Correia, and Graça Fernandes. 2005a. Léxico Gramática das Frases Fixas do
Portugués Europeo», Cadernos de Fraseoloxía Galega, 7: 41-53.
Jorge Baptista, Anabela Correia, and Graça Fernandes. 2005b. Frozen Sentences of Portuguese: Formal De-
scriptions for NLP. Proceedings of the ACL workshop on Multiword Expressions: 72-79.
Jorge Baptista, Nuno Mamede, and Ilia Markov. 2014. Integrating a lexicon-grammar of verbal idioms in a
Portuguese NLP system. COST Action IC1207 PARSEME meeting, 10-11 March 2014.
Cristina Cacciari, and Patrizia Tabossi. 1988. The comprehension of idioms. Journal of Memory and Lan-
guage, 27: 668–683.
</reference>
<footnote confidence="0.9074365">
7 Cignoni and Coffey (1998) provides the corpus-based results of the lexical variations of idioms.
8 The complete Lexicon-Grammar classification of Italian idioms will be available at
.unisa.it/docenti/simonettavietri/index.
9 In this regard, see Giménez and Márquez (2010), Costa-jussà and Farrús (2013).
</footnote>
<page confidence="0.994619">
144
</page>
<reference confidence="0.998929416666667">
Federica Casadei. 1996. Metafore ed espsressioni idiomatiche. Uno studio semantico sull&apos;italiano. Roma:
Bulzoni.
Laura Cignoni, and Stephen Coffey. 1998. A corpus-based study of Italian idiomstic phrases: from citation
forms to &apos;real-life&apos; occurrences. Euralex 1998 Proceedings: 291-300.
Marta Ruiz Costa-jussà, and Mireia Farrús. 2013. Towards human linguistic machine translation evaluation.
Literary and Linguistic Computing, Online publication date: 6-Dec-2013.
Cooper Cutting, and Kathryn Bock. 1997. That’s the way the cookie bounces: Syntactic and semantic com-
ponents of experimentally elicited idiom blends. Memory and Cognition, 25:57–71.
Laurence Danlos. 1988. Les phrases à verbe support être Prép. Langages, vol. 23, n. 90: 23-37.
Michele De Gioia. 2001. Avverbi idiomatici dell’italiano. Analisi lessico-grammaticale. Torino:
L’Harmattan Italia.
Elisabete Ranchod. 1983. On the support verbs ser and estar in Portuguese. Lingvisticae Investigationes,
VII(2): 317-353.
Afsaneh Fazly, Paul Cook, and Susanne Stevenson, S. (2009). Unsupervised Type and Token Identification
of Idiomatic Expressions. Computational Linguistics, Vol. 35(1): 62-103.
Christiane Fellbaum. 2011. Idioms and Collocations. In C. Maienborn, K. von Heusinger, &amp; P. Portner
(Eds.), Semantics. An International Handbook of Natural Language Meaning. Vol. 1, Berlin/Boston: De
Gruyter Mouton: 441-456.
Richard Fothergill, and Timothy Baldwin. 2012. Combining resources for MWE-token classification. In
Proceedings of the First Joint Conference on Lexical and Computational Semantics: 100-104.
Peter Freckleton. 1985. Sentence idioms in English. Working Papers in Linguistics 11, University of Mel-
bourne: 153-168.
Gerald Gazdar, Ewan Klein, Geoffrey Pullum, and Ivan Sag. 1985. Generalized Phrase Structure Grammar,
Oxford: Basil Blackwell.
Raymond Gibbs. 1995. Idiomaticity and Human Cognition. In M. Everaert, E-J. van der Linden, A. Schenk,
&amp; R. Schreuder (Eds.), Idioms: structural and psychological perspectives. Hillsdale, NJ: Lawrence Erl-
baum Associates: 97-116.
Jesùs Giménez, and Lluìs Màrquez. 2010. Linguistic mesures for automatic machine translation evaluation.
Machine Translation, 24:209-240.
Maurice Gross. 1975. Mèthodes en syntaxe. Paris: Hermann.
Maurice Gross. 1979. On the failure of generative grammar. Language, 55(4): 859-885.
Maurice Gross. 1981. Les bases empiriques de la notion de prédicat semantique. Langages, 63, Paris: La-
rousse: 7-52.
Maurice Gross. 1982. Une classification des phrases &amp;quot;figées&amp;quot; du français. Revue Québécoise de Linguistique
11.2, Montréal: UQAM: 151-185.
Maurice Gross. 1984. Une famille d’adverbes figés: les constructions comparative en comme. Revue
Québécoise de Linguistique 13.2:237-269
Maurice Gross. 1988. Les limites de la phrase figée. Langages 90, Paris: Larousse: 7-22.
Maurice Gross. 1998. La fonction sémantique des verbes supports. Travaux de linguistique, 37, Duculot:
Louvain-la-Neuve: 25-46.
Daniela Guglielmo. 2013. Italian Verb-Adverbial Particle Constructions: Predicative Structures and Patterns
of Variation. Linguisticae Investigationes, 36.2:229-243.
Zellig Harris. 1982. A Grammar of English on Mathematical Principles, New York: John Winsley and Sons.
Christian Leclère. 2002. Organization of the Lexicon-Grammar of French verbs. Lingvisticæ Investigationes
XX(1): 29-48.
Linlin Li, and Caroline Sporleder. 2009. Classifier Combination for Contextual Idiom Detection Without
Labelled Data. Proceedings of the Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing
(EMNLP 2009) Singapore: 315-323.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.986481">
145
</page>
<reference confidence="0.99982071875">
Peter Machonis. 1985. Transformations of verb phrase idioms: passivization, particle movement, dative
shift. American Speech 60(4): 291-308.
Peter Machonis. 2011. Sorting Nooj out to take MWE&apos;s into account. In K. Vučković, B. Bekavac, &amp; M.
Silberztein (Eds.), Automatic Processing of Various Levels of Linguistic Phenomena. Newcastle upon
Tyne: Cambridge Scholars Publishing: 152-165.
Francesca Masini. 2005. Multi-word Expressions between Syntax and the Lexicon: the Case of Italian Verb-
particle Constructions.SKY Journal of Linguistics 18, pp. 145-173.
Marjorie McShane, and Sergei Nirenburg. 2014. The Idiom-reference Connection. STEP &apos;08 Proceedings of
the 2008 Conference on Semantics in Text Processing, ACL Stroudsburg, PA, USA: 165-177.
Grace Muzny, and Luke Zettlemoyer. 2013. Automatic Idiom Identification in Wiktionary. Proceedings of
the Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural language Processing (EMNLP 2013), Seattle, Wash-
ington, USA: 1417-1421.
Geoffrey Nunberg, Ivan Sag, and Tom Wasow. 1994. Idioms. Language, Vol. 70, No. 3, 491-538.
Stephen Pulman. 1993. The recognition and Interpretation of idioms, Cacciari C. &amp; Tabossi, P. (Eds.), Idi-
oms. Processing, Structure, and Interpretation. New Jersey: Lawrence Erlbaum Associates: 249-270.
Ivan Sag, Timothy Baldwin, Francis Bond, Ann Copestake, and Dan Flickinger. 2001. Multiword Expres-
sions: A Pain in the Neck for NLP. Computational Linguistics and Intelligent Text Processing. Berlin
Heidelberg: Springer: 1-15.
Max Silberztein. 2003-. NooJ Manual. Available for download at: www.nooj4nlp.net.
Simone Sprenger, Willem Levelt, and Gerard Kempen. 2006. Lexical Access during the Production of Idio-
matic Phrases. Journal of Memory and Language, 54: 161-184.
David Swinney, and Ann Cutler. 1979. The access and processing of idiomatic expressions. Journal of Ver-
bal Learning and Verbal Behavior, 18: 523–534
Simonetta Vietri. 1984. Lessico e sintassi delle espressioni idiomatiche. Una tipologia tassonomica in ita-
liano e in inglese. Napoli: Liguori.
Simonetta Vietri. 1996. The Syntax of the Italian verb &apos;essere Prep&apos;, Lingvisticae Investigationes, XX.2: 287-
350.
Simonetta Vietri. 2014. Idiomatic Constructions in Italian. A Lexicon-Grammar Approach. Linguisticae
Investigationes Supplementa, 31. Amsterdam &amp; Philadelphia: John Benjamins (forthcoming).
Aline Villavicencio, Timothy Baldwin, T., and Benjamin Waldron. 2004. A Multilingual Database of idi-
oms. Proceedings of the Fourth International Conference on language Resources and Evaluation (LREC
2004), Lisbon, Portugal: 1127-30.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.99882">
146
</page>
</variant>
</algorithm>
<algorithm name="ParsHed" version="110505">
<variant no="0" confidence="0.651340">
<title confidence="0.999753">The Lexicon-Grammar of Italian Idioms</title>
<author confidence="0.992324">Simonetta</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.993006">Department of Social and University of Salerno, Italy</affiliation>
<email confidence="0.994829">vietri@unisa.it</email>
<abstract confidence="0.9723725">This paper presents the Lexicon-Grammar classification of Italian idioms that has been constructed on formal principles and, as such, can be exploited in information extraction. Among MWEs, idioms are those fixed constructions which are hard to automatically detect, given their syntactic flexibility and lexical variation. The syntactic properties of idioms have been formally represented and coded in binary matrixes according to the Lexicon-Grammar framework. The research takes into account idioms with ordinary verbs as well as support verb idiomatic constructions. The overall classification counts 7,000+ Italian idioms. In particular, two binary matrixes of two classes of idioms will be presented. class to the Verb + Object constructions, whereas the class to the preposiconstructions with the support verb Pre-constructed lexical resources facilitate idioms retrieval both in the case of &amp;quot;hybrid&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;knowledge-based&amp;quot; approaches to Natural Language Processing.</abstract>
</variant>
</algorithm>
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Anne Abeillé</author>
</authors>
<title>The Flexibility of French Idioms: a Representation with Lexicalized Tree Adjoining Grammar. In</title>
<date>1995</date>
<pages>15--41</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="1514" citStr="Abeillé (1995)" startWordPosition="222" endWordPosition="223">e Verb + Object constructions, whereas the class EPC refers to the prepositional constructions with the support verb essere. Pre-constructed lexical resources facilitate idioms retrieval both in the case of &amp;quot;hybrid&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;knowledge-based&amp;quot; approaches to Natural Language Processing. 1 Introduction Idioms, and multi-word expressions in general, have always been &amp;quot;a pain in the neck&amp;quot;, as Sag et al. (2001) state in the title of their paper. The formal representation and the construction of a computational linguistic model of idioms is not an easy task as shown by Gazdar et al. (1985), Pulman (1993), Abeillé (1995), Villavicencio et al. (2004), Muzny and Zettlemoyer (2013) to name a few of the many (computational) linguists who have carried out research on this topic. It has always been pointed out that the main problem concerning the automatic analysis of idioms is the difficulty to disambiguate such constructions which are ambiguous by definition (Fothergill and Baldwin 2012, Li and Sporlender 2009, Fazly et al. 2009, McShane and Nirenburg 2014). However, given the flexibility of idioms, a more basic and still unsolved problem has to be taken into account: that is, the extraction and annotation of suc</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Abeillé, 1995</marker>
<rawString>Anne Abeillé. 1995. The Flexibility of French Idioms: a Representation with Lexicalized Tree Adjoining Grammar. In M. Everaert, E-J. van der Linden, A. Schenk, &amp; R. Schreuder (Eds.), Idioms: structural and psychological perspectives. Hillsdale, NJ: Lawrence Erlbaum Associates: 15-41.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>Jorge Baptista</author>
</authors>
<title>Anabela Correia, and Graça Fernandes.</title>
<booktitle>2005a. Léxico Gramática das Frases Fixas do Portugués Europeo», Cadernos de Fraseoloxía Galega,</booktitle>
<volume>7</volume>
<pages>41--53</pages>
<marker>Baptista, </marker>
<rawString>Jorge Baptista, Anabela Correia, and Graça Fernandes. 2005a. Léxico Gramática das Frases Fixas do Portugués Europeo», Cadernos de Fraseoloxía Galega, 7: 41-53.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Jorge Baptista</author>
<author>Anabela Correia</author>
<author>Graça Fernandes</author>
</authors>
<title>Frozen Sentences of Portuguese: Formal Descriptions for NLP.</title>
<date>2005</date>
<booktitle>Proceedings of the ACL workshop on Multiword Expressions:</booktitle>
<pages>72--79</pages>
<marker>Baptista, Correia, Fernandes, 2005</marker>
<rawString>Jorge Baptista, Anabela Correia, and Graça Fernandes. 2005b. Frozen Sentences of Portuguese: Formal Descriptions for NLP. Proceedings of the ACL workshop on Multiword Expressions: 72-79.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Jorge Baptista</author>
<author>Nuno Mamede</author>
<author>Ilia Markov</author>
</authors>
<title>Integrating a lexicon-grammar of verbal idioms</title>
<date>2014</date>
<booktitle>in a Portuguese NLP system. COST Action IC1207 PARSEME meeting,</booktitle>
<pages>10--11</pages>
<marker>Baptista, Mamede, Markov, 2014</marker>
<rawString>Jorge Baptista, Nuno Mamede, and Ilia Markov. 2014. Integrating a lexicon-grammar of verbal idioms in a Portuguese NLP system. COST Action IC1207 PARSEME meeting, 10-11 March 2014.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Cristina Cacciari</author>
<author>Patrizia Tabossi</author>
</authors>
<title>The comprehension of idioms.</title>
<date>1988</date>
<journal>Journal of Memory and Language,</journal>
<volume>27</volume>
<pages>668--683</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="3819" citStr="Cacciari and Tabossi, 1988" startWordPosition="572" endWordPosition="575">14, forthcoming). It is for these peculiarities that idioms have also aroused the interest of the psycholinguistic researchers who have advanced several hypothesis on the processing of idioms (Swinney and Cutler, This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International Licence. Page numbers and proceedings footer are added by the organisers. Licence details: http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/. 137 Proceedings of the Workshop on Lexical and Grammatical Resources for Language Processing, pages 137–146, Coling 2014, Dublin, Ireland, August 24 2014. 1979; Gibbs, 1995; Cacciari and Tabossi, 1988; Cutting and Bock, 1997; Sprenger et al., 2006). The systematic description of French idiomatic and non-idiomatic constructions has been carried out by Gross (1982, 1988) and his colleagues (Leclère, 2002) on the basis of the formal principles of the Lexicon-Grammar methodology, as developed by Gross (1975, 1979). According to Gross, the basic syntactic unit is not the word but the simple or elementary sentence, and the Lexicon-Grammar of a language is organized into three main components: free sentences, frozen sentences (or idioms), support verbs sentences (Gross 1981, 1998). For each compo</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Cacciari, Tabossi, 1988</marker>
<rawString>Cristina Cacciari, and Patrizia Tabossi. 1988. The comprehension of idioms. Journal of Memory and Language, 27: 668–683.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Federica Casadei</author>
</authors>
<title>Metafore ed espsressioni idiomatiche. Uno studio semantico sull&apos;italiano.</title>
<date>1996</date>
<location>Roma: Bulzoni.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="7964" citStr="Casadei (1996)" startWordPosition="1233" endWordPosition="1234">s previously stated, the fixed element. The subscripts 0 and 1 indicate the position of the noun within the sentence in a linear order, in this case, the subject and the object position. Idioms such as (2) have been listed and analyzed in the class named CAN, that counts 320 entries. The definitional structure of this class is N0 V C1 (a + di) N2, since these idioms have two arguments, 1 Vietri (1984) includes the very first classification of Italian idioms. Since then, the classification has been widely enriched, updated and completely re-examined. For a semantic study of Italian idioms, see Casadei (1996). A LexiconGrammar classification of Verb-particle constructions has been developed by Guglielmo (2013). From a different perspective, Masini (2005) provides a synchronic and diacronic analysis of Italian verb-particle constructions found in a corpus. 138 i.e. the subject N0 and the noun N2. The alternation of the prepositions a and di is represented between brackets, and the &amp;quot;+&amp;quot; sign indicates &amp;quot;either/or&amp;quot;. Each class, formally represented by a table in the form of a binary matrix, contains a specific number of idiomatic entries associated with a specific number of distributional and syntactic</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Casadei, 1996</marker>
<rawString>Federica Casadei. 1996. Metafore ed espsressioni idiomatiche. Uno studio semantico sull&apos;italiano. Roma: Bulzoni.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Laura Cignoni</author>
<author>Stephen Coffey</author>
</authors>
<title>A corpus-based study of Italian idiomstic phrases: from citation forms to &apos;real-life&apos; occurrences. Euralex</title>
<date>1998</date>
<booktitle>Proceedings:</booktitle>
<pages>291--300</pages>
<marker>Cignoni, Coffey, 1998</marker>
<rawString>Laura Cignoni, and Stephen Coffey. 1998. A corpus-based study of Italian idiomstic phrases: from citation forms to &apos;real-life&apos; occurrences. Euralex 1998 Proceedings: 291-300.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Marta Ruiz Costa-jussà</author>
<author>Mireia Farrús</author>
</authors>
<title>Towards human linguistic machine translation evaluation. Literary and Linguistic Computing, Online publication date:</title>
<date>2013</date>
<pages>6--2013</pages>
<marker>Costa-jussà, Farrús, 2013</marker>
<rawString>Marta Ruiz Costa-jussà, and Mireia Farrús. 2013. Towards human linguistic machine translation evaluation. Literary and Linguistic Computing, Online publication date: 6-Dec-2013.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Cooper Cutting</author>
<author>Kathryn Bock</author>
</authors>
<title>That’s the way the cookie bounces: Syntactic and semantic components of experimentally elicited idiom blends.</title>
<date>1997</date>
<booktitle>Memory and Cognition, 25:57–71. Laurence Danlos. 1988. Les phrases à verbe support être Prép. Langages,</booktitle>
<volume>23</volume>
<pages>23--37</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="3843" citStr="Cutting and Bock, 1997" startWordPosition="576" endWordPosition="579">these peculiarities that idioms have also aroused the interest of the psycholinguistic researchers who have advanced several hypothesis on the processing of idioms (Swinney and Cutler, This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International Licence. Page numbers and proceedings footer are added by the organisers. Licence details: http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/. 137 Proceedings of the Workshop on Lexical and Grammatical Resources for Language Processing, pages 137–146, Coling 2014, Dublin, Ireland, August 24 2014. 1979; Gibbs, 1995; Cacciari and Tabossi, 1988; Cutting and Bock, 1997; Sprenger et al., 2006). The systematic description of French idiomatic and non-idiomatic constructions has been carried out by Gross (1982, 1988) and his colleagues (Leclère, 2002) on the basis of the formal principles of the Lexicon-Grammar methodology, as developed by Gross (1975, 1979). According to Gross, the basic syntactic unit is not the word but the simple or elementary sentence, and the Lexicon-Grammar of a language is organized into three main components: free sentences, frozen sentences (or idioms), support verbs sentences (Gross 1981, 1998). For each component, Gross and his coll</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Cutting, Bock, 1997</marker>
<rawString>Cooper Cutting, and Kathryn Bock. 1997. That’s the way the cookie bounces: Syntactic and semantic components of experimentally elicited idiom blends. Memory and Cognition, 25:57–71. Laurence Danlos. 1988. Les phrases à verbe support être Prép. Langages, vol. 23, n. 90: 23-37.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Michele De Gioia</author>
</authors>
<title>Avverbi idiomatici dell’italiano. Analisi lessico-grammaticale.</title>
<date>2001</date>
<location>Torino: L’Harmattan Italia.</location>
<marker>De Gioia, 2001</marker>
<rawString>Michele De Gioia. 2001. Avverbi idiomatici dell’italiano. Analisi lessico-grammaticale. Torino: L’Harmattan Italia.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Elisabete Ranchod</author>
</authors>
<title>On the support verbs ser and estar in Portuguese. Lingvisticae Investigationes,</title>
<date>1983</date>
<volume>2</volume>
<pages>317--353</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="16523" citStr="Ranchod (1983)" startWordPosition="2867" endWordPosition="2868">fixed prepositional complement PC does not require a further argument besides the subject, whereas a free prepositional complement PI is required in the case of (9). Therefore, idioms like (8) and (9) have been listed in two different classes, respectively, EPC and EPCPI, where E indicates the verb essere (&apos;to be&apos;), P the preposition, C indicates the constrained noun, and I the free noun. Figure 2 is an excerpt of the class EPC which includes 500+ entries. 3 The Lexicon-grammar of the French être Prep constructions has been built by Danlos (1988). The Portuguese constructions were analyzed by Ranchod (1983). A first classification of the Italian essere Prep constructions has been built by Vietri (1996). This early classification has been completely revised. 141 [1] N0 = + hum [2] N0 = - hum [3] N0 = Che F [4] C1 = body-part [5] Vsup = Stare [6] Vsup = Restare-Rimanere [7] Vsup = Diventare [8] Vmt = Andare [9] Vcaus = Mandare [10] Vcaus = Mettere [11] Vcaus = Ridurre [12] Vop = Avere [9] [1 [1 V Prep Prep-Det C1 + + - essere in - ballo - + + - - - + - - + - - essere in - bestia - + + - + + - - - - + - essere sotto - chiave - + + - - - + - - + - - essere - sulla corda - + + - - - + - - + - - esser</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Ranchod, 1983</marker>
<rawString>Elisabete Ranchod. 1983. On the support verbs ser and estar in Portuguese. Lingvisticae Investigationes, VII(2): 317-353.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Afsaneh Fazly</author>
<author>Paul Cook</author>
<author>Susanne Stevenson</author>
<author>S</author>
</authors>
<title>Unsupervised Type and Token Identification of Idiomatic Expressions.</title>
<date>2009</date>
<journal>Computational Linguistics,</journal>
<volume>35</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<pages>62--103</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="1926" citStr="Fazly et al. 2009" startWordPosition="285" endWordPosition="288">in the title of their paper. The formal representation and the construction of a computational linguistic model of idioms is not an easy task as shown by Gazdar et al. (1985), Pulman (1993), Abeillé (1995), Villavicencio et al. (2004), Muzny and Zettlemoyer (2013) to name a few of the many (computational) linguists who have carried out research on this topic. It has always been pointed out that the main problem concerning the automatic analysis of idioms is the difficulty to disambiguate such constructions which are ambiguous by definition (Fothergill and Baldwin 2012, Li and Sporlender 2009, Fazly et al. 2009, McShane and Nirenburg 2014). However, given the flexibility of idioms, a more basic and still unsolved problem has to be taken into account: that is, the extraction and annotation of such constructions (Fellbaum 2011). As Fazly et al. (2009, p. 61) point out &amp;quot;despite a great deal of research on the properties of idioms in the linguistics literature, there is not much agreement on which properties are characteristics of these expressions&amp;quot;. The distinction drawn by Nunberg et al. (1994) between idiomatic phrases and idiomatically combining expressions has been adopted by most of the research o</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Fazly, Cook, Stevenson, S, 2009</marker>
<rawString>Afsaneh Fazly, Paul Cook, and Susanne Stevenson, S. (2009). Unsupervised Type and Token Identification of Idiomatic Expressions. Computational Linguistics, Vol. 35(1): 62-103.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Christiane Fellbaum</author>
</authors>
<title>Idioms and Collocations. In</title>
<date>2011</date>
<journal>International Handbook of Natural Language Meaning.</journal>
<volume>1</volume>
<pages>441--456</pages>
<publisher>Semantics. An</publisher>
<location>Berlin/Boston: De Gruyter Mouton:</location>
<contexts>
<context position="2145" citStr="Fellbaum 2011" startWordPosition="321" endWordPosition="322">t al. (2004), Muzny and Zettlemoyer (2013) to name a few of the many (computational) linguists who have carried out research on this topic. It has always been pointed out that the main problem concerning the automatic analysis of idioms is the difficulty to disambiguate such constructions which are ambiguous by definition (Fothergill and Baldwin 2012, Li and Sporlender 2009, Fazly et al. 2009, McShane and Nirenburg 2014). However, given the flexibility of idioms, a more basic and still unsolved problem has to be taken into account: that is, the extraction and annotation of such constructions (Fellbaum 2011). As Fazly et al. (2009, p. 61) point out &amp;quot;despite a great deal of research on the properties of idioms in the linguistics literature, there is not much agreement on which properties are characteristics of these expressions&amp;quot;. The distinction drawn by Nunberg et al. (1994) between idiomatic phrases and idiomatically combining expressions has been adopted by most of the research on idioms. However, many problems still remain and they are due to two basic reasons. On one hand, idioms can be considered lexical units, given the fact that their &amp;quot;special meaning&amp;quot; is associated to a particular verb an</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Fellbaum, 2011</marker>
<rawString>Christiane Fellbaum. 2011. Idioms and Collocations. In C. Maienborn, K. von Heusinger, &amp; P. Portner (Eds.), Semantics. An International Handbook of Natural Language Meaning. Vol. 1, Berlin/Boston: De Gruyter Mouton: 441-456.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Richard Fothergill</author>
<author>Timothy Baldwin</author>
</authors>
<title>Combining resources for MWE-token classification.</title>
<date>2012</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the First Joint Conference on Lexical and Computational Semantics:</booktitle>
<pages>100--104</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="1883" citStr="Fothergill and Baldwin 2012" startWordPosition="277" endWordPosition="280">een &amp;quot;a pain in the neck&amp;quot;, as Sag et al. (2001) state in the title of their paper. The formal representation and the construction of a computational linguistic model of idioms is not an easy task as shown by Gazdar et al. (1985), Pulman (1993), Abeillé (1995), Villavicencio et al. (2004), Muzny and Zettlemoyer (2013) to name a few of the many (computational) linguists who have carried out research on this topic. It has always been pointed out that the main problem concerning the automatic analysis of idioms is the difficulty to disambiguate such constructions which are ambiguous by definition (Fothergill and Baldwin 2012, Li and Sporlender 2009, Fazly et al. 2009, McShane and Nirenburg 2014). However, given the flexibility of idioms, a more basic and still unsolved problem has to be taken into account: that is, the extraction and annotation of such constructions (Fellbaum 2011). As Fazly et al. (2009, p. 61) point out &amp;quot;despite a great deal of research on the properties of idioms in the linguistics literature, there is not much agreement on which properties are characteristics of these expressions&amp;quot;. The distinction drawn by Nunberg et al. (1994) between idiomatic phrases and idiomatically combining expressions</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Fothergill, Baldwin, 2012</marker>
<rawString>Richard Fothergill, and Timothy Baldwin. 2012. Combining resources for MWE-token classification. In Proceedings of the First Joint Conference on Lexical and Computational Semantics: 100-104.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Peter Freckleton</author>
</authors>
<title>Sentence idioms in English. Working Papers in Linguistics 11,</title>
<date>1985</date>
<pages>153--168</pages>
<institution>University of Melbourne:</institution>
<contexts>
<context position="5229" citStr="Freckleton (1985)" startWordPosition="775" endWordPosition="776">ional property is marked &amp;quot;+&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;-&amp;quot; if accepted or not by a certain lexical unit. In the Lexicon-Grammar methodology, idiomatic and non-idiomatic constructions are built according to the same formal principles. The difference between these two types of constructions mainly concerns the distribution: idioms show a higher level of restricted distribution than non-idioms. The French Lexicon-Grammars are available at http://infolingu.univmlv.fr/english/. A classification of English idioms and phrasal verbs has been carried out according to the same formal principles and criteria, respectively, by Freckleton (1985) and Machonis (1985). A LexiconGrammar of European Portuguese idioms has been built by Baptista (2005a, 2005b). The Lexicon-Grammar classification of Italian idioms has been implemented on the basis of Gross&apos; methodology. It includes more than 30 Lexicon-Grammar classes of idioms with ordinary verbs (sec. 2) and support verbs (sec. 3), for a total of more than 7,000 lexical entries1. The binary matrixes are created in Excel format. 2 The Lexicon-Grammar of Italian Idioms with Ordinary Verbs The Lexicon-Grammar of idioms using ordinary verbs includes 12 classes for a total of 3,990 entries (sec</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Freckleton, 1985</marker>
<rawString>Peter Freckleton. 1985. Sentence idioms in English. Working Papers in Linguistics 11, University of Melbourne: 153-168.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Gerald Gazdar</author>
<author>Ewan Klein</author>
<author>Geoffrey Pullum</author>
<author>Ivan Sag</author>
</authors>
<date>1985</date>
<booktitle>Generalized Phrase Structure Grammar,</booktitle>
<publisher>Basil Blackwell.</publisher>
<location>Oxford:</location>
<contexts>
<context position="1483" citStr="Gazdar et al. (1985)" startWordPosition="216" endWordPosition="219"> presented. The class C1 refers to the Verb + Object constructions, whereas the class EPC refers to the prepositional constructions with the support verb essere. Pre-constructed lexical resources facilitate idioms retrieval both in the case of &amp;quot;hybrid&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;knowledge-based&amp;quot; approaches to Natural Language Processing. 1 Introduction Idioms, and multi-word expressions in general, have always been &amp;quot;a pain in the neck&amp;quot;, as Sag et al. (2001) state in the title of their paper. The formal representation and the construction of a computational linguistic model of idioms is not an easy task as shown by Gazdar et al. (1985), Pulman (1993), Abeillé (1995), Villavicencio et al. (2004), Muzny and Zettlemoyer (2013) to name a few of the many (computational) linguists who have carried out research on this topic. It has always been pointed out that the main problem concerning the automatic analysis of idioms is the difficulty to disambiguate such constructions which are ambiguous by definition (Fothergill and Baldwin 2012, Li and Sporlender 2009, Fazly et al. 2009, McShane and Nirenburg 2014). However, given the flexibility of idioms, a more basic and still unsolved problem has to be taken into account: that is, the e</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Gazdar, Klein, Pullum, Sag, 1985</marker>
<rawString>Gerald Gazdar, Ewan Klein, Geoffrey Pullum, and Ivan Sag. 1985. Generalized Phrase Structure Grammar, Oxford: Basil Blackwell.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Raymond Gibbs</author>
</authors>
<title>Idiomaticity and Human Cognition. In</title>
<date>1995</date>
<pages>97--116</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="3791" citStr="Gibbs, 1995" startWordPosition="570" endWordPosition="571">see Vietri 2014, forthcoming). It is for these peculiarities that idioms have also aroused the interest of the psycholinguistic researchers who have advanced several hypothesis on the processing of idioms (Swinney and Cutler, This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International Licence. Page numbers and proceedings footer are added by the organisers. Licence details: http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/. 137 Proceedings of the Workshop on Lexical and Grammatical Resources for Language Processing, pages 137–146, Coling 2014, Dublin, Ireland, August 24 2014. 1979; Gibbs, 1995; Cacciari and Tabossi, 1988; Cutting and Bock, 1997; Sprenger et al., 2006). The systematic description of French idiomatic and non-idiomatic constructions has been carried out by Gross (1982, 1988) and his colleagues (Leclère, 2002) on the basis of the formal principles of the Lexicon-Grammar methodology, as developed by Gross (1975, 1979). According to Gross, the basic syntactic unit is not the word but the simple or elementary sentence, and the Lexicon-Grammar of a language is organized into three main components: free sentences, frozen sentences (or idioms), support verbs sentences (Gross</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Gibbs, 1995</marker>
<rawString>Raymond Gibbs. 1995. Idiomaticity and Human Cognition. In M. Everaert, E-J. van der Linden, A. Schenk, &amp; R. Schreuder (Eds.), Idioms: structural and psychological perspectives. Hillsdale, NJ: Lawrence Erlbaum Associates: 97-116.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Jesùs Giménez</author>
<author>Lluìs Màrquez</author>
</authors>
<title>Linguistic mesures for automatic machine translation evaluation.</title>
<date>2010</date>
<journal>Machine Translation,</journal>
<pages>24--209</pages>
<marker>Giménez, Màrquez, 2010</marker>
<rawString>Jesùs Giménez, and Lluìs Màrquez. 2010. Linguistic mesures for automatic machine translation evaluation. Machine Translation, 24:209-240.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Maurice Gross</author>
</authors>
<title>Mèthodes en syntaxe.</title>
<date>1975</date>
<journal>Language,</journal>
<volume>55</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<pages>859--885</pages>
<location>Paris: Hermann. Maurice Gross.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="4127" citStr="Gross (1975" startWordPosition="620" endWordPosition="621">ings footer are added by the organisers. Licence details: http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/. 137 Proceedings of the Workshop on Lexical and Grammatical Resources for Language Processing, pages 137–146, Coling 2014, Dublin, Ireland, August 24 2014. 1979; Gibbs, 1995; Cacciari and Tabossi, 1988; Cutting and Bock, 1997; Sprenger et al., 2006). The systematic description of French idiomatic and non-idiomatic constructions has been carried out by Gross (1982, 1988) and his colleagues (Leclère, 2002) on the basis of the formal principles of the Lexicon-Grammar methodology, as developed by Gross (1975, 1979). According to Gross, the basic syntactic unit is not the word but the simple or elementary sentence, and the Lexicon-Grammar of a language is organized into three main components: free sentences, frozen sentences (or idioms), support verbs sentences (Gross 1981, 1998). For each component, Gross and his colleagues built exhaustive classifications, systematically organized and represented by binary matrixes (named LexiconGrammar tables), where each syntactic and/or distributional property is marked &amp;quot;+&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;-&amp;quot; if accepted or not by a certain lexical unit. In the Lexicon-Grammar methodolog</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Gross, 1975</marker>
<rawString>Maurice Gross. 1975. Mèthodes en syntaxe. Paris: Hermann. Maurice Gross. 1979. On the failure of generative grammar. Language, 55(4): 859-885.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Maurice Gross</author>
</authors>
<title>Les bases empiriques de la notion de prédicat semantique.</title>
<date>1981</date>
<journal>Langages,</journal>
<volume>63</volume>
<pages>7--52</pages>
<location>Paris: Larousse:</location>
<contexts>
<context position="4396" citStr="Gross 1981" startWordPosition="661" endWordPosition="662"> 1995; Cacciari and Tabossi, 1988; Cutting and Bock, 1997; Sprenger et al., 2006). The systematic description of French idiomatic and non-idiomatic constructions has been carried out by Gross (1982, 1988) and his colleagues (Leclère, 2002) on the basis of the formal principles of the Lexicon-Grammar methodology, as developed by Gross (1975, 1979). According to Gross, the basic syntactic unit is not the word but the simple or elementary sentence, and the Lexicon-Grammar of a language is organized into three main components: free sentences, frozen sentences (or idioms), support verbs sentences (Gross 1981, 1998). For each component, Gross and his colleagues built exhaustive classifications, systematically organized and represented by binary matrixes (named LexiconGrammar tables), where each syntactic and/or distributional property is marked &amp;quot;+&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;-&amp;quot; if accepted or not by a certain lexical unit. In the Lexicon-Grammar methodology, idiomatic and non-idiomatic constructions are built according to the same formal principles. The difference between these two types of constructions mainly concerns the distribution: idioms show a higher level of restricted distribution than non-idioms. The French L</context>
<context position="19364" citStr="Gross 1981" startWordPosition="3517" endWordPosition="3518"> mettere (&apos;to put&apos;), ridurre (&apos;make&apos;), as in the following: 4 I will literally translate this verb as &amp;quot;to stay&amp;quot;. However, there is no equivalent in English since this verb is to be found in Romance languages like Italian, Portuguese and Spanish. - al verde - + + - - - + + - 142 12. Joe (mandò + *mise + *ridusse) Ielly al settimo cielo &amp;quot;to be in seventh heaven&amp;quot; Joe-(sent + *put + *reduced)-Nelly-at-the-seventh-sky 13. Joe (mandò + mise + ridusse) Ielly sul lastrico &amp;quot;to be on the skids&amp;quot; Joe-(sent + put + reduced)-Nelly-on-the-pavement Finally, property [12] indicates that the link operator (see Gross 1981) avere (&apos;to have&apos;) may produce an acceptable sentence, as in (14b): 14a. La situazione in Ukraina è sott&apos;occhio &amp;quot;to monitor N&amp;quot; The-situation-in-Ukraine-is-under-eye 14b. Obama ha sott&apos;occhio la situazione in Ukraina Obama-has-under-eye-the-situation-in-Ukraine 3.1 The Classes of Idioms with Support Verbs Table 2 lists only those classes of SV idioms containing at least 50 idiomatic entries5. As a general rule, the classes of idioms with the verb essere start with E, those ones with the verb avere start with A, and finally, those classes involving the verb fare start with F. The only exception </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Gross, 1981</marker>
<rawString>Maurice Gross. 1981. Les bases empiriques de la notion de prédicat semantique. Langages, 63, Paris: Larousse: 7-52.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Maurice Gross</author>
</authors>
<title>Une classification des phrases &amp;quot;figées&amp;quot; du français.</title>
<date>1982</date>
<booktitle>Revue Québécoise de Linguistique 11.2,</booktitle>
<pages>151--185</pages>
<location>Montréal: UQAM:</location>
<contexts>
<context position="3983" citStr="Gross (1982" startWordPosition="598" endWordPosition="599">ng of idioms (Swinney and Cutler, This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International Licence. Page numbers and proceedings footer are added by the organisers. Licence details: http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/. 137 Proceedings of the Workshop on Lexical and Grammatical Resources for Language Processing, pages 137–146, Coling 2014, Dublin, Ireland, August 24 2014. 1979; Gibbs, 1995; Cacciari and Tabossi, 1988; Cutting and Bock, 1997; Sprenger et al., 2006). The systematic description of French idiomatic and non-idiomatic constructions has been carried out by Gross (1982, 1988) and his colleagues (Leclère, 2002) on the basis of the formal principles of the Lexicon-Grammar methodology, as developed by Gross (1975, 1979). According to Gross, the basic syntactic unit is not the word but the simple or elementary sentence, and the Lexicon-Grammar of a language is organized into three main components: free sentences, frozen sentences (or idioms), support verbs sentences (Gross 1981, 1998). For each component, Gross and his colleagues built exhaustive classifications, systematically organized and represented by binary matrixes (named LexiconGrammar tables), where ea</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Gross, 1982</marker>
<rawString>Maurice Gross. 1982. Une classification des phrases &amp;quot;figées&amp;quot; du français. Revue Québécoise de Linguistique 11.2, Montréal: UQAM: 151-185.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Maurice Gross</author>
</authors>
<title>Une famille d’adverbes figés: les constructions comparative en comme. Revue Québécoise de Linguistique 13.2:237-269 Maurice Gross.</title>
<date>1984</date>
<pages>7--22</pages>
<location>Paris: Larousse:</location>
<contexts>
<context position="21384" citStr="Gross (1984)" startWordPosition="3900" endWordPosition="3901">sono a fior di pelle ACPN N0 avere C1 Prep N2 non avere la testa di I 50 ACPC N0 avere C1 Prep C2 avere il cervello tra le nuvole 200 FC N0 fare C1 fare melina, fare lo gnorri 300 FCPN N0 fare C1 Prep N2 fare le bucce a, fare man bassa di I 300 FCDC N0 fare (C di C)1 fare l&apos;arte dei pazzi 80 FCPC N0 fare C1 Prep C2 fare un buco nell&apos; acqua 220 FPC(PN) N0 fare Prep C1 (E + Prep N2) fare sul serio, farsi in quattro per I 50 Total 3,235 Table 2. Idioms with Support Verbs 5 See Vietri (2014, forthcoming) for the complete classification. 6 For the French classification of idiomatic comparisons see Gross (1984). 143 4 Annotating and Parsing Idioms The Lexicon-Grammar classes of idioms can be exploited by the hybrid as well as the symbolic approach to Natural Language Processing. Some experimentation in this direction has already been carried out by Machonis (2011), who used NooJ to retrieve and disambiguate English phrasal verbs. NooJ is an NLP application developed by Silberztein (2003) that relies heavily on linguistic resources. NooJ has been used to carry out experimentation on some of the Lexicon-Grammar classes of Italian idioms. The experimentation, still in progress, concerns the annotation </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Gross, 1984</marker>
<rawString>Maurice Gross. 1984. Une famille d’adverbes figés: les constructions comparative en comme. Revue Québécoise de Linguistique 13.2:237-269 Maurice Gross. 1988. Les limites de la phrase figée. Langages 90, Paris: Larousse: 7-22.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Maurice Gross</author>
</authors>
<title>La fonction sémantique des verbes supports. Travaux de linguistique, 37, Duculot: Louvain-la-Neuve:</title>
<date>1998</date>
<pages>25--46</pages>
<marker>Gross, 1998</marker>
<rawString>Maurice Gross. 1998. La fonction sémantique des verbes supports. Travaux de linguistique, 37, Duculot: Louvain-la-Neuve: 25-46.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Daniela Guglielmo</author>
</authors>
<title>Italian Verb-Adverbial Particle Constructions: Predicative Structures and Patterns of Variation. Linguisticae Investigationes,</title>
<date>2013</date>
<pages>36--2</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="8067" citStr="Guglielmo (2013)" startWordPosition="1246" endWordPosition="1247">in the sentence in a linear order, in this case, the subject and the object position. Idioms such as (2) have been listed and analyzed in the class named CAN, that counts 320 entries. The definitional structure of this class is N0 V C1 (a + di) N2, since these idioms have two arguments, 1 Vietri (1984) includes the very first classification of Italian idioms. Since then, the classification has been widely enriched, updated and completely re-examined. For a semantic study of Italian idioms, see Casadei (1996). A LexiconGrammar classification of Verb-particle constructions has been developed by Guglielmo (2013). From a different perspective, Masini (2005) provides a synchronic and diacronic analysis of Italian verb-particle constructions found in a corpus. 138 i.e. the subject N0 and the noun N2. The alternation of the prepositions a and di is represented between brackets, and the &amp;quot;+&amp;quot; sign indicates &amp;quot;either/or&amp;quot;. Each class, formally represented by a table in the form of a binary matrix, contains a specific number of idiomatic entries associated with a specific number of distributional and syntactic properties. In particular, each row of the matrix corresponds to an idiom, and each column to a proper</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Guglielmo, 2013</marker>
<rawString>Daniela Guglielmo. 2013. Italian Verb-Adverbial Particle Constructions: Predicative Structures and Patterns of Variation. Linguisticae Investigationes, 36.2:229-243.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Zellig Harris</author>
</authors>
<title>A Grammar of</title>
<date>1982</date>
<booktitle>English on Mathematical Principles,</booktitle>
<publisher>John Winsley and Sons.</publisher>
<location>New York:</location>
<contexts>
<context position="6089" citStr="Harris 1982" startWordPosition="907" endWordPosition="908">exicon-Grammar classes of idioms with ordinary verbs (sec. 2) and support verbs (sec. 3), for a total of more than 7,000 lexical entries1. The binary matrixes are created in Excel format. 2 The Lexicon-Grammar of Italian Idioms with Ordinary Verbs The Lexicon-Grammar of idioms using ordinary verbs includes 12 classes for a total of 3,990 entries (sec. 2.1, Table 1). Each class of idioms contains those constructions which share the same definitional structure. In the Lexicon-Grammar framework, the definitional structure is identified on the basis of the arguments required by the operators (see Harris 1982). In the case of idioms, the operator consists of the Verb and the Fixed element(s), while the argument may be the subject and/or a free complement. This section shows only the main differences between the idioms&apos; classes C1 and CAN. For example, idioms in (1) and (2) have two different definitional structures. On one hand, an idiom such as tagliare la corda in (1) is an operator that requires only one argument, i.e. the subject. On the other hand, an idiom such as rompere le balle in (2) is an operator that requires two arguments, the subject and the noun Amy within the prepositional compleme</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Harris, 1982</marker>
<rawString>Zellig Harris. 1982. A Grammar of English on Mathematical Principles, New York: John Winsley and Sons.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Christian Leclère</author>
</authors>
<title>Organization of the Lexicon-Grammar of French verbs.</title>
<date>2002</date>
<booktitle>Lingvisticæ Investigationes XX(1):</booktitle>
<pages>29--48</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="4025" citStr="Leclère, 2002" startWordPosition="604" endWordPosition="605">work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International Licence. Page numbers and proceedings footer are added by the organisers. Licence details: http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/. 137 Proceedings of the Workshop on Lexical and Grammatical Resources for Language Processing, pages 137–146, Coling 2014, Dublin, Ireland, August 24 2014. 1979; Gibbs, 1995; Cacciari and Tabossi, 1988; Cutting and Bock, 1997; Sprenger et al., 2006). The systematic description of French idiomatic and non-idiomatic constructions has been carried out by Gross (1982, 1988) and his colleagues (Leclère, 2002) on the basis of the formal principles of the Lexicon-Grammar methodology, as developed by Gross (1975, 1979). According to Gross, the basic syntactic unit is not the word but the simple or elementary sentence, and the Lexicon-Grammar of a language is organized into three main components: free sentences, frozen sentences (or idioms), support verbs sentences (Gross 1981, 1998). For each component, Gross and his colleagues built exhaustive classifications, systematically organized and represented by binary matrixes (named LexiconGrammar tables), where each syntactic and/or distributional propert</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Leclère, 2002</marker>
<rawString>Christian Leclère. 2002. Organization of the Lexicon-Grammar of French verbs. Lingvisticæ Investigationes XX(1): 29-48.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Linlin Li</author>
<author>Caroline Sporleder</author>
</authors>
<title>Classifier Combination for Contextual Idiom Detection Without Labelled Data.</title>
<date>2009</date>
<booktitle>Proceedings of the Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing (EMNLP 2009) Singapore:</booktitle>
<pages>315--323</pages>
<marker>Li, Sporleder, 2009</marker>
<rawString>Linlin Li, and Caroline Sporleder. 2009. Classifier Combination for Contextual Idiom Detection Without Labelled Data. Proceedings of the Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing (EMNLP 2009) Singapore: 315-323.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Peter Machonis</author>
</authors>
<title>Transformations of verb phrase idioms: passivization, particle movement, dative shift.</title>
<date>1985</date>
<journal>American Speech</journal>
<volume>60</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<pages>291--308</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="5249" citStr="Machonis (1985)" startWordPosition="778" endWordPosition="779">ed &amp;quot;+&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;-&amp;quot; if accepted or not by a certain lexical unit. In the Lexicon-Grammar methodology, idiomatic and non-idiomatic constructions are built according to the same formal principles. The difference between these two types of constructions mainly concerns the distribution: idioms show a higher level of restricted distribution than non-idioms. The French Lexicon-Grammars are available at http://infolingu.univmlv.fr/english/. A classification of English idioms and phrasal verbs has been carried out according to the same formal principles and criteria, respectively, by Freckleton (1985) and Machonis (1985). A LexiconGrammar of European Portuguese idioms has been built by Baptista (2005a, 2005b). The Lexicon-Grammar classification of Italian idioms has been implemented on the basis of Gross&apos; methodology. It includes more than 30 Lexicon-Grammar classes of idioms with ordinary verbs (sec. 2) and support verbs (sec. 3), for a total of more than 7,000 lexical entries1. The binary matrixes are created in Excel format. 2 The Lexicon-Grammar of Italian Idioms with Ordinary Verbs The Lexicon-Grammar of idioms using ordinary verbs includes 12 classes for a total of 3,990 entries (sec. 2.1, Table 1). Eac</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Machonis, 1985</marker>
<rawString>Peter Machonis. 1985. Transformations of verb phrase idioms: passivization, particle movement, dative shift. American Speech 60(4): 291-308.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Peter Machonis</author>
</authors>
<title>Sorting Nooj out to take MWE&apos;s into account. In</title>
<date>2011</date>
<pages>152--165</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="21642" citStr="Machonis (2011)" startWordPosition="3942" endWordPosition="3943">re (C di C)1 fare l&apos;arte dei pazzi 80 FCPC N0 fare C1 Prep C2 fare un buco nell&apos; acqua 220 FPC(PN) N0 fare Prep C1 (E + Prep N2) fare sul serio, farsi in quattro per I 50 Total 3,235 Table 2. Idioms with Support Verbs 5 See Vietri (2014, forthcoming) for the complete classification. 6 For the French classification of idiomatic comparisons see Gross (1984). 143 4 Annotating and Parsing Idioms The Lexicon-Grammar classes of idioms can be exploited by the hybrid as well as the symbolic approach to Natural Language Processing. Some experimentation in this direction has already been carried out by Machonis (2011), who used NooJ to retrieve and disambiguate English phrasal verbs. NooJ is an NLP application developed by Silberztein (2003) that relies heavily on linguistic resources. NooJ has been used to carry out experimentation on some of the Lexicon-Grammar classes of Italian idioms. The experimentation, still in progress, concerns the annotation and parsing of idioms. This application allows the construction of lexicons/dictionaries whose entries contain information such as the distributional and syntactic properties indicated in the Lexicon-Grammar classes. The LexiconGrammar classes of idioms can </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Machonis, 2011</marker>
<rawString>Peter Machonis. 2011. Sorting Nooj out to take MWE&apos;s into account. In K. Vučković, B. Bekavac, &amp; M. Silberztein (Eds.), Automatic Processing of Various Levels of Linguistic Phenomena. Newcastle upon Tyne: Cambridge Scholars Publishing: 152-165.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Francesca Masini</author>
</authors>
<title>Multi-word Expressions between Syntax and the Lexicon: the Case of Italian Verbparticle</title>
<date>2005</date>
<journal>Constructions.SKY Journal of Linguistics</journal>
<volume>18</volume>
<pages>145--173</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="8112" citStr="Masini (2005)" startWordPosition="1253" endWordPosition="1254"> the subject and the object position. Idioms such as (2) have been listed and analyzed in the class named CAN, that counts 320 entries. The definitional structure of this class is N0 V C1 (a + di) N2, since these idioms have two arguments, 1 Vietri (1984) includes the very first classification of Italian idioms. Since then, the classification has been widely enriched, updated and completely re-examined. For a semantic study of Italian idioms, see Casadei (1996). A LexiconGrammar classification of Verb-particle constructions has been developed by Guglielmo (2013). From a different perspective, Masini (2005) provides a synchronic and diacronic analysis of Italian verb-particle constructions found in a corpus. 138 i.e. the subject N0 and the noun N2. The alternation of the prepositions a and di is represented between brackets, and the &amp;quot;+&amp;quot; sign indicates &amp;quot;either/or&amp;quot;. Each class, formally represented by a table in the form of a binary matrix, contains a specific number of idiomatic entries associated with a specific number of distributional and syntactic properties. In particular, each row of the matrix corresponds to an idiom, and each column to a property (or a construction). If the idiom accepts </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Masini, 2005</marker>
<rawString>Francesca Masini. 2005. Multi-word Expressions between Syntax and the Lexicon: the Case of Italian Verbparticle Constructions.SKY Journal of Linguistics 18, pp. 145-173.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Marjorie McShane</author>
<author>Sergei Nirenburg</author>
</authors>
<title>The Idiom-reference Connection.</title>
<date>2014</date>
<booktitle>STEP &apos;08 Proceedings of the 2008 Conference on Semantics in Text Processing, ACL</booktitle>
<pages>165--177</pages>
<location>Stroudsburg, PA, USA:</location>
<contexts>
<context position="1955" citStr="McShane and Nirenburg 2014" startWordPosition="289" endWordPosition="292">ir paper. The formal representation and the construction of a computational linguistic model of idioms is not an easy task as shown by Gazdar et al. (1985), Pulman (1993), Abeillé (1995), Villavicencio et al. (2004), Muzny and Zettlemoyer (2013) to name a few of the many (computational) linguists who have carried out research on this topic. It has always been pointed out that the main problem concerning the automatic analysis of idioms is the difficulty to disambiguate such constructions which are ambiguous by definition (Fothergill and Baldwin 2012, Li and Sporlender 2009, Fazly et al. 2009, McShane and Nirenburg 2014). However, given the flexibility of idioms, a more basic and still unsolved problem has to be taken into account: that is, the extraction and annotation of such constructions (Fellbaum 2011). As Fazly et al. (2009, p. 61) point out &amp;quot;despite a great deal of research on the properties of idioms in the linguistics literature, there is not much agreement on which properties are characteristics of these expressions&amp;quot;. The distinction drawn by Nunberg et al. (1994) between idiomatic phrases and idiomatically combining expressions has been adopted by most of the research on idioms. However, many probl</context>
</contexts>
<marker>McShane, Nirenburg, 2014</marker>
<rawString>Marjorie McShane, and Sergei Nirenburg. 2014. The Idiom-reference Connection. STEP &apos;08 Proceedings of the 2008 Conference on Semantics in Text Processing, ACL Stroudsburg, PA, USA: 165-177.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Grace Muzny</author>
<author>Luke Zettlemoyer</author>
</authors>
<title>Automatic Idiom Identification in Wiktionary.</title>
<date>2013</date>
<journal>Idioms. Language,</journal>
<booktitle>Proceedings of the Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural language Processing (EMNLP 2013),</booktitle>
<volume>70</volume>
<pages>1417--1421</pages>
<location>Seattle, Washington, USA:</location>
<contexts>
<context position="1573" citStr="Muzny and Zettlemoyer (2013)" startWordPosition="228" endWordPosition="231">ass EPC refers to the prepositional constructions with the support verb essere. Pre-constructed lexical resources facilitate idioms retrieval both in the case of &amp;quot;hybrid&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;knowledge-based&amp;quot; approaches to Natural Language Processing. 1 Introduction Idioms, and multi-word expressions in general, have always been &amp;quot;a pain in the neck&amp;quot;, as Sag et al. (2001) state in the title of their paper. The formal representation and the construction of a computational linguistic model of idioms is not an easy task as shown by Gazdar et al. (1985), Pulman (1993), Abeillé (1995), Villavicencio et al. (2004), Muzny and Zettlemoyer (2013) to name a few of the many (computational) linguists who have carried out research on this topic. It has always been pointed out that the main problem concerning the automatic analysis of idioms is the difficulty to disambiguate such constructions which are ambiguous by definition (Fothergill and Baldwin 2012, Li and Sporlender 2009, Fazly et al. 2009, McShane and Nirenburg 2014). However, given the flexibility of idioms, a more basic and still unsolved problem has to be taken into account: that is, the extraction and annotation of such constructions (Fellbaum 2011). As Fazly et al. (2009, p. </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Muzny, Zettlemoyer, 2013</marker>
<rawString>Grace Muzny, and Luke Zettlemoyer. 2013. Automatic Idiom Identification in Wiktionary. Proceedings of the Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural language Processing (EMNLP 2013), Seattle, Washington, USA: 1417-1421. Geoffrey Nunberg, Ivan Sag, and Tom Wasow. 1994. Idioms. Language, Vol. 70, No. 3, 491-538.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Stephen Pulman</author>
</authors>
<title>The recognition and Interpretation of idioms,</title>
<date>1993</date>
<journal>Cacciari</journal>
<pages>249--270</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="1498" citStr="Pulman (1993)" startWordPosition="220" endWordPosition="221">C1 refers to the Verb + Object constructions, whereas the class EPC refers to the prepositional constructions with the support verb essere. Pre-constructed lexical resources facilitate idioms retrieval both in the case of &amp;quot;hybrid&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;knowledge-based&amp;quot; approaches to Natural Language Processing. 1 Introduction Idioms, and multi-word expressions in general, have always been &amp;quot;a pain in the neck&amp;quot;, as Sag et al. (2001) state in the title of their paper. The formal representation and the construction of a computational linguistic model of idioms is not an easy task as shown by Gazdar et al. (1985), Pulman (1993), Abeillé (1995), Villavicencio et al. (2004), Muzny and Zettlemoyer (2013) to name a few of the many (computational) linguists who have carried out research on this topic. It has always been pointed out that the main problem concerning the automatic analysis of idioms is the difficulty to disambiguate such constructions which are ambiguous by definition (Fothergill and Baldwin 2012, Li and Sporlender 2009, Fazly et al. 2009, McShane and Nirenburg 2014). However, given the flexibility of idioms, a more basic and still unsolved problem has to be taken into account: that is, the extraction and a</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Pulman, 1993</marker>
<rawString>Stephen Pulman. 1993. The recognition and Interpretation of idioms, Cacciari C. &amp; Tabossi, P. (Eds.), Idioms. Processing, Structure, and Interpretation. New Jersey: Lawrence Erlbaum Associates: 249-270.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Ivan Sag</author>
<author>Timothy Baldwin</author>
<author>Francis Bond</author>
<author>Ann Copestake</author>
<author>Dan Flickinger</author>
</authors>
<date>2001</date>
<booktitle>Multiword Expressions: A Pain in the Neck for NLP. Computational Linguistics and Intelligent Text Processing.</booktitle>
<pages>1--15</pages>
<publisher>Springer:</publisher>
<location>Berlin Heidelberg:</location>
<contexts>
<context position="1302" citStr="Sag et al. (2001)" startWordPosition="183" endWordPosition="186">erbs as well as support verb idiomatic constructions. The overall classification counts 7,000+ Italian idioms. In particular, two binary matrixes of two classes of idioms will be presented. The class C1 refers to the Verb + Object constructions, whereas the class EPC refers to the prepositional constructions with the support verb essere. Pre-constructed lexical resources facilitate idioms retrieval both in the case of &amp;quot;hybrid&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;knowledge-based&amp;quot; approaches to Natural Language Processing. 1 Introduction Idioms, and multi-word expressions in general, have always been &amp;quot;a pain in the neck&amp;quot;, as Sag et al. (2001) state in the title of their paper. The formal representation and the construction of a computational linguistic model of idioms is not an easy task as shown by Gazdar et al. (1985), Pulman (1993), Abeillé (1995), Villavicencio et al. (2004), Muzny and Zettlemoyer (2013) to name a few of the many (computational) linguists who have carried out research on this topic. It has always been pointed out that the main problem concerning the automatic analysis of idioms is the difficulty to disambiguate such constructions which are ambiguous by definition (Fothergill and Baldwin 2012, Li and Sporlender</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Sag, Baldwin, Bond, Copestake, Flickinger, 2001</marker>
<rawString>Ivan Sag, Timothy Baldwin, Francis Bond, Ann Copestake, and Dan Flickinger. 2001. Multiword Expressions: A Pain in the Neck for NLP. Computational Linguistics and Intelligent Text Processing. Berlin Heidelberg: Springer: 1-15.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Max Silberztein</author>
</authors>
<title>NooJ Manual. Available for download at: www.nooj4nlp.net.</title>
<date>2003</date>
<contexts>
<context position="21768" citStr="Silberztein (2003)" startWordPosition="3961" endWordPosition="3962">p N2) fare sul serio, farsi in quattro per I 50 Total 3,235 Table 2. Idioms with Support Verbs 5 See Vietri (2014, forthcoming) for the complete classification. 6 For the French classification of idiomatic comparisons see Gross (1984). 143 4 Annotating and Parsing Idioms The Lexicon-Grammar classes of idioms can be exploited by the hybrid as well as the symbolic approach to Natural Language Processing. Some experimentation in this direction has already been carried out by Machonis (2011), who used NooJ to retrieve and disambiguate English phrasal verbs. NooJ is an NLP application developed by Silberztein (2003) that relies heavily on linguistic resources. NooJ has been used to carry out experimentation on some of the Lexicon-Grammar classes of Italian idioms. The experimentation, still in progress, concerns the annotation and parsing of idioms. This application allows the construction of lexicons/dictionaries whose entries contain information such as the distributional and syntactic properties indicated in the Lexicon-Grammar classes. The LexiconGrammar classes of idioms can be converted in a NooJ dictionary of idioms. This dictionary, which contains thousands of entries, has to be linked to a gramm</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Silberztein, 2003</marker>
<rawString>Max Silberztein. 2003-. NooJ Manual. Available for download at: www.nooj4nlp.net.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Simone Sprenger</author>
<author>Willem Levelt</author>
<author>Gerard Kempen</author>
</authors>
<title>Lexical Access during the Production of Idiomatic Phrases.</title>
<date>2006</date>
<journal>Journal of Memory and Language,</journal>
<volume>54</volume>
<pages>161--184</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="3867" citStr="Sprenger et al., 2006" startWordPosition="580" endWordPosition="583"> idioms have also aroused the interest of the psycholinguistic researchers who have advanced several hypothesis on the processing of idioms (Swinney and Cutler, This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International Licence. Page numbers and proceedings footer are added by the organisers. Licence details: http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/. 137 Proceedings of the Workshop on Lexical and Grammatical Resources for Language Processing, pages 137–146, Coling 2014, Dublin, Ireland, August 24 2014. 1979; Gibbs, 1995; Cacciari and Tabossi, 1988; Cutting and Bock, 1997; Sprenger et al., 2006). The systematic description of French idiomatic and non-idiomatic constructions has been carried out by Gross (1982, 1988) and his colleagues (Leclère, 2002) on the basis of the formal principles of the Lexicon-Grammar methodology, as developed by Gross (1975, 1979). According to Gross, the basic syntactic unit is not the word but the simple or elementary sentence, and the Lexicon-Grammar of a language is organized into three main components: free sentences, frozen sentences (or idioms), support verbs sentences (Gross 1981, 1998). For each component, Gross and his colleagues built exhaustive </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Sprenger, Levelt, Kempen, 2006</marker>
<rawString>Simone Sprenger, Willem Levelt, and Gerard Kempen. 2006. Lexical Access during the Production of Idiomatic Phrases. Journal of Memory and Language, 54: 161-184.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>David Swinney</author>
<author>Ann Cutler</author>
</authors>
<title>The access and processing of idiomatic expressions.</title>
<date>1979</date>
<journal>Journal of Verbal Learning and Verbal Behavior,</journal>
<volume>18</volume>
<pages>523--534</pages>
<marker>Swinney, Cutler, 1979</marker>
<rawString>David Swinney, and Ann Cutler. 1979. The access and processing of idiomatic expressions. Journal of Verbal Learning and Verbal Behavior, 18: 523–534</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Simonetta Vietri</author>
</authors>
<title>Lessico e sintassi delle espressioni idiomatiche. Una tipologia tassonomica in italiano e in inglese.</title>
<date>1984</date>
<location>Napoli: Liguori.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="7754" citStr="Vietri (1984)" startWordPosition="1202" endWordPosition="1203">bject position. These idioms have only one argument, that is the (non-fixed noun) in subject position. The definitional structure of the class C1 is N0 V C1 where N indicates the free noun, V the verb and C, as previously stated, the fixed element. The subscripts 0 and 1 indicate the position of the noun within the sentence in a linear order, in this case, the subject and the object position. Idioms such as (2) have been listed and analyzed in the class named CAN, that counts 320 entries. The definitional structure of this class is N0 V C1 (a + di) N2, since these idioms have two arguments, 1 Vietri (1984) includes the very first classification of Italian idioms. Since then, the classification has been widely enriched, updated and completely re-examined. For a semantic study of Italian idioms, see Casadei (1996). A LexiconGrammar classification of Verb-particle constructions has been developed by Guglielmo (2013). From a different perspective, Masini (2005) provides a synchronic and diacronic analysis of Italian verb-particle constructions found in a corpus. 138 i.e. the subject N0 and the noun N2. The alternation of the prepositions a and di is represented between brackets, and the &amp;quot;+&amp;quot; sign in</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Vietri, 1984</marker>
<rawString>Simonetta Vietri. 1984. Lessico e sintassi delle espressioni idiomatiche. Una tipologia tassonomica in italiano e in inglese. Napoli: Liguori.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Simonetta Vietri</author>
</authors>
<title>The Syntax of the Italian verb &apos;essere Prep&apos;, Lingvisticae Investigationes,</title>
<date>1996</date>
<volume>2</volume>
<pages>287--350</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="16620" citStr="Vietri (1996)" startWordPosition="2882" endWordPosition="2883"> a free prepositional complement PI is required in the case of (9). Therefore, idioms like (8) and (9) have been listed in two different classes, respectively, EPC and EPCPI, where E indicates the verb essere (&apos;to be&apos;), P the preposition, C indicates the constrained noun, and I the free noun. Figure 2 is an excerpt of the class EPC which includes 500+ entries. 3 The Lexicon-grammar of the French être Prep constructions has been built by Danlos (1988). The Portuguese constructions were analyzed by Ranchod (1983). A first classification of the Italian essere Prep constructions has been built by Vietri (1996). This early classification has been completely revised. 141 [1] N0 = + hum [2] N0 = - hum [3] N0 = Che F [4] C1 = body-part [5] Vsup = Stare [6] Vsup = Restare-Rimanere [7] Vsup = Diventare [8] Vmt = Andare [9] Vcaus = Mandare [10] Vcaus = Mettere [11] Vcaus = Ridurre [12] Vop = Avere [9] [1 [1 V Prep Prep-Det C1 + + - essere in - ballo - + + - - - + - - + - - essere in - bestia - + + - + + - - - - + - essere sotto - chiave - + + - - - + - - + - - essere - sulla corda - + + - - - + - - + - - essere - alle corde - + + - - - + - - - + - essere - al dente + - + - - - - - - + - - essere in - erba</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Vietri, 1996</marker>
<rawString>Simonetta Vietri. 1996. The Syntax of the Italian verb &apos;essere Prep&apos;, Lingvisticae Investigationes, XX.2: 287-350.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Simonetta Vietri</author>
</authors>
<title>Idiomatic Constructions in Italian. A Lexicon-Grammar Approach.</title>
<date>2014</date>
<booktitle>Linguisticae Investigationes Supplementa, 31. Amsterdam &amp; Philadelphia: John Benjamins (forthcoming).</booktitle>
<contexts>
<context position="3195" citStr="Vietri 2014" startWordPosition="489" endWordPosition="490"> due to two basic reasons. On one hand, idioms can be considered lexical units, given the fact that their &amp;quot;special meaning&amp;quot; is associated to a particular verb and one or more particular complements. On the other hand, idioms syntactically behave as non-idiomatic constructions. Passive is the syntactic construction more frequently analyzed by the linguistic research on idioms since it involves the occurrence of the fixed object to the left of the verb. However, idioms show a great deal of other syntactic constructions where the fixed object may not necessarily occur in postverbal position (see Vietri 2014, forthcoming). It is for these peculiarities that idioms have also aroused the interest of the psycholinguistic researchers who have advanced several hypothesis on the processing of idioms (Swinney and Cutler, This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International Licence. Page numbers and proceedings footer are added by the organisers. Licence details: http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/. 137 Proceedings of the Workshop on Lexical and Grammatical Resources for Language Processing, pages 137–146, Coling 2014, Dublin, Ireland, August 24 2014. 1979; Gibbs, 1995; Ca</context>
<context position="21263" citStr="Vietri (2014" startWordPosition="3884" endWordPosition="3885">emoria corta 400 ACXC N0 avere C1 Prep C2 avere i nervi a fior di pelle 180 &lt;=&gt; C1 di N1 essere Prep C2 &lt;=&gt; i nervi di I sono a fior di pelle ACPN N0 avere C1 Prep N2 non avere la testa di I 50 ACPC N0 avere C1 Prep C2 avere il cervello tra le nuvole 200 FC N0 fare C1 fare melina, fare lo gnorri 300 FCPN N0 fare C1 Prep N2 fare le bucce a, fare man bassa di I 300 FCDC N0 fare (C di C)1 fare l&apos;arte dei pazzi 80 FCPC N0 fare C1 Prep C2 fare un buco nell&apos; acqua 220 FPC(PN) N0 fare Prep C1 (E + Prep N2) fare sul serio, farsi in quattro per I 50 Total 3,235 Table 2. Idioms with Support Verbs 5 See Vietri (2014, forthcoming) for the complete classification. 6 For the French classification of idiomatic comparisons see Gross (1984). 143 4 Annotating and Parsing Idioms The Lexicon-Grammar classes of idioms can be exploited by the hybrid as well as the symbolic approach to Natural Language Processing. Some experimentation in this direction has already been carried out by Machonis (2011), who used NooJ to retrieve and disambiguate English phrasal verbs. NooJ is an NLP application developed by Silberztein (2003) that relies heavily on linguistic resources. NooJ has been used to carry out experimentation o</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Vietri, 2014</marker>
<rawString>Simonetta Vietri. 2014. Idiomatic Constructions in Italian. A Lexicon-Grammar Approach. Linguisticae Investigationes Supplementa, 31. Amsterdam &amp; Philadelphia: John Benjamins (forthcoming).</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Aline Villavicencio</author>
<author>Timothy Baldwin</author>
<author>T</author>
<author>Benjamin Waldron</author>
</authors>
<title>A Multilingual Database of idioms.</title>
<date>2004</date>
<booktitle>Proceedings of the Fourth International Conference on language Resources and Evaluation (LREC 2004),</booktitle>
<pages>1127--30</pages>
<location>Lisbon, Portugal:</location>
<contexts>
<context position="1543" citStr="Villavicencio et al. (2004)" startWordPosition="224" endWordPosition="227">constructions, whereas the class EPC refers to the prepositional constructions with the support verb essere. Pre-constructed lexical resources facilitate idioms retrieval both in the case of &amp;quot;hybrid&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;knowledge-based&amp;quot; approaches to Natural Language Processing. 1 Introduction Idioms, and multi-word expressions in general, have always been &amp;quot;a pain in the neck&amp;quot;, as Sag et al. (2001) state in the title of their paper. The formal representation and the construction of a computational linguistic model of idioms is not an easy task as shown by Gazdar et al. (1985), Pulman (1993), Abeillé (1995), Villavicencio et al. (2004), Muzny and Zettlemoyer (2013) to name a few of the many (computational) linguists who have carried out research on this topic. It has always been pointed out that the main problem concerning the automatic analysis of idioms is the difficulty to disambiguate such constructions which are ambiguous by definition (Fothergill and Baldwin 2012, Li and Sporlender 2009, Fazly et al. 2009, McShane and Nirenburg 2014). However, given the flexibility of idioms, a more basic and still unsolved problem has to be taken into account: that is, the extraction and annotation of such constructions (Fellbaum 201</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Villavicencio, Baldwin, T, Waldron, 2004</marker>
<rawString>Aline Villavicencio, Timothy Baldwin, T., and Benjamin Waldron. 2004. A Multilingual Database of idioms. Proceedings of the Fourth International Conference on language Resources and Evaluation (LREC 2004), Lisbon, Portugal: 1127-30.</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>