<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="SectLabel" version="110505">
<variant no="0" confidence="0.018555">
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.373387">
Preface
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.996679916666667">
Intelligent Computer-Assisted Language Learning (ICALL), i.e., the integration of Natural Lan-
guage Processing (NLP) and Speech Technologies (ST) in language learning applications, is
a rapidly developing area which has started to attract increased attention from the Language
Technology (LT) – generally understood as encompassing both NLP and ST – community. ICALL
research has generated a number of successful applications for alleviating a variety of (mechanical)
tasks that teachers face daily in their work, for example grammar or spelling error marking, essay
grading, preparation of text questions for reading activities, creating tests and exercises, etc.
However, reusing LT methods or tools (developed for other than pedagogical purposes) in
pedagogical applications is not always straightforward since they need to be adapted to the
educational tasks, e.g. readability measures for legal texts adapted to the second language learning
context. Thus, LT researchers who intend to re-use their algorithms and techniques in CALL
applications need new datasets, specifically designed corpora, databases, etc. to fine-tune their
tools for new target groups, the design and compilation of which are both critical for achieving
good results and time-consuming.
There are other challenges that the area of LT-based CALL faces: re-use and sharing of existing
LT components, copyright issues, standardization of pedagogical framework, lack of collaboration
with end-users, to name just a few. Probably the most significant challenge is to make sure that the
research results reach the actual end-users in the form of tools which can become a part of the
educational process, and which are both easy to use and have a pedagogically sound basis. The
goal of the workshop was to bring together (computational) linguists involved in research aiming
at integrating LT in CALL systems and exploring the theoretical and methodological issues arising
in this connection, with the purpose of sharing experiences, achievements and setbacks, and to
discuss potential ways of addressing the challenges that need to be overcome.
This year we invited submissions of papers and software demonstrations that would
</bodyText>
<listItem confidence="0.995665125">
• describe research directly aimed at ICALL
• demonstrate actual or discuss potential use of existing LT tools or resources for language
learning
• describe ongoing development of resources and tools with potential usage in ICALL, either
directly in interactive applications, or indirectly in materials, application or curriculum
development, e.g. collecting and annotating learner corpora; developing tools and algorithms
for readability analysis, selecting optimal corpus examples, etc.
• discuss challenges and/or research agendas for ICALL
</listItem>
<bodyText confidence="0.565144">
with a special focus on Nordic languages. Out of 13 submissions, 10 papers have been accepted
following the recommendations of two anonymous reviews per paper provided by the members of
our Program Committee:
</bodyText>
<listItem confidence="0.9196136">
• Lars Ahrenberg, Linköping University, Sweden
• Lars Borin, University of Gothenburg, Sweden
• Antonio Branco, University of Lisboa, Portugal
• Simon Dobnik, University of Gothenburg, Sweden
• Robert Eklund, Linköping University, Sweden
• Katarina Heimann Mühlenbock, DART, Sahlgrenska Universitetssjukhuset, Göteborg, Swe-
den
Elena Volodina, Lars Borin and Ildikó Pilán 2014. Preface. Proceedings of the third workshop on NLP for computer-assisted
language learning. NEALT Proceedings Series 22 / Linköping Electronic Conference Proceedings 107: i–ii.
i
• Thomas François, UCLouvain, Belgium
• Arne Jönsson, Linköping University, Sweden
• Sofie Johansson Kokkinakis, University of Gothenburg, Sweden
• Chris Koniaris, University of Gothenburg, Sweden
• Peter Ljunglöf, University of Gothenburg, Sweden
• Hrafn Loftsson, Reykjavik University, Iceland
• Montse Maritxalar, University of the Basque country, Spain
• Detmar Meurers, University of Tübingen, Germany
• Martí Quixal, University of Tübingen, Germany
• Mathias Schulze, University of Waterloo, Canada
• Joel Tetreault, Yahoo! Labs, US
• Trond Trosterud, Universitetet i Tromsø, Norway
• Cornelia Tschichold, Swansea University, UK
• Francis Tyers, The Arctic University of Norway, Norway
• Elena Volodina, University of Gothenburg, Sweden
</listItem>
<bodyText confidence="0.998032333333333">
The geography of accepted papers (i.e. author affiliations) covered Belgium, Canada, Germany,
Norway, Russia, Spain, Sweden and USA. The resources and tools described in the papers in
this volume are aimed at a range of languages: Swedish, Russian, Estonian, French, German,
Spanish and English. The papers cover three main topic areas: resources for development of ICALL
applications (learner corpora vs coursebook corpora), tools and algorithms for the analysis of
learner language (focusing on collocations, reading tasks, cloze items, pronunciation, spelling,
level classification of learner production), and generation of learning materials (e.g., exercise
generators).
The workshop started off with short presentations of each paper, followed by discussions
during the two poster sessions. The workshop concluded with an invited talk by Detmar Meurers
on A roadmap connecting NLP research and language learning which developed into a free
discussion on challenges and future prospects of ICALL.
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.623213625">
The workshop organizers:
Elena Volodina
Lars Borin
Ildikó Pilán
WSwebsite: http://spraakbanken.gu.se/eng/Research/ICALL/3rdNLP4CALL
Acknowledgements: Financial support for the organization of the workshop has come from
the University of Gothenburg through its support of the Centre for Language Technology: http:
//www.clt.gu.se
</reference>
<page confidence="0.781084">
ii
</page>
</variant>
</algorithm>
<algorithm name="ParsHed" version="110505">
<variant no="0" confidence="0.000195">
<title confidence="0.980801">Preface</title>
<abstract confidence="0.9587556">Intelligent Computer-Assisted Language Learning (ICALL), i.e., the integration of Natural Language Processing (NLP) and Speech Technologies (ST) in language learning applications, is a rapidly developing area which has started to attract increased attention from the Language Technology (LT) – generally understood as encompassing both NLP and ST – community. ICALL research has generated a number of successful applications for alleviating a variety of (mechanical) tasks that teachers face daily in their work, for example grammar or spelling error marking, essay grading, preparation of text questions for reading activities, creating tests and exercises, etc. However, reusing LT methods or tools (developed for other than pedagogical purposes) in pedagogical applications is not always straightforward since they need to be adapted to the educational tasks, e.g. readability measures for legal texts adapted to the second language learning context. Thus, LT researchers who intend to re-use their algorithms and techniques in CALL applications need new datasets, specifically designed corpora, databases, etc. to fine-tune their tools for new target groups, the design and compilation of which are both critical for achieving good results and time-consuming. There are other challenges that the area of LT-based CALL faces: re-use and sharing of existing LT components, copyright issues, standardization of pedagogical framework, lack of collaboration with end-users, to name just a few. Probably the most significant challenge is to make sure that the research results reach the actual end-users in the form of tools which can become a part of the educational process, and which are both easy to use and have a pedagogically sound basis. The goal of the workshop was to bring together (computational) linguists involved in research aiming at integrating LT in CALL systems and exploring the theoretical and methodological issues arising in this connection, with the purpose of sharing experiences, achievements and setbacks, and to discuss potential ways of addressing the challenges that need to be overcome. This year we invited submissions of papers and software demonstrations that would • describe research directly aimed at ICALL • demonstrate actual or discuss potential use of existing LT tools or resources for language learning • describe ongoing development of resources and tools with potential usage in ICALL, either directly in interactive applications, or indirectly in materials, application or curriculum development, e.g. collecting and annotating learner corpora; developing tools and algorithms for readability analysis, selecting optimal corpus examples, etc. • discuss challenges and/or research agendas for ICALL with a special focus on Nordic languages. Out of 13 submissions, 10 papers have been accepted following the recommendations of two anonymous reviews per paper provided by the members of our Program Committee:</abstract>
<note confidence="0.833871666666667">Lars Ahrenberg, Linköping University, Sweden • Lars Borin, University of Gothenburg, Sweden • Antonio Branco, University of Lisboa, Portugal • Simon Dobnik, University of Gothenburg, Sweden • Robert Eklund, Linköping University, Sweden • Katarina Heimann Mühlenbock, DART, Sahlgrenska Universitetssjukhuset, Göteborg, Sweden Volodina, Lars Borin and Ildikó Pilán 2014. Preface. of the third workshop on NLP for computer-assisted learning. Proceedings Series 22 / Linköping Electronic Conference Proceedings 107: i–ii.</note>
<email confidence="0.162577">i</email>
<degree confidence="0.250009470588235">Thomas François, UCLouvain, Belgium • Arne Jönsson, Linköping University, Sweden • Sofie Johansson Kokkinakis, University of Gothenburg, Sweden • Chris Koniaris, University of Gothenburg, Sweden • Peter Ljunglöf, University of Gothenburg, Sweden • Hrafn Loftsson, Reykjavik University, Iceland • Montse Maritxalar, University of the Basque country, Spain • Detmar Meurers, University of Tübingen, Germany • Martí Quixal, University of Tübingen, Germany • Mathias Schulze, University of Waterloo, Canada • Joel Tetreault, Yahoo! Labs, US • Trond Trosterud, Universitetet i Tromsø, Norway • Cornelia Tschichold, Swansea University, UK • Francis Tyers, The Arctic University of Norway, Norway • Elena Volodina, University of Gothenburg, Sweden The geography of accepted papers (i.e. author affiliations) covered Belgium, Canada, Germany, Norway, Russia, Spain, Sweden and USA. The resources and tools described in the papers in</degree>
<abstract confidence="0.9937454">this volume are aimed at a range of languages: Swedish, Russian, Estonian, French, German, and English. The papers cover three main topic areas: for development of ICALL corpora vs coursebook corpora), and algorithms for the analysis of language on collocations, reading tasks, cloze items, pronunciation, spelling, classification of learner production), and of learning materials exercise generators). The workshop started off with short presentations of each paper, followed by discussions during the two poster sessions. The workshop concluded with an invited talk by Detmar Meurers roadmap connecting NLP research and language learning developed into a free discussion on challenges and future prospects of ICALL.</abstract>
<title confidence="0.72181">The workshop organizers:</title>
<author confidence="0.927100666666667">Elena Volodina Lars Borin Ildikó Pilán</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.8224885">support for the organization of the workshop has come from University of Gothenburg through its support of the for Language</affiliation>
<email confidence="0.698565">//www.clt.gu.se</email>
<intro confidence="0.692448">ii</intro>
</variant>
</algorithm>
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="false">
<title>The workshop organizers: Elena Volodina Lars Borin Ildikó Pilán WSwebsite: http://spraakbanken.gu.se/eng/Research/ICALL/3rdNLP4CALL Acknowledgements: Financial support for the organization of the workshop has come from the University of Gothenburg through its support of the Centre for Language Technology: http: //www.clt.gu.se</title>
<marker></marker>
<rawString>The workshop organizers: Elena Volodina Lars Borin Ildikó Pilán WSwebsite: http://spraakbanken.gu.se/eng/Research/ICALL/3rdNLP4CALL Acknowledgements: Financial support for the organization of the workshop has come from the University of Gothenburg through its support of the Centre for Language Technology: http: //www.clt.gu.se</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>