<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="SectLabel" version="110505">
<variant no="0" confidence="0.000002">
<note confidence="0.937531">
COLING 2014
</note>
<title confidence="0.9841546">
The 25th International Conference
on Computational Linguistics
Proceedings of the Conference
the 5th Workshop on South and Southeast Asian NLP
WSSANLP - 2014
</title>
<author confidence="0.370635">
August 23, 2014
Dublin, Ireland
</author>
<note confidence="0.8000865">
© 2014 The Authors
The papers in this volume are licensed by the authors under a
Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.
ISBN 978-1-873769-41-6
Proceedings of the Fifth Workshop on South and Southeast Asian Natural Language Processing
Christian Boitet and M.G. Abbas Malik (eds.)
</note>
<page confidence="0.716682">
ii
</page>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.369045">
Preface
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998145681818182">
Welcome to the 5th Workshop on South and Southeast Asian Natural Language Processing (WSSANLP
- 2014), a collocated event at the 25th International Conference on Computational Linguistics (COLING
2014) , 23 - 29 August, 2014.
South and Southeast Asia comprise of the countries, Afghanistan, Bangladesh, Bhutan, India, Maldives,
Nepal, Pakistan and Sri Lanka. Southeast Asia, on the other hand, consists of Brunei, Burma, Cambodia,
East Timor, Indonesia, Laos, Malaysia, Philippines, Singapore, Thailand and Vietnam.
This area is the home to thousands of languages that belong to different language families like Indo-
Aryan, Indo-Iranian, Dravidian, Sino-Tibetan, Austro-Asiatic, Kradai, Hmong-Mien, etc. In terms of
population, South Asian and Southeast Asia represent 35 percent of the total population of the world
which means as much as 2.5 billion speakers. Some of the languages of these regions have a large
number of native speakers: Hindi (5th largest according to number of its native speakers), Bengali (6th),
Punjabi (12th), Tamil(18th), Urdu (20th), etc.
As internet and electronic devices including PCs and hand held devices including mobile phones have
spread far and wide in the region, it has become imperative to develop language technology for these
languages. It is important for economic development as well as for social and individual progress.
A characteristic of these languages is that they are under-resourced. The words of these languages show
rich variations in morphology. Moreover they are often heavily agglutinated and synthetic, making
segmentation an important issue. The intellectual motivation for this workshop comes from the need to
explore ways of harnessing the morphology of these languages for higher level processing. The task of
morphology, however, in South and Southeast Asian Languages is intimately linked with segmentation
for these languages.
The goal of WSSANLP is:
</bodyText>
<listItem confidence="0.991559">
• Providing a platform to linguistic and NLP communities for sharing and discussing ideas and work on
South and Southeast Asian languages and combining efforts.
• Development of useful and high quality computational resources for under resourced South and
Southeast Asian languages.
</listItem>
<bodyText confidence="0.9979318">
We are delighted to present to you this volume of proceedings of the 5th Workshop on South and
Southeast Asian Natural Language Processing. We have received total 18 submission in the categories
of long paper and short paper. On the basis of our review process, we have competitively selected 7 long
(regular) papers for oral presentations and 7 short papers for poster presentations.
We look forward to an invigorating workshop.
</bodyText>
<author confidence="0.293178">
Christian Boitet (Chair WSSANLP-2014),
</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.598236">
University of Grenoble I, France
</affiliation>
<author confidence="0.429392">
M.G. Abbas Malik (Co-Chair WSSANLP-2014),
</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.6326785">
Faculty of Computing and Information Technology (North Jeddah Branch),
King Abdulaziz University, Saudi Arabia
</affiliation>
<page confidence="0.492282">
iii
</page>
<figure confidence="0.573690222222222">
The Fifth Workshop on
South and Southeast Asian Natural Language processing
WSSANLP-2014
WSSANLP Organizers
Workshop Chair
Christian Boitet, University of Grenoble I, France
Workshop Co-Chairs
M. G. Abbas Malik, King Abdulaziz University, Saudi Arabia
Organizing Committee
</figure>
<affiliation confidence="0.635864">
Amitava Das, University of North Texas, USA
Sadaf Abdul Rauf, Fatima Jinnah Women University, Pakistan
</affiliation>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.882021" genericHeader="abstract">
WSSANLP Invited Speaker
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.971610333333333">
Vincent Berment, INaLCO, Paris, France (Lecturer)
LIG/GÉTALP, Grenoble, France (Associated Researcher)
Taranis Software, Paris, France (Director)
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.935086">
Program Committee
</subsectionHeader>
<table confidence="0.928840025">
Sadaf Abdul Rauf, Fatima Jinnah Women University, Pakistan
Naveed Afzal, King Abdulaziz University, Saudi Arabia
Aasim Ali, University of the Punjab, Pakistan
M. Waqas Anwar, COMSATS Institute of Information Technology, Pakistan
Bal Krishna Bal, Kathmandu University, Nepal
Sivaji Bandyopadhyay, Jadavpur University, India
Vincent Berment, GETALP-LIG / INALCO, France
Laurent Besacier, GETALP-LIG, Université de Grenoble, France
Pushpak Bhattacharyya, IIT Bombay, India
Hervé Blanchon, GETALP-LIG, Université de Grenoble, France
Christian Boitet, GETALP-LIG, Université de Grenoble, France
Erik Cambria, National University of Singapore, Singapore
Eric Castelli, International Research Center MICA, Vietnam
Sandipan Dandapat, IIT Guwahati, India
Amitava Das, University of North Texas, USA
Alexander Gelbukh, Center for Computing Research, CIC, Mexico
Choochart Haruechaiyasak, NECTEC, Thailand
Sarmad Hussain, Al-Khawarizmi Institute of Computer Science, University of Engineering and
v
Technology, Pakistan
Aravind K. Joshi, University of Pennsylvania, USA
Abid Khan, University of Peshawar, Pakistan
Malhar Kulkarni, Indian Institute of Technology Bombay, India
Amba Kulkarni, Department of Sanskrit Studies, University of Hyderabad, India
A. Kumaran, Microsoft Research, India
Gurpreet Singh Lehal, Punjabi University, Patiala, India
M. G. Abbas Malik, King Abdulaziz University, Saudi Arabia
Bali Ranaivo-Malançon, University Malaysia Sarawak, Malaysia
Fuji Ren, University of Tokushima, Japan
Hammam Riza, Agency for the Assessment and Application of Technology (BPPT), Indonesia
Paolo Rosso, Universitat Politècnica de València, Spain
Huda Sarfraz, Beacon house National University, Pakistan
Dipti Mishra Sharma, IIIT Hyderabad, India
Sunil Sivadas, Institute for Infocomm Research, Singapore
L. Sobha, AU-KBC Research Centre, India
Virach Sornlertlamvanich, TCL, National Institute of Information and Communication Technol-
ogy, Thailand
Sriram Venkatapathy, Xerox Research Center Europe, France
Eric Wehrli, University of Geneva, Switzerland
vi
</table>
<tableCaption confidence="0.975577">
Table of Contents
</tableCaption>
<figure confidence="0.904241508196721">
Towards Identifying Hindi/Urdu Noun Templates in Support of a Large-Scale LFG Grammar
Sebastian Sulger and Ashwini Vaidya 1
Konkanverter - A Finite State Transducer based Statistical Machine Transliteration Engine for Konkani
Language
Vinodh Rajan 11
Integrating Dictionaries into an Unsupervised Model for Myanmar Word Segmentation
Ye Kyaw Thu, Andrew Finch, Eichiro SUMITA and Yoshinori Sagisaka 20
A Framework for Learning Morphology using Suffix Association Matrix
Shilpa Desai, Jyoti Pawar and Pushpak Bhattacharyya 28
English to Urdu Statistical Machine Translation: Establishing a Baseline
Bushra Jawaid, Amir Kamran and Ondrej Bojar 37
A hybrid approach for automatic clause boundary identification in Hindi
Rahul Sharma and Soma Paul 43
RBMT as an alternative to SMT for under-resourced languages
Guillaume de Malézieux, Amélie Bosc and Vincent Berment 50
Developing an interlingual translation lexicon using WordNets and Grammatical Framework
Shafqat Mumtaz Virk, K.V.S Prasad, Aarne Ranta and Krasimir Angelov 55
A Dictionary Data Processing Environment and Its Application in Algorithmic Processing of Pali Dic-
tionary Data for Future NLP Tasks
Jürgen Knauth and David Alfter 65
Constituent structure representation of Pashto Endoclitics
Azizud Din, Bali Ranaivo-Malançon and M. G. Abbas Malik 74
Real Time Early-stage Influenza Detection with Emotion Factors from Sina Microblog
Xiao Sun, Jiaqi Ye and Fuji Ren 80
Building English-Vietnamese Named Entity Corpus with Aligned Bilingual News Articles
Quoc Hung Ngo, Dinh Dien and Werner Winiwarter 85
Character-Cluster-Based Segmentation using Monolingual and Bilingual Information for Statistical Ma-
chine Translation
Vipas Sutantayawalee, Peerachet Porkeaw, Thepchai Supnithi, Prachya Boonkwan and Sitthaa Pha-
holphinyo 94
A rule based approach for automatic clause boundary detection and classification in Hindi
Rahul Sharma 102
vii
WSSANLP 2014 Program
Saturday August 23, 2014
(8:45 - 9:00) Openning Session
(9:00 - 10:15) Invited Talk
+ by Vincent Berment
(10:15 - 10:45) Coffee Break
Session Regular Papers 1: (10:45 - 12:30) WSSANLP Session 1
10:45 Towards Identifying Hindi/Urdu Noun Templates in Support of a Large-Scale LFG
Grammar
Sebastian Sulger and Ashwini Vaidya
11:10 Konkanverter - A Finite State Transducer based Statistical Machine Transliteration
Engine for Konkani Language
Vinodh Rajan
11:35 Integrating Dictionaries into an Unsupervised Model for Myanmar Word Segmen-
tation
Ye Kyaw Thu, Andrew Finch, Eichiro SUMITA and Yoshinori Sagisaka
12:00 A Framework for Learning Morphology using Suffix Association Matrix
Shilpa Desai, Jyoti Pawar and Pushpak Bhattacharyya
(12:30 - 14:00) Lunch break
ix
Saturday August 23, 2014 (continued)
Session Short Papers: (14:00 - 15:15) WSSANLP Session 2
English to Urdu Statistical Machine Translation: Establishing a Baseline
Bushra Jawaid, Amir Kamran and Ondrej Bojar
A hybrid approach for automatic clause boundary identification in Hindi
Rahul Sharma and Soma Paul
RBMT as an alternative to SMT for under-resourced languages
Guillaume de Malézieux, Amélie Bosc and Vincent Berment
</figure>
<reference confidence="0.935991565217391">
Developing an interlingual translation lexicon using WordNets and Grammatical Frame-
work
Shafqat Mumtaz Virk, K.V.S Prasad, Aarne Ranta and Krasimir Angelov
A Dictionary Data Processing Environment and Its Application in Algorithmic Processing
of Pali Dictionary Data for Future NLP Tasks
Jürgen Knauth and David Alfter
Constituent structure representation of Pashto Endoclitics
Azizud Din, Bali Ranaivo-Malançon and M. G. Abbas Malik
Real Time Early-stage Influenza Detection with Emotion Factors from Sina Microblog
Xiao Sun, Jiaqi Ye and Fuji Ren
(15:15 - 15:45) Coffee Break
Session Regular Papers 2: (15:45 - 17:00) WSSANLP Session 3
15:45 Building English-Vietnamese Named Entity Corpus with Aligned Bilingual News Articles
Quoc Hung Ngo, Dinh Dien and Werner Winiwarter
16:10 Character-Cluster-Based Segmentation using Monolingual and Bilingual Information for
Statistical Machine Translation
Vipas Sutantayawalee, Peerachet Porkeaw, Thepchai Supnithi, Prachya Boonkwan and
Sitthaa Phaholphinyo
16:35 A rule based approach for automatic clause boundary detection and classification in Hindi
Rahul Sharma
x
Saturday August 23, 2014 (continued)
(17:00 -17:15) Closing Remarks
</reference>
<page confidence="0.698362">
xi
</page>
</variant>
</algorithm>
<algorithm name="ParsHed" version="110505">
<variant no="0" confidence="0.000000">
<note confidence="0.920044583333333">COLING 2014 The 25th International on Computational Linguistics Proceedings of the Conference the 5th Workshop on South and Southeast Asian NLP WSSANLP - 2014 August 23, Dublin, Ireland The Authors The papers in this volume are licensed by the authors under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License. ISBN 978-1-873769-41-6</note>
<title confidence="0.777767">Proceedings of the Fifth Workshop on South and Southeast Asian Natural Language Processing</title>
<author confidence="0.80717">Christian Boitet</author>
<author confidence="0.80717">M G Abbas Malik</author>
<email confidence="0.387244">ii</email>
<note confidence="0.895529555555556">Preface Welcome to the 5th Workshop on South and Southeast Asian Natural Language Processing (WSSANLP - 2014), a collocated event at the 25th International Conference on Computational Linguistics (COLING 2014) , 23 - 29 August, 2014. South and Southeast Asia comprise of the countries, Afghanistan, Bangladesh, Bhutan, India, Maldives, Nepal, Pakistan and Sri Lanka. Southeast Asia, on the other hand, consists of Brunei, Burma, Cambodia, East Timor, Indonesia, Laos, Malaysia, Philippines, Singapore, Thailand and Vietnam. This area is the home to thousands of languages that belong to different language families like Indo- Aryan, Indo-Iranian, Dravidian, Sino-Tibetan, Austro-Asiatic, Kradai, Hmong-Mien, etc. In terms of</note>
<abstract confidence="0.994606565217391">population, South Asian and Southeast Asia represent 35 percent of the total population of the world which means as much as 2.5 billion speakers. Some of the languages of these regions have a large number of native speakers: Hindi (5th largest according to number of its native speakers), Bengali (6th), Punjabi (12th), Tamil(18th), Urdu (20th), etc. As internet and electronic devices including PCs and hand held devices including mobile phones have spread far and wide in the region, it has become imperative to develop language technology for these languages. It is important for economic development as well as for social and individual progress. A characteristic of these languages is that they are under-resourced. The words of these languages show rich variations in morphology. Moreover they are often heavily agglutinated and synthetic, making segmentation an important issue. The intellectual motivation for this workshop comes from the need to explore ways of harnessing the morphology of these languages for higher level processing. The task of morphology, however, in South and Southeast Asian Languages is intimately linked with segmentation for these languages. The goal of WSSANLP is: • Providing a platform to linguistic and NLP communities for sharing and discussing ideas and work on South and Southeast Asian languages and combining efforts. • Development of useful and high quality computational resources for under resourced South and Southeast Asian languages. We are delighted to present to you this volume of proceedings of the 5th Workshop on South and Southeast Asian Natural Language Processing. We have received total 18 submission in the categories of long paper and short paper. On the basis of our review process, we have competitively selected 7 long (regular) papers for oral presentations and 7 short papers for poster presentations. We look forward to an invigorating workshop.</abstract>
<author confidence="0.666995">Boitet</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.955585">University of Grenoble I, France</affiliation>
<author confidence="0.731296">Abbas Malik</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.800739">Faculty of Computing and Information Technology (North Jeddah Branch),</affiliation>
<author confidence="0.683644">King Abdulaziz University</author>
<author confidence="0.683644">Saudi Arabia</author>
<email confidence="0.810841">iii</email>
<title confidence="0.7965595">The Fifth Workshop on South and Southeast Asian Natural Language processing</title>
<pubnum confidence="0.531901">WSSANLP-2014</pubnum>
<title confidence="0.9765895">WSSANLP Organizers Workshop Chair</title>
<author confidence="0.888615">Christian Boitet</author>
<author confidence="0.888615">University of Grenoble I</author>
<author confidence="0.888615">France</author>
<title confidence="0.96868">Workshop Co-Chairs</title>
<author confidence="0.984822">M G Abbas Malik</author>
<author confidence="0.984822">King Abdulaziz University</author>
<author confidence="0.984822">Saudi Arabia</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.911531">Organizing Committee</affiliation>
<address confidence="0.940079">Amitava Das, University of North Texas, USA</address>
<degree confidence="0.740730166666667">Sadaf Abdul Rauf, Fatima Jinnah Women University, Pakistan WSSANLP Invited Speaker Vincent Berment, INaLCO, Paris, France (Lecturer) LIG/GÉTALP, Grenoble, France (Associated Researcher) Taranis Software, Paris, France (Director) Program Committee Sadaf Abdul Rauf, Fatima Jinnah Women University, Pakistan Naveed Afzal, King Abdulaziz University, Saudi Arabia Aasim Ali, University of the Punjab, Pakistan M. Waqas Anwar, COMSATS Institute of Information Technology, Pakistan Bal Krishna Bal, Kathmandu University, Nepal Sivaji Bandyopadhyay, Jadavpur University, India Vincent Berment, GETALP-LIG / INALCO, France Laurent Besacier, GETALP-LIG, Université de Grenoble, France Pushpak Bhattacharyya, IIT Bombay, India Hervé Blanchon, GETALP-LIG, Université de Grenoble, France Christian Boitet, GETALP-LIG, Université de Grenoble, France Erik Cambria, National University of Singapore, Singapore</degree>
<address confidence="0.7218632">Eric Castelli, International Research Center MICA, Vietnam Sandipan Dandapat, IIT Guwahati, India Amitava Das, University of North Texas, USA Alexander Gelbukh, Center for Computing Research, CIC, Mexico Choochart Haruechaiyasak, NECTEC, Thailand</address>
<author confidence="0.609834">Sarmad Hussain</author>
<author confidence="0.609834">Al-Khawarizmi Institute of Computer Science</author>
<author confidence="0.609834">University of Engineering</author>
<email confidence="0.58601">v</email>
<affiliation confidence="0.453747">Technology, Pakistan</affiliation>
<address confidence="0.689881">Aravind K. Joshi, University of Pennsylvania, USA Abid Khan, University of Peshawar, Pakistan Malhar Kulkarni, Indian Institute of Technology Bombay, India Amba Kulkarni, Department of Sanskrit Studies, University of Hyderabad, India A. Kumaran, Microsoft Research, India Gurpreet Singh Lehal, Punjabi University, Patiala, India</address>
<author confidence="0.917022">M G Abbas Malik</author>
<author confidence="0.917022">King Abdulaziz University</author>
<author confidence="0.917022">Saudi Arabia</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.72621">Bali Ranaivo-Malançon, University Malaysia Sarawak, Malaysia</affiliation>
<address confidence="0.7231635">Fuji Ren, University of Tokushima, Japan Hammam Riza, Agency for the Assessment and Application of Technology (BPPT), Indonesia</address>
<author confidence="0.799499">Paolo Rosso</author>
<author confidence="0.799499">Universitat Politècnica de_València</author>
<author confidence="0.799499">Spain</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.962419">Huda Sarfraz, Beacon house National University, Pakistan</affiliation>
<address confidence="0.690277833333333">Dipti Mishra Sharma, IIIT Hyderabad, India Sunil Sivadas, Institute for Infocomm Research, Singapore L. Sobha, AU-KBC Research Centre, India Sornlertlamvanich, TCL, National Institute of Information and Communication Technology, Thailand Sriram Venkatapathy, Xerox Research Center Europe, France</address>
<author confidence="0.77595">Eric Wehrli</author>
<author confidence="0.77595">University of Geneva</author>
<author confidence="0.77595">Switzerland</author>
<email confidence="0.800321">vi</email>
<title confidence="0.884577857142857">Table of Contents Towards Identifying Hindi/Urdu Noun Templates in Support of a Large-Scale LFG Grammar Sulger and Ashwini Vaidya Konkanverter - A Finite State Transducer based Statistical Machine Transliteration Engine for Konkani Language Rajan 11 Integrating Dictionaries into an Unsupervised Model for Myanmar Word Segmentation</title>
<note confidence="0.758025222222222">Kyaw Thu, Andrew Finch, Eichiro SUMITA and Yoshinori Sagisaka20 A Framework for Learning Morphology using Suffix Association Matrix Shilpa Desai, Jyoti Pawar and Pushpak Bhattacharyya 28 English to Urdu Statistical Machine Translation: Establishing a Baseline Bushra Jawaid, Amir Kamran and Ondrej Bojar 37 A hybrid approach for automatic clause boundary identification in Hindi Sharma and Soma Paul43 RBMT as an alternative to SMT for under-resourced languages Guillaume de Malézieux, Amélie Bosc and Vincent Berment 50</note>
<title confidence="0.8976035">Developing an interlingual translation lexicon using WordNets and Grammatical Framework Mumtaz Virk, K.V.S Prasad, Aarne Ranta and Krasimir Angelov55 A Dictionary Data Processing Environment and Its Application in Algorithmic Processing of Pali Dictionary Data for Future NLP Tasks</title>
<note confidence="0.545804">Jürgen Knauth and David Alfter 65 Constituent structure representation of Pashto Endoclitics Din, Bali Ranaivo-Malançon and M. G. Abbas Malik74 Real Time Early-stage Influenza Detection with Emotion Factors from Sina Microblog Sun, Jiaqi Ye and Fuji Ren80</note>
<title confidence="0.925277">Building English-Vietnamese Named Entity Corpus with Aligned Bilingual News Articles</title>
<author confidence="0.624665">Hung Ngo</author>
<author confidence="0.624665">Dinh Dien</author>
<author confidence="0.624665">Werner Winiwarter</author>
<title confidence="0.600937">Character-Cluster-Based Segmentation using Monolingual and Bilingual Information for Statistical Machine Translation Sutantayawalee, Peerachet Porkeaw, Thepchai Supnithi, Prachya Boonkwan and Sitthaa Pha-</title>
<date confidence="0.483528">holphinyo 94</date>
<note confidence="0.7315053">A rule based approach for automatic clause boundary detection and classification in Hindi Sharma102 vii WSSANLP 2014 Program Saturday August 23, 2014 (8:45 - 9:00) Openning Session (9:00 - 10:15) Invited Talk + by Vincent Berment (10:15 - 10:45) Coffee Break Session Regular Papers 1: (10:45 - 12:30) WSSANLP Session 1</note>
<title confidence="0.975896">10:45Towards Identifying Hindi/Urdu Noun Templates in Support of a Large-Scale LFG Grammar</title>
<author confidence="0.959316">Sebastian Sulger</author>
<author confidence="0.959316">Ashwini Vaidya</author>
<title confidence="0.821281">11:10Konkanverter - A Finite State Transducer based Statistical Machine Transliteration Engine for Konkani Language</title>
<author confidence="0.614353">Vinodh Rajan Integrating Dictionaries into an Unsupervised Model for Myanmar Word Segmen-</author>
<email confidence="0.493265">tation</email>
<author confidence="0.856713">Ye Kyaw Thu</author>
<author confidence="0.856713">Andrew Finch</author>
<author confidence="0.856713">Eichiro SUMITA</author>
<author confidence="0.856713">Yoshinori Sagisaka</author>
<note confidence="0.514591571428571">12:00A Framework for Learning Morphology using Suffix Association Matrix Shilpa Desai, Jyoti Pawar and Pushpak Bhattacharyya (12:30 - 14:00) Lunch break ix Saturday August 23, 2014 (continued) Session Short Papers: (14:00 - 15:15) WSSANLP Session 2 English to Urdu Statistical Machine Translation: Establishing a Baseline</note>
<title confidence="0.8226265">Bushra Jawaid, Amir Kamran and Ondrej Bojar A hybrid approach for automatic clause boundary identification in Hindi</title>
<author confidence="0.637201">Rahul Sharma</author>
<author confidence="0.637201">Soma Paul</author>
<title confidence="0.795029285714286">RBMT as an alternative to SMT for under-resourced languages Guillaume de Malézieux, Amélie Bosc and Vincent Berment Developing an interlingual translation lexicon using WordNets and Grammatical Framework Shafqat Mumtaz Virk, K.V.S Prasad, Aarne Ranta and Krasimir Angelov A Dictionary Data Processing Environment and Its Application in Algorithmic Processing of Pali Dictionary Data for Future NLP Tasks</title>
<author confidence="0.630194">Jürgen Knauth</author>
<author confidence="0.630194">David Alfter</author>
<title confidence="0.705626">Constituent structure representation of Pashto Endoclitics</title>
<author confidence="0.655634333333333">Azizud Din</author>
<author confidence="0.655634333333333">Bali Ranaivo-Malançon</author>
<author confidence="0.655634333333333">M G Abbas Malik Real Time Early-stage Influenza Detection with Emotion Factors from Sina Microblog Xiao Sun</author>
<author confidence="0.655634333333333">Jiaqi Ye</author>
<author confidence="0.655634333333333">Fuji Ren</author>
<note confidence="0.7541">(15:15 - 15:45) Coffee Break Session Regular Papers 2: (15:45 - 17:00) WSSANLP Session 3</note>
<title confidence="0.821181">15:45Building English-Vietnamese Named Entity Corpus with Aligned Bilingual News Articles</title>
<author confidence="0.805056">Quoc Hung Ngo</author>
<author confidence="0.805056">Dinh Dien</author>
<author confidence="0.805056">Werner Winiwarter</author>
<title confidence="0.6886554">16:10Character-Cluster-Based Segmentation using Monolingual and Bilingual Information for Statistical Machine Translation Vipas Sutantayawalee, Peerachet Porkeaw, Thepchai Supnithi, Prachya Boonkwan and Sitthaa Phaholphinyo 16:35A rule based approach for automatic clause boundary detection and classification in Hindi</title>
<author confidence="0.948962">Rahul Sharma</author>
<email confidence="0.773559">x</email>
<note confidence="0.58133">Saturday August 23, 2014 (continued) (17:00 -17:15) Closing Remarks</note>
<intro confidence="0.597104">xi</intro>
</variant>
</algorithm>
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="false">
<title>Developing an interlingual translation lexicon using WordNets and Grammatical Framework</title>
<marker></marker>
<rawString>Developing an interlingual translation lexicon using WordNets and Grammatical Framework</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>Shafqat Mumtaz Virk</author>
<author>K V S Prasad</author>
</authors>
<title>Aarne Ranta and Krasimir Angelov A Dictionary Data Processing Environment and Its Application</title>
<booktitle>in Algorithmic Processing of Pali Dictionary Data for Future NLP Tasks Jürgen Knauth and David</booktitle>
<location>Alfter</location>
<marker>Virk, Prasad, </marker>
<rawString>Shafqat Mumtaz Virk, K.V.S Prasad, Aarne Ranta and Krasimir Angelov A Dictionary Data Processing Environment and Its Application in Algorithmic Processing of Pali Dictionary Data for Future NLP Tasks Jürgen Knauth and David Alfter</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>M G</author>
</authors>
<title>Constituent structure representation of Pashto Endoclitics Azizud Din, Bali Ranaivo-Malançon</title>
<location>Fuji Ren</location>
<marker>G, </marker>
<rawString>Constituent structure representation of Pashto Endoclitics Azizud Din, Bali Ranaivo-Malançon and M. G. Abbas Malik Real Time Early-stage Influenza Detection with Emotion Factors from Sina Microblog Xiao Sun, Jiaqi Ye and Fuji Ren</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<title>15:45) Coffee Break Session Regular Papers 2: (15:45 - 17:00) WSSANLP Session 3 15:45 Building English-Vietnamese Named Entity Corpus with Aligned Bilingual News Articles Quoc Hung Ngo, Dinh Dien and Werner Winiwarter 16:10 Character-Cluster-Based Segmentation using Monolingual and Bilingual Information for Statistical Machine Translation Vipas Sutantayawalee, Peerachet Porkeaw, Thepchai Supnithi, Prachya Boonkwan and Sitthaa Phaholphinyo</title>
<marker></marker>
<rawString>(15:15 - 15:45) Coffee Break Session Regular Papers 2: (15:45 - 17:00) WSSANLP Session 3 15:45 Building English-Vietnamese Named Entity Corpus with Aligned Bilingual News Articles Quoc Hung Ngo, Dinh Dien and Werner Winiwarter 16:10 Character-Cluster-Based Segmentation using Monolingual and Bilingual Information for Statistical Machine Translation Vipas Sutantayawalee, Peerachet Porkeaw, Thepchai Supnithi, Prachya Boonkwan and Sitthaa Phaholphinyo</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<title>16:35 A rule based approach for automatic clause boundary detection and classification in Hindi Rahul Sharma x</title>
<marker></marker>
<rawString>16:35 A rule based approach for automatic clause boundary detection and classification in Hindi Rahul Sharma x</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Saturday August</author>
</authors>
<date>2014</date>
<note>(continued) (17:00 -17:15) Closing Remarks</note>
<contexts>
<context position="733" citStr="August, 2014" startWordPosition="109" endWordPosition="110"> on South and Southeast Asian NLP WSSANLP - 2014 August 23, 2014 Dublin, Ireland © 2014 The Authors The papers in this volume are licensed by the authors under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License. ISBN 978-1-873769-41-6 Proceedings of the Fifth Workshop on South and Southeast Asian Natural Language Processing Christian Boitet and M.G. Abbas Malik (eds.) ii Preface Welcome to the 5th Workshop on South and Southeast Asian Natural Language Processing (WSSANLP - 2014), a collocated event at the 25th International Conference on Computational Linguistics (COLING 2014) , 23 - 29 August, 2014. South and Southeast Asia comprise of the countries, Afghanistan, Bangladesh, Bhutan, India, Maldives, Nepal, Pakistan and Sri Lanka. Southeast Asia, on the other hand, consists of Brunei, Burma, Cambodia, East Timor, Indonesia, Laos, Malaysia, Philippines, Singapore, Thailand and Vietnam. This area is the home to thousands of languages that belong to different language families like IndoAryan, Indo-Iranian, Dravidian, Sino-Tibetan, Austro-Asiatic, Kradai, Hmong-Mien, etc. In terms of population, South Asian and Southeast Asia represent 35 percent of the total population of the world which me</context>
</contexts>
<marker>August, 2014</marker>
<rawString>Saturday August 23, 2014 (continued) (17:00 -17:15) Closing Remarks</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>