<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="SectLabel" version="110505">
<variant no="0" confidence="0.003529">
<title confidence="0.9983515">
Improving Collocation Correction by Ranking Suggestions
Using Linguistic Knowledge
</title>
<author confidence="0.997155">
Roberto Carlini1, Joan Codina-Filba1, Leo Wanner2,1
</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.785895666666667">
(1) Natural Language Processing Group, Department of Information and Communication Technologies
Pompeu Fabra University, Barcelona
(2) Catalan Institute for Research and Advanced Studies (ICREA)
</affiliation>
<email confidence="0.99722">
roberto.carlini@upf.edu,joan.codina@upf.edu,leo.wanner@upf.edu
</email>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.995224" genericHeader="abstract">
ABSTRACT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99704932">
The importance of collocations in the context of second language learning is generally ac-
knowledged. Studies show that the “collocation density&amp;quot; in learner corpora is nearly the same
as in native corpora, i.e., that use of collocations by learners is as common as it is by native
speakers, while the collocation error rate in learner corpora is about ten times as high as in
native reference corpora. Therefore, CALL could be of great aid to support the learners for better
mastering of collocations. However, surprisingly few works address specifically research on
CALL-oriented collocation learning assistants that detect miscollocations in the writings of the
learners and propose suggestions for their correction or that offer the learner the possibility to
verify a word co-occurrence with respect to its correctness as collocation and obtain suggestions
for its correction in case it is determined to be a miscollocation. This disregard is likely to
be, on the one hand, due to the focus of the CALL research so far on grammatical matters,
and, on the other hand, due to the complexity of the problem. In order to be able to provide
an adequate correction of a miscollocation, the collocation learning assistant must “guess&amp;quot;
the meaning that the learner intended to express. This makes it very different from grammar
or spell checkers, which can draw on grammatical respectively orthographic regularities of a
language. In this paper, we focus on the problem of the provision of a ranked list of correction
suggestions in a context in which the learner submits a collocation for verification and obtains a
list of correction suggestions in the case of a miscollocation. We show that the retrieval of the
suggestions and their ranking benefits greatly from NLP techniques that provide the syntactic
dependency structure and subcategorization information of the word co-occurrences and a
weighted Pointwise Mutual Information (PMI) that reflects the fact that in a collocation, it is
the base that is subject of the free choice of the speaker, while the occurrence of the collocate is
restricted by the base, i.e., that collocations are per se asymmetric.
KEYWORDS: CALL, collocations, miscollocation correction, syntactic dependencies, sub-
categorization, PMI.
</bodyText>
<note confidence="0.994325333333333">
Roberto Carlini, Joan Codina-Filba and Leo Wanner 2014. Improving collocation correction by ranking suggestions using
linguistic knowledge. Proceedings of the third workshop on NLP for computer-assisted language learning. NEALT
Proceedings Series 22 / Linköping Electronic Conference Proceedings 107: 1–12.
</note>
<page confidence="0.978823">
1
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.991278" genericHeader="keywords">
1 Introduction
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999772333333333">
The importance of collocations in the context of second language learning is beyond any doubt;
see, among others, (Granger, 1998; Lewis, 2000; Nesselhauf, 2004, 2005; Lesniewska, 2006;
Alonso Ramos et al., 2010) for studies in this respect. Orol and Alonso Ramos (2013) even show
in their study that the “collocation density&amp;quot; in learner corpora is nearly the same as in native
corpora, i.e., that the use of collocations by learners is as common as it is by native speakers. At
the same time, they also find that the collocation error rate in learner corpora is about 32%
(compared to about 3% by native speakers). That is, Computer Assisted Language Learning
(CALL) could be of great aid to support the learners for better mastering of collocations. However,
surprisingly few works address specifically CALL-oriented collocation learning assistants that
detect miscollocations in the writings of the learners and propose suggestions for their correction
or that offer the learner the possibility to verify using an interactive interface a word co-
occurrence with respect to its correctness as collocation and obtain suggestions for its correction
in case it is determined to be a miscollocation; cf. (Wanner et al., 2013) for an overview. This is
likely to be, on the one hand, due to the focus on grammatical matters that CALL research had
so far, and, on the other hand, due to the complexity of the problem. The problem envisaged by
a collocation learning assistant is that in order to be able to provide an adequate correction of a
miscollocation, it must “guess&amp;quot; the meaning that the learner intended to express. Thus, if the
learner writes assume an exam, we do not know a priori (especially not when the learner uses
an interface for the verification of assume an exam as an isolated word co-occurrence; cf., e.g.,
http://miscollocation-richtrf.rhcloud.com/ for illustration), whether she wants to say take an
exam or pass an exam. This makes collocation checkers very different from grammar or spell
checkers, which can draw on grammatical respectively orthographic regularities of a language.
In what follows, we focus on the problem of the collocation learning assistants of the verification
of isolated word co-occurrences introduced by the learner with respect to their collocation status
and the provision of a ranked list of correction suggestions in case a co-occurrence is considered
to be a miscollocation. In the state-of-the-art proposals, the correction suggestions are ranked
in terms of occurrence frequency or point-wise mutual information (PMI). Both measures do
not take into account the essential linguistic features of collocations, and, in particular, their
dependency structures and subcategorization and their asymmetric nature that results from the
fact that the base element of a collocation is subject of the free choice of the speaker, while the
occurrence of the collocate element is restricted by the base.
In the next section, we introduce the linguistic considerations on collocations that motivate
our proposal. Section 3 presents how we draw upon these linguistic considerations to rank
collocation correction suggestions. Section 4 outlines the experiments we carried out to verify
our proposal, and Section 5 discusses the outcome of these experiments. In Section 6, a short
summary of the related work is presented, before Section 7 draws some conclusions.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.880933" genericHeader="introduction">
2 The Linguistic nature of collocations
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999598">
The term “collocation&amp;quot; as introduced by Firth (1957) and cast into a definition by Halliday
(1961) encompasses the statistical distribution of lexical items in context: lexical items that form
high probability associations are considered collocations. It is this interpretation that underlies
most works on automatic identification of collocations in corpora; see, e.g., (Choueka, 1988;
Church and Hanks, 1989; Pecina, 2008; Evert, 2007; Bouma, 2010). However, in contemporary
lexicography and lexicology an interpretation that stresses the idiosyncratic nature of collocations
prevails. Thus, Benson (1989) states that “collocations should be defined not just as ‘recurrent
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.988295">
2
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999921684210526">
word combinations’, but as ‘ARBITRARY recurrent word combinations’ ”. “Arbitrary” as opposed
to “regular” means that collocations are unpredictable and language-specific. For instance,
in English, one takes a walk, while in French, German and Italian one ‘makes’ it: faire une
promenade, einen Spaziergang machen, fare una passeggiata, and in Spanish one ‘gives’ it: dar
un paseo. In English, one gives a lecture, in German and Italian one ‘holds’ it: eine Vorlesung
halten, tenere una lezione, and in Russian one ‘reads’ it: ˇcitat′ lekciju.
According to Hausmann (1984), Cowie (1994), Mel’ˇcuk (1995) and others, a collocation is a
binary idiosyncratic co-occurrence of lexical items between which a direct syntactic dependency
holds and where the occurrence of one of the items (the base) is subject of the free choice of the
speaker, while the occurrence of the other item (the collocate) is restricted by the base. Thus, in
the case of take [a] walk, walk is the base and take the collocate, in the case of high speed, speed
is the base and high the collocate, etc. It is this understanding of the term “collocation” that we
find reflected in general public collocation dictionaries and that we follow since it seems most
useful in the context of second language acquisition. However, this is not to say that the two
main interpretations of the term “collocation”, the distributional and the idiosyncratic one, are
disjoint, i.e., necessarily lead to a different judgement with respect to the collocation status of a
word combination. On the contrary: two lexical items that form an idiosyncratic co-occurrence
are likely to occur together in a corpus with a high value of Pointwise Mutual Information (PMI)
(Church and Hanks, 1989):
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.98041">
PMI = lo P(a ∩ b) l = lo P(a|b) l = log (1)
g •P(a)P(b)J g • P(a) J g • P(b) ‹
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.999597714285714">
The PMI indicates that if two variables a and b are independent, the probability of their
intersection is the product of their probabilities. A PMI equal to 0 means that the variables are
independent; a positive PMI implies a correlation beyond independence; and a negative PMI
signals that the co-occurrence of the variables is lower than the average. Two lexemes are thus
considered to form a collocation when they have a positive PMI, i.e., they are found together
more often that this would happen if they would be independent variables.
PMI has been a standard collocation measure throughout the literature since Church and
Hank’s proposal in 1989. It can be used not only for collocation detection, but also for ranking
miscollocation correction suggestions: collocations of the base of the miscollocation retrieved
from a reference corpus are ranked such that those with a higher PMI appear higher in the
correction list than those with a lower PMI. Since for lexemes with largely different individual
probabilities (the probabilities can be measured in terms of the number of sentences that contain
these words) the PMIs cannot be compared in magnitude, a normalization has been suggested
by Bouma (2009):
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.9489306">
€ Š
log P(a,b)
P(a)P(b)
NPMICB = (2)
−log P(a, b)
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.8078815">
However, a mere use of PMI, NPMICB or any similar measure does not consider two central
linguistic features of collocations:
1. The lexical dependencies between the base and the collocate are not symmetric, while
PMI is commutative, i.e., PMI(a, b) = PMI(b, a).
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.995677">
3
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.983165">
2. Between the base and the collocate of a collocation, always a direct syntactic dependency
holds whose sub-categorization structure depends on the base (as the semantic head of
the collocation).
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.999049">
2.1 Lexical asymmetry of collocations
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9998295">
Collocations are lexically asymmetrical. Consider, for instance, the collocation take an exam.
The base exam is far less frequent than the collocate take. Thus, if we suppose that in a collection
of 10000 sentences take appears 1000 times, exam 10 times, and take an exam 5 times, we
obtain:
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.992537">
P(take|exam) = 0.5 ≫ 0, 005 = P(exam|take)
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.690385">
with the PMI:
</bodyText>
<listItem confidence="0.769184">
• P(take ∩ exam) ‹ •P(take|exam) ‹ •P(exam|take) ‹
</listItem>
<equation confidence="0.9997325">
PMI = log = log = log (3)
P(take)P(exam) P(take) P(exam)
PMI = log •0 0.00050.50.005
0 .001 ‹ = log •0.1 ‹ = log •0.001 ‹ = log(5)
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.999933666666667">
On the other hand, analyzing the co-occurrence of exam with a less frequent verb such as cheat,
and considering that in the same collection cheat appears 10 times and cheat on an exam 5
times, we obtain:
</bodyText>
<listItem confidence="0.989276">
• P(cheat ∩ exam) ‹ •P(cheat|exam) ‹ •P(exam|cheat) ‹
</listItem>
<equation confidence="0.990683">
PMI = log = log = log
P(cheat)P(exam) P(cheat) P(exam)
0.0005 •0.001 ‹ log •0. 000.50.51 ‹ = log(500)
PMI = log•= log
0.001 · 0.001
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.997231416666667">
In both cases, the PMI is positive, such that we can consider both co-occurrences to be valid
collocations. However, the PMI of take [an] exam is much smaller than the PMI of cheat [on
an] exam. This means that when using the PMI as criterion for ranking collocation suggestions,
take [an] exam is ranked much lower than cheat [on an] exam — although take [an] exam is a
very common collocation and should be ranked higher.
To address this inconvenience, Bouma (2009) normalizes in Eq. (2) the collocation PMI (i.e.,
for PMI &gt; 0) with a neutral (or symmetric) p(collocate ∩ base). However, Eq. (2) does not
compensate the penalization of highly frequent collocates: In general, it can be observed that
when the collocate is a very common word, the NPMICB is still penalized. This is because
NPMICB is symmetric with respect to the base and the collocate.
In order to account for this problem, we propose an asymmetric normalization that uses
p(collocate):
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.894660666666667">
NPMIC = PMI(collocate, base)
(4)
−log(p(collocate))
</equation>
<page confidence="0.961162">
4
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.994793">
Normalizing with p(collocate) and replacing the PMI computed with conditional probabilities,
as done in Eq. ((1)), we obtain:
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.985285">
PMI(collocate, base)
−log(P(collocatel))collocate|
(5a)
log (P(P(colloca te) base) /
= (5b)
−log(P(collocate))
log(P(collocate|base)) −log(P(collocate))
= (5c)
−log(P(collocate))
= −log(P(collocate|base)) +1 (5d)
log(P(collocate))
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.9455715">
= 1 −logP(collocate)(P(collocate|base)) (5e)
In Eq. ((5e)), we can observe that the NPMIC is the logarithm of the conditional probability,
with the probability of the collocate as its base. Figure 1 shows that in the interval [0,1], NPMIC
is always above NPMICB. Furthermore, NPMIC is much less influenced by high frequencies
of the collocate. In the next sections, we will analyze how this changes the ratings of the
collocation correction suggestions in some sample cases.
Figure 1: Graph showing the differences between the NPMIC (continuous line) and
NPMICB (dashed line). Each line shows the variation of the NPMI for different values of
p(collocate|base) as the probability of the collocate changes, given a probability of the base of
10−10.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.998496">
2.2 Syntactic dependencies in collocations
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9994825">
As argued in lexicography (see the citations above), an essential feature of a collocation is that
a direct dependency holds between the base and the collocate. Thus, in take [a ] walk as in I
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.879916">
NPMIC =
</equation>
<page confidence="0.876653">
5
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.9991276875">
took a walk with Mary, the base walk is the direct object of the collocate take. In contrast, in
Wexford followed him through the pleached walk and they entered the house by a glazed garden
door,1 pleached is a participle modifier of walk. It may thus be considered as an adjective–noun
collocation, but not as a verb–direct object collocation pleach [a] walk — as assumed by the
MUST collocation checker.
In I enjoyed the privacy during my walk with Mary, enjoy and walk cannot form a collocation at
all, even if they may have a rather high PMI, because there is no direct syntactic dependency
between them.
Apart from syntactic dependencies, the sub-categorization information of the base must be
considered. We say applyfor [a] job, apply to college and apply [a] theory; nominate for presidency,
and nominate [the] candidate; and so on. Governed prepositions must be clearly distinguished
from semantically full prepositions; cf. to in go to the concert or through in drive through the city.
That is, when searching for correction suggestions for a given miscollocation, we need to be
aware that a collocation is not a mere prominent co-occurrence of words, as argued in early
works in the field; see, e.g., (Choueka, 1988; Church and Hanks, 1989). Rather, it implies
dependency information that needs to be taken into account.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.82723" genericHeader="method">
3 Ranking of Collocation Suggestions
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9998347">
The basic source that allows us to check a sequence of words provided by the user for its
collocation status and to come up with corrections suggestions is a large reference dependency
treebank. For each pair of POS-tagged tokens between which a relevant dependency relation
holds, the PMI, NPMICB and NPMIC are calculated; proper nouns, determiners, conjunctions,
numerals, etc. are excluded. As “relevant&amp;quot;, we consider relations that have been observed to
hold between collocation elements; the most prominent of them are: direct object, indirect
object, subject, modifier, and adverbial. When the noun is not a direct dependant of the verb
because there is a preposition in between, the preposition is considered part of the relation.
In order to check the validity of a word combination introduced by the user as collocation and
to propose correction suggestions for a miscollocation, the following procedure is followed:
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.379814" genericHeader="method">
1. Check the NPMIC value of the combination in the database:
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.88833225">
(a) If the combination is found in the reference corpus, the collocation is considered
correct or wrong depending on whether the NPMIC value is positive or negative
respectively.
(b) If the combination does not exist in the reference corpus, we consider its elements
as mutually exclusive and, accordingly, the combination as a miscollocation.2
2. If the collocation is considered wrong, we attempt to find candidate suggestions for its
correction: any valid combination with the base or the collocate of the miscollocation that
fits the dependency profile of the miscollocation are retrieved from the corpus.
</bodyText>
<footnote confidence="0.92221">
1Example offered by the MUST collocation checker (http://miscollocation-richtrf.rhcloud.com/) on October, 1st
2014 for pleach walk, which has been proposed by MUST as one of the collocations the learner should consider along
with take [a] walk.
2This criterion can be improved by checking whether the individual words exist in the reference corpus. If the
collocate or the base are missing, we could pre-calculate PMI values using semantic information from EuroWordNet
and search for the missing word using its hypernym.
</footnote>
<page confidence="0.997375">
6
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.96271875">
3. Retrieved candidate suggestions are ranked according to their NPMIC. Only the first
items of the list are shown, but the user can ask to go down in the list. Also, the user can
solicit sample sentences from the corpus in which the corresponding collocation occurs
(as in the MUST collocation checker) to help them to understand the correct use of it.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.999014" genericHeader="method">
4 Experiments
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999510083333333">
In order to validate our model, we carried out experiments on Spanish material, taking as
starting point some miscollocations with the bases siesta ‘nap’ (Table 1), meta ‘finish line , target,
objective, goal, goalkeeper’ (Table 3), examen ‘exam’ (Table 2) , and teléfono ‘phone’ (Table 4)
from the learner corpus CEDEL2 (Lozano, 2009). As reference treebank, we use a treebank
of Spanish newspaper material. The sentences of the treebank are indexed in a Solr (Lucene)
index for more efficient access. The index allows us to retrieve directly the list of tokens, the list
of lemmas and all the tokens related with another token by a given relation type. It is also used
to retrieve examples to be shown to the user.
The table of each base lists the most common collocates, indicating the frequencies in the corpus,
the PMI, NPMICB and NPMIC; for meta the table contains two parts, a list for meta acting as
direct object and another for meta being the subject. That is, the tables can be considered as
ranked lists of collocation suggestions.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.990962666666667">
collocate FreqC FreqCB PMI NPMICB NPMIC
dormir 612 69 3,611 0,716 0,881
echar 5847 42 2,415 0,459 0,775
hacer 165124 18 0,597 0,106 0,358
estar 13349 3 0,911 0,142 0,33
haber 149464 9 0,339 0,057 0,198
Table 1: Table of PMI and normalized PMIs for the base siesta.
collocate FreqC FreqCB PMI NPMICB NPMIC
pasar 23170 228 1,69 0,373 0,671
superar 19861 119 1,475 0,307 0,57
aprobar 12676 82 1,508 0,303 0,542
realizar 28999 99 1,231 0,252 0,508
suspender 6241 32 1,407 0,262 0,455
preparar 11526 35 1,18 0,221 0,418
someter 1927 11 1,454 0,249 0,404
hacer 165124 139 0,623 0,131 0,373
ordenar 6494 15 1,061 0,186 0,345
terminar 4906 11 1,048 0,179 0,328
efectuar 4909 11 1,048 0,179 0,328
practicar 5091 11 1,032 0,177 0,325
afrontar 8994 11 0,785 0,134 0,268
</table>
<tableCaption confidence="0.999727">
Table 2: Table of PMI and normalized PMIs for the base examen.
</tableCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.6903235">
The miscollocations have been entered in sequence via an interface comparable to the MUST
collocation checker (http://miscollocation.appspot.com/).
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.99911">
7
</page>
<table confidence="0.99996608">
collocate FreqC FreqCB PMI NPMICB NPMIC
cruzar1 4608 223 2,442 0,538 0,758
alcanzar1 25412 227 1,708 0,377 0,689
fijar3 8803 43 1,446 0,275 0,492
batir2 2066 17 1,672 0,296 0,468
perforar2 217 5 2,12 0,343 0,466
lograr2 3 21357 50 1,126 0,217 0,441
conseguir 25486 50 1,05 0,202 0,423
regatear2 342 3 1,7 0,265 0,391
encarar2 1200 6 1,456 0,238 0,383
inquietar2 520 3 1,518 0,237 0,364
marcar2 15636 26 0,978 0,179 0,363
cumplir3 19295 26 0,887 0,162 0,341
perseguir3 3462 8 1,121 0,187 0,335
rebasar3 958 3 1,253 0,195 0,321
conquistar3 2033 5 1,148 0,186 0,321
collocate FreqC FreqCB PMI NPMICB NPMIC
ser1,2,3,4 784559 388 0,558 0,13 0,564
desviar4 532 6 1,917 0,314 0,461
parar4 1999 6 1,342 0,22 0,374
salvar4 2045 6 1,332 0,218 0,373
alcanzar3,4 11168 15 0,992 0,174 0,35
estar1,2,3,4 171062 80 0,534 0,107 0,323
fijar3 3394 5 1,033 0,167 0,308
tocar4 3227 4 0,958 0,152 0,284
</table>
<tableCaption confidence="0.959465">
Table 3: Table of PMI and normalized PMIs for the base meta. The upper part of the table
captures the figures for meta as direct object and the lower part for meta as subject. Each
collocate corresponds to a given sense of meta: ‘1’ stands for ‘the finish line’ , ‘2’ for ‘goal’ in
football, ‘3’ for ‘objective’ and ‘4’ for ‘goalkeeper’.
</tableCaption>
<table confidence="0.999913307692308">
collocate FreqC FreqCB PMI NPMICB NPMIC
pinchar 403 77 2,789 0,558 0,652
descolgar 230 61 2,931 0,575 0,648
sonar 2218 105 2,183 0,449 0,617
coger 4627 123 1,932 0,403 0,6
intervenir 1294 55 2,136 0,415 0,566
colgar 1723 61 2,057 0,403 0,564
llamar 12957 111 1,44 0,298 0,519
desconectar 234 14 2,285 0,398 0,506
contestar 3066 41 1,634 0,31 0,481
atender 8563 57 1,331 0,259 0,451
usar 6286 46 1,372 0,263 0,444
habilitar 760 14 1,773 0,309 0,443
</table>
<tableCaption confidence="0.9998">
Table 4: Table of PMI and normalized PMIs for the base teléfono.
</tableCaption>
<page confidence="0.998805">
8
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.997652" genericHeader="method">
5 Discussion
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999939958333333">
In the tables, we can appreciate the differences produced by the different measures used to
calculate the co-occurrence strength between the collocation elements. The main differences
occur with verbs that are very common, such as hacer ‘[to] make’ as collocate of siesta or examen.
In both cases, NPMIC considers it more important than other verbs. Thus, PMI and NPMICB
rank hacer in co-occurrence with examen as lowest (0.623 respectively 0,131), while NPMIC
keeps it in the middle of the table, ranking it higher than efectuar ‘[to] effect’ or afrontar ‘[to]
face’, which are much less common (which makes the NPMIC ranking more appropriate).
In co-occurrence with the base teléfono, the verb llamar ‘[to] call’ appears in the middle of the
list when ranked by NPMIC, while when ranked by PMI or NPMICB it appears down in the
least, even if it is almost the most common collocate of phone (5% of the cases).
Table 3 shows that the verb ser ‘[to] be’ is the most common (33 of the cases) for meta as
subject; the NPMIC upgrades it, ranking it higher, even if is a very common verb and has a
low PMI. Looking at the list, we see that there is also estar ‘[to] be’ with similar PMI. However,
NPMIC does not promote it. Analyzing the data more deeply, we can observe that p(meta|ser)
∼ p(meta|estar), but p(ser|meta) ≫ p(estar|meta). That is, the penalization of estar by NPMIC
is correct.
The tables show the relationship between the base and the collocate when the collocate is a verb
and the base its direct object. When the base is subject (or a different kind of object), different
collocations may appear. Table 3 shows that when the base meta has a different grammatical
function in the sentence, it often also has a different sense. It tends to mean ‘goal’, ‘finish line’ or
‘objective’ when is the direct object, but when appears as subject it often stands for ‘goalkeeper’.
There are some coincidences between the two lists of verbs in Table 3. This is because of their
use as both passive and active. For the moment, we do not make any distinction between passive
and active forms.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.999862" genericHeader="method">
6 Related Work
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999551176470588">
A number of works deal with detection of miscollocations and collocation error correction in
learners’ writings. However, only a few allow for the validation of isolated word co-occurrences
with respect to their collocation status and provide ranked lists of correction suggestions.
One of them is (Chang et al., 2008). They check a V–N co-occurrence provided by a learner
against a collocation list obtained before from a reference corpus. Co-occurrences not found in
this collocation list are variegated in that their verbal elements are substituted by all English
translations of their L1 (Chinese, in this case) counterpart in an electronic dictionary. The
variants are again matched against the collocation list. The finally matching co-occurrences
that contain the noun of a non-matching co-occurrence are offered as correction suggestions.
The Mutual Reciprocal Rank (MRR) of the correction list is reported to reach 0.66.
Dahlmeier and Ng (2011), who deal with the detection of miscollocations in writings also
exploits L1 interference in learners. They work with confusion sets of semantically similar
words. Given an input text in L2, they generate L1 paraphrases, which are then looked up in a
large parallel corpus to obtain the most likely L2 co-occurrences. For this strategy, they report a
precision of 38%.
Futagi et al. (2008) target the detection of miscollocations in learner texts, leaving the correction
aside. Unlike the above proposals, they are not restricted to V+N co-occurrences. But similar
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.992837">
9
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999612103448276">
to (Chang et al., 2008), they extract the co-occurrences from a learner text, variegate them
and then look up the original co-occurrence and its variants in a reference list to decide on its
status. To obtain the variants, they apply spell checking, vary articles and inflections and use
WordNet to retrieve synonyms of the collocate. Wu et al. (2010) use a classifier to provide a
number of collocate corrections. The classifier takes the learner sentence as lexical context.
The probability predicted by the classifier for each suggestion is used to rank the suggestions.
According to the evaluation included in (Wu et al., 2010), an MRR of 0.518 for the first five
correction suggestions has been achieved. Liu et al. (2009) retrieve miscollocation correction
suggestions from a reference corpus using three metrics: (i) mutual information (Church and
Hanks, 1989), (ii) semantic similarity of an incorrect collocate to other potential collocates
based on their distance in WordNet, and (iii) the membership of the incorrect collocate with a
potential correct collocate in the same “collocation cluster’”. A combination of (ii)+(iii) leads
to the best precision achieved for the suggestion of a correction: 55.95%. A combination of
(i)+(ii)+(iii) leads to the best precision of 85.71% when a list of five possible corrections is
returned.
Ferraro et al. (2014) suggest a two stage strategy for correction of miscollocations in Spanish.
The first stage is rather similar to the one proposed by Futagi et al. (2008): it retrieves the
synonyms of the collocate in the miscollocation in question from a number of auxiliary resources
(including thesauri, bilingual L1-L2 dictionaries, etc.) and combines them with the base of the
miscollocation to candidate corrections. The candidate corrections that are valid collocations of
Spanish are returned as correction suggestions. If none of them is, the second stage applies a
metric to retrieve correction suggestions. Three metrics have been experimented with: affinity
metric, lexical context metric and context feature metric. The context feature metric, which
uses the contextual features of the miscollocation (tokens, PoS tags, punctuation, grammatical
functions, etc.), performed best in that it achieved an MRR of the top five suggestions of 0.72.
However, none of the above mentioned works considers in detail the asymmetric nature of
collocations as captured by NPMIC and none of them takes into account that the co-occurrence
strength between tokens (as captured by the (normalized) PMIs) needs to be calculated
differentiating between different dependency relations and different sub-categorization frames.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.999235" genericHeader="conclusions">
7 Conclusions
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9993456">
In this paper, we have shown that the asymmetric nature of collocations requires an “asymmetric&amp;quot;
normalization of the commonly used PMI measure and that any co-occurrence measure should
be applied to co-occurrences of the same syntactic profile, i.e., with the same syntactic depen-
dency relation and the same sub-categorization frame. The consideration of these characteristics
of collocations allows for a more accurate ranking of correction suggestions for miscollocations.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.998813" genericHeader="acknowledgments">
Acknowledgments
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99844375">
The work presented in this paper has been supported by the Spanish Ministry of Economy and
Competitiveness under the contract number FFI2011-30219-C02-02 in the framework of the
HARENES Project, carried out in collaboration with the DICE Group of the University of La
Coruña.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998027">
10
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.996378" genericHeader="references">
References
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.998393702702703">
Alonso Ramos, M., Wanner, L., Vincze, O., Casamayor, G., Vázquez, N., Mosqueira, E., and
Prieto, S. (2010). Towards a motivated annotation schema of collocation errors in learner
corpora. In Proceedings of the 7th International Conference on Language Resources and Evaluation
(LREC), pages 3209–3214, La Valetta, Malta.
Benson, M. (1989). The structure of the collocational dictionary. International Journal of
Lexicography, 2(1):1–13.
Bouma, G. (2009). Normalized (pointwise) mutual information in collocation extraction. In
Chiarcos, C., Eckart de Castilho, R., and Stede, M., editors, Von der Form zur Bedeutung: Texte
automatisch verarbeiten /From Form to Meaning: Processing Texts Automatically. Proceedings of
the Biennial GSCL Conference, pages 31–40. Gunter Narr Verlag, Tübingen.
Bouma, G. (2010). Collocation extraction beyond the independence assumption. In Proceedings
of the ACL 2010, Short paper track, Uppsala.
Chang, Y., Chang, J., Chen, H., and Liou, H. (2008). An Automatic Collocation Writing
Assistant for Taiwanese EFL learners. A case of Corpus Based NLP Technology. Computer
Assisted Language Learning, 21(3):283–299.
Choueka, Y. (1988). Looking for needles in a haystack or locating interesting collocational
expressions in large textual databases. In In Proceedings of the RIAO, pages 34–38.
Church, K. and Hanks, P. (1989). Word Association Norms, Mutual Information, and Lexicog-
raphy. In Proceedings of the 27th Annual Meeting of the ACL, pages 76–83.
Cowie, A. (1994). Phraseology. In Asher, R. and Simpson, J., editors, The Encyclopedia of
Language and Linguistics, Vol. 6, pages 3168–3171. Pergamon, Oxford.
Dahlmeier, D. and Ng, H. (2011). Correcting semantic collocation errors with L1-induced
paraphrases. In Proceedings of the 2011 Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language
Processing, pages 107–117, Edinburgh, Scotland.
Evert, S. (2007). Corpora and collocations. In Lüdeling, A. and Kytö, M., editors, Corpus
Linguistics. An International Handbook. Mouton de Gruyter, Berlin.
Ferraro, G., Nazar, R., Ramos, M. A., and Wanner, L. (2014). Towards advanced collocation
error correction in Spanish learner corpora. Language Resources and Evaluation, 48(1):45–64.
Firth, J. (1957). Modes of meaning. In Firth, J., editor, Papers in Linguistics, 1934-1951, pages
190–215. Oxford University Press, Oxford.
Futagi, Y., Deane, P., Chodorow, M., and Tetreault, J. (2008). A computational approach to
detecting collocation errors in the writing of non-native speakers of English. Computer Assisted
Language Learning, 21(1):353–367.
Granger, S. (1998). Prefabricated patterns in advanced EFL writing: Collocations and Formulae.
In Cowie, A., editor, Phraseology: Theory, Analysis and Applications, pages 145–160. Oxford
University Press, Oxford.
Halliday, M. (1961). Categories of the theory of grammar. Word, 17:241–292.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.990676">
11
</page>
<reference confidence="0.9964083125">
Hausmann, F.-J. (1984). Wortschatzlernen ist kollokationslernen. zum lehren und lernen
französischer wortwendungen. Praxis des neusprachlichen Unterrichts, 31(1):395–406.
Lesniewska, J. (2006). Collocations and second language use. Studia Lingüística Universitatis
lagellonicae Cracoviensis, 123:95–105.
Lewis, M. (2000). Teaching Collocation. Further Developments in the Lexical Approach. LTP,
London.
Liu, A. L.-E., Wible, D., and Tsao, N.-L. (2009). Automated suggestions for miscollocations.
In Proceedings of the NAACL HLT Workshop on Innovative Use of NLP for Building Educational
Applications, pages 47–50, Boulder, CO.
Lozano, C. (2009). CEDEL2: Corpus escrito del español L2. In Bretones Callejas, C., editor,
Applied Linguistics Now: Understanding Language and Mind, pages 197–212. Universidad de
Almería, Almería.
Mel’ˇcuk, I. (1995). Phrasemes in Language and Phraseology in Linguistics. In Everaert, M.,
van der Linden, E.-J., Schenk, A., and Schreuder, R., editors, Idioms: Structural and Psychological
Perspectives, pages 167–232. Lawrence Erlbaum Associates, Hillsdale.
Nesselhauf, N. (2004). How learner corpus analysis can contribute to language teaching: A
study of support verb constructions. In Aston, G., Bernardini, S., and Stewart, D., editors,
Corpora and language learners, pages 109–124. Benjamins Academic Publishers, Amsterdam.
Nesselhauf, N. (2005). Collocations in a Learner Corpus. Benjamins Academic Publishers,
Amsterdam.
Orol, A. and Alonso Ramos, M. (2013). A Comparative Study of Collocations in a Native Corpus
and a Learner Corpus of Spanish. Procedia–Social and Behavioural Sciences, 96:563–570.
Pecina, P. (2008). A machine learning approach to multiword expression extraction. In
Proceedings of the LREC 2008 Workshop Towards a Shared Task for Multiword Expressions (MWE
2008), pages 54–57, Marrakech.
Wanner, L., Verlinde, S., and Alonso Ramos, M. (2013). Writing assistants and automatic lexical
error correction: word combinatorics. In Kosem, I., Kallas, J., Gantar, P., Krek, S., Langemets,
M., and Tuulik, M., editors, Electronic lexicography in the 21st century: Thinking outside the
paper. Proceedings of the eLex 2013 conference, pages 472–487, Tallinn &amp; Ljubljana. Trojina,
Institute for Applied Slovene Studies &amp; Eesti Keele Instituut.
Wu, J.-C., Chang, Y.-C., Mitamura, T., and Chang, J. (2010). Automatic collocation suggestion
in academic writing. In Proceedings of the ACL Conference, Short paper track, Uppsala.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.998458">
12
</page>
</variant>
</algorithm>
<algorithm name="ParsHed" version="110505">
<variant no="0" confidence="0.169199">
<title confidence="0.9995545">Improving Collocation Correction by Ranking Using Linguistic Knowledge</title>
<author confidence="0.99992">Joan Leo</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.841966">(1) Natural Language Processing Group, Department of Information and Communication Technologies Pompeu Fabra University, Barcelona</affiliation>
<abstract confidence="0.982485428571429">(2) Catalan Institute for Research and Advanced Studies (ICREA) The importance of collocations in the context of second language learning is generally acknowledged. Studies show that the “collocation density&amp;quot; in learner corpora is nearly the same as in native corpora, i.e., that use of collocations by learners is as common as it is by native speakers, while the collocation error rate in learner corpora is about ten times as high as in native reference corpora. Therefore, CALL could be of great aid to support the learners for better mastering of collocations. However, surprisingly few works address specifically research on CALL-oriented collocation learning assistants that detect miscollocations in the writings of the learners and propose suggestions for their correction or that offer the learner the possibility to verify a word co-occurrence with respect to its correctness as collocation and obtain suggestions for its correction in case it is determined to be a miscollocation. This disregard is likely to be, on the one hand, due to the focus of the CALL research so far on grammatical matters, and, on the other hand, due to the complexity of the problem. In order to be able to provide an adequate correction of a miscollocation, the collocation learning assistant must “guess&amp;quot; the meaning that the learner intended to express. This makes it very different from grammar or spell checkers, which can draw on grammatical respectively orthographic regularities of a language. In this paper, we focus on the problem of the provision of a ranked list of correction suggestions in a context in which the learner submits a collocation for verification and obtains a list of correction suggestions in the case of a miscollocation. We show that the retrieval of the suggestions and their ranking benefits greatly from NLP techniques that provide the syntactic dependency structure and subcategorization information of the word co-occurrences and a weighted Pointwise Mutual Information (PMI) that reflects the fact that in a collocation, it is the base that is subject of the free choice of the speaker, while the occurrence of the collocate is restricted by the base, i.e., that collocations are per se asymmetric. collocations, miscollocation correction, syntactic dependencies, subcategorization, PMI. Roberto Carlini, Joan Codina-Filba and Leo Wanner 2014. Improving collocation correction by ranking suggestions using knowledge. of the third workshop on NLP for computer-assisted language learning.</abstract>
<note confidence="0.623849">Proceedings Series 22 / Linköping Electronic Conference Proceedings 107: 1–12. 1</note>
</variant>
</algorithm>
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Alonso Ramos</author>
<author>M Wanner</author>
<author>L Vincze</author>
<author>O Casamayor</author>
<author>G Vázquez</author>
<author>N Mosqueira</author>
<author>E</author>
<author>S Prieto</author>
</authors>
<title>Towards a motivated annotation schema of collocation errors in learner corpora.</title>
<date>2010</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 7th International Conference on Language Resources and Evaluation (LREC),</booktitle>
<pages>3209--3214</pages>
<location>La Valetta,</location>
<contexts>
<context position="3202" citStr="Ramos et al., 2010" startWordPosition="467" endWordPosition="470">cations, miscollocation correction, syntactic dependencies, subcategorization, PMI. Roberto Carlini, Joan Codina-Filba and Leo Wanner 2014. Improving collocation correction by ranking suggestions using linguistic knowledge. Proceedings of the third workshop on NLP for computer-assisted language learning. NEALT Proceedings Series 22 / Linköping Electronic Conference Proceedings 107: 1–12. 1 1 Introduction The importance of collocations in the context of second language learning is beyond any doubt; see, among others, (Granger, 1998; Lewis, 2000; Nesselhauf, 2004, 2005; Lesniewska, 2006; Alonso Ramos et al., 2010) for studies in this respect. Orol and Alonso Ramos (2013) even show in their study that the “collocation density&amp;quot; in learner corpora is nearly the same as in native corpora, i.e., that the use of collocations by learners is as common as it is by native speakers. At the same time, they also find that the collocation error rate in learner corpora is about 32% (compared to about 3% by native speakers). That is, Computer Assisted Language Learning (CALL) could be of great aid to support the learners for better mastering of collocations. However, surprisingly few works address specifically CALL-or</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Ramos, Wanner, Vincze, Casamayor, Vázquez, Mosqueira, E, Prieto, 2010</marker>
<rawString>Alonso Ramos, M., Wanner, L., Vincze, O., Casamayor, G., Vázquez, N., Mosqueira, E., and Prieto, S. (2010). Towards a motivated annotation schema of collocation errors in learner corpora. In Proceedings of the 7th International Conference on Language Resources and Evaluation (LREC), pages 3209–3214, La Valetta, Malta.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M Benson</author>
</authors>
<title>The structure of the collocational dictionary.</title>
<date>1989</date>
<journal>International Journal of Lexicography,</journal>
<volume>2</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<contexts>
<context position="7038" citStr="Benson (1989)" startWordPosition="1060" endWordPosition="1061">tions The term “collocation&amp;quot; as introduced by Firth (1957) and cast into a definition by Halliday (1961) encompasses the statistical distribution of lexical items in context: lexical items that form high probability associations are considered collocations. It is this interpretation that underlies most works on automatic identification of collocations in corpora; see, e.g., (Choueka, 1988; Church and Hanks, 1989; Pecina, 2008; Evert, 2007; Bouma, 2010). However, in contemporary lexicography and lexicology an interpretation that stresses the idiosyncratic nature of collocations prevails. Thus, Benson (1989) states that “collocations should be defined not just as ‘recurrent 2 word combinations’, but as ‘ARBITRARY recurrent word combinations’ ”. “Arbitrary” as opposed to “regular” means that collocations are unpredictable and language-specific. For instance, in English, one takes a walk, while in French, German and Italian one ‘makes’ it: faire une promenade, einen Spaziergang machen, fare una passeggiata, and in Spanish one ‘gives’ it: dar un paseo. In English, one gives a lecture, in German and Italian one ‘holds’ it: eine Vorlesung halten, tenere una lezione, and in Russian one ‘reads’ it: ˇcit</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Benson, 1989</marker>
<rawString>Benson, M. (1989). The structure of the collocational dictionary. International Journal of Lexicography, 2(1):1–13.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>G Bouma</author>
</authors>
<title>Normalized (pointwise) mutual information in collocation extraction.</title>
<date>2009</date>
<booktitle>Von der Form zur Bedeutung: Texte automatisch verarbeiten /From Form to Meaning: Processing Texts Automatically. Proceedings of the Biennial GSCL Conference,</booktitle>
<pages>31--40</pages>
<editor>In Chiarcos, C., Eckart de Castilho, R., and Stede, M., editors,</editor>
<publisher>Gunter Narr Verlag,</publisher>
<location>Tübingen.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="10138" citStr="Bouma (2009)" startWordPosition="1570" endWordPosition="1571"> literature since Church and Hank’s proposal in 1989. It can be used not only for collocation detection, but also for ranking miscollocation correction suggestions: collocations of the base of the miscollocation retrieved from a reference corpus are ranked such that those with a higher PMI appear higher in the correction list than those with a lower PMI. Since for lexemes with largely different individual probabilities (the probabilities can be measured in terms of the number of sentences that contain these words) the PMIs cannot be compared in magnitude, a normalization has been suggested by Bouma (2009): € Š log P(a,b) P(a)P(b) NPMICB = (2) −log P(a, b) However, a mere use of PMI, NPMICB or any similar measure does not consider two central linguistic features of collocations: 1. The lexical dependencies between the base and the collocate are not symmetric, while PMI is commutative, i.e., PMI(a, b) = PMI(b, a). 3 2. Between the base and the collocate of a collocation, always a direct syntactic dependency holds whose sub-categorization structure depends on the base (as the semantic head of the collocation). 2.1 Lexical asymmetry of collocations Collocations are lexically asymmetrical. Consider</context>
<context position="12077" citStr="Bouma (2009)" startWordPosition="1912" endWordPosition="1913">xam|cheat) ‹ PMI = log = log = log P(cheat)P(exam) P(cheat) P(exam) 0.0005 •0.001 ‹ log •0. 000.50.51 ‹ = log(500) PMI = log•= log 0.001 · 0.001 In both cases, the PMI is positive, such that we can consider both co-occurrences to be valid collocations. However, the PMI of take [an] exam is much smaller than the PMI of cheat [on an] exam. This means that when using the PMI as criterion for ranking collocation suggestions, take [an] exam is ranked much lower than cheat [on an] exam — although take [an] exam is a very common collocation and should be ranked higher. To address this inconvenience, Bouma (2009) normalizes in Eq. (2) the collocation PMI (i.e., for PMI &gt; 0) with a neutral (or symmetric) p(collocate ∩ base). However, Eq. (2) does not compensate the penalization of highly frequent collocates: In general, it can be observed that when the collocate is a very common word, the NPMICB is still penalized. This is because NPMICB is symmetric with respect to the base and the collocate. In order to account for this problem, we propose an asymmetric normalization that uses p(collocate): NPMIC = PMI(collocate, base) (4) −log(p(collocate)) 4 Normalizing with p(collocate) and replacing the PMI compu</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Bouma, 2009</marker>
<rawString>Bouma, G. (2009). Normalized (pointwise) mutual information in collocation extraction. In Chiarcos, C., Eckart de Castilho, R., and Stede, M., editors, Von der Form zur Bedeutung: Texte automatisch verarbeiten /From Form to Meaning: Processing Texts Automatically. Proceedings of the Biennial GSCL Conference, pages 31–40. Gunter Narr Verlag, Tübingen.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>G Bouma</author>
</authors>
<title>Collocation extraction beyond the independence assumption.</title>
<date>2010</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the ACL 2010, Short paper track,</booktitle>
<location>Uppsala.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="6881" citStr="Bouma, 2010" startWordPosition="1041" endWordPosition="1042">ese experiments. In Section 6, a short summary of the related work is presented, before Section 7 draws some conclusions. 2 The Linguistic nature of collocations The term “collocation&amp;quot; as introduced by Firth (1957) and cast into a definition by Halliday (1961) encompasses the statistical distribution of lexical items in context: lexical items that form high probability associations are considered collocations. It is this interpretation that underlies most works on automatic identification of collocations in corpora; see, e.g., (Choueka, 1988; Church and Hanks, 1989; Pecina, 2008; Evert, 2007; Bouma, 2010). However, in contemporary lexicography and lexicology an interpretation that stresses the idiosyncratic nature of collocations prevails. Thus, Benson (1989) states that “collocations should be defined not just as ‘recurrent 2 word combinations’, but as ‘ARBITRARY recurrent word combinations’ ”. “Arbitrary” as opposed to “regular” means that collocations are unpredictable and language-specific. For instance, in English, one takes a walk, while in French, German and Italian one ‘makes’ it: faire une promenade, einen Spaziergang machen, fare una passeggiata, and in Spanish one ‘gives’ it: dar un</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Bouma, 2010</marker>
<rawString>Bouma, G. (2010). Collocation extraction beyond the independence assumption. In Proceedings of the ACL 2010, Short paper track, Uppsala.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Y Chang</author>
<author>J Chang</author>
<author>H Chen</author>
<author>H Liou</author>
</authors>
<title>An Automatic Collocation Writing Assistant for Taiwanese EFL learners. A case of Corpus Based</title>
<date>2008</date>
<journal>NLP Technology. Computer Assisted Language Learning,</journal>
<volume>21</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<contexts>
<context position="24017" citStr="Chang et al., 2008" startWordPosition="3878" endWordPosition="3881">direct object, but when appears as subject it often stands for ‘goalkeeper’. There are some coincidences between the two lists of verbs in Table 3. This is because of their use as both passive and active. For the moment, we do not make any distinction between passive and active forms. 6 Related Work A number of works deal with detection of miscollocations and collocation error correction in learners’ writings. However, only a few allow for the validation of isolated word co-occurrences with respect to their collocation status and provide ranked lists of correction suggestions. One of them is (Chang et al., 2008). They check a V–N co-occurrence provided by a learner against a collocation list obtained before from a reference corpus. Co-occurrences not found in this collocation list are variegated in that their verbal elements are substituted by all English translations of their L1 (Chinese, in this case) counterpart in an electronic dictionary. The variants are again matched against the collocation list. The finally matching co-occurrences that contain the noun of a non-matching co-occurrence are offered as correction suggestions. The Mutual Reciprocal Rank (MRR) of the correction list is reported to </context>
<context position="25243" citStr="Chang et al., 2008" startWordPosition="4068" endWordPosition="4071">.66. Dahlmeier and Ng (2011), who deal with the detection of miscollocations in writings also exploits L1 interference in learners. They work with confusion sets of semantically similar words. Given an input text in L2, they generate L1 paraphrases, which are then looked up in a large parallel corpus to obtain the most likely L2 co-occurrences. For this strategy, they report a precision of 38%. Futagi et al. (2008) target the detection of miscollocations in learner texts, leaving the correction aside. Unlike the above proposals, they are not restricted to V+N co-occurrences. But similar 9 to (Chang et al., 2008), they extract the co-occurrences from a learner text, variegate them and then look up the original co-occurrence and its variants in a reference list to decide on its status. To obtain the variants, they apply spell checking, vary articles and inflections and use WordNet to retrieve synonyms of the collocate. Wu et al. (2010) use a classifier to provide a number of collocate corrections. The classifier takes the learner sentence as lexical context. The probability predicted by the classifier for each suggestion is used to rank the suggestions. According to the evaluation included in (Wu et al</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Chang, Chang, Chen, Liou, 2008</marker>
<rawString>Chang, Y., Chang, J., Chen, H., and Liou, H. (2008). An Automatic Collocation Writing Assistant for Taiwanese EFL learners. A case of Corpus Based NLP Technology. Computer Assisted Language Learning, 21(3):283–299.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Y Choueka</author>
</authors>
<title>Looking for needles in a haystack or locating interesting collocational expressions in large textual databases. In</title>
<date>1988</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the RIAO,</booktitle>
<pages>34--38</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="6816" citStr="Choueka, 1988" startWordPosition="1031" endWordPosition="1032"> to verify our proposal, and Section 5 discusses the outcome of these experiments. In Section 6, a short summary of the related work is presented, before Section 7 draws some conclusions. 2 The Linguistic nature of collocations The term “collocation&amp;quot; as introduced by Firth (1957) and cast into a definition by Halliday (1961) encompasses the statistical distribution of lexical items in context: lexical items that form high probability associations are considered collocations. It is this interpretation that underlies most works on automatic identification of collocations in corpora; see, e.g., (Choueka, 1988; Church and Hanks, 1989; Pecina, 2008; Evert, 2007; Bouma, 2010). However, in contemporary lexicography and lexicology an interpretation that stresses the idiosyncratic nature of collocations prevails. Thus, Benson (1989) states that “collocations should be defined not just as ‘recurrent 2 word combinations’, but as ‘ARBITRARY recurrent word combinations’ ”. “Arbitrary” as opposed to “regular” means that collocations are unpredictable and language-specific. For instance, in English, one takes a walk, while in French, German and Italian one ‘makes’ it: faire une promenade, einen Spaziergang ma</context>
<context position="15197" citStr="Choueka, 1988" startWordPosition="2406" endWordPosition="2407">t from syntactic dependencies, the sub-categorization information of the base must be considered. We say applyfor [a] job, apply to college and apply [a] theory; nominate for presidency, and nominate [the] candidate; and so on. Governed prepositions must be clearly distinguished from semantically full prepositions; cf. to in go to the concert or through in drive through the city. That is, when searching for correction suggestions for a given miscollocation, we need to be aware that a collocation is not a mere prominent co-occurrence of words, as argued in early works in the field; see, e.g., (Choueka, 1988; Church and Hanks, 1989). Rather, it implies dependency information that needs to be taken into account. 3 Ranking of Collocation Suggestions The basic source that allows us to check a sequence of words provided by the user for its collocation status and to come up with corrections suggestions is a large reference dependency treebank. For each pair of POS-tagged tokens between which a relevant dependency relation holds, the PMI, NPMICB and NPMIC are calculated; proper nouns, determiners, conjunctions, numerals, etc. are excluded. As “relevant&amp;quot;, we consider relations that have been observed to</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Choueka, 1988</marker>
<rawString>Choueka, Y. (1988). Looking for needles in a haystack or locating interesting collocational expressions in large textual databases. In In Proceedings of the RIAO, pages 34–38.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>K Church</author>
<author>P Hanks</author>
</authors>
<title>Word Association Norms, Mutual Information, and Lexicography.</title>
<date>1989</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 27th Annual Meeting of the ACL,</booktitle>
<pages>76--83</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="6840" citStr="Church and Hanks, 1989" startWordPosition="1033" endWordPosition="1036">proposal, and Section 5 discusses the outcome of these experiments. In Section 6, a short summary of the related work is presented, before Section 7 draws some conclusions. 2 The Linguistic nature of collocations The term “collocation&amp;quot; as introduced by Firth (1957) and cast into a definition by Halliday (1961) encompasses the statistical distribution of lexical items in context: lexical items that form high probability associations are considered collocations. It is this interpretation that underlies most works on automatic identification of collocations in corpora; see, e.g., (Choueka, 1988; Church and Hanks, 1989; Pecina, 2008; Evert, 2007; Bouma, 2010). However, in contemporary lexicography and lexicology an interpretation that stresses the idiosyncratic nature of collocations prevails. Thus, Benson (1989) states that “collocations should be defined not just as ‘recurrent 2 word combinations’, but as ‘ARBITRARY recurrent word combinations’ ”. “Arbitrary” as opposed to “regular” means that collocations are unpredictable and language-specific. For instance, in English, one takes a walk, while in French, German and Italian one ‘makes’ it: faire une promenade, einen Spaziergang machen, fare una passeggia</context>
<context position="8845" citStr="Church and Hanks, 1989" startWordPosition="1349" endWordPosition="1352">cation” that we find reflected in general public collocation dictionaries and that we follow since it seems most useful in the context of second language acquisition. However, this is not to say that the two main interpretations of the term “collocation”, the distributional and the idiosyncratic one, are disjoint, i.e., necessarily lead to a different judgement with respect to the collocation status of a word combination. On the contrary: two lexical items that form an idiosyncratic co-occurrence are likely to occur together in a corpus with a high value of Pointwise Mutual Information (PMI) (Church and Hanks, 1989): PMI = lo P(a ∩ b) l = lo P(a|b) l = log (1) g •P(a)P(b)J g • P(a) J g • P(b) ‹ The PMI indicates that if two variables a and b are independent, the probability of their intersection is the product of their probabilities. A PMI equal to 0 means that the variables are independent; a positive PMI implies a correlation beyond independence; and a negative PMI signals that the co-occurrence of the variables is lower than the average. Two lexemes are thus considered to form a collocation when they have a positive PMI, i.e., they are found together more often that this would happen if they would be </context>
<context position="15222" citStr="Church and Hanks, 1989" startWordPosition="2408" endWordPosition="2411">c dependencies, the sub-categorization information of the base must be considered. We say applyfor [a] job, apply to college and apply [a] theory; nominate for presidency, and nominate [the] candidate; and so on. Governed prepositions must be clearly distinguished from semantically full prepositions; cf. to in go to the concert or through in drive through the city. That is, when searching for correction suggestions for a given miscollocation, we need to be aware that a collocation is not a mere prominent co-occurrence of words, as argued in early works in the field; see, e.g., (Choueka, 1988; Church and Hanks, 1989). Rather, it implies dependency information that needs to be taken into account. 3 Ranking of Collocation Suggestions The basic source that allows us to check a sequence of words provided by the user for its collocation status and to come up with corrections suggestions is a large reference dependency treebank. For each pair of POS-tagged tokens between which a relevant dependency relation holds, the PMI, NPMICB and NPMIC are calculated; proper nouns, determiners, conjunctions, numerals, etc. are excluded. As “relevant&amp;quot;, we consider relations that have been observed to hold between collocation</context>
<context position="26087" citStr="Church and Hanks, 1989" startWordPosition="4201" endWordPosition="4204">king, vary articles and inflections and use WordNet to retrieve synonyms of the collocate. Wu et al. (2010) use a classifier to provide a number of collocate corrections. The classifier takes the learner sentence as lexical context. The probability predicted by the classifier for each suggestion is used to rank the suggestions. According to the evaluation included in (Wu et al., 2010), an MRR of 0.518 for the first five correction suggestions has been achieved. Liu et al. (2009) retrieve miscollocation correction suggestions from a reference corpus using three metrics: (i) mutual information (Church and Hanks, 1989), (ii) semantic similarity of an incorrect collocate to other potential collocates based on their distance in WordNet, and (iii) the membership of the incorrect collocate with a potential correct collocate in the same “collocation cluster’”. A combination of (ii)+(iii) leads to the best precision achieved for the suggestion of a correction: 55.95%. A combination of (i)+(ii)+(iii) leads to the best precision of 85.71% when a list of five possible corrections is returned. Ferraro et al. (2014) suggest a two stage strategy for correction of miscollocations in Spanish. The first stage is rather si</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Church, Hanks, 1989</marker>
<rawString>Church, K. and Hanks, P. (1989). Word Association Norms, Mutual Information, and Lexicography. In Proceedings of the 27th Annual Meeting of the ACL, pages 76–83.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>A Cowie</author>
</authors>
<date>1994</date>
<booktitle>The Encyclopedia of Language and Linguistics,</booktitle>
<volume>6</volume>
<pages>3168--3171</pages>
<editor>Phraseology. In Asher, R. and Simpson, J., editors,</editor>
<publisher>Pergamon,</publisher>
<location>Oxford.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="7693" citStr="Cowie (1994)" startWordPosition="1160" endWordPosition="1161">d not just as ‘recurrent 2 word combinations’, but as ‘ARBITRARY recurrent word combinations’ ”. “Arbitrary” as opposed to “regular” means that collocations are unpredictable and language-specific. For instance, in English, one takes a walk, while in French, German and Italian one ‘makes’ it: faire une promenade, einen Spaziergang machen, fare una passeggiata, and in Spanish one ‘gives’ it: dar un paseo. In English, one gives a lecture, in German and Italian one ‘holds’ it: eine Vorlesung halten, tenere una lezione, and in Russian one ‘reads’ it: ˇcitat′ lekciju. According to Hausmann (1984), Cowie (1994), Mel’ˇcuk (1995) and others, a collocation is a binary idiosyncratic co-occurrence of lexical items between which a direct syntactic dependency holds and where the occurrence of one of the items (the base) is subject of the free choice of the speaker, while the occurrence of the other item (the collocate) is restricted by the base. Thus, in the case of take [a] walk, walk is the base and take the collocate, in the case of high speed, speed is the base and high the collocate, etc. It is this understanding of the term “collocation” that we find reflected in general public collocation dictionari</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Cowie, 1994</marker>
<rawString>Cowie, A. (1994). Phraseology. In Asher, R. and Simpson, J., editors, The Encyclopedia of Language and Linguistics, Vol. 6, pages 3168–3171. Pergamon, Oxford.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>D Dahlmeier</author>
<author>H Ng</author>
</authors>
<title>Correcting semantic collocation errors with L1-induced paraphrases.</title>
<date>2011</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 2011 Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing,</booktitle>
<pages>107--117</pages>
<location>Edinburgh, Scotland.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="24652" citStr="Dahlmeier and Ng (2011)" startWordPosition="3973" endWordPosition="3976"> a V–N co-occurrence provided by a learner against a collocation list obtained before from a reference corpus. Co-occurrences not found in this collocation list are variegated in that their verbal elements are substituted by all English translations of their L1 (Chinese, in this case) counterpart in an electronic dictionary. The variants are again matched against the collocation list. The finally matching co-occurrences that contain the noun of a non-matching co-occurrence are offered as correction suggestions. The Mutual Reciprocal Rank (MRR) of the correction list is reported to reach 0.66. Dahlmeier and Ng (2011), who deal with the detection of miscollocations in writings also exploits L1 interference in learners. They work with confusion sets of semantically similar words. Given an input text in L2, they generate L1 paraphrases, which are then looked up in a large parallel corpus to obtain the most likely L2 co-occurrences. For this strategy, they report a precision of 38%. Futagi et al. (2008) target the detection of miscollocations in learner texts, leaving the correction aside. Unlike the above proposals, they are not restricted to V+N co-occurrences. But similar 9 to (Chang et al., 2008), they ex</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Dahlmeier, Ng, 2011</marker>
<rawString>Dahlmeier, D. and Ng, H. (2011). Correcting semantic collocation errors with L1-induced paraphrases. In Proceedings of the 2011 Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing, pages 107–117, Edinburgh, Scotland.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S Evert</author>
</authors>
<title>Corpora and collocations.</title>
<date>2007</date>
<booktitle>Corpus Linguistics. An International Handbook. Mouton de Gruyter,</booktitle>
<editor>In Lüdeling, A. and Kytö, M., editors,</editor>
<location>Berlin.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="6867" citStr="Evert, 2007" startWordPosition="1039" endWordPosition="1040">outcome of these experiments. In Section 6, a short summary of the related work is presented, before Section 7 draws some conclusions. 2 The Linguistic nature of collocations The term “collocation&amp;quot; as introduced by Firth (1957) and cast into a definition by Halliday (1961) encompasses the statistical distribution of lexical items in context: lexical items that form high probability associations are considered collocations. It is this interpretation that underlies most works on automatic identification of collocations in corpora; see, e.g., (Choueka, 1988; Church and Hanks, 1989; Pecina, 2008; Evert, 2007; Bouma, 2010). However, in contemporary lexicography and lexicology an interpretation that stresses the idiosyncratic nature of collocations prevails. Thus, Benson (1989) states that “collocations should be defined not just as ‘recurrent 2 word combinations’, but as ‘ARBITRARY recurrent word combinations’ ”. “Arbitrary” as opposed to “regular” means that collocations are unpredictable and language-specific. For instance, in English, one takes a walk, while in French, German and Italian one ‘makes’ it: faire une promenade, einen Spaziergang machen, fare una passeggiata, and in Spanish one ‘giv</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Evert, 2007</marker>
<rawString>Evert, S. (2007). Corpora and collocations. In Lüdeling, A. and Kytö, M., editors, Corpus Linguistics. An International Handbook. Mouton de Gruyter, Berlin.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>G Ferraro</author>
<author>R Nazar</author>
<author>M A Ramos</author>
<author>L Wanner</author>
</authors>
<title>Towards advanced collocation error correction in Spanish learner corpora. Language Resources and Evaluation,</title>
<date>2014</date>
<pages>48--1</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="26583" citStr="Ferraro et al. (2014)" startWordPosition="4277" endWordPosition="4280">llocation correction suggestions from a reference corpus using three metrics: (i) mutual information (Church and Hanks, 1989), (ii) semantic similarity of an incorrect collocate to other potential collocates based on their distance in WordNet, and (iii) the membership of the incorrect collocate with a potential correct collocate in the same “collocation cluster’”. A combination of (ii)+(iii) leads to the best precision achieved for the suggestion of a correction: 55.95%. A combination of (i)+(ii)+(iii) leads to the best precision of 85.71% when a list of five possible corrections is returned. Ferraro et al. (2014) suggest a two stage strategy for correction of miscollocations in Spanish. The first stage is rather similar to the one proposed by Futagi et al. (2008): it retrieves the synonyms of the collocate in the miscollocation in question from a number of auxiliary resources (including thesauri, bilingual L1-L2 dictionaries, etc.) and combines them with the base of the miscollocation to candidate corrections. The candidate corrections that are valid collocations of Spanish are returned as correction suggestions. If none of them is, the second stage applies a metric to retrieve correction suggestions.</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Ferraro, Nazar, Ramos, Wanner, 2014</marker>
<rawString>Ferraro, G., Nazar, R., Ramos, M. A., and Wanner, L. (2014). Towards advanced collocation error correction in Spanish learner corpora. Language Resources and Evaluation, 48(1):45–64.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>J Firth</author>
</authors>
<title>Modes of meaning.</title>
<date>1957</date>
<booktitle>Papers in Linguistics, 1934-1951,</booktitle>
<pages>190--215</pages>
<editor>In Firth, J., editor,</editor>
<publisher>Oxford University Press,</publisher>
<location>Oxford.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="6483" citStr="Firth (1957)" startWordPosition="985" endWordPosition="986">occurrence of the collocate element is restricted by the base. In the next section, we introduce the linguistic considerations on collocations that motivate our proposal. Section 3 presents how we draw upon these linguistic considerations to rank collocation correction suggestions. Section 4 outlines the experiments we carried out to verify our proposal, and Section 5 discusses the outcome of these experiments. In Section 6, a short summary of the related work is presented, before Section 7 draws some conclusions. 2 The Linguistic nature of collocations The term “collocation&amp;quot; as introduced by Firth (1957) and cast into a definition by Halliday (1961) encompasses the statistical distribution of lexical items in context: lexical items that form high probability associations are considered collocations. It is this interpretation that underlies most works on automatic identification of collocations in corpora; see, e.g., (Choueka, 1988; Church and Hanks, 1989; Pecina, 2008; Evert, 2007; Bouma, 2010). However, in contemporary lexicography and lexicology an interpretation that stresses the idiosyncratic nature of collocations prevails. Thus, Benson (1989) states that “collocations should be defined </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Firth, 1957</marker>
<rawString>Firth, J. (1957). Modes of meaning. In Firth, J., editor, Papers in Linguistics, 1934-1951, pages 190–215. Oxford University Press, Oxford.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Y Futagi</author>
<author>P Deane</author>
<author>M Chodorow</author>
<author>J Tetreault</author>
</authors>
<title>A computational approach to detecting collocation errors in the writing of non-native speakers of English.</title>
<date>2008</date>
<journal>Computer Assisted Language Learning,</journal>
<volume>21</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<contexts>
<context position="25042" citStr="Futagi et al. (2008)" startWordPosition="4037" endWordPosition="4040">inally matching co-occurrences that contain the noun of a non-matching co-occurrence are offered as correction suggestions. The Mutual Reciprocal Rank (MRR) of the correction list is reported to reach 0.66. Dahlmeier and Ng (2011), who deal with the detection of miscollocations in writings also exploits L1 interference in learners. They work with confusion sets of semantically similar words. Given an input text in L2, they generate L1 paraphrases, which are then looked up in a large parallel corpus to obtain the most likely L2 co-occurrences. For this strategy, they report a precision of 38%. Futagi et al. (2008) target the detection of miscollocations in learner texts, leaving the correction aside. Unlike the above proposals, they are not restricted to V+N co-occurrences. But similar 9 to (Chang et al., 2008), they extract the co-occurrences from a learner text, variegate them and then look up the original co-occurrence and its variants in a reference list to decide on its status. To obtain the variants, they apply spell checking, vary articles and inflections and use WordNet to retrieve synonyms of the collocate. Wu et al. (2010) use a classifier to provide a number of collocate corrections. The cla</context>
<context position="26736" citStr="Futagi et al. (2008)" startWordPosition="4303" endWordPosition="4306"> an incorrect collocate to other potential collocates based on their distance in WordNet, and (iii) the membership of the incorrect collocate with a potential correct collocate in the same “collocation cluster’”. A combination of (ii)+(iii) leads to the best precision achieved for the suggestion of a correction: 55.95%. A combination of (i)+(ii)+(iii) leads to the best precision of 85.71% when a list of five possible corrections is returned. Ferraro et al. (2014) suggest a two stage strategy for correction of miscollocations in Spanish. The first stage is rather similar to the one proposed by Futagi et al. (2008): it retrieves the synonyms of the collocate in the miscollocation in question from a number of auxiliary resources (including thesauri, bilingual L1-L2 dictionaries, etc.) and combines them with the base of the miscollocation to candidate corrections. The candidate corrections that are valid collocations of Spanish are returned as correction suggestions. If none of them is, the second stage applies a metric to retrieve correction suggestions. Three metrics have been experimented with: affinity metric, lexical context metric and context feature metric. The context feature metric, which uses th</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Futagi, Deane, Chodorow, Tetreault, 2008</marker>
<rawString>Futagi, Y., Deane, P., Chodorow, M., and Tetreault, J. (2008). A computational approach to detecting collocation errors in the writing of non-native speakers of English. Computer Assisted Language Learning, 21(1):353–367.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S Granger</author>
</authors>
<title>Prefabricated patterns in advanced EFL writing: Collocations and Formulae.</title>
<date>1998</date>
<booktitle>Phraseology: Theory, Analysis and Applications,</booktitle>
<pages>145--160</pages>
<editor>In Cowie, A., editor,</editor>
<publisher>Oxford University Press,</publisher>
<location>Oxford.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="3119" citStr="Granger, 1998" startWordPosition="457" endWordPosition="458">he base, i.e., that collocations are per se asymmetric. KEYWORDS: CALL, collocations, miscollocation correction, syntactic dependencies, subcategorization, PMI. Roberto Carlini, Joan Codina-Filba and Leo Wanner 2014. Improving collocation correction by ranking suggestions using linguistic knowledge. Proceedings of the third workshop on NLP for computer-assisted language learning. NEALT Proceedings Series 22 / Linköping Electronic Conference Proceedings 107: 1–12. 1 1 Introduction The importance of collocations in the context of second language learning is beyond any doubt; see, among others, (Granger, 1998; Lewis, 2000; Nesselhauf, 2004, 2005; Lesniewska, 2006; Alonso Ramos et al., 2010) for studies in this respect. Orol and Alonso Ramos (2013) even show in their study that the “collocation density&amp;quot; in learner corpora is nearly the same as in native corpora, i.e., that the use of collocations by learners is as common as it is by native speakers. At the same time, they also find that the collocation error rate in learner corpora is about 32% (compared to about 3% by native speakers). That is, Computer Assisted Language Learning (CALL) could be of great aid to support the learners for better mast</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Granger, 1998</marker>
<rawString>Granger, S. (1998). Prefabricated patterns in advanced EFL writing: Collocations and Formulae. In Cowie, A., editor, Phraseology: Theory, Analysis and Applications, pages 145–160. Oxford University Press, Oxford.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M Halliday</author>
</authors>
<title>Categories of the theory of grammar.</title>
<date>1961</date>
<pages>31--1</pages>
<location>Word, 17:241–292. Hausmann, F.-J.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="6529" citStr="Halliday (1961)" startWordPosition="993" endWordPosition="994">ricted by the base. In the next section, we introduce the linguistic considerations on collocations that motivate our proposal. Section 3 presents how we draw upon these linguistic considerations to rank collocation correction suggestions. Section 4 outlines the experiments we carried out to verify our proposal, and Section 5 discusses the outcome of these experiments. In Section 6, a short summary of the related work is presented, before Section 7 draws some conclusions. 2 The Linguistic nature of collocations The term “collocation&amp;quot; as introduced by Firth (1957) and cast into a definition by Halliday (1961) encompasses the statistical distribution of lexical items in context: lexical items that form high probability associations are considered collocations. It is this interpretation that underlies most works on automatic identification of collocations in corpora; see, e.g., (Choueka, 1988; Church and Hanks, 1989; Pecina, 2008; Evert, 2007; Bouma, 2010). However, in contemporary lexicography and lexicology an interpretation that stresses the idiosyncratic nature of collocations prevails. Thus, Benson (1989) states that “collocations should be defined not just as ‘recurrent 2 word combinations’, b</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Halliday, 1961</marker>
<rawString>Halliday, M. (1961). Categories of the theory of grammar. Word, 17:241–292. Hausmann, F.-J. (1984). Wortschatzlernen ist kollokationslernen. zum lehren und lernen französischer wortwendungen. Praxis des neusprachlichen Unterrichts, 31(1):395–406.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>J Lesniewska</author>
</authors>
<title>Collocations and second language use. Studia Lingüística Universitatis lagellonicae Cracoviensis,</title>
<date>2006</date>
<pages>123--95</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="3174" citStr="Lesniewska, 2006" startWordPosition="464" endWordPosition="465">ic. KEYWORDS: CALL, collocations, miscollocation correction, syntactic dependencies, subcategorization, PMI. Roberto Carlini, Joan Codina-Filba and Leo Wanner 2014. Improving collocation correction by ranking suggestions using linguistic knowledge. Proceedings of the third workshop on NLP for computer-assisted language learning. NEALT Proceedings Series 22 / Linköping Electronic Conference Proceedings 107: 1–12. 1 1 Introduction The importance of collocations in the context of second language learning is beyond any doubt; see, among others, (Granger, 1998; Lewis, 2000; Nesselhauf, 2004, 2005; Lesniewska, 2006; Alonso Ramos et al., 2010) for studies in this respect. Orol and Alonso Ramos (2013) even show in their study that the “collocation density&amp;quot; in learner corpora is nearly the same as in native corpora, i.e., that the use of collocations by learners is as common as it is by native speakers. At the same time, they also find that the collocation error rate in learner corpora is about 32% (compared to about 3% by native speakers). That is, Computer Assisted Language Learning (CALL) could be of great aid to support the learners for better mastering of collocations. However, surprisingly few works </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Lesniewska, 2006</marker>
<rawString>Lesniewska, J. (2006). Collocations and second language use. Studia Lingüística Universitatis lagellonicae Cracoviensis, 123:95–105.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M Lewis</author>
</authors>
<title>Teaching Collocation. Further Developments in the Lexical Approach.</title>
<date>2000</date>
<location>LTP, London.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="3132" citStr="Lewis, 2000" startWordPosition="459" endWordPosition="460">that collocations are per se asymmetric. KEYWORDS: CALL, collocations, miscollocation correction, syntactic dependencies, subcategorization, PMI. Roberto Carlini, Joan Codina-Filba and Leo Wanner 2014. Improving collocation correction by ranking suggestions using linguistic knowledge. Proceedings of the third workshop on NLP for computer-assisted language learning. NEALT Proceedings Series 22 / Linköping Electronic Conference Proceedings 107: 1–12. 1 1 Introduction The importance of collocations in the context of second language learning is beyond any doubt; see, among others, (Granger, 1998; Lewis, 2000; Nesselhauf, 2004, 2005; Lesniewska, 2006; Alonso Ramos et al., 2010) for studies in this respect. Orol and Alonso Ramos (2013) even show in their study that the “collocation density&amp;quot; in learner corpora is nearly the same as in native corpora, i.e., that the use of collocations by learners is as common as it is by native speakers. At the same time, they also find that the collocation error rate in learner corpora is about 32% (compared to about 3% by native speakers). That is, Computer Assisted Language Learning (CALL) could be of great aid to support the learners for better mastering of coll</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Lewis, 2000</marker>
<rawString>Lewis, M. (2000). Teaching Collocation. Further Developments in the Lexical Approach. LTP, London.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>A L-E Liu</author>
<author>D Wible</author>
<author>N-L Tsao</author>
</authors>
<title>Automated suggestions for miscollocations.</title>
<date>2009</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the NAACL HLT Workshop on Innovative Use of NLP for Building Educational Applications,</booktitle>
<pages>47--50</pages>
<location>Boulder, CO.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="25947" citStr="Liu et al. (2009)" startWordPosition="4183" endWordPosition="4186">the original co-occurrence and its variants in a reference list to decide on its status. To obtain the variants, they apply spell checking, vary articles and inflections and use WordNet to retrieve synonyms of the collocate. Wu et al. (2010) use a classifier to provide a number of collocate corrections. The classifier takes the learner sentence as lexical context. The probability predicted by the classifier for each suggestion is used to rank the suggestions. According to the evaluation included in (Wu et al., 2010), an MRR of 0.518 for the first five correction suggestions has been achieved. Liu et al. (2009) retrieve miscollocation correction suggestions from a reference corpus using three metrics: (i) mutual information (Church and Hanks, 1989), (ii) semantic similarity of an incorrect collocate to other potential collocates based on their distance in WordNet, and (iii) the membership of the incorrect collocate with a potential correct collocate in the same “collocation cluster’”. A combination of (ii)+(iii) leads to the best precision achieved for the suggestion of a correction: 55.95%. A combination of (i)+(ii)+(iii) leads to the best precision of 85.71% when a list of five possible correction</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Liu, Wible, Tsao, 2009</marker>
<rawString>Liu, A. L.-E., Wible, D., and Tsao, N.-L. (2009). Automated suggestions for miscollocations. In Proceedings of the NAACL HLT Workshop on Innovative Use of NLP for Building Educational Applications, pages 47–50, Boulder, CO.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>C Lozano</author>
</authors>
<title>CEDEL2: Corpus escrito del español L2.</title>
<date>2009</date>
<booktitle>Applied Linguistics Now: Understanding Language and Mind,</booktitle>
<pages>197--212</pages>
<editor>In Bretones Callejas, C., editor,</editor>
<location>Almería.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="18163" citStr="Lozano, 2009" startWordPosition="2872" endWordPosition="2873">ms of the list are shown, but the user can ask to go down in the list. Also, the user can solicit sample sentences from the corpus in which the corresponding collocation occurs (as in the MUST collocation checker) to help them to understand the correct use of it. 4 Experiments In order to validate our model, we carried out experiments on Spanish material, taking as starting point some miscollocations with the bases siesta ‘nap’ (Table 1), meta ‘finish line , target, objective, goal, goalkeeper’ (Table 3), examen ‘exam’ (Table 2) , and teléfono ‘phone’ (Table 4) from the learner corpus CEDEL2 (Lozano, 2009). As reference treebank, we use a treebank of Spanish newspaper material. The sentences of the treebank are indexed in a Solr (Lucene) index for more efficient access. The index allows us to retrieve directly the list of tokens, the list of lemmas and all the tokens related with another token by a given relation type. It is also used to retrieve examples to be shown to the user. The table of each base lists the most common collocates, indicating the frequencies in the corpus, the PMI, NPMICB and NPMIC; for meta the table contains two parts, a list for meta acting as direct object and another f</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Lozano, 2009</marker>
<rawString>Lozano, C. (2009). CEDEL2: Corpus escrito del español L2. In Bretones Callejas, C., editor, Applied Linguistics Now: Understanding Language and Mind, pages 197–212. Universidad de Almería, Almería.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>I Mel’ˇcuk</author>
</authors>
<title>Phrasemes in Language and Phraseology in Linguistics.</title>
<date>1995</date>
<booktitle>Idioms: Structural and Psychological Perspectives,</booktitle>
<pages>167--232</pages>
<editor>In Everaert, M., van der Linden, E.-J., Schenk, A., and Schreuder, R., editors,</editor>
<location>Hillsdale.</location>
<marker>Mel’ˇcuk, 1995</marker>
<rawString>Mel’ˇcuk, I. (1995). Phrasemes in Language and Phraseology in Linguistics. In Everaert, M., van der Linden, E.-J., Schenk, A., and Schreuder, R., editors, Idioms: Structural and Psychological Perspectives, pages 167–232. Lawrence Erlbaum Associates, Hillsdale.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>N Nesselhauf</author>
</authors>
<title>How learner corpus analysis can contribute to language teaching: A study of support verb constructions.</title>
<date>2004</date>
<booktitle>Corpora and language learners,</booktitle>
<pages>109--124</pages>
<editor>In Aston, G., Bernardini, S., and Stewart, D., editors,</editor>
<publisher>Benjamins Academic Publishers,</publisher>
<location>Amsterdam.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="3150" citStr="Nesselhauf, 2004" startWordPosition="461" endWordPosition="462">ions are per se asymmetric. KEYWORDS: CALL, collocations, miscollocation correction, syntactic dependencies, subcategorization, PMI. Roberto Carlini, Joan Codina-Filba and Leo Wanner 2014. Improving collocation correction by ranking suggestions using linguistic knowledge. Proceedings of the third workshop on NLP for computer-assisted language learning. NEALT Proceedings Series 22 / Linköping Electronic Conference Proceedings 107: 1–12. 1 1 Introduction The importance of collocations in the context of second language learning is beyond any doubt; see, among others, (Granger, 1998; Lewis, 2000; Nesselhauf, 2004, 2005; Lesniewska, 2006; Alonso Ramos et al., 2010) for studies in this respect. Orol and Alonso Ramos (2013) even show in their study that the “collocation density&amp;quot; in learner corpora is nearly the same as in native corpora, i.e., that the use of collocations by learners is as common as it is by native speakers. At the same time, they also find that the collocation error rate in learner corpora is about 32% (compared to about 3% by native speakers). That is, Computer Assisted Language Learning (CALL) could be of great aid to support the learners for better mastering of collocations. However,</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Nesselhauf, 2004</marker>
<rawString>Nesselhauf, N. (2004). How learner corpus analysis can contribute to language teaching: A study of support verb constructions. In Aston, G., Bernardini, S., and Stewart, D., editors, Corpora and language learners, pages 109–124. Benjamins Academic Publishers, Amsterdam.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>N Nesselhauf</author>
</authors>
<title>Collocations in a Learner Corpus.</title>
<date>2005</date>
<publisher>Benjamins Academic Publishers,</publisher>
<location>Amsterdam.</location>
<marker>Nesselhauf, 2005</marker>
<rawString>Nesselhauf, N. (2005). Collocations in a Learner Corpus. Benjamins Academic Publishers, Amsterdam.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>A Orol</author>
<author>Alonso Ramos</author>
<author>M</author>
</authors>
<title>A Comparative Study of Collocations in a Native Corpus and a Learner Corpus of Spanish.</title>
<date>2013</date>
<booktitle>Procedia–Social and Behavioural Sciences,</booktitle>
<pages>96--563</pages>
<marker>Orol, Ramos, M, 2013</marker>
<rawString>Orol, A. and Alonso Ramos, M. (2013). A Comparative Study of Collocations in a Native Corpus and a Learner Corpus of Spanish. Procedia–Social and Behavioural Sciences, 96:563–570.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>P Pecina</author>
</authors>
<title>A machine learning approach to multiword expression extraction.</title>
<date>2008</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the LREC 2008 Workshop Towards a Shared Task for Multiword Expressions (MWE</booktitle>
<pages>54--57</pages>
<location>Marrakech.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="6854" citStr="Pecina, 2008" startWordPosition="1037" endWordPosition="1038">discusses the outcome of these experiments. In Section 6, a short summary of the related work is presented, before Section 7 draws some conclusions. 2 The Linguistic nature of collocations The term “collocation&amp;quot; as introduced by Firth (1957) and cast into a definition by Halliday (1961) encompasses the statistical distribution of lexical items in context: lexical items that form high probability associations are considered collocations. It is this interpretation that underlies most works on automatic identification of collocations in corpora; see, e.g., (Choueka, 1988; Church and Hanks, 1989; Pecina, 2008; Evert, 2007; Bouma, 2010). However, in contemporary lexicography and lexicology an interpretation that stresses the idiosyncratic nature of collocations prevails. Thus, Benson (1989) states that “collocations should be defined not just as ‘recurrent 2 word combinations’, but as ‘ARBITRARY recurrent word combinations’ ”. “Arbitrary” as opposed to “regular” means that collocations are unpredictable and language-specific. For instance, in English, one takes a walk, while in French, German and Italian one ‘makes’ it: faire une promenade, einen Spaziergang machen, fare una passeggiata, and in Spa</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Pecina, 2008</marker>
<rawString>Pecina, P. (2008). A machine learning approach to multiword expression extraction. In Proceedings of the LREC 2008 Workshop Towards a Shared Task for Multiword Expressions (MWE 2008), pages 54–57, Marrakech.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>L Wanner</author>
<author>S Verlinde</author>
<author>Alonso Ramos</author>
<author>M</author>
</authors>
<title>Writing assistants and automatic lexical error correction: word combinatorics.</title>
<date>2013</date>
<booktitle>Electronic lexicography in the 21st century: Thinking outside the paper. Proceedings of the eLex 2013 conference,</booktitle>
<pages>472--487</pages>
<editor>In Kosem, I., Kallas, J., Gantar, P., Krek, S., Langemets, M., and Tuulik, M., editors,</editor>
<contexts>
<context position="4212" citStr="Wanner et al., 2013" startWordPosition="629" endWordPosition="632">ve speakers). That is, Computer Assisted Language Learning (CALL) could be of great aid to support the learners for better mastering of collocations. However, surprisingly few works address specifically CALL-oriented collocation learning assistants that detect miscollocations in the writings of the learners and propose suggestions for their correction or that offer the learner the possibility to verify using an interactive interface a word cooccurrence with respect to its correctness as collocation and obtain suggestions for its correction in case it is determined to be a miscollocation; cf. (Wanner et al., 2013) for an overview. This is likely to be, on the one hand, due to the focus on grammatical matters that CALL research had so far, and, on the other hand, due to the complexity of the problem. The problem envisaged by a collocation learning assistant is that in order to be able to provide an adequate correction of a miscollocation, it must “guess&amp;quot; the meaning that the learner intended to express. Thus, if the learner writes assume an exam, we do not know a priori (especially not when the learner uses an interface for the verification of assume an exam as an isolated word co-occurrence; cf., e.g.,</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Wanner, Verlinde, Ramos, M, 2013</marker>
<rawString>Wanner, L., Verlinde, S., and Alonso Ramos, M. (2013). Writing assistants and automatic lexical error correction: word combinatorics. In Kosem, I., Kallas, J., Gantar, P., Krek, S., Langemets, M., and Tuulik, M., editors, Electronic lexicography in the 21st century: Thinking outside the paper. Proceedings of the eLex 2013 conference, pages 472–487, Tallinn &amp; Ljubljana. Trojina, Institute for Applied Slovene Studies &amp; Eesti Keele Instituut.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>J-C Wu</author>
<author>Y-C Chang</author>
<author>T Mitamura</author>
<author>J Chang</author>
</authors>
<title>Automatic collocation suggestion in academic writing.</title>
<date>2010</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the ACL Conference, Short paper track,</booktitle>
<location>Uppsala.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="25571" citStr="Wu et al. (2010)" startWordPosition="4122" endWordPosition="4125">co-occurrences. For this strategy, they report a precision of 38%. Futagi et al. (2008) target the detection of miscollocations in learner texts, leaving the correction aside. Unlike the above proposals, they are not restricted to V+N co-occurrences. But similar 9 to (Chang et al., 2008), they extract the co-occurrences from a learner text, variegate them and then look up the original co-occurrence and its variants in a reference list to decide on its status. To obtain the variants, they apply spell checking, vary articles and inflections and use WordNet to retrieve synonyms of the collocate. Wu et al. (2010) use a classifier to provide a number of collocate corrections. The classifier takes the learner sentence as lexical context. The probability predicted by the classifier for each suggestion is used to rank the suggestions. According to the evaluation included in (Wu et al., 2010), an MRR of 0.518 for the first five correction suggestions has been achieved. Liu et al. (2009) retrieve miscollocation correction suggestions from a reference corpus using three metrics: (i) mutual information (Church and Hanks, 1989), (ii) semantic similarity of an incorrect collocate to other potential collocates b</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Wu, Chang, Mitamura, Chang, 2010</marker>
<rawString>Wu, J.-C., Chang, Y.-C., Mitamura, T., and Chang, J. (2010). Automatic collocation suggestion in academic writing. In Proceedings of the ACL Conference, Short paper track, Uppsala.</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>