<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="SectLabel" version="110505">
<variant no="0" confidence="0.026941">
<title confidence="0.996302">
gdbank: The beginnings of a corpus of dependency structures and
type-logical grammar in Scottish Gaelic
</title>
<author confidence="0.994084">
Colin Batchelor
</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.97421">
Royal Society of Chemistry, Cambridge, UK CB4 0WF
</affiliation>
<email confidence="0.98324">
batchelorc@rsc.org
</email>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.993574" genericHeader="abstract">
Abstract
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99995425">
We present gdbank, a small handbuilt corpus of 32 sentences with dependency structures and
categorial grammar type assignments. The sentences have been chosen to illustrate as broad a
range of the unusual features of Scottish Gaelic as possible, particularly nouns being used to
represent psychological states where more thoroughly-studied languages such as English and
French would prefer a verb, and prepositions marking aspect, as is also seen in Welsh and, for
example, Irish Gaelic. We provide hand-built dependency trees, building on previous work on
Irish Gaelic and using the Universal Dependency Scheme. We also provide a tentative categorial
grammar account of the words in the sentences, based largely on previous work on English.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.998794" genericHeader="introduction">
1 Introduction
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999854666666667">
Scottish Gaelic (usually hereafter Gaelic) is a Celtic language, rather closely related to Irish, with around
59,000 speakers as of the last UK census in 2011. As opposed to the situation for Irish Gaelic (Lynn et
al., 2012a; Lynn et al., 2012b; Lynn et al., 2013; Lynn et al., 2014) there are no treebanks or tagging
schemes for Scottish Gaelic, although there are machine-readable dictionaries and databases available
from Sabhal M`or Ostaig. A single paper in the ACL Anthology (Kessler, 1995) mentions Scottish Gaelic
in the context of computational dialectology of Irish. There is also an LREC workshop paper (Scan-
nell, 2006) on machine translation between Irish and Scottish Gaelic. Elsewhere in the Celtic languages,
Welsh has an LFG grammar (Mittendorf and Sadler, 2005) but no treebanks. For Breton there is a small
amount of work on morphological analysis and Constraint-Grammar-based machine translation (Tyers,
2010). Recent work on the grammar of Scottish Gaelic (for example (Adger and Ramchand, 2003; Adger
and Ramchand, 2005), but there are many more examples) has largely focussed on theoretical syntac-
tic issues somewhat distant from the more surfacy approaches popular in the field of natural language
processing. This paper explores grammatical issues in Scottish Gaelic by means of dependency tagging
and combinatory categorial grammar (CCG), which we see as complementary approaches. As such it
is explicitly inspired by CCGbank (Hockenmaier and Steedman, 2007), which consists of dependency
structures and CCG derivations for over 99% of the Penn Treebank. It is hoped that this corpus will be
a useful adjunct to currently on-going work in developing a part-of-speech tagset and tagger for Scottish
Gaelic.
Section 2 describes how the corpus was prepared, sections 3 and 4 give some context for the depen-
dency scheme and categorial grammar annotations respectively, and the main part of the paper is section
5, which deals with language-specific features of the corpus.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.725064" genericHeader="method">
2 Preparing the corpus
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99825125">
The corpus consists of a small handbuilt selection of sentences from the transcripts of An Litir Bheag,
which is a weekly podcast from the BBC written by a native speaker and aimed at Gaelic learners,
example sentences from (Lamb, 2003), the BBC’s online news in Gaelic and the Gaelic column in the
Scotsman newspaper. In order to illustrate as much of the interesting points of Scottish Gaelic as possible,
</bodyText>
<footnote confidence="0.509859">
This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International Licence. Page numbers and proceedings footer
are added by the organisers. Licence details: http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/
</footnote>
<page confidence="0.973848">
60
</page>
<note confidence="0.789417">
Proceedings of the First Celtic Language Technology Workshop, pages 60–65,
Dublin, Ireland, August 23 2014.
</note>
<bodyText confidence="0.764924363636364">
Dependency Example Gloss GR
det gach latha (det latha gach) every day det
dobj Ithidh i im (dobj Ithidh im) She eats butter dobj
adpmod Tha piseag agam (adpmod Tha agam) I have a kitten ncmod
adpobj as an eilean (adpobj `as eilean) from the island dobj
nsubj Tha mi a’ dol (Tha mi) I am coming ncsubj
prt Chan eil (prt eil chan) is not ncmod
xcomp Tha mi ag iarraidh (xcomp Tha iarraidh) I want xcomp
acomp Tha i breagha (xcomp Tha breagha) It is fine xcomp
ccomp bheachd gun tigeadh e (ccomp bheachd tigeadh) thought he would come ccomp
mark gun tigeadh e (mark tigeadh gun) that he would come ncmod
</bodyText>
<tableCaption confidence="0.996739">
Table 1: Examples of the UDS-based scheme in this paper mapped to the Briscoe and Carroll scheme.
</tableCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.996614375">
we looked in particular for sentences describing psychological states and made sure that a reasonable
number of the sentences used each verb for “to be”, which we will illustrate in section 5.
The sentences are tokenized by hand using the following rules: (1) Punctuation which never forms
part of a lexical item such as the comma, the full stop, the colon and the semicolon is always separated
out from the previous word. (2) Strings connected by a hyphen, for example h-Alba in Banca na h-Alba
(Bank of Scotland) or t-Oban as in an t-Oban (the town of Oban) are always kept together. (3) The
apostrophe is kept together with the copula where it proceeds it, for example in ’S fhearr leam (I like).
(4) Because the past tense particle do is reduced to dh’ before a vowel and before f, and this is always
typographically closed up, we separate out past-tense dh’ as its own token. These rules work for the
small dataset described here but would clearly need to be expanded for work in the wild.
In this preliminary work the dependencies and types have been determined by a single, non-native
speaker, annotator, according to a set of guidelines which were built up during the annotation process.
This is clearly less than ideal, however, the guidelines are available along with the corpus and we hope
to be able to get the input of a native speaker, not least for interannotator studies.
We use the CoNLL-X format (Buchholz and Marsi, 2006), leaving the POS and projective dependency
fields empty and store the categorial grammar type under field 6, FEATS.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.984002" genericHeader="method">
3 Dependency scheme
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.996379533333333">
There are four dependency schemes that we consulted while preparing the corpus. The initial inspiration
was provided by the C&amp;C parser (Curran et al., 2007), which in addition to providing categorial gram-
mar derivations for sentences provides a dependency structure in the GR (Grammatical Representation)
scheme due to (Briscoe and Carroll, 2000; Briscoe and Carroll, 2002). This contains 23 types and was
developed originally for parser evaluation. Another popular scheme is the Stanford Dependency scheme
(de Marneffe and Manning, 2008; de Marneffe and Manning, 2013), which is more finely-grained with
over twice the number of dependency types to deal specifically with noisy data and to make it more
accessible to non-linguists building information extraction applications. A very important scheme is the
Dublin scheme for Irish (Lynn et al., 2012a; Lynn et al., 2012b; Lynn et al., 2013), which is of a similar
size to the Stanford scheme, but the reason for its size relative to GR is that it includes a large num-
ber of dependencies intended to handle grammatical features found in Irish but not in English. Lastly
we mention the Universal Dependency Scheme developed in (McDonald et al., 2013), which we have
adopted, despite its being coarser-grained than the Dublin scheme, on account of its simplicity and utility
for cross-lingual comparisons and cross-training (Lynn et al., 2014).
Table 1 gives examples of the dependency relations used along with their mapping to the GR scheme.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.987401" genericHeader="method">
4 Categorial grammar
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9958585">
Combinatory categorial grammar (CCG) is a type-logical system which was developed to represent nat-
ural languages such as English but has subsequently been extended to other systems such as chord se-
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.996001">
61
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.99988525">
quences in jazz (Granroth-Wilding and Steedman, 2012). For a full description the reader is referred to
(Steedman and Baldridge, 2003), but in order to follow the rest of this paper you merely need to know
that the type N/N is a function which takes an argument of N to its right, returning N, and that the type
N\N is a function expecting an argument of N to its left and that these are combined by application,
composition, where A/B combines with B/C to yield A/C, and type-raising where N is converted to
T/(N\T). Attractive features of CCG for modelling a less-well-studied language include that it is a lex-
ical theory in which it is the lexicon contains the rules for how words are combined to make sense rather
than an external grammar, that it allows all manner of unconventional constituents, which is particularly
powerful for parsing coordinated structures in English, that it is equivalent to a weakly context-sensitive
grammar and hence has the power of a real natural language. In Steedman and Baldridge (2003) there are
examples of the application of multimodal CCG to Irish Gaelic. However, to the best of our knowledge
this paper is the first application of CCG to Scottish Gaelic.
In gdbank, there is a single hand-built CCG derivation for every sentence. The notation is based on that
in CCGbank with a small number of adaptations for Gaelic (see next section). The basic units that can be
assembled into types are S (clauses), N (nouns), con (conjugations), and PP (prepositional phrases).
For subcategorization purposes and to help keep things clear for the annotator and the reader we mark
prepositional phrases with the dictionary form of the preposition.
We have not yet investigated overgeneration and ungrammatical sentences, hence there is only one
kind of modality in gdbank; however restricting the way words can combine to the way in which they
actually do combine in Gaelic is an obvious and essential next step.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.998414" genericHeader="method">
5 Language-specific features
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999855517241379">
Prepositional phrases in Gaelic are often single-word, fused preposition–pronouns, a part-of-speech
found across the Celtic languages. An ambiguous case of this is the token ris, which can be either ri with
the pronoun e, hence taking the CCG type PP[ri], or the pre-determiner form of ri, hence PP[ri]/N[b].
The other class of fused preposition–pronoun we need to consider is that in sentences like Tha mi gad
chluinntinn, “I can hear you”, where gad is ag fused with do “your”. In this case it has type PP[ag]/S[n].
Adjectives as in CCGbank are treated as clauses, S[ad ]. The verbal noun is labelled S[n] by analogy
with Hockenmaier and Steedman (2007). In addition to declarative and interrogative clauses, S[dcl]
and S[q], we take our lead from the fourfold division of preverbal particles and add negative clauses
S[neg], usually introduced by cha or chan, and negative interrogative clauses, S[negq], introduced
by nach.
There are two verbs for “to be” in Scottish Gaelic, bi and is. Bi is used for predicate statements
about nouns, to forming the present tense and to describe some psychological states. It does not usually
equate two NPs, with an exception we will come to. In the Dublin scheme the prepositional phrase
headed by ag in Td se ag iascaireacht (“He is fishing.”) is treated as being an externally-controlled
complement of Td (Gaelic tha) and we carry this analysis over into Scottish Gaelic where this is the
most common way of expressing the present tense. Figure 1 demonstrates this, where dhachaigh is a
non-clausal modifier of dol, the verbal noun for “to go”. Is can be used as the copula between two NPs,
and to express psychological states such as liking and preference. To say “I am a teacher”, the Gaelic
is ‘S e tidsear a th’ annam. This, at least on the surface, equates pronoun e, with a noun described by a
relative clause including the verb bi. Fig. 1 shows our dependency tree for this. Note that this is different
from the scheme in Lynn et al. (2012b) because of a difference between the two languages. They treat
the analogous sentence Is tusa an muinteoir “You are the teacher” as having a subject, “the teacher”, and
a clausal predicate, tusa, “you indeed”.
The most straightforward way of expressing a preference is the assertive is followed by an adjective
or noun, a PP marking the preferrer, and then the object. If you dislike music, you might say Is beag orm
ceol. There are exactly analogous constructions in Irish with is + adjective + PP[le] + object, for example
Is maith liom... “I like...”, which in (UiDhonnchadha, 2009) is treated as having the prepositional
phrase as the subject and the adjective as predicate. We modify this to use adpmod as in the Universal
Dependency Scheme as shown in Fig. 1.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.992638">
62
</page>
<figure confidence="0.73952">
dobj
</figure>
<figureCaption confidence="0.996419">
Figure 1: Dependency trees for (a) “I am going home”, (b) “I am a teacher” and (c) “I hate music”.
</figureCaption>
<figure confidence="0.988438666666667">
(a) Tha mi a’ dol dhachaigh (b) ’S e tidsear a th’ annam (c) Is beag orm ce`ol
nsubj
xcomp
prt
adpmod
dobj
prt
xcomp
nsubj
advmod
adpmod
acomp
</figure>
<table confidence="0.9827155">
Type Count Notes Type Count
N 104 noun N\N 13
PP/N 41 preposition PP/S[n] 10
N/N 38 determiner S[dep]/PP/N 8
. 31 . (N\N)/S[dcl] 7
S[dcl]/PP/N 25 bi, is S[n] 7
PP 18 PP (N\N)/(N\N) 7
Notes
adjective/genitive noun
ag/a’/air etc.
bi, is (after particle)
relative
intransitive verbal noun
genitive article
</table>
<tableCaption confidence="0.9677245">
Table 2: Counts for most common types found in corpus. PP[air], PP[aig] and so on have been
merged.
</tableCaption>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.96601" genericHeader="conclusions">
6 Conclusions and future work
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998098071428572">
In this paper we have presented a small handbuilt corpus of Scottish Gaelic sentences, their dependency
structures and their CCG derivations. To the best of our knowledge this represents the first attempt to
handle a range of real-life Scottish Gaelic sentences in such a way. gdbank itself and the guidelines
used to build it are available from https://code.google.com/p/gdbank/ and we welcome
feedback. We have of course only been able to illustrate a small number of constructions. Tables 2 and
3 list counts for the categorial types and dependency relations used. In 32 sentences there are a total of
406 tokens.
We have not yet on the other hand attempted to deal with the morphology of Scottish Gaelic, for
example lenition and slenderization, beyond drawing the attention of the human annotator to these phe-
nomena when they may affect the correct parsing of a sentence. Clearly for automated natural-language
processing of Gaelic these will need to be treated programmatically. We also disregard case and gender,
although we expect that these will be dealt with as part of a rather more ambitious project, that of the
Lamb group at the University of Edinburgh to build a part-of-speech tagset and tagged corpus which we
look forward to seeing.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.97352" genericHeader="acknowledgments">
Acknowledgements
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.624228">
The anonymous referees for their very constructive comments.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.998120428571428">
Relation Count Relation Count Relation Count
adpmod 58 mark 23 amod 11
nsubj 47 nmod 18 advmod 9
adpobj 38 ccomp 17 acomp 7
det 34 prt 14 cc 6
p 33 dobj 13 rcmod 4
ROOT 32 xcomp 13 appos 2
</table>
<tableCaption confidence="0.9131215">
Table 3: Counts for dependency relations in gdbank. Note the high number of adpmod relations which
is significantly larger than adpobj because of fused preposition–pronouns in Gaelic.
</tableCaption>
<page confidence="0.999199">
63
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.98136" genericHeader="references">
References
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.997480755102041">
David Adger and Gillian Ramchand. 2003. Predication and equation. Linguistic Enquiry, 34:325–359.
David Adger and Gillian Ramchand. 2005. Psych nouns and predications. In Proceedings of the 36th Annual
Meeting of the North East Linguistic Society, Amherst, MA, October.
Ted Briscoe and John Carroll. 2000. Grammatical relation annotation. Online at
http://www.sussex.ac.uk/Users/johnca/grdescription/index.html.
Ted Briscoe and John Carroll. 2002. Robust accurate statistical annotation of general text. In Proceedings of
the Third International Conference on Language Resources and Evaluation (LREC’02), Las Palmas, Canary
Islands, Spain, May.
Sabine Buchholz and Erwin Marsi. 2006. CoNLL-X shared task on multilingual dependency parsing. In Proceed-
ings of the Tenth Conference on Computational Natural Language Learning, New York, NY, June.
James Curran, Stephen Clark, and Johan Bos. 2007. Linguistically motivated large-scale NLP with C&amp;C and
Boxer. In Proceedings of the 45th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics Companion
Volume Proceedings of the Demo and Poster Sessions, pages 33–36, Prague, Czech Republic, June. Association
for Computational Linguistics.
Marie-Catherine de Marneffe and Christopher D. Manning. 2008. The Stanford typed dependencies representa-
tion. In Coling 2008: Proceedings of the workshop on Cross-Framework and Cross-Domain Parser Evaluation,
pages 1–8, Manchester, UK, August. Coling 2008 Organizing Committee.
Marie-Catherine de Marneffe and Christopher D. Manning. 2013. Stanford typed dependencies manual. Online
at http://nlp.stanford.edu/software/dependencies manual.pdf.
Mark Granroth-Wilding and Mark Steedman. 2012. Statistical parsing for harmonic analysis of jazz chord se-
quences. In Proceedings of the International Computer Music Conference, pages 478–485. International Com-
puter Music Association, September.
Julia Hockenmaier and Mark Steedman. 2007. CCGBank: A corpus of CCG derivations and dependency struc-
tures extracted from the Penn Treebank. Computational Linguistics, 33:355–356.
Brett Kessler. 1995. Computational dialectology in Irish Gaelic. In Seventh Conference of the European Chapter
of the Association for Computational Linguistics, page 60, Dublin, Ireland, March.
William Lamb. 2003. Scottish Gaelic, 2nd edn. Lincom Europa, Munich, Germany.
Teresa Lynn, Ozlem Cetinoglu, Jennifer Foster, Elaine U´ı Dhonnchadha, Mark Dras, and Josef van Genabith.
2012a. Irish treebanking and parsing: A preliminary evaluation. In Nicoletta Calzolari, Khalid Choukri, Thierry
Declerck, Mehmet U˘gur Do˘gan, Bente Maegaard, Joseph Mariani, Jan Odijk, and Stelios Piperidis, editors,
Proceedings of the Eighth International Conference on Language Resources and Evaluation (LREC-2012),
pages 1939–1946, Istanbul, Turkey, May. European Language Resources Association (ELRA). ACL Anthology
Identifier: L12-1189.
Teresa Lynn, Jennifer Foster, Mark Dras, and Elaine U´ı Dhonnchadha. 2012b. Active learning and the irish
treebank. In Proceedings of the Australasian Language Technology Association Workshop 2012, pages 23–32,
Dunedin, New Zealand, December.
Teresa Lynn, Jennifer Foster, and Mark Dras. 2013. Working with a small dataset - semi-supervised dependency
parsing for Irish. In Proceedings of the Fourth Workshop on Statistical Parsing of Morphologically-Rich Lan-
guages, pages 1–11, Seattle, Washington, USA, October. Association for Computational Linguistics.
Teresa Lynn, Jennifer Foster, Mark Dras, and Lamia Tounsi. 2014. Cross-lingual transfer parsing for low-
resourced languages: An Irish case study. In Proceedings of Celtic Language Technology Workshop 2014,
Dublin, Ireland, August.
Ryan McDonald, Joakim Nivre, Yvonne Quirmbach-Brundage, Yoav Goldberg, Dipanjan Das, Kuzman Ganchev,
Keith Hall, Slav Petrov, Hao Zhang, Oscar T¨ackstr¨om, Claudia Bedini, N´uria Bertomeu Castell´o, and Jungmee
Lee. 2013. Universal dependency annotation for multilingual parsing. In Proceedings of the 51st Annual Meet-
ing of the Association for Computational Linguistics (Volume 2: Short Papers), pages 92–97, Sofia, Bulgaria,
August. Association for Computational Linguistics.
Ingo Mittendorf and Louisa Sadler. 2005. The Welsh PARGRAM grammar. In 12th Welsh Syntax Workshop,
Gregynog, Wales, July.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.986342">
64
</page>
<reference confidence="0.9969226">
Kevin P. Scannell. 2006. Machine translation for closely related language pairs. In Proceedings of the LREC 2006
Workshop on Strategies for developing machine translation for minority languages, pages 103–107, Genoa,
Italy, May.
Mark Steedman and Jason Baldridge. 2003. Combinatory Categorial Grammar. Online at
http://homepages.inf.ed.ac.uk/steedman/papers/ccg/SteedmanBaldridgeNTSyntax.pdf.
F. M. Tyers. 2010. Rule-based Breton to French machine translation. In Proceeedings of the 14th Annual Con-
ference of the European Association of Machine Translation, EAMT10, pages 174–181, Saint-Rapha¨el, France,
May.
Elaine U´ı Dhonnchadha. 2009. Part-of-speech tagging and partial parsing for Irish using finite-state transducers
and constraint grammar. Ph.D. thesis, Dublin City University.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.999612">
65
</page>
</variant>
</algorithm>
<algorithm name="ParsHed" version="110505">
<variant no="0" confidence="0.331996">
<title confidence="0.9566125">gdbank: The beginnings of a corpus of dependency structures type-logical grammar in Scottish Gaelic</title>
<author confidence="0.68925">Colin Batchelor Royal Society of Chemistry</author>
<author confidence="0.68925">UK CB Cambridge</author>
<email confidence="0.991445">batchelorc@rsc.org</email>
<abstract confidence="0.992612111111111">We present gdbank, a small handbuilt corpus of 32 sentences with dependency structures and categorial grammar type assignments. The sentences have been chosen to illustrate as broad a range of the unusual features of Scottish Gaelic as possible, particularly nouns being used to represent psychological states where more thoroughly-studied languages such as English and French would prefer a verb, and prepositions marking aspect, as is also seen in Welsh and, for example, Irish Gaelic. We provide hand-built dependency trees, building on previous work on Irish Gaelic and using the Universal Dependency Scheme. We also provide a tentative categorial grammar account of the words in the sentences, based largely on previous work on English.</abstract>
</variant>
</algorithm>
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>David Adger</author>
<author>Gillian Ramchand</author>
</authors>
<title>Predication and equation. Linguistic Enquiry,</title>
<date>2003</date>
<pages>34--325</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="1969" citStr="Adger and Ramchand, 2003" startWordPosition="297" endWordPosition="300">aries and databases available from Sabhal M`or Ostaig. A single paper in the ACL Anthology (Kessler, 1995) mentions Scottish Gaelic in the context of computational dialectology of Irish. There is also an LREC workshop paper (Scannell, 2006) on machine translation between Irish and Scottish Gaelic. Elsewhere in the Celtic languages, Welsh has an LFG grammar (Mittendorf and Sadler, 2005) but no treebanks. For Breton there is a small amount of work on morphological analysis and Constraint-Grammar-based machine translation (Tyers, 2010). Recent work on the grammar of Scottish Gaelic (for example (Adger and Ramchand, 2003; Adger and Ramchand, 2005), but there are many more examples) has largely focussed on theoretical syntactic issues somewhat distant from the more surfacy approaches popular in the field of natural language processing. This paper explores grammatical issues in Scottish Gaelic by means of dependency tagging and combinatory categorial grammar (CCG), which we see as complementary approaches. As such it is explicitly inspired by CCGbank (Hockenmaier and Steedman, 2007), which consists of dependency structures and CCG derivations for over 99% of the Penn Treebank. It is hoped that this corpus will </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Adger, Ramchand, 2003</marker>
<rawString>David Adger and Gillian Ramchand. 2003. Predication and equation. Linguistic Enquiry, 34:325–359.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>David Adger</author>
<author>Gillian Ramchand</author>
</authors>
<title>Psych nouns and predications.</title>
<date>2005</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 36th Annual Meeting of the North East Linguistic Society,</booktitle>
<location>Amherst, MA,</location>
<contexts>
<context position="1996" citStr="Adger and Ramchand, 2005" startWordPosition="301" endWordPosition="304">ble from Sabhal M`or Ostaig. A single paper in the ACL Anthology (Kessler, 1995) mentions Scottish Gaelic in the context of computational dialectology of Irish. There is also an LREC workshop paper (Scannell, 2006) on machine translation between Irish and Scottish Gaelic. Elsewhere in the Celtic languages, Welsh has an LFG grammar (Mittendorf and Sadler, 2005) but no treebanks. For Breton there is a small amount of work on morphological analysis and Constraint-Grammar-based machine translation (Tyers, 2010). Recent work on the grammar of Scottish Gaelic (for example (Adger and Ramchand, 2003; Adger and Ramchand, 2005), but there are many more examples) has largely focussed on theoretical syntactic issues somewhat distant from the more surfacy approaches popular in the field of natural language processing. This paper explores grammatical issues in Scottish Gaelic by means of dependency tagging and combinatory categorial grammar (CCG), which we see as complementary approaches. As such it is explicitly inspired by CCGbank (Hockenmaier and Steedman, 2007), which consists of dependency structures and CCG derivations for over 99% of the Penn Treebank. It is hoped that this corpus will be a useful adjunct to curr</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Adger, Ramchand, 2005</marker>
<rawString>David Adger and Gillian Ramchand. 2005. Psych nouns and predications. In Proceedings of the 36th Annual Meeting of the North East Linguistic Society, Amherst, MA, October.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Ted Briscoe</author>
<author>John Carroll</author>
</authors>
<title>Grammatical relation annotation. Online at http://www.sussex.ac.uk/Users/johnca/grdescription/index.html.</title>
<date>2000</date>
<contexts>
<context position="6324" citStr="Briscoe and Carroll, 2000" startWordPosition="1018" endWordPosition="1021">ope to be able to get the input of a native speaker, not least for interannotator studies. We use the CoNLL-X format (Buchholz and Marsi, 2006), leaving the POS and projective dependency fields empty and store the categorial grammar type under field 6, FEATS. 3 Dependency scheme There are four dependency schemes that we consulted while preparing the corpus. The initial inspiration was provided by the C&amp;C parser (Curran et al., 2007), which in addition to providing categorial grammar derivations for sentences provides a dependency structure in the GR (Grammatical Representation) scheme due to (Briscoe and Carroll, 2000; Briscoe and Carroll, 2002). This contains 23 types and was developed originally for parser evaluation. Another popular scheme is the Stanford Dependency scheme (de Marneffe and Manning, 2008; de Marneffe and Manning, 2013), which is more finely-grained with over twice the number of dependency types to deal specifically with noisy data and to make it more accessible to non-linguists building information extraction applications. A very important scheme is the Dublin scheme for Irish (Lynn et al., 2012a; Lynn et al., 2012b; Lynn et al., 2013), which is of a similar size to the Stanford scheme, </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Briscoe, Carroll, 2000</marker>
<rawString>Ted Briscoe and John Carroll. 2000. Grammatical relation annotation. Online at http://www.sussex.ac.uk/Users/johnca/grdescription/index.html.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Ted Briscoe</author>
<author>John Carroll</author>
</authors>
<title>Robust accurate statistical annotation of general text.</title>
<date>2002</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the Third International Conference on Language Resources and Evaluation (LREC’02),</booktitle>
<location>Las Palmas, Canary Islands, Spain,</location>
<contexts>
<context position="6352" citStr="Briscoe and Carroll, 2002" startWordPosition="1022" endWordPosition="1025">nput of a native speaker, not least for interannotator studies. We use the CoNLL-X format (Buchholz and Marsi, 2006), leaving the POS and projective dependency fields empty and store the categorial grammar type under field 6, FEATS. 3 Dependency scheme There are four dependency schemes that we consulted while preparing the corpus. The initial inspiration was provided by the C&amp;C parser (Curran et al., 2007), which in addition to providing categorial grammar derivations for sentences provides a dependency structure in the GR (Grammatical Representation) scheme due to (Briscoe and Carroll, 2000; Briscoe and Carroll, 2002). This contains 23 types and was developed originally for parser evaluation. Another popular scheme is the Stanford Dependency scheme (de Marneffe and Manning, 2008; de Marneffe and Manning, 2013), which is more finely-grained with over twice the number of dependency types to deal specifically with noisy data and to make it more accessible to non-linguists building information extraction applications. A very important scheme is the Dublin scheme for Irish (Lynn et al., 2012a; Lynn et al., 2012b; Lynn et al., 2013), which is of a similar size to the Stanford scheme, but the reason for its size </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Briscoe, Carroll, 2002</marker>
<rawString>Ted Briscoe and John Carroll. 2002. Robust accurate statistical annotation of general text. In Proceedings of the Third International Conference on Language Resources and Evaluation (LREC’02), Las Palmas, Canary Islands, Spain, May.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Sabine Buchholz</author>
<author>Erwin Marsi</author>
</authors>
<title>CoNLL-X shared task on multilingual dependency parsing.</title>
<date>2006</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the Tenth Conference on Computational Natural Language Learning,</booktitle>
<location>New York, NY,</location>
<contexts>
<context position="5842" citStr="Buchholz and Marsi, 2006" startWordPosition="945" endWordPosition="948">cally closed up, we separate out past-tense dh’ as its own token. These rules work for the small dataset described here but would clearly need to be expanded for work in the wild. In this preliminary work the dependencies and types have been determined by a single, non-native speaker, annotator, according to a set of guidelines which were built up during the annotation process. This is clearly less than ideal, however, the guidelines are available along with the corpus and we hope to be able to get the input of a native speaker, not least for interannotator studies. We use the CoNLL-X format (Buchholz and Marsi, 2006), leaving the POS and projective dependency fields empty and store the categorial grammar type under field 6, FEATS. 3 Dependency scheme There are four dependency schemes that we consulted while preparing the corpus. The initial inspiration was provided by the C&amp;C parser (Curran et al., 2007), which in addition to providing categorial grammar derivations for sentences provides a dependency structure in the GR (Grammatical Representation) scheme due to (Briscoe and Carroll, 2000; Briscoe and Carroll, 2002). This contains 23 types and was developed originally for parser evaluation. Another popul</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Buchholz, Marsi, 2006</marker>
<rawString>Sabine Buchholz and Erwin Marsi. 2006. CoNLL-X shared task on multilingual dependency parsing. In Proceedings of the Tenth Conference on Computational Natural Language Learning, New York, NY, June.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>James Curran</author>
<author>Stephen Clark</author>
<author>Johan Bos</author>
</authors>
<title>Linguistically motivated large-scale NLP with C&amp;C and Boxer.</title>
<date>2007</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 45th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics Companion Volume Proceedings of the Demo and Poster Sessions,</booktitle>
<pages>33--36</pages>
<publisher>Association</publisher>
<institution>for Computational Linguistics.</institution>
<location>Prague, Czech Republic,</location>
<contexts>
<context position="6135" citStr="Curran et al., 2007" startWordPosition="991" endWordPosition="994">ccording to a set of guidelines which were built up during the annotation process. This is clearly less than ideal, however, the guidelines are available along with the corpus and we hope to be able to get the input of a native speaker, not least for interannotator studies. We use the CoNLL-X format (Buchholz and Marsi, 2006), leaving the POS and projective dependency fields empty and store the categorial grammar type under field 6, FEATS. 3 Dependency scheme There are four dependency schemes that we consulted while preparing the corpus. The initial inspiration was provided by the C&amp;C parser (Curran et al., 2007), which in addition to providing categorial grammar derivations for sentences provides a dependency structure in the GR (Grammatical Representation) scheme due to (Briscoe and Carroll, 2000; Briscoe and Carroll, 2002). This contains 23 types and was developed originally for parser evaluation. Another popular scheme is the Stanford Dependency scheme (de Marneffe and Manning, 2008; de Marneffe and Manning, 2013), which is more finely-grained with over twice the number of dependency types to deal specifically with noisy data and to make it more accessible to non-linguists building information ext</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Curran, Clark, Bos, 2007</marker>
<rawString>James Curran, Stephen Clark, and Johan Bos. 2007. Linguistically motivated large-scale NLP with C&amp;C and Boxer. In Proceedings of the 45th Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics Companion Volume Proceedings of the Demo and Poster Sessions, pages 33–36, Prague, Czech Republic, June. Association for Computational Linguistics.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Marie-Catherine de Marneffe</author>
<author>Christopher D Manning</author>
</authors>
<title>The Stanford typed dependencies representation.</title>
<date>2008</date>
<journal>Organizing Committee.</journal>
<booktitle>In Coling 2008: Proceedings of the workshop on Cross-Framework and Cross-Domain Parser Evaluation,</booktitle>
<pages>1--8</pages>
<location>Manchester, UK,</location>
<marker>de Marneffe, Manning, 2008</marker>
<rawString>Marie-Catherine de Marneffe and Christopher D. Manning. 2008. The Stanford typed dependencies representation. In Coling 2008: Proceedings of the workshop on Cross-Framework and Cross-Domain Parser Evaluation, pages 1–8, Manchester, UK, August. Coling 2008 Organizing Committee.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Marie-Catherine de Marneffe</author>
<author>Christopher D Manning</author>
</authors>
<date>2013</date>
<note>Stanford typed dependencies manual. Online at http://nlp.stanford.edu/software/dependencies manual.pdf.</note>
<marker>de Marneffe, Manning, 2013</marker>
<rawString>Marie-Catherine de Marneffe and Christopher D. Manning. 2013. Stanford typed dependencies manual. Online at http://nlp.stanford.edu/software/dependencies manual.pdf.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Mark Granroth-Wilding</author>
<author>Mark Steedman</author>
</authors>
<title>Statistical parsing for harmonic analysis of jazz chord sequences.</title>
<date>2012</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the International Computer Music Conference,</booktitle>
<pages>478--485</pages>
<institution>International Computer Music Association,</institution>
<contexts>
<context position="7746" citStr="Granroth-Wilding and Steedman, 2012" startWordPosition="1244" endWordPosition="1247"> the Universal Dependency Scheme developed in (McDonald et al., 2013), which we have adopted, despite its being coarser-grained than the Dublin scheme, on account of its simplicity and utility for cross-lingual comparisons and cross-training (Lynn et al., 2014). Table 1 gives examples of the dependency relations used along with their mapping to the GR scheme. 4 Categorial grammar Combinatory categorial grammar (CCG) is a type-logical system which was developed to represent natural languages such as English but has subsequently been extended to other systems such as chord se61 quences in jazz (Granroth-Wilding and Steedman, 2012). For a full description the reader is referred to (Steedman and Baldridge, 2003), but in order to follow the rest of this paper you merely need to know that the type N/N is a function which takes an argument of N to its right, returning N, and that the type N\N is a function expecting an argument of N to its left and that these are combined by application, composition, where A/B combines with B/C to yield A/C, and type-raising where N is converted to T/(N\T). Attractive features of CCG for modelling a less-well-studied language include that it is a lexical theory in which it is the lexicon co</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Granroth-Wilding, Steedman, 2012</marker>
<rawString>Mark Granroth-Wilding and Mark Steedman. 2012. Statistical parsing for harmonic analysis of jazz chord sequences. In Proceedings of the International Computer Music Conference, pages 478–485. International Computer Music Association, September.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Julia Hockenmaier</author>
<author>Mark Steedman</author>
</authors>
<title>CCGBank: A corpus of CCG derivations and dependency structures extracted from the Penn Treebank. Computational Linguistics,</title>
<date>2007</date>
<pages>33--355</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="2438" citStr="Hockenmaier and Steedman, 2007" startWordPosition="366" endWordPosition="369">ical analysis and Constraint-Grammar-based machine translation (Tyers, 2010). Recent work on the grammar of Scottish Gaelic (for example (Adger and Ramchand, 2003; Adger and Ramchand, 2005), but there are many more examples) has largely focussed on theoretical syntactic issues somewhat distant from the more surfacy approaches popular in the field of natural language processing. This paper explores grammatical issues in Scottish Gaelic by means of dependency tagging and combinatory categorial grammar (CCG), which we see as complementary approaches. As such it is explicitly inspired by CCGbank (Hockenmaier and Steedman, 2007), which consists of dependency structures and CCG derivations for over 99% of the Penn Treebank. It is hoped that this corpus will be a useful adjunct to currently on-going work in developing a part-of-speech tagset and tagger for Scottish Gaelic. Section 2 describes how the corpus was prepared, sections 3 and 4 give some context for the dependency scheme and categorial grammar annotations respectively, and the main part of the paper is section 5, which deals with language-specific features of the corpus. 2 Preparing the corpus The corpus consists of a small handbuilt selection of sentences fr</context>
<context position="10321" citStr="Hockenmaier and Steedman (2007)" startWordPosition="1674" endWordPosition="1677"> Gaelic are often single-word, fused preposition–pronouns, a part-of-speech found across the Celtic languages. An ambiguous case of this is the token ris, which can be either ri with the pronoun e, hence taking the CCG type PP[ri], or the pre-determiner form of ri, hence PP[ri]/N[b]. The other class of fused preposition–pronoun we need to consider is that in sentences like Tha mi gad chluinntinn, “I can hear you”, where gad is ag fused with do “your”. In this case it has type PP[ag]/S[n]. Adjectives as in CCGbank are treated as clauses, S[ad ]. The verbal noun is labelled S[n] by analogy with Hockenmaier and Steedman (2007). In addition to declarative and interrogative clauses, S[dcl] and S[q], we take our lead from the fourfold division of preverbal particles and add negative clauses S[neg], usually introduced by cha or chan, and negative interrogative clauses, S[negq], introduced by nach. There are two verbs for “to be” in Scottish Gaelic, bi and is. Bi is used for predicate statements about nouns, to forming the present tense and to describe some psychological states. It does not usually equate two NPs, with an exception we will come to. In the Dublin scheme the prepositional phrase headed by ag in Td se ag i</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Hockenmaier, Steedman, 2007</marker>
<rawString>Julia Hockenmaier and Mark Steedman. 2007. CCGBank: A corpus of CCG derivations and dependency structures extracted from the Penn Treebank. Computational Linguistics, 33:355–356.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Brett Kessler</author>
</authors>
<title>Computational dialectology in Irish Gaelic.</title>
<date>1995</date>
<booktitle>In Seventh Conference of the European Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics,</booktitle>
<pages>60</pages>
<location>Dublin, Ireland, March. William Lamb.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="1451" citStr="Kessler, 1995" startWordPosition="221" endWordPosition="222">e categorial grammar account of the words in the sentences, based largely on previous work on English. 1 Introduction Scottish Gaelic (usually hereafter Gaelic) is a Celtic language, rather closely related to Irish, with around 59,000 speakers as of the last UK census in 2011. As opposed to the situation for Irish Gaelic (Lynn et al., 2012a; Lynn et al., 2012b; Lynn et al., 2013; Lynn et al., 2014) there are no treebanks or tagging schemes for Scottish Gaelic, although there are machine-readable dictionaries and databases available from Sabhal M`or Ostaig. A single paper in the ACL Anthology (Kessler, 1995) mentions Scottish Gaelic in the context of computational dialectology of Irish. There is also an LREC workshop paper (Scannell, 2006) on machine translation between Irish and Scottish Gaelic. Elsewhere in the Celtic languages, Welsh has an LFG grammar (Mittendorf and Sadler, 2005) but no treebanks. For Breton there is a small amount of work on morphological analysis and Constraint-Grammar-based machine translation (Tyers, 2010). Recent work on the grammar of Scottish Gaelic (for example (Adger and Ramchand, 2003; Adger and Ramchand, 2005), but there are many more examples) has largely focusse</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Kessler, 1995</marker>
<rawString>Brett Kessler. 1995. Computational dialectology in Irish Gaelic. In Seventh Conference of the European Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics, page 60, Dublin, Ireland, March. William Lamb. 2003. Scottish Gaelic, 2nd edn. Lincom Europa, Munich, Germany.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>Teresa Lynn</author>
<author>Ozlem Cetinoglu</author>
<author>Jennifer Foster</author>
</authors>
<title>Elaine U´ı Dhonnchadha, Mark Dras, and Josef van Genabith. 2012a. Irish treebanking and parsing: A preliminary evaluation.</title>
<date></date>
<booktitle>Proceedings of the Eighth International Conference on Language Resources and Evaluation (LREC-2012),</booktitle>
<pages>1939--1946</pages>
<editor>In Nicoletta Calzolari, Khalid Choukri, Thierry Declerck, Mehmet U˘gur Do˘gan, Bente Maegaard, Joseph Mariani, Jan Odijk, and Stelios Piperidis, editors,</editor>
<location>Istanbul, Turkey,</location>
<marker>Lynn, Cetinoglu, Foster, </marker>
<rawString>Teresa Lynn, Ozlem Cetinoglu, Jennifer Foster, Elaine U´ı Dhonnchadha, Mark Dras, and Josef van Genabith. 2012a. Irish treebanking and parsing: A preliminary evaluation. In Nicoletta Calzolari, Khalid Choukri, Thierry Declerck, Mehmet U˘gur Do˘gan, Bente Maegaard, Joseph Mariani, Jan Odijk, and Stelios Piperidis, editors, Proceedings of the Eighth International Conference on Language Resources and Evaluation (LREC-2012), pages 1939–1946, Istanbul, Turkey, May. European Language Resources Association (ELRA). ACL Anthology Identifier: L12-1189.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Teresa Lynn</author>
<author>Jennifer Foster</author>
<author>Mark Dras</author>
<author>Elaine U´ı Dhonnchadha</author>
</authors>
<title>Active learning and the irish treebank.</title>
<date>2012</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the Australasian Language Technology Association Workshop</booktitle>
<pages>23--32</pages>
<location>Dunedin, New Zealand,</location>
<contexts>
<context position="1178" citStr="Lynn et al., 2012" startWordPosition="176" endWordPosition="179">sh and French would prefer a verb, and prepositions marking aspect, as is also seen in Welsh and, for example, Irish Gaelic. We provide hand-built dependency trees, building on previous work on Irish Gaelic and using the Universal Dependency Scheme. We also provide a tentative categorial grammar account of the words in the sentences, based largely on previous work on English. 1 Introduction Scottish Gaelic (usually hereafter Gaelic) is a Celtic language, rather closely related to Irish, with around 59,000 speakers as of the last UK census in 2011. As opposed to the situation for Irish Gaelic (Lynn et al., 2012a; Lynn et al., 2012b; Lynn et al., 2013; Lynn et al., 2014) there are no treebanks or tagging schemes for Scottish Gaelic, although there are machine-readable dictionaries and databases available from Sabhal M`or Ostaig. A single paper in the ACL Anthology (Kessler, 1995) mentions Scottish Gaelic in the context of computational dialectology of Irish. There is also an LREC workshop paper (Scannell, 2006) on machine translation between Irish and Scottish Gaelic. Elsewhere in the Celtic languages, Welsh has an LFG grammar (Mittendorf and Sadler, 2005) but no treebanks. For Breton there is a smal</context>
<context position="6830" citStr="Lynn et al., 2012" startWordPosition="1095" endWordPosition="1098">provides a dependency structure in the GR (Grammatical Representation) scheme due to (Briscoe and Carroll, 2000; Briscoe and Carroll, 2002). This contains 23 types and was developed originally for parser evaluation. Another popular scheme is the Stanford Dependency scheme (de Marneffe and Manning, 2008; de Marneffe and Manning, 2013), which is more finely-grained with over twice the number of dependency types to deal specifically with noisy data and to make it more accessible to non-linguists building information extraction applications. A very important scheme is the Dublin scheme for Irish (Lynn et al., 2012a; Lynn et al., 2012b; Lynn et al., 2013), which is of a similar size to the Stanford scheme, but the reason for its size relative to GR is that it includes a large number of dependencies intended to handle grammatical features found in Irish but not in English. Lastly we mention the Universal Dependency Scheme developed in (McDonald et al., 2013), which we have adopted, despite its being coarser-grained than the Dublin scheme, on account of its simplicity and utility for cross-lingual comparisons and cross-training (Lynn et al., 2014). Table 1 gives examples of the dependency relations used a</context>
<context position="11655" citStr="Lynn et al. (2012" startWordPosition="1905" endWordPosition="1908">y this analysis over into Scottish Gaelic where this is the most common way of expressing the present tense. Figure 1 demonstrates this, where dhachaigh is a non-clausal modifier of dol, the verbal noun for “to go”. Is can be used as the copula between two NPs, and to express psychological states such as liking and preference. To say “I am a teacher”, the Gaelic is ‘S e tidsear a th’ annam. This, at least on the surface, equates pronoun e, with a noun described by a relative clause including the verb bi. Fig. 1 shows our dependency tree for this. Note that this is different from the scheme in Lynn et al. (2012b) because of a difference between the two languages. They treat the analogous sentence Is tusa an muinteoir “You are the teacher” as having a subject, “the teacher”, and a clausal predicate, tusa, “you indeed”. The most straightforward way of expressing a preference is the assertive is followed by an adjective or noun, a PP marking the preferrer, and then the object. If you dislike music, you might say Is beag orm ceol. There are exactly analogous constructions in Irish with is + adjective + PP[le] + object, for example Is maith liom... “I like...”, which in (UiDhonnchadha, 2009) is treated a</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Lynn, Foster, Dras, Dhonnchadha, 2012</marker>
<rawString>Teresa Lynn, Jennifer Foster, Mark Dras, and Elaine U´ı Dhonnchadha. 2012b. Active learning and the irish treebank. In Proceedings of the Australasian Language Technology Association Workshop 2012, pages 23–32, Dunedin, New Zealand, December.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Teresa Lynn</author>
<author>Jennifer Foster</author>
<author>Mark Dras</author>
</authors>
<title>Working with a small dataset - semi-supervised dependency parsing for Irish.</title>
<date>2013</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the Fourth Workshop on Statistical Parsing of Morphologically-Rich Languages,</booktitle>
<pages>1--11</pages>
<publisher>Association</publisher>
<institution>for Computational Linguistics.</institution>
<location>Seattle, Washington, USA,</location>
<contexts>
<context position="1218" citStr="Lynn et al., 2013" startWordPosition="184" endWordPosition="187">repositions marking aspect, as is also seen in Welsh and, for example, Irish Gaelic. We provide hand-built dependency trees, building on previous work on Irish Gaelic and using the Universal Dependency Scheme. We also provide a tentative categorial grammar account of the words in the sentences, based largely on previous work on English. 1 Introduction Scottish Gaelic (usually hereafter Gaelic) is a Celtic language, rather closely related to Irish, with around 59,000 speakers as of the last UK census in 2011. As opposed to the situation for Irish Gaelic (Lynn et al., 2012a; Lynn et al., 2012b; Lynn et al., 2013; Lynn et al., 2014) there are no treebanks or tagging schemes for Scottish Gaelic, although there are machine-readable dictionaries and databases available from Sabhal M`or Ostaig. A single paper in the ACL Anthology (Kessler, 1995) mentions Scottish Gaelic in the context of computational dialectology of Irish. There is also an LREC workshop paper (Scannell, 2006) on machine translation between Irish and Scottish Gaelic. Elsewhere in the Celtic languages, Welsh has an LFG grammar (Mittendorf and Sadler, 2005) but no treebanks. For Breton there is a small amount of work on morphological analys</context>
<context position="6871" citStr="Lynn et al., 2013" startWordPosition="1103" endWordPosition="1106">R (Grammatical Representation) scheme due to (Briscoe and Carroll, 2000; Briscoe and Carroll, 2002). This contains 23 types and was developed originally for parser evaluation. Another popular scheme is the Stanford Dependency scheme (de Marneffe and Manning, 2008; de Marneffe and Manning, 2013), which is more finely-grained with over twice the number of dependency types to deal specifically with noisy data and to make it more accessible to non-linguists building information extraction applications. A very important scheme is the Dublin scheme for Irish (Lynn et al., 2012a; Lynn et al., 2012b; Lynn et al., 2013), which is of a similar size to the Stanford scheme, but the reason for its size relative to GR is that it includes a large number of dependencies intended to handle grammatical features found in Irish but not in English. Lastly we mention the Universal Dependency Scheme developed in (McDonald et al., 2013), which we have adopted, despite its being coarser-grained than the Dublin scheme, on account of its simplicity and utility for cross-lingual comparisons and cross-training (Lynn et al., 2014). Table 1 gives examples of the dependency relations used along with their mapping to the GR scheme.</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Lynn, Foster, Dras, 2013</marker>
<rawString>Teresa Lynn, Jennifer Foster, and Mark Dras. 2013. Working with a small dataset - semi-supervised dependency parsing for Irish. In Proceedings of the Fourth Workshop on Statistical Parsing of Morphologically-Rich Languages, pages 1–11, Seattle, Washington, USA, October. Association for Computational Linguistics.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Teresa Lynn</author>
<author>Jennifer Foster</author>
<author>Mark Dras</author>
<author>Lamia Tounsi</author>
</authors>
<title>Cross-lingual transfer parsing for lowresourced languages: An Irish case study.</title>
<date>2014</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of Celtic Language Technology Workshop 2014,</booktitle>
<location>Dublin, Ireland,</location>
<contexts>
<context position="1238" citStr="Lynn et al., 2014" startWordPosition="188" endWordPosition="191"> aspect, as is also seen in Welsh and, for example, Irish Gaelic. We provide hand-built dependency trees, building on previous work on Irish Gaelic and using the Universal Dependency Scheme. We also provide a tentative categorial grammar account of the words in the sentences, based largely on previous work on English. 1 Introduction Scottish Gaelic (usually hereafter Gaelic) is a Celtic language, rather closely related to Irish, with around 59,000 speakers as of the last UK census in 2011. As opposed to the situation for Irish Gaelic (Lynn et al., 2012a; Lynn et al., 2012b; Lynn et al., 2013; Lynn et al., 2014) there are no treebanks or tagging schemes for Scottish Gaelic, although there are machine-readable dictionaries and databases available from Sabhal M`or Ostaig. A single paper in the ACL Anthology (Kessler, 1995) mentions Scottish Gaelic in the context of computational dialectology of Irish. There is also an LREC workshop paper (Scannell, 2006) on machine translation between Irish and Scottish Gaelic. Elsewhere in the Celtic languages, Welsh has an LFG grammar (Mittendorf and Sadler, 2005) but no treebanks. For Breton there is a small amount of work on morphological analysis and Constraint-Gr</context>
<context position="7371" citStr="Lynn et al., 2014" startWordPosition="1185" endWordPosition="1188">ns. A very important scheme is the Dublin scheme for Irish (Lynn et al., 2012a; Lynn et al., 2012b; Lynn et al., 2013), which is of a similar size to the Stanford scheme, but the reason for its size relative to GR is that it includes a large number of dependencies intended to handle grammatical features found in Irish but not in English. Lastly we mention the Universal Dependency Scheme developed in (McDonald et al., 2013), which we have adopted, despite its being coarser-grained than the Dublin scheme, on account of its simplicity and utility for cross-lingual comparisons and cross-training (Lynn et al., 2014). Table 1 gives examples of the dependency relations used along with their mapping to the GR scheme. 4 Categorial grammar Combinatory categorial grammar (CCG) is a type-logical system which was developed to represent natural languages such as English but has subsequently been extended to other systems such as chord se61 quences in jazz (Granroth-Wilding and Steedman, 2012). For a full description the reader is referred to (Steedman and Baldridge, 2003), but in order to follow the rest of this paper you merely need to know that the type N/N is a function which takes an argument of N to its righ</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Lynn, Foster, Dras, Tounsi, 2014</marker>
<rawString>Teresa Lynn, Jennifer Foster, Mark Dras, and Lamia Tounsi. 2014. Cross-lingual transfer parsing for lowresourced languages: An Irish case study. In Proceedings of Celtic Language Technology Workshop 2014, Dublin, Ireland, August.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>Ryan McDonald</author>
<author>Joakim Nivre</author>
<author>Yvonne Quirmbach-Brundage</author>
<author>Yoav Goldberg</author>
<author>Dipanjan Das</author>
<author>Kuzman Ganchev</author>
<author>Keith Hall</author>
<author>Slav Petrov</author>
<author>Hao Zhang</author>
<author>Oscar T¨ackstr¨om</author>
<author>Claudia Bedini</author>
<author>N´uria Bertomeu Castell´o</author>
<author>Jungmee Lee</author>
</authors>
<title>Universal dependency annotation for multilingual parsing.</title>
<date>2013</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 51st Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (Volume 2: Short Papers),</booktitle>
<pages>92--97</pages>
<publisher>Association</publisher>
<institution>for Computational Linguistics.</institution>
<location>Sofia, Bulgaria,</location>
<marker>McDonald, Nivre, Quirmbach-Brundage, Goldberg, Das, Ganchev, Hall, Petrov, Zhang, T¨ackstr¨om, Bedini, Castell´o, Lee, 2013</marker>
<rawString>Ryan McDonald, Joakim Nivre, Yvonne Quirmbach-Brundage, Yoav Goldberg, Dipanjan Das, Kuzman Ganchev, Keith Hall, Slav Petrov, Hao Zhang, Oscar T¨ackstr¨om, Claudia Bedini, N´uria Bertomeu Castell´o, and Jungmee Lee. 2013. Universal dependency annotation for multilingual parsing. In Proceedings of the 51st Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (Volume 2: Short Papers), pages 92–97, Sofia, Bulgaria, August. Association for Computational Linguistics.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Ingo Mittendorf</author>
<author>Louisa Sadler</author>
</authors>
<title>The Welsh PARGRAM grammar.</title>
<date>2005</date>
<booktitle>In 12th Welsh Syntax Workshop,</booktitle>
<location>Gregynog, Wales,</location>
<contexts>
<context position="1733" citStr="Mittendorf and Sadler, 2005" startWordPosition="262" endWordPosition="265"> in 2011. As opposed to the situation for Irish Gaelic (Lynn et al., 2012a; Lynn et al., 2012b; Lynn et al., 2013; Lynn et al., 2014) there are no treebanks or tagging schemes for Scottish Gaelic, although there are machine-readable dictionaries and databases available from Sabhal M`or Ostaig. A single paper in the ACL Anthology (Kessler, 1995) mentions Scottish Gaelic in the context of computational dialectology of Irish. There is also an LREC workshop paper (Scannell, 2006) on machine translation between Irish and Scottish Gaelic. Elsewhere in the Celtic languages, Welsh has an LFG grammar (Mittendorf and Sadler, 2005) but no treebanks. For Breton there is a small amount of work on morphological analysis and Constraint-Grammar-based machine translation (Tyers, 2010). Recent work on the grammar of Scottish Gaelic (for example (Adger and Ramchand, 2003; Adger and Ramchand, 2005), but there are many more examples) has largely focussed on theoretical syntactic issues somewhat distant from the more surfacy approaches popular in the field of natural language processing. This paper explores grammatical issues in Scottish Gaelic by means of dependency tagging and combinatory categorial grammar (CCG), which we see a</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Mittendorf, Sadler, 2005</marker>
<rawString>Ingo Mittendorf and Louisa Sadler. 2005. The Welsh PARGRAM grammar. In 12th Welsh Syntax Workshop, Gregynog, Wales, July.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Kevin P Scannell</author>
</authors>
<title>Machine translation for closely related language pairs.</title>
<date>2006</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the LREC 2006 Workshop on Strategies for</booktitle>
<pages>103--107</pages>
<location>Genoa, Italy,</location>
<contexts>
<context position="1585" citStr="Scannell, 2006" startWordPosition="241" endWordPosition="243"> (usually hereafter Gaelic) is a Celtic language, rather closely related to Irish, with around 59,000 speakers as of the last UK census in 2011. As opposed to the situation for Irish Gaelic (Lynn et al., 2012a; Lynn et al., 2012b; Lynn et al., 2013; Lynn et al., 2014) there are no treebanks or tagging schemes for Scottish Gaelic, although there are machine-readable dictionaries and databases available from Sabhal M`or Ostaig. A single paper in the ACL Anthology (Kessler, 1995) mentions Scottish Gaelic in the context of computational dialectology of Irish. There is also an LREC workshop paper (Scannell, 2006) on machine translation between Irish and Scottish Gaelic. Elsewhere in the Celtic languages, Welsh has an LFG grammar (Mittendorf and Sadler, 2005) but no treebanks. For Breton there is a small amount of work on morphological analysis and Constraint-Grammar-based machine translation (Tyers, 2010). Recent work on the grammar of Scottish Gaelic (for example (Adger and Ramchand, 2003; Adger and Ramchand, 2005), but there are many more examples) has largely focussed on theoretical syntactic issues somewhat distant from the more surfacy approaches popular in the field of natural language processin</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Scannell, 2006</marker>
<rawString>Kevin P. Scannell. 2006. Machine translation for closely related language pairs. In Proceedings of the LREC 2006 Workshop on Strategies for developing machine translation for minority languages, pages 103–107, Genoa, Italy, May.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Mark Steedman</author>
<author>Jason Baldridge</author>
</authors>
<date>2003</date>
<booktitle>Combinatory Categorial Grammar. Online at http://homepages.inf.ed.ac.uk/steedman/papers/ccg/SteedmanBaldridgeNTSyntax.pdf.</booktitle>
<contexts>
<context position="7827" citStr="Steedman and Baldridge, 2003" startWordPosition="1257" endWordPosition="1260">pted, despite its being coarser-grained than the Dublin scheme, on account of its simplicity and utility for cross-lingual comparisons and cross-training (Lynn et al., 2014). Table 1 gives examples of the dependency relations used along with their mapping to the GR scheme. 4 Categorial grammar Combinatory categorial grammar (CCG) is a type-logical system which was developed to represent natural languages such as English but has subsequently been extended to other systems such as chord se61 quences in jazz (Granroth-Wilding and Steedman, 2012). For a full description the reader is referred to (Steedman and Baldridge, 2003), but in order to follow the rest of this paper you merely need to know that the type N/N is a function which takes an argument of N to its right, returning N, and that the type N\N is a function expecting an argument of N to its left and that these are combined by application, composition, where A/B combines with B/C to yield A/C, and type-raising where N is converted to T/(N\T). Attractive features of CCG for modelling a less-well-studied language include that it is a lexical theory in which it is the lexicon contains the rules for how words are combined to make sense rather than an external</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Steedman, Baldridge, 2003</marker>
<rawString>Mark Steedman and Jason Baldridge. 2003. Combinatory Categorial Grammar. Online at http://homepages.inf.ed.ac.uk/steedman/papers/ccg/SteedmanBaldridgeNTSyntax.pdf.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>F M Tyers</author>
</authors>
<title>Rule-based Breton to French machine translation.</title>
<date>2010</date>
<booktitle>In Proceeedings of the 14th Annual Conference of the European Association of Machine Translation, EAMT10,</booktitle>
<pages>174--181</pages>
<location>Saint-Rapha¨el, France,</location>
<contexts>
<context position="1883" citStr="Tyers, 2010" startWordPosition="285" endWordPosition="286">g schemes for Scottish Gaelic, although there are machine-readable dictionaries and databases available from Sabhal M`or Ostaig. A single paper in the ACL Anthology (Kessler, 1995) mentions Scottish Gaelic in the context of computational dialectology of Irish. There is also an LREC workshop paper (Scannell, 2006) on machine translation between Irish and Scottish Gaelic. Elsewhere in the Celtic languages, Welsh has an LFG grammar (Mittendorf and Sadler, 2005) but no treebanks. For Breton there is a small amount of work on morphological analysis and Constraint-Grammar-based machine translation (Tyers, 2010). Recent work on the grammar of Scottish Gaelic (for example (Adger and Ramchand, 2003; Adger and Ramchand, 2005), but there are many more examples) has largely focussed on theoretical syntactic issues somewhat distant from the more surfacy approaches popular in the field of natural language processing. This paper explores grammatical issues in Scottish Gaelic by means of dependency tagging and combinatory categorial grammar (CCG), which we see as complementary approaches. As such it is explicitly inspired by CCGbank (Hockenmaier and Steedman, 2007), which consists of dependency structures and</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Tyers, 2010</marker>
<rawString>F. M. Tyers. 2010. Rule-based Breton to French machine translation. In Proceeedings of the 14th Annual Conference of the European Association of Machine Translation, EAMT10, pages 174–181, Saint-Rapha¨el, France, May.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Elaine U´ı Dhonnchadha</author>
</authors>
<title>Part-of-speech tagging and partial parsing for Irish using finite-state transducers and constraint grammar.</title>
<date>2009</date>
<tech>Ph.D. thesis,</tech>
<institution>Dublin City University.</institution>
<contexts>
<context position="12242" citStr="Dhonnchadha, 2009" startWordPosition="2005" endWordPosition="2006">the scheme in Lynn et al. (2012b) because of a difference between the two languages. They treat the analogous sentence Is tusa an muinteoir “You are the teacher” as having a subject, “the teacher”, and a clausal predicate, tusa, “you indeed”. The most straightforward way of expressing a preference is the assertive is followed by an adjective or noun, a PP marking the preferrer, and then the object. If you dislike music, you might say Is beag orm ceol. There are exactly analogous constructions in Irish with is + adjective + PP[le] + object, for example Is maith liom... “I like...”, which in (UiDhonnchadha, 2009) is treated as having the prepositional phrase as the subject and the adjective as predicate. We modify this to use adpmod as in the Universal Dependency Scheme as shown in Fig. 1. 62 dobj Figure 1: Dependency trees for (a) “I am going home”, (b) “I am a teacher” and (c) “I hate music”. (a) Tha mi a’ dol dhachaigh (b) ’S e tidsear a th’ annam (c) Is beag orm ce`ol nsubj xcomp prt adpmod dobj prt xcomp nsubj advmod adpmod acomp Type Count Notes Type Count N 104 noun N\N 13 PP/N 41 preposition PP/S[n] 10 N/N 38 determiner S[dep]/PP/N 8 . 31 . (N\N)/S[dcl] 7 S[dcl]/PP/N 25 bi, is S[n] 7 PP 18 PP </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Dhonnchadha, 2009</marker>
<rawString>Elaine U´ı Dhonnchadha. 2009. Part-of-speech tagging and partial parsing for Irish using finite-state transducers and constraint grammar. Ph.D. thesis, Dublin City University.</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>