<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="SectLabel" version="110505">
<variant no="0" confidence="0.001052">
<note confidence="0.936722">
COLING 2014
</note>
<title confidence="0.998299">
The 25th International Conference
on Computational Linguistics
Proceedings of the AHA!-Workshop on Information
Discovery in Text
</title>
<author confidence="0.702976">
August 23, 2014
</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.438485">
Dublin, Ireland
</affiliation>
<note confidence="0.56573675">
© 2014 The Authors
The papers in this volume are licensed by the authors under a
Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.
ISBN 978-1-873769-31-7
</note>
<page confidence="0.745276">
ii
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.984354" genericHeader="abstract">
Introduction
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999498052631579">
Welcome to the First AHA!-Workshop on Information Discovery in Text!
In this workshop, we are bringing together leading researchers in the emerging field of Information
Discovery to discuss approaches for Information Extraction that are not bound by a pre-specified
schema of information, but rather discover relational or categorial structure automatically from given
unstructured data.
This includes approaches that are based on unsupervised machine-learning over models of distributional
semantics, as well as OpenIE methods that relax the definition of semantic relations in order to more
openly extract structured information. Other approaches focus on inexpensively training information
extractors to be used across different domains with minimal supervision, or on adapting existing IE
systems to new domains and relations.
As different approaches on Information Discovery are gaining momentum, many fundamental questions
arise that merit discussion: How do these approaches compare and what are their relative strengths and
weaknesses? What are the desiderata and applications for Information Discovery methods? How can
such methods be evaluated and compared? And most importantly, what is the potential of Information
Discovery methods and where can current research lead?
We received 19 paper submissions of which the programme committee has accepted ten - six of which
were chosen for oral presentation and four as posters.
We look forward to a workshop full of interesting paper presentations, invited talks and lively discussion.
Sincerely,
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.718560428571429">
Alan Akbik and Larysa Visengeriyeva
AHA! Chairs
iii
Workshop Chairs and Organizers
Alan Akbik, Technische Universität Berlin
Larysa Visengeriyeva, Technische Universität Berlin
Programme Committee
</figure>
<affiliation confidence="0.9876486">
Isabelle Augenstein, University of Sheffield
Christoph Boden, Technische Universität Berlin
Danushka Bollegala, University of Liverpool
Leon Derczynski, University of Sheffield
Jonathan Gordon, University of Rochester
</affiliation>
<table confidence="0.9433995">
Max Heimel, Technische Universität Berlin
Holmer Hemsen, Technische Universität Berlin
Johannes Kirschnick, Technische Universität Berlin
Xiao Ling, University of Washington
Steffen Remus, Technische Universität Darmstadt
Martin Riedl, Technische Universität Darmstadt
</table>
<affiliation confidence="0.724720166666667">
Tim Rocktäschel, University College London
Vivek Srikumar, Stanford University
Mark Steedman, University of Edinburgh
Andreas Vlachos, University College London
Gerhard Weikum, Max Plank Institute Saarbrücken
Limin Yao, University of Massachusetts
</affiliation>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.756507">
Steering Committee
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.7400555">
Hans Uszkoreit, German Center for Artificial Intelligence
Volker Markl, Technische Universität Berlin
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.712658">
v
</page>
<tableCaption confidence="0.927684">
Table of Contents
</tableCaption>
<figure confidence="0.972822592592593">
Application-Driven Relation Extraction with Limited Distant Supervision
Andreas Vlachos and Stephen Clark 1
A Comparative Study of Conversion Aided Methods for WordNet Sentence Textual Similarity
Muhidin Mohamed and Mourad Oussalah 7
Word Clustering Based on Un-LP Algorithm
Jiguang Liang, Xiaofei Zhou, Yue Hu, Li Guo and Shuo Bai 13
Mining temporal footprints from Wikipedia
Michele Filannino and Goran Nenadic 19
Automatic Detection and Analysis of Impressive Japanese Sentences Using Supervised Machine Learn-
ing
Daiki Hazure, Masaki Murata and Masato Tokuhisa 26
Proposition Knowledge Graphs
Gabriel Stanovsky, Omer Levy and Ido Dagan 32
Using Distributional Semantics to Trace Influence and Imitation in Romantic Orientalist Poetry
Nitish Aggarwal, Justin Tonra and Paul Buitelaar 38
Unsupervised Approach to Extracting Problem Phrases from User Reviews of Products
Elena Tutubalina and Vladimir Ivanov 43
Extracting a Repository of Events and Event References from News Clusters
Silvia Julinda, Christoph Boden and Alan Akbik 49
Towards Social Event Detection and Contextualisation for Journalists
Prashant Khare and Bahareh Heravi 54
vii
Conference Program
Application-Driven Relation Extraction with Limited Distant Supervision
Andreas Vlachos and Stephen Clark
A Comparative Study of Conversion Aided Methods for WordNet Sentence Textual
Similarity
</figure>
<reference confidence="0.8841811">
Muhidin Mohamed and Mourad Oussalah
Word Clustering Based on Un-LP Algorithm
Jiguang Liang, Xiaofei Zhou, Yue Hu, Li Guo and Shuo Bai
Mining temporal footprints from Wikipedia
Michele Filannino and Goran Nenadic
Automatic Detection and Analysis of Impressive Japanese Sentences Using Super-
vised Machine Learning
Daiki Hazure, Masaki Murata and Masato Tokuhisa
Proposition Knowledge Graphs
Gabriel Stanovsky, Omer Levy and Ido Dagan
Using Distributional Semantics to Trace Influence and Imitation in Romantic Ori-
entalist Poetry
Nitish Aggarwal, Justin Tonra and Paul Buitelaar
Unsupervised Approach to Extracting Problem Phrases from User Reviews of Prod-
ucts
Elena Tutubalina and Vladimir Ivanov
Extracting a Repository of Events and Event References from News Clusters
Silvia Julinda, Christoph Boden and Alan Akbik
Towards Social Event Detection and Contextualisation for Journalists
Prashant Khare and Bahareh Heravi
</reference>
<page confidence="0.813621">
ix
</page>
</variant>
</algorithm>
<algorithm name="ParsHed" version="110505">
<variant no="0" confidence="0.339529">
<note confidence="0.925411909090909">COLING 2014 The 25th International on Computational Linguistics Proceedings of the AHA!-Workshop on Information Discovery in Text August 23, Dublin, Ireland The Authors The papers in this volume are licensed by the authors under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License. ISBN 978-1-873769-31-7</note>
<intro confidence="0.591781">ii</intro>
</variant>
</algorithm>
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>Muhidin Mohamed</author>
<author>Mourad Oussalah</author>
</authors>
<title>Word Clustering Based on Un-LP Algorithm Jiguang Liang, Xiaofei Zhou, Yue Hu, Li Guo and Shuo Bai Mining temporal footprints from Wikipedia Michele Filannino and Goran Nenadic Automatic Detection and Analysis of Impressive Japanese Sentences Using Supervised Machine Learning Daiki Hazure, Masaki Murata and Masato Tokuhisa Proposition Knowledge Graphs</title>
<marker>Mohamed, Oussalah, </marker>
<rawString>Muhidin Mohamed and Mourad Oussalah Word Clustering Based on Un-LP Algorithm Jiguang Liang, Xiaofei Zhou, Yue Hu, Li Guo and Shuo Bai Mining temporal footprints from Wikipedia Michele Filannino and Goran Nenadic Automatic Detection and Analysis of Impressive Japanese Sentences Using Supervised Machine Learning Daiki Hazure, Masaki Murata and Masato Tokuhisa Proposition Knowledge Graphs</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>Gabriel Stanovsky</author>
</authors>
<title>Omer Levy and Ido Dagan Using Distributional Semantics to Trace Influence and Imitation in Romantic Orientalist</title>
<publisher>Poetry</publisher>
<marker>Stanovsky, </marker>
<rawString>Gabriel Stanovsky, Omer Levy and Ido Dagan Using Distributional Semantics to Trace Influence and Imitation in Romantic Orientalist Poetry</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>Nitish Aggarwal</author>
</authors>
<title>Justin Tonra and Paul Buitelaar Unsupervised Approach to Extracting Problem Phrases from User Reviews of Products</title>
<marker>Aggarwal, </marker>
<rawString>Nitish Aggarwal, Justin Tonra and Paul Buitelaar Unsupervised Approach to Extracting Problem Phrases from User Reviews of Products</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>Elena</author>
</authors>
<title>Tutubalina and Vladimir Ivanov Extracting a Repository of Events and Event References from News Clusters Silvia Julinda, Christoph Boden and Alan Akbik</title>
<marker>Elena, </marker>
<rawString>Elena Tutubalina and Vladimir Ivanov Extracting a Repository of Events and Event References from News Clusters Silvia Julinda, Christoph Boden and Alan Akbik</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<title>Towards Social Event Detection and Contextualisation for Journalists Prashant Khare and Bahareh Heravi</title>
<marker></marker>
<rawString>Towards Social Event Detection and Contextualisation for Journalists Prashant Khare and Bahareh Heravi</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>