<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="SectLabel" version="110505">
<variant no="0" confidence="0.002514">
<title confidence="0.892352">
OpenWordNet-PT: A Project Report
</title>
<author confidence="0.710527">
Alexandre Rademaker
</author>
<note confidence="0.6597415">
IBM Research Brazil / FGV/EMAp
Rio de Janeiro, Brazil
</note>
<email confidence="0.764293">
alexrad@br.ibm.com
</email>
<note confidence="0.398517666666667">
Valeria de Paiva
Nunance Communications
Sunnyvale, CA, USA
</note>
<email confidence="0.951616">
valeria.depaiva@gmail.com
</email>
<author confidence="0.98092">
Gerard de Melo Livy Maria Real Coelho Maira Gatti
</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.7544105">
Tsinghua University Univ. Federal do Paran´a IBM Research Brazil
Beijing, China Curitiba, Brazil Rio de Janeiro, Brazil
</affiliation>
<email confidence="0.997504">
gdm@demelo.org livyreal@gmail.com mairacg@br.ibm.com
</email>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.995628" genericHeader="abstract">
Abstract
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999785230769231">
This paper presents OpenWordNet-PT, a
freely available open-source wordnet for
Portuguese, with its latest developments
and practical uses. We provide a detailed
description of the RDF representation de-
veloped for OpenWordnet-PT. We high-
light our efforts to extend the coverage of
our resource and add nominalization rela-
tions connecting nouns and verbs. Finally,
we present several real-world applications
where OpenWordnet-PT was put to use,
including a large-scale high-throughput
sentiment analysis system.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.998993" genericHeader="introduction">
1 Introduction
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999830666666667">
Semantic relationships between words are crucial
in many forms of natural language processing.
Computational systems are not aware of the fact
that carro and autom´ovel both refer to cars, or that
caminh˜ao (truck) is related to these words as well
in that they all share a common more general hy-
pernym.
OpenWordnet-PT (or OpenWN-PT for short)
is a lexical-semantic resource describing (Brazil-
ian) Portuguese words and their relationships. It
is modelled after and fully interoperable with
the original Princeton WordNet for English (Fell-
baum, 1998), relying on the same identifiers as
WordNet 3.0. This means that one can easily
find Portuguese equivalents for specific English
word senses and vice versa. This also means
that OpenWN-PT is part of a large ecosystem
of compatible resources, including domain identi-
fiers (Magnini and Cavaglia, 2000) and mappings
to Wikipedia (de Melo and Weikum, 2010).
In this paper, we specify the RDF-based repre-
sentation chosen for OpenWN-PT (Section 2) and
describe our recent efforts to extend this resource
(Sections 3 to 5), most notably with nominaliza-
tion relations connecting nouns and verbs (Sec-
tion 4). We also highlight several important ap-
plications of OpenWN-PT (Section 6).
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.993508" genericHeader="method">
2 RDF Representation
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999904604651163">
Wordnets have been distributed in a wide range of
different incompatible data formats. An increas-
ingly popular way of addressing the issue of in-
teroperability is to rely on Linked Data and Se-
mantic Web standards such as RDF (Cyganiak
and Wood, 2003) and OWL (Hitzler et al., 2012),
which have led to the emergence of a number
of Linked Data projects for lexical resources (de
Melo and Weikum, 2008; Chiarcos et al., 2012).
We believe that OpenWN-PT should best be en-
coded and distributed in RDF/OWL. Not only do
these standards allow us to publish both the data
model and the actual data in the same format.
They also provide for instant compatibility with
a vast range of existing data processing tools, in-
cluding databases (so-called “triple stores”) pro-
viding SQL-like query interfaces based on the
SPARQL standard (Harris and Seaborne, 2013).
Some years ago, a task force of the Semantic
Web Best Practices Working Group proposed a
standard encoding of WordNet in RDF (van As-
sem et al., 2006). This effort made WordNet di-
rectly accessible to Semantic Web applications.
The proposed conversion aimed to be as complete
as possible. The suggested representation also
stayed as close to the original source as possible,
that is, it reflects the original WordNet data model
without interpretation. Comparing with previous
RDF translations of WordNet, the main features
of this version are: (1) It does not model the hy-
ponym hierarchy as a subclass hierarchy. (2) It
represents words and word senses as separate en-
tities with their own URI which makes it possi-
ble to refer to them directly. (3) It contains all
relations that are present in Princeton WordNet.
(4) It provides OWL semantics in the form of in-
verse properties, definition of property character-
istics and property restrictions on classes that can
be used by both the RDFS and OWL infrastruc-
tures.
The schema of the conversion has three main
classes: Synset, Word and WordSense. There
are three kinds of properties in the schema.
A first set of properties connects instances of
the main classes together. The class Synset
is linked to its WordSenses with the prop-
erty containsWordSense, and WordSense
to its Word with the property word. A sec-
ond set of properties represents the WordNet re-
lations such as hyponymy and meronymy, in-
cluding those that relate two Synsets to each
other (e.g. hyponymOf), those that relate two
WordSenses to each other (e.g. antonymOf),
and a miscellaneous set containing gloss and
frame. Finally, a third set of properties pro-
vides additional information about entities using
literals. Examples are synsetId, which records
the original ID given in Princeton WordNet to a
synset, and the tagCount of a WordSense.
The actual lexical form of a Word is recorded with
the property lexicalForm. Each synset has an
rdfs:label that is filled with the lexical form
of the first word sense in the synset.
OpenWN-PT is completely aligned to Prince-
ton WordNet. This means that each OpenWN-
PT synset is a translation of an original Prince-
ton WordNet synset, with no additional synsets
or relations so far. Given this direct relation, we
decided that our RDF representation does not re-
quire a full redundant modeling of all relations and
information in Princeton WordNet. Instead, we
chose to model our RDF as an add-on to Word-
Net 3.0 that extends it with information about the
Portuguese language. For this, we simply add
new Synset and WordSense instances that are
linked to the English WordNet.
OpenWN-PT’s RDF will thus only be useful to-
gether with an RDF version of Princeton WordNet.
While there is a previous RDF version of WordNet
3.0 online, 1 we wanted to ensure that all infor-
mation in the WordNet 3.0 distribution was trans-
formed to RDF. To this end, we wrote our own
Common Lisp code to translate the WordNet 3.0
data files to RDF, following the W3C model (van
Assem et al., 2006) with a few modifications as
follows.
</bodyText>
<listItem confidence="0.97965432">
1. We add two more classes named
BaseConcept and CoreConcept to
identify the synsets that are base con-
cepts (Vossen, 2002) or core concepts (Boyd-
Graber et al., 2006), respectively.
2. We have added properties to capture infor-
mation from WordNet 3.0 not available in
the Prolog distribution nor in the “database
files only” distribution. To this end, we
have parsed and read the files sents.vrb, sent-
idx.vrb and lexnames. A WordSense can
have a lexFile, lexId, senseKey, and
an example sentence (for a WordSense of
a VerbSynset). A synset can have a
lexicographerFile and a frame (in
the case of a VerbSynset).
3. We omitted redundant subclasses of
WordSense like NounWordSense,
as the part-of-speech can be derived from the
corresponding synset. A subclass of Word
called Collocation is also omitted, as the
lexical form of Word instances can easily be
examined to check for collocations.
4. We have adopted a different schema for nam-
ing the resources identifiers (URIs).
</listItem>
<bodyText confidence="0.8766864">
In Figure 1, we show the synset 00001740-n en-
coded in RDF in its more readable N3 notation
variant (Berners-Lee and Connolly, 2011). Word
instances are blank resources, that is, resources
without a URI or unnamed resources. In Figure 2,
we present the same synset in a graphical way, ad-
ditionally showing its connection with the corre-
sponding synset in the Princeton WordNet, includ-
ing relevant semantic relations. Our code for this
RDF version of WordNet 3.0 is freely available. 2
</bodyText>
<footnote confidence="0.9991662">
1See http://bit.ly/1cVExvj.
2See http://bit.ly/1ctbGSL. The code requires
AllegroGraph and Allegro Common Lisp. Both are commer-
cial tools but free editions can be obtained on the Franz Inc.
website at http://www.franz.com.
</footnote>
<equation confidence="0.953448736842105">
@prefix rdf: &lt;http : / /www.w3. org /1999/02/22 − rdf−syntax−ns#&gt; .
@prefix wn30 : &lt;http://arademaker.github.com/wn30/schema/&gt; .
@prefix wn30en : &lt;http : / / arademaker . github . com / wn30−en / i n s t a n c e s /&gt; .
@prefix wn30br : &lt;http : / / arademaker . github . com / wn30−br / i n s t a n c e s /&gt; .
wn30br :synset −00001740−n wn30 : synsetId ”00001740” ;
rdf : type wn30 : NounSynset ; rdf : type wn30 : BaseConcept ;
owl : sameAs wn30en: synset −00001740−n ;
wn30 : containsWordSense wn30br :wordsense −00001740−n−1 ;
wn30 : containsWordSense wn30br : wordsense −00001740−n−3 ;
wn30 : gloss ”o que e´ percebido , conhecido ou inferido como
tendo e x i s t eˆncia pr o´pria (vivente ou n ˜ao vivente )” .
wn30br : wordsense −00001740−n−1 wn30 : wordNumber ”1” ;
rdfs:label ” ser ” ;
rdf : type wn30 : WordSense ;
wn30 : word :anon642 .
wn30br : wordsense −00001740−n−3 rdfs:label ” entidade ” ;
wn30 : wordNumber ”3” ;
rdf : type wn30 : WordSense ;
wn30 : word :anon24777 .
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.828413">
: anon24777 wn30 : lexicalForm ” entidade ” ; rdf : type wn30 : Word .
: anon642 wn30 : lexicalForm ” ser ” ; rdf : type wn30 : Word .
</bodyText>
<figureCaption confidence="0.99984">
Figure 1: The synset 00001740-n in N3 notation
Figure 2: Synset 00001740-n and its neighbors in Princeton WordNet and OpenWordNet-PT
</figureCaption>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.901707" genericHeader="method">
3 Extending the Coverage
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99961475">
The first version of OpenWN-PT was created us-
ing a semi-automated process drawing on UWN
(de Melo and Weikum, 2009) and on manual re-
visions and gloss translations (Rademaker et al.,
2012). Table 1 summarizes how OpenWN-PT has
increased over the last two years. The number
of synsets should be understood as the number of
synsets with at least one Portuguese word. The
sources of the new data were (Bond and Foster,
2013) and some manual addition of entries while
working on projects that make use of the resource.
These use cases are described later in Section 6.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.8649585">
2011 2013 increase
synsets 41,810 43,895 5%
words 52,220 54,125 3%
senses 68,285 74,054 8%
</table>
<tableCaption confidence="0.998528">
Table 1: OpenWN-PT’s coverage development
</tableCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.999912693877551">
Among resources that we can use to expand
OpenWN-PT, we are considering (Dias-Da-Silva
and de Moraes, 2003) and (Gonc¸alo Oliveira,
2013). Both projects are also concerned with the
construction of a WordNet-like lexical resource
for Portuguese. The former is more limited, of-
fering around 19,888 synsets without any links to
the Princeton WordNet and no relations between
synsets, other than synonymy. The latter has al-
ready incorporated OpenWN-PT and is also en-
coded in RDF following the same vocabulary of
(van Assem et al., 2006). This means that it should
be straightfoward to obtain data from Onto.PT.
Besides the continuous work on increasing the
number of translated synsets, we have also in-
vested some time to expand the relations. All
semantic relations in Princeton WordNet 3.0 are
included in our RDF export. Figure 2 shows
how one can navigate from a OpenWN-PT synset
in the graph to the Princeton WordNet synset.
Most semantic relations also apply to the Por-
tuguese words. However, since the first version
of OpenWN-PT came from the UWN, which does
not have word sense-specific relations, we do not
have any generic way to map the lexical relations
(relations between word senses) from Princeton
WordNet to specific words in OpenWN-PT.
Mainly because of the sentiment analysis
project described later in Section 6, we focused
in particular on antonomy relationships. Study-
ing the plot in Figure 3, which shows the dis-
tribution of the number of senses per synset in
both wordnets, it is clear that we could take ad-
vantage of the fact that the majority of synsets in
both wordnets have only one sense to propagate
the antonoym pairs in Princeton WordNet to the
senses in OpenWN-PT with also only one sense.
We search for synsets A in Princeton WordNet
with only one sense, where this specific sense is
related to another sense that is also unique in its
synset in Princeton WordNet, say B. We can prop-
agate this antonymy relation to OpenWN-PT if
synset A and B in OpenWN-PT also have only
one sense each. Using this idea, we were able to
add 707 antonymy relation instances to OpenWN-
PT (only about 10% of the number of pairs in the
antonym relation of Princeton WordNet 3.0). In
the future, we plan to additionally use common
prefixes like “des”, “in” to match senses.
</bodyText>
<figureCaption confidence="0.996935">
Figure 3: distribution of senses per synset
</figureCaption>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.934726" genericHeader="method">
4 Nominalizations and NomLex-BR
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999720577777778">
Another extension of OpenWN-PT aims at incor-
porating links to connect deverbal nouns with their
corresponding verbs. A sentence like “Alexander
destroyed the city in 332 BC” can easily be parsed
to obtain its semantic arguments, such as the agent
(Alexander), the object destroyed (the city), and
the time of the destruction (332 BC). In contrast, a
sentence like “Alexander’s destruction of the city
happened in 332 BC” is typically much harder to
interpret correctly. The latter sentence describes
the same event with the same semantic arguments,
but these arguments are usually much harder to ob-
tain automatically from a syntactic parser, given
that the event is described in terms of its nominal-
ization destruction instead of its verbal form de-
stroy. A proper handling of nominalizations (we
are especially interested here in nominalizations of
verbs, also called deverbal nouns) is important in
numerous natural language understanding and in-
ference tasks (Gurevich et al., 2008).
For English, NOMLEX (Macleod et al., 1998)
has provided extensive descriptions of nominal-
izations. The original NOMLEX was constructed
starting out with nominalizations with the suffixes
-ion, -ment and -er, relying on frequent words in a
corpus. NOMLEX sought not only to describe the
possible complements for a nominalization, but
also to relate the nominal complements to the ar-
guments of the corresponding verb.
Our NomLex-BR project (Coelho et al., 2014)
started with a manual translation of NOMLEX
to Brazilian Portuguese, as NOMLEX is rela-
tively small but still covers the most salient vo-
cabulary. Many cases were very straightforward,
due to the morphology of the words with sim-
ilar nominalizer morphemes in both languages,
e.g. pairs like adjournment/adiamento, ben-
eficiary/benefici´ario, corrosion/ corros˜ao.
Overall, we have created over 1,000 entries.
These have been integrated into OpenWN-PT,
which we hope will facilitate their use for lin-
guistic research of the traditional kind. For now,
most of the words from NomLex-BR are linked to
Word instances of OpenWN-PT. Eventually, we
would like to have entries of NomLex-BR linked
to specific WordSense instances of OpenWN-
PT to the extent possible. We are currently also
devising strategies to create entries and model phe-
nomena specific to Portuguese.
Incorporating NomLex-BR data into OpenWN-
PT has shown itself useful in pinpointing some is-
sues with the coherence and richness of OpenWN-
PT. In particular, it seems that 20% of words in
NomLex-BR (which were manually chosen) are
missing in OpenWN-PT. For instance, the word
abasement corresponds in NOMLEX to the verb
abase, and thus we would like a similar correspon-
dence between the Portuguese noun aviltamento
and the verb aviltar (our suggested translations).
However, while abasement in English is present
in two synsets with Portuguese equivalents, the
synsets for the verb abase have a repetition in
Portuguese. OpenWN-PT simply has two synsets
humilhar, abaixar and humilhar, rebaixar. The
more common verb humilhar is repeated, while
the uncommon aviltar was left out. Thus by veri-
fying that verb-noun pairs in English are mapped
to verb-noun pairs in Portuguese, we help ensure
that the richness of synonyms in Portuguese is not
lost in OpenWN-PT, which, being automatically
derived from connectivity graphs, often gives pref-
erence to more commonly used words.
Other useful kinds of relationships between
parts of speech (say the connections between ad-
jectives and adverbs) are likely to also help to
improve the accuracy and richness of our auto-
matically derived resource. Altogether we reckon
that by examining at random relationships that we
know hold in the English WordNet in its translated
Portuguese version, we should be able to both
check the accuracy of OpenWordNet-PT and si-
multaneously investigate the parallelism between
the two languages. From this perspective, one of
the more interesting relationships, as far as knowl-
edge representation is concerned, is the relation-
ship of entailment between synsets. We have a
goal of checking some 200 random English rela-
tionships in their translated forms as a way of mea-
suring accuracy of the OpenWN-PT in the very
immediate future.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.996889" genericHeader="method">
5 Accuracy
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9993112">
Following the ideas of (Cruse, 1986), both
(Vossen, 2002) and (Marrafa, 2002) used
diagnostic templates of sentences to ver-
ify relations between synsets. We started
a similar exercise. We choose six rela-
tions: hypernymOf, memberHolonymOf,
instanceOf, substanceHolonymOf,
entails and causes. For each of these
relations, we randomly chose 30 pairs of synsets
and then random words from each synset. Note
that we had to keep drawing random synset
relationships until both synsets included at least
one Portuguese word. We ended up with 180
random sentences that we submitted to a linguist
for manual verification (a single linguist to begin
with). The linguist had to mark each sentence
as being “correct”, “wrong” or “dubious”. As
a result, we obtained 150 sentences marked as
correct (83% of the sentences), 17 marked as
wrong (one of the two words used to fill the
template is probably placed in a wrong synset),
and 13 marked as dubious (the linguist was not
sure about the semantics of the sentence). In some
cases, the linguist was able to give detailed feed-
back like indicating misspelt words or providing
a more specific reason for why the sentence was
considered wrong. There were also trivial pairs
in which the same word was chosen from both
synsets. We hope to improve our tests in these
cases.
Finally, some data mining could also help us
to improve the accuracy of OpenWN-PT. For in-
stance, synsets with an uncommonly high number
of senses or words with an unexpected number of
senses should be reviewed.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.997291" genericHeader="method">
6 Usage Reports
</sectionHeader>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.999514">
6.1 Word Sense Disambiguation
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999973">
OpenWN-PT has been incorporated into Freel-
ing (Padr´o and Stanilovsky, 2012), a well-known
suite of NLP tools. With OpenWN-PT’s data and
Freeling’s word sense disambiguation framework,
a given Portuguese text can automatically be an-
notated with word senses, and we can use these
annotations in the projects below.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.999826">
6.2 Sentiment Analysis
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999789423076923">
We have been investigating the OpenWN-PT us-
age in one of our projects at IBM Research-Brazil.
In this project the main concern is to gather the
sentiment of microblogging posts about football
matches in Portuguese in real-time. The most
famous microblogging online social network is
Twitter3. As of 2013, there are more than 550 mil-
lion active registered users and 58 million tweets
are posted per day on average. These tweets are
short messages that people send to provide up-
dates on their activities, observations, or other in-
teresting content, directly or indirectly to others.
In sports, for instance, a lot of sentiment is ex-
pressed during a game match. Recently there have
been several approaches that tackle the problem
of classifying tweet sentiments using supervised
or semi-supervised machine learning approaches
(Celikyilmaz et al., 2010; Bakliwal et al., 2012)
or lexicon-based methods, which are mostly unsu-
pervised approaches (Li et al., 2011; Hogenboom
et al., 2013).
As people react to events and generate a large
Twitter stream of data, it is impossible to manu-
ally process and analyze all these data during the
event’s lifespan. There are several challenges re-
lated to analyzing all this data as quickly as possi-
</bodyText>
<footnote confidence="0.649737">
3Seehttp://twitter.com
</footnote>
<bodyText confidence="0.999835425925926">
ble. First, the system must be reliable: no informa-
tion should be lost. This means that a highly avail-
able system is called for, with redundancy and ac-
tive fault tolerance mechanisms. Second, it must
have a high throughput, which leads us to an in-
frastructure that allows parallelism. Thirdly, sen-
timent classifiers should be able to work with lim-
ited resources in both time and space. The training
phase should handle an unbalanced distribution of
sentiments and in real time, it should be adaptive.
OpenWN-PT, Princeton WordNet, and Senti-
WordNet (Baccianella et al., 2010) were used with
the goal of assessing a Machine Learning-based
sentiment analysis component integrated into the
IBM InfoSphere Streams (ISS) platform. ISS was
used to address the problem of handling large
streaming Twitter data with availability and scal-
ability in real-time. One main advantage of us-
ing OpenWN-PT and SentiWordNet during the de-
velopment of the Machine Learning-based classi-
fier was that we could start experimenting without
training data. The experiment was possible be-
cause OpenWN-PT synsets are linked to Princeton
WordNet synsets which, in turn, have their senti-
ment scores in SentiWordNet. In order to train the
classifiers for sentiment analysis, we have built a
training corpus comprising data posted on Twitter
during four friendly matches of the Brazilian team
in 2013. About 1 million tweets have been gath-
ered from these games. We built an online inter-
face for a collaborative labeling of the tweets with
respect to seven different classes: Certainly Neg-
ative (CN), Negative (N), Maybe Negative (MN),
Neutral (N), Maybe Positive (MP), Positive (P),
and Certainly Positive (CP). Here, we divided both
negative and positive sentiment into three more
specific classes in order to capture the degree of
confidence for which the user is able to associate
that tweet with one of these two main sentiment
classes. Another class, Don’t Know (D), repre-
sents tweets for which the sentiment could not be
identified by the user. We used this annotated cor-
pus to train a Naive Bayes classifier. OpenWN-PT
and SentiWordNet were used to check the consis-
tency of the annotations and to provide insights
during the entire course of the project. Unfortu-
nately, given the real-time characteristic of project
we were not able to run both classifiers on all
collected data. As future work, we plan to use
OpenWN-PT to expand the training corpus. For
instance, from the manually annotated tweets we
can produce others tweets with synonym words
which are likely to retain the same semantics and
thus also the same sentiment with high probability.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.999051">
6.3 Historical Biographic Dictionary
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999973677419355">
The second project we used OpenWN-PT for is
related to the digitalization of a dictionary of his-
torical biographies. The Getulio Vargas Founda-
tion (FGV) maintains the Brazilian Dictionary of
Historical Biographies (DHBB), a resource with
7,000 entries, the majority of which are biograph-
ical entries about politicians in Brazil’s recent his-
tory. The FGV would like to transform this static
collection of entries into new methods of learning,
teaching, acquiring, storing, and using informa-
tion. Thus we decided that this knowledge would
be more actionable if we could operate on it with
semantic tools.
We used Freeling to automatically process this
data by performing tokenization, sentence split-
ting, part-of-speech tagging, and finally word
sense disambiguation with respect to OpenWN-
PT. The DHBB corpus has a vocabulary size of
247,063 words. Table 2 shows the most frequent
synsets in the corpus. The first line refers to the
number of tokens without any associated synset.
For instance, synset 00024720-n refers to “the
way something is with respect to its main at-
tributes” and synset 08050678-n is about “the
organization that is the governing authority of a
political unit” which, in OpenWN-PT, contains the
word “governo”. Note that synset 10467395-n
is about “ the person who holds the office of
head of state of the United States government”,
for which OpenWN-PT contains the word “pres-
idente” (president) as one of its words.
</bodyText>
<footnote confidence="0.975948636363636">
Var1 Freq
- 7343611
01835496-v 76589
02604760-v 47854
00047534-r 30351
00065639-v 28571
15202634-n 27294
08050678-n 26527
10467395-n 23238
00024720-n 23026
00118531-r 20434
</footnote>
<tableCaption confidence="0.999944">
Table 2: Frequent synsets in DHBB entries
Table 3 presents some of the most frequent to-
</tableCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.9986854">
kens (after lemmatization) that could not be found
in OpenWN-PT. The entries are not very surpris-
ing, as our efforts have not focused on domain-
specific vocabulary from the political/historical
domain.4 The exercise of running FreeLing on
the DHBB entries gave us good insights about the
coverage of OpenWN-PT and we plan to extend
the translations of synsets from the most frequent
missing words in OpenWN-PT to the less frequent
ones.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.9811636875">
Token Freq
[??:??/1/??:??.??:??] 15294
partido 15292
durante 10962
contra 10180
tornar 9991
militar 9906
outro 9739
segundo 9577
s˜ao paulo 8803
estadual 8727
voto 8287
pmdb 6615
cˆam 6271
direito 6170
cˆamara dos deputados 5849
</table>
<tableCaption confidence="0.999363">
Table 3: Frequent tokens without synset
</tableCaption>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.99545" genericHeader="conclusions">
7 Conclusion
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999583785714286">
We have discussed the implementation and some
applications of OpenWordNet-PT, an open Word-
Net for Brazilian Portuguese. Recent improve-
ments include better coverage and nominaliza-
tion links connecting nouns and verbs. The
resource has been used in developing a high-
throughput commercial system as well as in a
cultural heritage project, and we anticipate that
numerous further applications will follow. The
data is freely available from http://github.
com/arademaker/wordnet-br/ and via a
SPARQL endpoint5. We are also grateful to Fran-
cis Bond for providing an online interface via the
Open Multilingual Wordnet website6.
</bodyText>
<footnote confidence="0.999965666666667">
4The first entry is the January encoded as a date template.
5Seehttp://logics.emap.fgv.br:10035
6See http://bit.ly/1aN0Xxd
</footnote>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.888835" genericHeader="references">
References
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.999625447619047">
Stefano Baccianella, Andrea Esuli, and Fabrizio Sebas-
tiani. 2010. Sentiwordnet 3.0: An enhanced lexical
resource for sentiment analysis and opinion mining.
In LREC, volume 10, pages 2200–2204.
Akshat Bakliwal, Piyush Arora, Senthil Madhappan,
Nikhil Kapre, Mukesh Singh, and Vasudeva Varma.
2012. Mining sentiments from tweets. In Proc. of
the 3rd Workshop in Computational Approaches to
Subjectivity and Sentiment Analysis, pages 11–18.
Tim Berners-Lee and Dan Connolly. 2011. Notation3
(N3): A readable RDF syntax. http://bit.ly/
1bYAs8y.
Francis Bond and Ryan Foster. 2013. Linking and ex-
tending an open multilingual wordnet. In Proc. of
ACL 2013, pages 1352–1362, Bulgaria. ACL.
Jordan Boyd-Graber, Christiane Fellbaum, Daniel Os-
herson, and Robert Schapire. 2006. Adding dense,
weighted connections to wordnet. In Proc. of the
3th Global WordNet Conf., pages 29–36, Jeju Island,
Korea, January.
Asli Celikyilmaz, Dilek Hakkani-Tur, and Junlan Feng.
2010. Probabilistic model-based sentiment analy-
sis of twitter messages. In IEEE Spoken Language
Technology Workshop (SLT), pages 79–84.
Christian Chiarcos, Sebastian Nordhoff, and Sebastian
Hellmann. 2012. Linked data in linguistics: Repre-
senting and connecting language data and language
metadata. Springer.
Livy Maria Real Coelho, Alexandre Rademaker,
Valeria De Paiva, and Gerard de Melo. 2014.
Embedding NomLex-BR nominalizations into
OpenWordnet-PT. In Proc. of Global WordNet
Conf. 2014. to appear.
Alan Cruse. 1986. Lexical semantics. Cambridge Uni-
versity Press.
Richard Cyganiak and David Wood. 2003. RDF
1.1 concepts and abstract syntax. Technical Report
Draft 23 July 2013, W3C.
Gerard de Melo and Gerhard Weikum. 2008. Lan-
guage as a foundation of the Semantic Web. In Proc.
of ISWC 2008, volume 401.
Gerard de Melo and Gerhard Weikum. 2009. Towards
a universal wordnet by learning from combined evi-
dence. In Proc. of CIKM 2009, pages 513–522, New
York, USA. ACM.
Gerard de Melo and Gerhard Weikum. 2010. MENTA:
inducing multilingual taxonomies from Wikipedia.
In Proc. of CIKM 2010, pages 1099–1108. ACM.
Bento Carlos Dias-Da-Silva and Helio Roberto
de Moraes. 2003. A construc¸ao de um thesaurus
eletrˆonico para o portuguˆes do brasil. ALFA: Revista
de Linguistica, 47(2).
Christiane Fellbaum. 1998. WordNet: An electronic
lexical database. The MIT press.
Hugo Gonc¸alo Oliveira. 2013. Onto.PT: Towards the
Automatic Construction of a Lexical Ontology for
Portuguese. Ph.D. thesis, University of Coimbra.
Olga Gurevich, Richard Crouch, Tracy Holloway King,
and Valeria de Paiva. 2008. Deverbal nouns in
knowledge representation. J. Log. and Comput.,
18(3):385–404.
Steve Harris and Andy Seaborne. 2013. SPARQL
1.1 query language. Technical Report W3C Recom-
mendation 21 March 2013, W3C.
Pascal Hitzler, Markus Krotzsch, Bijan Parsia, Peter F.
Patel-Schneider, and Sebastian Rudolph. 2012.
OWL 2 web ontology language primer. Technical
Report W3C Rec 11 Dec 2012, W3C.
Alexander Hogenboom, Daniella Bal, Flavius Frasin-
car, Malissa Bal, Franciska de Jong, and Uzay Kay-
mak. 2013. Exploiting emoticons in sentiment anal-
ysis. In Proc. of the ACM Symposium on Applied
Computing, pages 703–710, New York, NY, USA.
ACM.
Lin Li, Yunqing Xia, and Pengzhou Zhang. 2011. An
unsupervised approach to sentiment word extraction
in complex sentiment analysis. International Jour-
nal of Knowledge and Language Processing, 2(1).
Catherine Macleod, Ralph Grishman, Adam Meyers,
Leslie Barret, and Ruth Reeves. 1998. Nomlex:
A lexicon of nominalizations. In Proc. of Euralex
1998, pages 187–193, Liege, Belgium.
Bernardo Magnini and Gabriela Cavaglia. 2000. Inte-
grating subject field codes into WordNet. In Proc. of
LREC, pages 1413–1418.
Palmira Marrafa. 2002. Portuguese wordnet: gen-
eral architecture and internal semantic relations.
DELTA: Documentac¸˜ao de Estudos em Ling¨uistica
Te´orica e Aplicada, 18(SPE):131–146.
Llu´ıs Padr´o and Evgeny Stanilovsky. 2012. Freeling
3.0: Towards wider multilinguality. In Proc. of the
8th Intern. Conf. on Language Resources and Eval-
uation (LREC’12), pages 23–25, Istanbul, Turkey,
may.
Alexandre Rademaker, Valeria De Paiva, and Gerard
de Melo. 2012. Openwordnet-pt: An open brazilian
wordnet for reasoning. In Proc. of COLING 2012,
pages 353–360, Mumbai.
Mark van Assem, Aldo Gangemi, and Guus Schreiber.
2006. RDF/OWL representation of WordNet. Tech-
nical Report W3C Working Draft 19 June 2006,
W3C. http://bit.ly/1jtGsA8.
Piek Vossen. 2002. EuroWordNet general document.
Technical Report Version 3 Final July 1, University
of Amsterdam.
</reference>
</variant>
</algorithm>
<algorithm name="ParsHed" version="110505">
<variant no="0" confidence="0.156263">
<title confidence="0.998151">OpenWordNet-PT: A Project Report</title>
<author confidence="0.991715">Alexandre</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.8374435">IBM Research Brazil / Rio de Janeiro,</affiliation>
<email confidence="0.998008">alexrad@br.ibm.com</email>
<author confidence="0.646002">Valeria de_Nunance</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.581629">Sunnyvale, CA,</affiliation>
<email confidence="0.997394">valeria.depaiva@gmail.com</email>
<author confidence="0.990579">Gerard de_Melo Livy Maria Real Coelho Maira Gatti</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.9463135">Tsinghua University Univ. Federal do Paran´a IBM Research Brazil Beijing, China Curitiba, Brazil Rio de Janeiro,</affiliation>
<email confidence="0.994947">gdm@demelo.orglivyreal@gmail.commairacg@br.ibm.com</email>
<abstract confidence="0.9996345">This paper presents OpenWordNet-PT, a freely available open-source wordnet for Portuguese, with its latest developments and practical uses. We provide a detailed description of the RDF representation developed for OpenWordnet-PT. We highlight our efforts to extend the coverage of our resource and add nominalization relations connecting nouns and verbs. Finally, we present several real-world applications where OpenWordnet-PT was put to use, including a large-scale high-throughput sentiment analysis system.</abstract>
</variant>
</algorithm>
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Stefano Baccianella</author>
<author>Andrea Esuli</author>
<author>Fabrizio Sebastiani</author>
</authors>
<title>Sentiwordnet 3.0: An enhanced lexical resource for sentiment analysis and opinion mining.</title>
<date>2010</date>
<booktitle>In LREC,</booktitle>
<volume>10</volume>
<pages>2200--2204</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="20062" citStr="Baccianella et al., 2010" startWordPosition="3286" endWordPosition="3289">his data as quickly as possi3Seehttp://twitter.com ble. First, the system must be reliable: no information should be lost. This means that a highly available system is called for, with redundancy and active fault tolerance mechanisms. Second, it must have a high throughput, which leads us to an infrastructure that allows parallelism. Thirdly, sentiment classifiers should be able to work with limited resources in both time and space. The training phase should handle an unbalanced distribution of sentiments and in real time, it should be adaptive. OpenWN-PT, Princeton WordNet, and SentiWordNet (Baccianella et al., 2010) were used with the goal of assessing a Machine Learning-based sentiment analysis component integrated into the IBM InfoSphere Streams (ISS) platform. ISS was used to address the problem of handling large streaming Twitter data with availability and scalability in real-time. One main advantage of using OpenWN-PT and SentiWordNet during the development of the Machine Learning-based classifier was that we could start experimenting without training data. The experiment was possible because OpenWN-PT synsets are linked to Princeton WordNet synsets which, in turn, have their sentiment scores in Sen</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Baccianella, Esuli, Sebastiani, 2010</marker>
<rawString>Stefano Baccianella, Andrea Esuli, and Fabrizio Sebastiani. 2010. Sentiwordnet 3.0: An enhanced lexical resource for sentiment analysis and opinion mining. In LREC, volume 10, pages 2200–2204.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Akshat Bakliwal</author>
<author>Piyush Arora</author>
<author>Senthil Madhappan</author>
<author>Nikhil Kapre</author>
<author>Mukesh Singh</author>
<author>Vasudeva Varma</author>
</authors>
<title>Mining sentiments from tweets.</title>
<date>2012</date>
<booktitle>In Proc. of the 3rd Workshop in Computational Approaches to Subjectivity and Sentiment Analysis,</booktitle>
<pages>11--18</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="19107" citStr="Bakliwal et al., 2012" startWordPosition="3129" endWordPosition="3132">logging online social network is Twitter3. As of 2013, there are more than 550 million active registered users and 58 million tweets are posted per day on average. These tweets are short messages that people send to provide updates on their activities, observations, or other interesting content, directly or indirectly to others. In sports, for instance, a lot of sentiment is expressed during a game match. Recently there have been several approaches that tackle the problem of classifying tweet sentiments using supervised or semi-supervised machine learning approaches (Celikyilmaz et al., 2010; Bakliwal et al., 2012) or lexicon-based methods, which are mostly unsupervised approaches (Li et al., 2011; Hogenboom et al., 2013). As people react to events and generate a large Twitter stream of data, it is impossible to manually process and analyze all these data during the event’s lifespan. There are several challenges related to analyzing all this data as quickly as possi3Seehttp://twitter.com ble. First, the system must be reliable: no information should be lost. This means that a highly available system is called for, with redundancy and active fault tolerance mechanisms. Second, it must have a high through</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Bakliwal, Arora, Madhappan, Kapre, Singh, Varma, 2012</marker>
<rawString>Akshat Bakliwal, Piyush Arora, Senthil Madhappan, Nikhil Kapre, Mukesh Singh, and Vasudeva Varma. 2012. Mining sentiments from tweets. In Proc. of the 3rd Workshop in Computational Approaches to Subjectivity and Sentiment Analysis, pages 11–18.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Tim Berners-Lee</author>
<author>Dan Connolly</author>
</authors>
<date>2011</date>
<booktitle>Notation3 (N3): A readable RDF syntax. http://bit.ly/ 1bYAs8y.</booktitle>
<contexts>
<context position="7223" citStr="Berners-Lee and Connolly, 2011" startWordPosition="1164" endWordPosition="1167">d an example sentence (for a WordSense of a VerbSynset). A synset can have a lexicographerFile and a frame (in the case of a VerbSynset). 3. We omitted redundant subclasses of WordSense like NounWordSense, as the part-of-speech can be derived from the corresponding synset. A subclass of Word called Collocation is also omitted, as the lexical form of Word instances can easily be examined to check for collocations. 4. We have adopted a different schema for naming the resources identifiers (URIs). In Figure 1, we show the synset 00001740-n encoded in RDF in its more readable N3 notation variant (Berners-Lee and Connolly, 2011). Word instances are blank resources, that is, resources without a URI or unnamed resources. In Figure 2, we present the same synset in a graphical way, additionally showing its connection with the corresponding synset in the Princeton WordNet, including relevant semantic relations. Our code for this RDF version of WordNet 3.0 is freely available. 2 1See http://bit.ly/1cVExvj. 2See http://bit.ly/1ctbGSL. The code requires AllegroGraph and Allegro Common Lisp. Both are commercial tools but free editions can be obtained on the Franz Inc. website at http://www.franz.com. @prefix rdf: &lt;http : / /w</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Berners-Lee, Connolly, 2011</marker>
<rawString>Tim Berners-Lee and Dan Connolly. 2011. Notation3 (N3): A readable RDF syntax. http://bit.ly/ 1bYAs8y.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Francis Bond</author>
<author>Ryan Foster</author>
</authors>
<title>Linking and extending an open multilingual wordnet.</title>
<date>2013</date>
<booktitle>In Proc. of ACL 2013,</booktitle>
<pages>1352--1362</pages>
<publisher>ACL.</publisher>
<contexts>
<context position="9495" citStr="Bond and Foster, 2013" startWordPosition="1573" endWordPosition="1576">icalForm ” ser ” ; rdf : type wn30 : Word . Figure 1: The synset 00001740-n in N3 notation Figure 2: Synset 00001740-n and its neighbors in Princeton WordNet and OpenWordNet-PT 3 Extending the Coverage The first version of OpenWN-PT was created using a semi-automated process drawing on UWN (de Melo and Weikum, 2009) and on manual revisions and gloss translations (Rademaker et al., 2012). Table 1 summarizes how OpenWN-PT has increased over the last two years. The number of synsets should be understood as the number of synsets with at least one Portuguese word. The sources of the new data were (Bond and Foster, 2013) and some manual addition of entries while working on projects that make use of the resource. These use cases are described later in Section 6. 2011 2013 increase synsets 41,810 43,895 5% words 52,220 54,125 3% senses 68,285 74,054 8% Table 1: OpenWN-PT’s coverage development Among resources that we can use to expand OpenWN-PT, we are considering (Dias-Da-Silva and de Moraes, 2003) and (Gonc¸alo Oliveira, 2013). Both projects are also concerned with the construction of a WordNet-like lexical resource for Portuguese. The former is more limited, offering around 19,888 synsets without any links t</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Bond, Foster, 2013</marker>
<rawString>Francis Bond and Ryan Foster. 2013. Linking and extending an open multilingual wordnet. In Proc. of ACL 2013, pages 1352–1362, Bulgaria. ACL.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Jordan Boyd-Graber</author>
<author>Christiane Fellbaum</author>
<author>Daniel Osherson</author>
<author>Robert Schapire</author>
</authors>
<title>Adding dense, weighted connections to wordnet.</title>
<date>2006</date>
<booktitle>In Proc. of the 3th Global WordNet Conf.,</booktitle>
<pages>29--36</pages>
<location>Jeju Island, Korea,</location>
<marker>Boyd-Graber, Fellbaum, Osherson, Schapire, 2006</marker>
<rawString>Jordan Boyd-Graber, Christiane Fellbaum, Daniel Osherson, and Robert Schapire. 2006. Adding dense, weighted connections to wordnet. In Proc. of the 3th Global WordNet Conf., pages 29–36, Jeju Island, Korea, January.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Asli Celikyilmaz</author>
<author>Dilek Hakkani-Tur</author>
<author>Junlan Feng</author>
</authors>
<title>Probabilistic model-based sentiment analysis of twitter messages.</title>
<date>2010</date>
<booktitle>In IEEE Spoken Language Technology Workshop (SLT),</booktitle>
<pages>79--84</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="19083" citStr="Celikyilmaz et al., 2010" startWordPosition="3125" endWordPosition="3128">me. The most famous microblogging online social network is Twitter3. As of 2013, there are more than 550 million active registered users and 58 million tweets are posted per day on average. These tweets are short messages that people send to provide updates on their activities, observations, or other interesting content, directly or indirectly to others. In sports, for instance, a lot of sentiment is expressed during a game match. Recently there have been several approaches that tackle the problem of classifying tweet sentiments using supervised or semi-supervised machine learning approaches (Celikyilmaz et al., 2010; Bakliwal et al., 2012) or lexicon-based methods, which are mostly unsupervised approaches (Li et al., 2011; Hogenboom et al., 2013). As people react to events and generate a large Twitter stream of data, it is impossible to manually process and analyze all these data during the event’s lifespan. There are several challenges related to analyzing all this data as quickly as possi3Seehttp://twitter.com ble. First, the system must be reliable: no information should be lost. This means that a highly available system is called for, with redundancy and active fault tolerance mechanisms. Second, it </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Celikyilmaz, Hakkani-Tur, Feng, 2010</marker>
<rawString>Asli Celikyilmaz, Dilek Hakkani-Tur, and Junlan Feng. 2010. Probabilistic model-based sentiment analysis of twitter messages. In IEEE Spoken Language Technology Workshop (SLT), pages 79–84.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Christian Chiarcos</author>
<author>Sebastian Nordhoff</author>
<author>Sebastian Hellmann</author>
</authors>
<title>Linked data in linguistics: Representing and connecting language data and language metadata.</title>
<date>2012</date>
<publisher>Springer.</publisher>
<contexts>
<context position="2636" citStr="Chiarcos et al., 2012" startWordPosition="393" endWordPosition="396">ce (Sections 3 to 5), most notably with nominalization relations connecting nouns and verbs (Section 4). We also highlight several important applications of OpenWN-PT (Section 6). 2 RDF Representation Wordnets have been distributed in a wide range of different incompatible data formats. An increasingly popular way of addressing the issue of interoperability is to rely on Linked Data and Semantic Web standards such as RDF (Cyganiak and Wood, 2003) and OWL (Hitzler et al., 2012), which have led to the emergence of a number of Linked Data projects for lexical resources (de Melo and Weikum, 2008; Chiarcos et al., 2012). We believe that OpenWN-PT should best be encoded and distributed in RDF/OWL. Not only do these standards allow us to publish both the data model and the actual data in the same format. They also provide for instant compatibility with a vast range of existing data processing tools, including databases (so-called “triple stores”) providing SQL-like query interfaces based on the SPARQL standard (Harris and Seaborne, 2013). Some years ago, a task force of the Semantic Web Best Practices Working Group proposed a standard encoding of WordNet in RDF (van Assem et al., 2006). This effort made WordNe</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Chiarcos, Nordhoff, Hellmann, 2012</marker>
<rawString>Christian Chiarcos, Sebastian Nordhoff, and Sebastian Hellmann. 2012. Linked data in linguistics: Representing and connecting language data and language metadata. Springer.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Livy Maria Real Coelho</author>
<author>Alexandre Rademaker</author>
<author>Valeria De Paiva</author>
<author>Gerard de Melo</author>
</authors>
<title>Embedding NomLex-BR nominalizations into OpenWordnet-PT.</title>
<date>2014</date>
<booktitle>In Proc. of Global WordNet Conf.</booktitle>
<note>to appear.</note>
<marker>Coelho, Rademaker, De Paiva, de Melo, 2014</marker>
<rawString>Livy Maria Real Coelho, Alexandre Rademaker, Valeria De Paiva, and Gerard de Melo. 2014. Embedding NomLex-BR nominalizations into OpenWordnet-PT. In Proc. of Global WordNet Conf. 2014. to appear.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Alan Cruse</author>
</authors>
<title>Lexical semantics.</title>
<date>1986</date>
<publisher>Cambridge University Press.</publisher>
<contexts>
<context position="16372" citStr="Cruse, 1986" startWordPosition="2687" endWordPosition="2688">relationships that we know hold in the English WordNet in its translated Portuguese version, we should be able to both check the accuracy of OpenWordNet-PT and simultaneously investigate the parallelism between the two languages. From this perspective, one of the more interesting relationships, as far as knowledge representation is concerned, is the relationship of entailment between synsets. We have a goal of checking some 200 random English relationships in their translated forms as a way of measuring accuracy of the OpenWN-PT in the very immediate future. 5 Accuracy Following the ideas of (Cruse, 1986), both (Vossen, 2002) and (Marrafa, 2002) used diagnostic templates of sentences to verify relations between synsets. We started a similar exercise. We choose six relations: hypernymOf, memberHolonymOf, instanceOf, substanceHolonymOf, entails and causes. For each of these relations, we randomly chose 30 pairs of synsets and then random words from each synset. Note that we had to keep drawing random synset relationships until both synsets included at least one Portuguese word. We ended up with 180 random sentences that we submitted to a linguist for manual verification (a single linguist to beg</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Cruse, 1986</marker>
<rawString>Alan Cruse. 1986. Lexical semantics. Cambridge University Press.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Richard Cyganiak</author>
<author>David Wood</author>
</authors>
<title>RDF 1.1 concepts and abstract syntax.</title>
<date>2003</date>
<tech>Technical Report Draft 23</tech>
<pages>3</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="2464" citStr="Cyganiak and Wood, 2003" startWordPosition="362" endWordPosition="365">edia (de Melo and Weikum, 2010). In this paper, we specify the RDF-based representation chosen for OpenWN-PT (Section 2) and describe our recent efforts to extend this resource (Sections 3 to 5), most notably with nominalization relations connecting nouns and verbs (Section 4). We also highlight several important applications of OpenWN-PT (Section 6). 2 RDF Representation Wordnets have been distributed in a wide range of different incompatible data formats. An increasingly popular way of addressing the issue of interoperability is to rely on Linked Data and Semantic Web standards such as RDF (Cyganiak and Wood, 2003) and OWL (Hitzler et al., 2012), which have led to the emergence of a number of Linked Data projects for lexical resources (de Melo and Weikum, 2008; Chiarcos et al., 2012). We believe that OpenWN-PT should best be encoded and distributed in RDF/OWL. Not only do these standards allow us to publish both the data model and the actual data in the same format. They also provide for instant compatibility with a vast range of existing data processing tools, including databases (so-called “triple stores”) providing SQL-like query interfaces based on the SPARQL standard (Harris and Seaborne, 2013). So</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Cyganiak, Wood, 2003</marker>
<rawString>Richard Cyganiak and David Wood. 2003. RDF 1.1 concepts and abstract syntax. Technical Report Draft 23 July 2013, W3C.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Gerard de Melo</author>
<author>Gerhard Weikum</author>
</authors>
<title>Language as a foundation of the Semantic Web. In</title>
<date>2008</date>
<booktitle>Proc. of ISWC</booktitle>
<volume>401</volume>
<marker>de Melo, Weikum, 2008</marker>
<rawString>Gerard de Melo and Gerhard Weikum. 2008. Language as a foundation of the Semantic Web. In Proc. of ISWC 2008, volume 401.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Gerard de Melo</author>
<author>Gerhard Weikum</author>
</authors>
<title>Towards a universal wordnet by learning from combined evidence.</title>
<date>2009</date>
<booktitle>In Proc. of CIKM 2009,</booktitle>
<pages>513--522</pages>
<publisher>ACM.</publisher>
<location>New York, USA.</location>
<marker>de Melo, Weikum, 2009</marker>
<rawString>Gerard de Melo and Gerhard Weikum. 2009. Towards a universal wordnet by learning from combined evidence. In Proc. of CIKM 2009, pages 513–522, New York, USA. ACM.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Gerard de Melo</author>
<author>Gerhard Weikum</author>
</authors>
<title>MENTA: inducing multilingual taxonomies from Wikipedia.</title>
<date>2010</date>
<booktitle>In Proc. of CIKM 2010,</booktitle>
<pages>1099--1108</pages>
<publisher>ACM.</publisher>
<marker>de Melo, Weikum, 2010</marker>
<rawString>Gerard de Melo and Gerhard Weikum. 2010. MENTA: inducing multilingual taxonomies from Wikipedia. In Proc. of CIKM 2010, pages 1099–1108. ACM.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Bento Carlos</author>
</authors>
<title>Dias-Da-Silva and Helio Roberto de Moraes.</title>
<date>2003</date>
<journal>ALFA: Revista de Linguistica,</journal>
<volume>47</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<marker>Carlos, 2003</marker>
<rawString>Bento Carlos Dias-Da-Silva and Helio Roberto de Moraes. 2003. A construc¸ao de um thesaurus eletrˆonico para o portuguˆes do brasil. ALFA: Revista de Linguistica, 47(2).</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Christiane Fellbaum</author>
</authors>
<title>WordNet: An electronic lexical database.</title>
<date>1998</date>
<publisher>The MIT press.</publisher>
<contexts>
<context position="1518" citStr="Fellbaum, 1998" startWordPosition="210" endWordPosition="212">e-scale high-throughput sentiment analysis system. 1 Introduction Semantic relationships between words are crucial in many forms of natural language processing. Computational systems are not aware of the fact that carro and autom´ovel both refer to cars, or that caminh˜ao (truck) is related to these words as well in that they all share a common more general hypernym. OpenWordnet-PT (or OpenWN-PT for short) is a lexical-semantic resource describing (Brazilian) Portuguese words and their relationships. It is modelled after and fully interoperable with the original Princeton WordNet for English (Fellbaum, 1998), relying on the same identifiers as WordNet 3.0. This means that one can easily find Portuguese equivalents for specific English word senses and vice versa. This also means that OpenWN-PT is part of a large ecosystem of compatible resources, including domain identifiers (Magnini and Cavaglia, 2000) and mappings to Wikipedia (de Melo and Weikum, 2010). In this paper, we specify the RDF-based representation chosen for OpenWN-PT (Section 2) and describe our recent efforts to extend this resource (Sections 3 to 5), most notably with nominalization relations connecting nouns and verbs (Section 4).</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Fellbaum, 1998</marker>
<rawString>Christiane Fellbaum. 1998. WordNet: An electronic lexical database. The MIT press.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Hugo Gonc¸alo Oliveira</author>
</authors>
<title>Onto.PT: Towards the Automatic Construction of a Lexical Ontology for Portuguese.</title>
<date>2013</date>
<tech>Ph.D. thesis,</tech>
<institution>University of Coimbra.</institution>
<contexts>
<context position="9909" citStr="Oliveira, 2013" startWordPosition="1641" endWordPosition="1642">PT has increased over the last two years. The number of synsets should be understood as the number of synsets with at least one Portuguese word. The sources of the new data were (Bond and Foster, 2013) and some manual addition of entries while working on projects that make use of the resource. These use cases are described later in Section 6. 2011 2013 increase synsets 41,810 43,895 5% words 52,220 54,125 3% senses 68,285 74,054 8% Table 1: OpenWN-PT’s coverage development Among resources that we can use to expand OpenWN-PT, we are considering (Dias-Da-Silva and de Moraes, 2003) and (Gonc¸alo Oliveira, 2013). Both projects are also concerned with the construction of a WordNet-like lexical resource for Portuguese. The former is more limited, offering around 19,888 synsets without any links to the Princeton WordNet and no relations between synsets, other than synonymy. The latter has already incorporated OpenWN-PT and is also encoded in RDF following the same vocabulary of (van Assem et al., 2006). This means that it should be straightfoward to obtain data from Onto.PT. Besides the continuous work on increasing the number of translated synsets, we have also invested some time to expand the relation</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Oliveira, 2013</marker>
<rawString>Hugo Gonc¸alo Oliveira. 2013. Onto.PT: Towards the Automatic Construction of a Lexical Ontology for Portuguese. Ph.D. thesis, University of Coimbra.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Olga Gurevich</author>
<author>Richard Crouch</author>
<author>Tracy Holloway King</author>
<author>Valeria de Paiva</author>
</authors>
<title>Deverbal nouns in knowledge representation.</title>
<date>2008</date>
<journal>J. Log. and Comput.,</journal>
<volume>18</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<marker>Gurevich, Crouch, King, de Paiva, 2008</marker>
<rawString>Olga Gurevich, Richard Crouch, Tracy Holloway King, and Valeria de Paiva. 2008. Deverbal nouns in knowledge representation. J. Log. and Comput., 18(3):385–404.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Steve Harris</author>
<author>Andy Seaborne</author>
</authors>
<title>query language.</title>
<date>2013</date>
<journal>SPARQL</journal>
<tech>Technical Report W3C Recommendation 21</tech>
<volume>1</volume>
<pages>3</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="3060" citStr="Harris and Seaborne, 2013" startWordPosition="462" endWordPosition="465"> RDF (Cyganiak and Wood, 2003) and OWL (Hitzler et al., 2012), which have led to the emergence of a number of Linked Data projects for lexical resources (de Melo and Weikum, 2008; Chiarcos et al., 2012). We believe that OpenWN-PT should best be encoded and distributed in RDF/OWL. Not only do these standards allow us to publish both the data model and the actual data in the same format. They also provide for instant compatibility with a vast range of existing data processing tools, including databases (so-called “triple stores”) providing SQL-like query interfaces based on the SPARQL standard (Harris and Seaborne, 2013). Some years ago, a task force of the Semantic Web Best Practices Working Group proposed a standard encoding of WordNet in RDF (van Assem et al., 2006). This effort made WordNet directly accessible to Semantic Web applications. The proposed conversion aimed to be as complete as possible. The suggested representation also stayed as close to the original source as possible, that is, it reflects the original WordNet data model without interpretation. Comparing with previous RDF translations of WordNet, the main features of this version are: (1) It does not model the hyponym hierarchy as a subclas</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Harris, Seaborne, 2013</marker>
<rawString>Steve Harris and Andy Seaborne. 2013. SPARQL 1.1 query language. Technical Report W3C Recommendation 21 March 2013, W3C.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Pascal Hitzler</author>
<author>Markus Krotzsch</author>
<author>Bijan Parsia</author>
<author>Peter F Patel-Schneider</author>
<author>Sebastian Rudolph</author>
</authors>
<title>web ontology language primer.</title>
<date>2012</date>
<journal>OWL</journal>
<tech>Technical Report W3C Rec 11</tech>
<volume>2</volume>
<pages>3</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="2495" citStr="Hitzler et al., 2012" startWordPosition="368" endWordPosition="371">n this paper, we specify the RDF-based representation chosen for OpenWN-PT (Section 2) and describe our recent efforts to extend this resource (Sections 3 to 5), most notably with nominalization relations connecting nouns and verbs (Section 4). We also highlight several important applications of OpenWN-PT (Section 6). 2 RDF Representation Wordnets have been distributed in a wide range of different incompatible data formats. An increasingly popular way of addressing the issue of interoperability is to rely on Linked Data and Semantic Web standards such as RDF (Cyganiak and Wood, 2003) and OWL (Hitzler et al., 2012), which have led to the emergence of a number of Linked Data projects for lexical resources (de Melo and Weikum, 2008; Chiarcos et al., 2012). We believe that OpenWN-PT should best be encoded and distributed in RDF/OWL. Not only do these standards allow us to publish both the data model and the actual data in the same format. They also provide for instant compatibility with a vast range of existing data processing tools, including databases (so-called “triple stores”) providing SQL-like query interfaces based on the SPARQL standard (Harris and Seaborne, 2013). Some years ago, a task force of t</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Hitzler, Krotzsch, Parsia, Patel-Schneider, Rudolph, 2012</marker>
<rawString>Pascal Hitzler, Markus Krotzsch, Bijan Parsia, Peter F. Patel-Schneider, and Sebastian Rudolph. 2012. OWL 2 web ontology language primer. Technical Report W3C Rec 11 Dec 2012, W3C.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Alexander Hogenboom</author>
<author>Daniella Bal</author>
<author>Flavius Frasincar</author>
<author>Malissa Bal</author>
<author>Franciska de Jong</author>
<author>Uzay Kaymak</author>
</authors>
<title>Exploiting emoticons in sentiment analysis.</title>
<date>2013</date>
<booktitle>In Proc. of the ACM Symposium on Applied Computing,</booktitle>
<pages>703--710</pages>
<publisher>ACM.</publisher>
<location>New York, NY, USA.</location>
<marker>Hogenboom, Bal, Frasincar, Bal, de Jong, Kaymak, 2013</marker>
<rawString>Alexander Hogenboom, Daniella Bal, Flavius Frasincar, Malissa Bal, Franciska de Jong, and Uzay Kaymak. 2013. Exploiting emoticons in sentiment analysis. In Proc. of the ACM Symposium on Applied Computing, pages 703–710, New York, NY, USA. ACM.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Lin Li</author>
<author>Yunqing Xia</author>
<author>Pengzhou Zhang</author>
</authors>
<title>An unsupervised approach to sentiment word extraction in complex sentiment analysis.</title>
<date>2011</date>
<journal>International Journal of Knowledge and Language Processing,</journal>
<volume>2</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<contexts>
<context position="19191" citStr="Li et al., 2011" startWordPosition="3142" endWordPosition="3145">ve registered users and 58 million tweets are posted per day on average. These tweets are short messages that people send to provide updates on their activities, observations, or other interesting content, directly or indirectly to others. In sports, for instance, a lot of sentiment is expressed during a game match. Recently there have been several approaches that tackle the problem of classifying tweet sentiments using supervised or semi-supervised machine learning approaches (Celikyilmaz et al., 2010; Bakliwal et al., 2012) or lexicon-based methods, which are mostly unsupervised approaches (Li et al., 2011; Hogenboom et al., 2013). As people react to events and generate a large Twitter stream of data, it is impossible to manually process and analyze all these data during the event’s lifespan. There are several challenges related to analyzing all this data as quickly as possi3Seehttp://twitter.com ble. First, the system must be reliable: no information should be lost. This means that a highly available system is called for, with redundancy and active fault tolerance mechanisms. Second, it must have a high throughput, which leads us to an infrastructure that allows parallelism. Thirdly, sentiment</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Li, Xia, Zhang, 2011</marker>
<rawString>Lin Li, Yunqing Xia, and Pengzhou Zhang. 2011. An unsupervised approach to sentiment word extraction in complex sentiment analysis. International Journal of Knowledge and Language Processing, 2(1).</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Catherine Macleod</author>
<author>Ralph Grishman</author>
<author>Adam Meyers</author>
<author>Leslie Barret</author>
<author>Ruth Reeves</author>
</authors>
<title>Nomlex: A lexicon of nominalizations.</title>
<date>1998</date>
<booktitle>In Proc. of Euralex</booktitle>
<pages>187--193</pages>
<location>Liege, Belgium.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="13155" citStr="Macleod et al., 1998" startWordPosition="2179" endWordPosition="2182">ned in 332 BC” is typically much harder to interpret correctly. The latter sentence describes the same event with the same semantic arguments, but these arguments are usually much harder to obtain automatically from a syntactic parser, given that the event is described in terms of its nominalization destruction instead of its verbal form destroy. A proper handling of nominalizations (we are especially interested here in nominalizations of verbs, also called deverbal nouns) is important in numerous natural language understanding and inference tasks (Gurevich et al., 2008). For English, NOMLEX (Macleod et al., 1998) has provided extensive descriptions of nominalizations. The original NOMLEX was constructed starting out with nominalizations with the suffixes -ion, -ment and -er, relying on frequent words in a corpus. NOMLEX sought not only to describe the possible complements for a nominalization, but also to relate the nominal complements to the arguments of the corresponding verb. Our NomLex-BR project (Coelho et al., 2014) started with a manual translation of NOMLEX to Brazilian Portuguese, as NOMLEX is relatively small but still covers the most salient vocabulary. Many cases were very straightforward,</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Macleod, Grishman, Meyers, Barret, Reeves, 1998</marker>
<rawString>Catherine Macleod, Ralph Grishman, Adam Meyers, Leslie Barret, and Ruth Reeves. 1998. Nomlex: A lexicon of nominalizations. In Proc. of Euralex 1998, pages 187–193, Liege, Belgium.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Bernardo Magnini</author>
<author>Gabriela Cavaglia</author>
</authors>
<title>Integrating subject field codes into WordNet.</title>
<date>2000</date>
<booktitle>In Proc. of LREC,</booktitle>
<pages>1413--1418</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="1818" citStr="Magnini and Cavaglia, 2000" startWordPosition="256" endWordPosition="259">ted to these words as well in that they all share a common more general hypernym. OpenWordnet-PT (or OpenWN-PT for short) is a lexical-semantic resource describing (Brazilian) Portuguese words and their relationships. It is modelled after and fully interoperable with the original Princeton WordNet for English (Fellbaum, 1998), relying on the same identifiers as WordNet 3.0. This means that one can easily find Portuguese equivalents for specific English word senses and vice versa. This also means that OpenWN-PT is part of a large ecosystem of compatible resources, including domain identifiers (Magnini and Cavaglia, 2000) and mappings to Wikipedia (de Melo and Weikum, 2010). In this paper, we specify the RDF-based representation chosen for OpenWN-PT (Section 2) and describe our recent efforts to extend this resource (Sections 3 to 5), most notably with nominalization relations connecting nouns and verbs (Section 4). We also highlight several important applications of OpenWN-PT (Section 6). 2 RDF Representation Wordnets have been distributed in a wide range of different incompatible data formats. An increasingly popular way of addressing the issue of interoperability is to rely on Linked Data and Semantic Web s</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Magnini, Cavaglia, 2000</marker>
<rawString>Bernardo Magnini and Gabriela Cavaglia. 2000. Integrating subject field codes into WordNet. In Proc. of LREC, pages 1413–1418.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Palmira Marrafa</author>
</authors>
<title>Portuguese wordnet: general architecture and internal semantic relations.</title>
<date>2002</date>
<booktitle>DELTA: Documentac¸˜ao de Estudos em Ling¨uistica Te´orica e Aplicada, 18(SPE):131–146.</booktitle>
<contexts>
<context position="16413" citStr="Marrafa, 2002" startWordPosition="2693" endWordPosition="2694">English WordNet in its translated Portuguese version, we should be able to both check the accuracy of OpenWordNet-PT and simultaneously investigate the parallelism between the two languages. From this perspective, one of the more interesting relationships, as far as knowledge representation is concerned, is the relationship of entailment between synsets. We have a goal of checking some 200 random English relationships in their translated forms as a way of measuring accuracy of the OpenWN-PT in the very immediate future. 5 Accuracy Following the ideas of (Cruse, 1986), both (Vossen, 2002) and (Marrafa, 2002) used diagnostic templates of sentences to verify relations between synsets. We started a similar exercise. We choose six relations: hypernymOf, memberHolonymOf, instanceOf, substanceHolonymOf, entails and causes. For each of these relations, we randomly chose 30 pairs of synsets and then random words from each synset. Note that we had to keep drawing random synset relationships until both synsets included at least one Portuguese word. We ended up with 180 random sentences that we submitted to a linguist for manual verification (a single linguist to begin with). The linguist had to mark each s</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Marrafa, 2002</marker>
<rawString>Palmira Marrafa. 2002. Portuguese wordnet: general architecture and internal semantic relations. DELTA: Documentac¸˜ao de Estudos em Ling¨uistica Te´orica e Aplicada, 18(SPE):131–146.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Llu´ıs Padr´o</author>
<author>Evgeny Stanilovsky</author>
</authors>
<title>Freeling 3.0: Towards wider multilinguality.</title>
<date>2012</date>
<booktitle>In Proc. of the 8th Intern. Conf. on Language Resources and Evaluation (LREC’12),</booktitle>
<pages>23--25</pages>
<location>Istanbul, Turkey,</location>
<marker>Padr´o, Stanilovsky, 2012</marker>
<rawString>Llu´ıs Padr´o and Evgeny Stanilovsky. 2012. Freeling 3.0: Towards wider multilinguality. In Proc. of the 8th Intern. Conf. on Language Resources and Evaluation (LREC’12), pages 23–25, Istanbul, Turkey, may.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Alexandre Rademaker</author>
<author>Valeria De Paiva</author>
<author>Gerard de Melo</author>
</authors>
<title>Openwordnet-pt: An open brazilian wordnet for reasoning.</title>
<date>2012</date>
<booktitle>In Proc. of COLING 2012,</booktitle>
<pages>353--360</pages>
<location>Mumbai.</location>
<marker>Rademaker, De Paiva, de Melo, 2012</marker>
<rawString>Alexandre Rademaker, Valeria De Paiva, and Gerard de Melo. 2012. Openwordnet-pt: An open brazilian wordnet for reasoning. In Proc. of COLING 2012, pages 353–360, Mumbai.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Mark van Assem</author>
<author>Aldo Gangemi</author>
<author>Guus Schreiber</author>
</authors>
<title>RDF/OWL representation of WordNet.</title>
<date>2006</date>
<tech>Technical Report W3C Working Draft 19</tech>
<note>W3C. http://bit.ly/1jtGsA8.</note>
<marker>van Assem, Gangemi, Schreiber, 2006</marker>
<rawString>Mark van Assem, Aldo Gangemi, and Guus Schreiber. 2006. RDF/OWL representation of WordNet. Technical Report W3C Working Draft 19 June 2006, W3C. http://bit.ly/1jtGsA8.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Piek Vossen</author>
</authors>
<title>EuroWordNet general document.</title>
<date>2002</date>
<tech>Technical Report Version 3 Final</tech>
<volume>1</volume>
<institution>University of Amsterdam.</institution>
<contexts>
<context position="6242" citStr="Vossen, 2002" startWordPosition="1004" endWordPosition="1005">rdSense instances that are linked to the English WordNet. OpenWN-PT’s RDF will thus only be useful together with an RDF version of Princeton WordNet. While there is a previous RDF version of WordNet 3.0 online, 1 we wanted to ensure that all information in the WordNet 3.0 distribution was transformed to RDF. To this end, we wrote our own Common Lisp code to translate the WordNet 3.0 data files to RDF, following the W3C model (van Assem et al., 2006) with a few modifications as follows. 1. We add two more classes named BaseConcept and CoreConcept to identify the synsets that are base concepts (Vossen, 2002) or core concepts (BoydGraber et al., 2006), respectively. 2. We have added properties to capture information from WordNet 3.0 not available in the Prolog distribution nor in the “database files only” distribution. To this end, we have parsed and read the files sents.vrb, sentidx.vrb and lexnames. A WordSense can have a lexFile, lexId, senseKey, and an example sentence (for a WordSense of a VerbSynset). A synset can have a lexicographerFile and a frame (in the case of a VerbSynset). 3. We omitted redundant subclasses of WordSense like NounWordSense, as the part-of-speech can be derived from th</context>
<context position="16393" citStr="Vossen, 2002" startWordPosition="2690" endWordPosition="2691">e know hold in the English WordNet in its translated Portuguese version, we should be able to both check the accuracy of OpenWordNet-PT and simultaneously investigate the parallelism between the two languages. From this perspective, one of the more interesting relationships, as far as knowledge representation is concerned, is the relationship of entailment between synsets. We have a goal of checking some 200 random English relationships in their translated forms as a way of measuring accuracy of the OpenWN-PT in the very immediate future. 5 Accuracy Following the ideas of (Cruse, 1986), both (Vossen, 2002) and (Marrafa, 2002) used diagnostic templates of sentences to verify relations between synsets. We started a similar exercise. We choose six relations: hypernymOf, memberHolonymOf, instanceOf, substanceHolonymOf, entails and causes. For each of these relations, we randomly chose 30 pairs of synsets and then random words from each synset. Note that we had to keep drawing random synset relationships until both synsets included at least one Portuguese word. We ended up with 180 random sentences that we submitted to a linguist for manual verification (a single linguist to begin with). The linguis</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Vossen, 2002</marker>
<rawString>Piek Vossen. 2002. EuroWordNet general document. Technical Report Version 3 Final July 1, University of Amsterdam.</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>