<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="SectLabel" version="110505">
<variant no="0" confidence="0.000641">
<note confidence="0.927846">
SWAIE 2014
</note>
<title confidence="0.946509333333333">
The Third Workshop on Semantic Web and Information
Extraction
Proceedings of the Workshop
</title>
<author confidence="0.694591">
August 24, 2014
</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.428396">
Dublin, Ireland
</affiliation>
<note confidence="0.923464857142857">
© 2014 The Authors
The papers in this volume are licensed by the authors under a
Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License.
ISBN 978-1-873769-48-5
Proceedings of the Third Workshop on Semantic Web and Information Extraction
(SWAIE 2014)
Diana Maynard, Marieke van Erp and Brian Davis (eds.)
</note>
<page confidence="0.773259">
ii
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.95022" genericHeader="abstract">
Introduction
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.92542504">
There is a vast wealth of information available in textual format that the Semantic Web cannot yet tap
into: 80% of data on the Web and on internal corporate intranets is unstructured, hence analysing
and structuring the data – social analytics and next generation analytics – is a large and growing
endeavour. Here, the Information Extraction community could help as they specialise in mining the
nuggets of information from text. Information Extraction techniques could be enhanced by annotated
data or domain-specific resources. The Semantic Web community has taken great strides in making
these resources available through the Linked Open Data cloud, which are now ready for uptake by the
Information Extraction community. Following the previous two SWAIE workshops at EKAW 2012 and
RANLP 2013 respectively, we have focused our attention on fostering awareness of how Semantic Web
technologies can benefit the traditional IE and NLP communities.
The workshop invited contributions around three particular topics: 1) Semantic Web-driven Information
Extraction, 2) Information Extraction for the Semantic Web, and 3) applications and architectures on the
intersection of Semantic Web and Information Extraction SWAIE 2014 had a number of high-quality
submissions. From these, 6 high quality papers were selected.
Two keynote speakers were invited to the workshop. The first talk was provided by D.J. McCloskey,
NLP Architect in IBM’s Watson Solutions division. The keynote presented the post-Watson role of
Information Extraction and its intersection with the Multilingual Semantic Web. The second talk was
provided by Lorraine Goeuriot, CNGL, DCU on Ontology Based IE for the medical domain. We would
like to thank the many people who helped make SWAIE 2014 such a success: the Programme Committee,
the paper contributors, the invited speakers and all the participants present at the workshop who engaged
in lively debate.
Diana Maynard, University of Sheffield
Marieke van Erp, VU University Amsterdam
Brian Davis, INSIGHT@NUI Galway
iii
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.932842033333333">
Organizers:
Diana Maynard, University of Sheffield
Marieke van Erp, VU University Amsterdam
Brian Davis, INSIGHT@NUI Galway
Program Committee:
Eneko Agirre, University of the Basque Country, Spain
Paul Buitelaar, INSIGHT@ NUIGalway, Ireland
Elena Cabrio, INRIA Sophia Antipolis Méditerannée, France
Philipp Cimiano,CITEC University of Bielefeld, Germany
Hamish Cunningham, University of Sheffield, UK
Mariana Damova, Mozajka, Bulgaria
Dana Dannélls, University of Gothenburg, Sweden
Thierry DeClerck, DFKI, Germany
Antske Fokkens, VU University Amsterdam, the Netherlands
Jens Grivolla, Universitat Pompeu Fabra, Spain
Dirk Hovy, University of Copenhagen, Denmark
Phil Gooch, City University London, UK
Siegfried Handschuh, INSIGHT@ NUIGalway, Ireland
John Judge, CNGL Dublin City University, Ireland
David Lewis, CNGL Trinity College Dublin, Ireland
Alex O’Conor, CNGL Trinity College Dublin, Ireland
Laurette Pretorius, University of South Africa, South Africa
Birgit Proell, Johannes Kepler University Linz, Austria
German Rigau, University of the Basque Country, Spain
Marco Rospocher, Fondazione Bruno Kessler, Italy
Sara Tonelli,Fondazione Bruno Kessler, Italy
Invited Speaker:
D.J. McCloskey, IBM Watson Solutions, Dublin
Lorraine Goeuriot, CNGL, Dublin
v
</table>
<tableCaption confidence="0.986958">
Table of Contents
</tableCaption>
<figure confidence="0.8720393">
Corpus-based Translation of Ontologies for Improved Multilingual Semantic Annotation
Claudia Bretschneider, Heiner Oberkampf, Sonja Zillner, Bernhard Bauer and Matthias Hammon1
Information Extraction for Social Media
Mena Badieh Habib Morgan and Maurice van Keulen 9
Seed Selection for Distantly Supervised Web-Based Relation Extraction
Isabelle Augenstein 17
Ontology-based Extraction of Structured Information from Publications on Preclinical Experiments for
Spinal Cord Injury Treatments
Benjamin Paassen, Andreas Stöckel, Raphael Dickfelder, Jan Philip Göpfert, Nicole Brazda, Tarek
Kirchhoffer, Hans Werner Müller, Roman Klinger, Matthias Hartung and Philipp Cimiano 25
Semi-supervised Sequence Labeling for Named Entity Extraction based on Tri-Training: Case Study on
Chinese Person Name Extraction
Chien-Lung Chou, Chia-Hui Chang and Shin-Yi Wu 33
Towards a robust framework for the semantic representation of temporal expressions in cultural legacy
data
Daniel Isemann, Gerard Lynch and Raffaella Lanino 41
vii
Workshop Program
Corpus-based Translation of Ontologies for Improved Multilingual Semantic Anno-
tation
</figure>
<reference confidence="0.899550764705883">
Claudia Bretschneider, Heiner Oberkampf, Sonja Zillner, Bernhard Bauer and
Matthias Hammon
Information Extraction for Social Media
Mena Badieh Habib Morgan and Maurice van Keulen
Seed Selection for Distantly Supervised Web-Based Relation Extraction
Isabelle Augenstein
Ontology-based Extraction of Structured Information from Publications on Preclin-
ical Experiments for Spinal Cord Injury Treatments
Benjamin Paassen, Andreas Stöckel, Raphael Dickfelder, Jan Philip Göpfert, Nicole
Brazda, Tarek Kirchhoffer, Hans Werner Müller, Roman Klinger, Matthias Hartung
and Philipp Cimiano
Semi-supervised Sequence Labeling for Named Entity Extraction based on Tri-
Training: Case Study on Chinese Person Name Extraction
Chien-Lung Chou, Chia-Hui Chang and Shin-Yi Wu
Towards a robustframeworkfor the semantic representation of temporal expressions
in cultural legacy data
Daniel Isemann, Gerard Lynch and Raffaella Lanino
</reference>
<page confidence="0.796219">
ix
</page>
</variant>
</algorithm>
<algorithm name="ParsHed" version="110505">
<variant no="0" confidence="0.110632">
<note confidence="0.821059923076923">SWAIE 2014 The Third Workshop on Semantic Web and Information Extraction Proceedings of the Workshop August 24, Dublin, Ireland The Authors The papers in this volume are licensed by the authors under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License. ISBN 978-1-873769-48-5 Proceedings of the Third Workshop on Semantic Web and Information Extraction (SWAIE 2014) Diana Maynard, Marieke van Erp and Brian Davis (eds.)</note>
<intro confidence="0.642046">ii</intro>
</variant>
</algorithm>
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>Claudia Bretschneider</author>
<author>Heiner Oberkampf</author>
<author>Sonja Zillner</author>
<author>Bernhard Bauer</author>
<author>Matthias Hammon</author>
</authors>
<title>Information Extraction for Social Media Mena Badieh Habib Morgan and Maurice van Keulen Seed Selection for Distantly Supervised Web-Based Relation Extraction Isabelle Augenstein Ontology-based Extraction of Structured Information from Publications on Preclinical Experiments for Spinal Cord Injury Treatments</title>
<marker>Bretschneider, Oberkampf, Zillner, Bauer, Hammon, </marker>
<rawString>Claudia Bretschneider, Heiner Oberkampf, Sonja Zillner, Bernhard Bauer and Matthias Hammon Information Extraction for Social Media Mena Badieh Habib Morgan and Maurice van Keulen Seed Selection for Distantly Supervised Web-Based Relation Extraction Isabelle Augenstein Ontology-based Extraction of Structured Information from Publications on Preclinical Experiments for Spinal Cord Injury Treatments</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>Benjamin Paassen</author>
<author>Andreas Stöckel</author>
<author>Raphael Dickfelder</author>
<author>Jan Philip Göpfert</author>
<author>Nicole Brazda</author>
</authors>
<title>Tarek Kirchhoffer, Hans Werner Müller, Roman Klinger, Matthias Hartung and Philipp Cimiano Semi-supervised Sequence Labeling for Named Entity Extraction based on TriTraining: Case Study on Chinese Person Name Extraction Chien-Lung Chou, Chia-Hui Chang and Shin-Yi Wu Towards a robustframeworkfor the semantic representation of temporal expressions in cultural legacy data</title>
<marker>Paassen, Stöckel, Dickfelder, Göpfert, Brazda, </marker>
<rawString>Benjamin Paassen, Andreas Stöckel, Raphael Dickfelder, Jan Philip Göpfert, Nicole Brazda, Tarek Kirchhoffer, Hans Werner Müller, Roman Klinger, Matthias Hartung and Philipp Cimiano Semi-supervised Sequence Labeling for Named Entity Extraction based on TriTraining: Case Study on Chinese Person Name Extraction Chien-Lung Chou, Chia-Hui Chang and Shin-Yi Wu Towards a robustframeworkfor the semantic representation of temporal expressions in cultural legacy data</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>Daniel Isemann</author>
</authors>
<title>Gerard Lynch and Raffaella Lanino</title>
<marker>Isemann, </marker>
<rawString>Daniel Isemann, Gerard Lynch and Raffaella Lanino</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>