<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="SectLabel" version="110505">
<variant no="0" confidence="0.350529">
<title confidence="0.99672">
The Construction of language Resource and Knowledge Base for Chi-
nese Language Computing
</title>
<author confidence="0.962382">
Zhifang Sui
</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.870776">
Peking University, China
</affiliation>
<email confidence="0.689859">
szf@pku.edu.cn
</email>
<bodyText confidence="0.998287875">
Abstract: With the urgent needs of enhancing the intelligence of the internet, Knowledge
engineering is attracting high attention from both industry and academia. Different from the
knowledge engineering (such as Dbpedia, Knowledge Graph, YAGO, etc.) based on
structured knowledge resources, the task of textual knowledge engineering is to mine
knowledge from unstructured natural language texts. One of the critical problems is, there is
gap between the shallow structures expressed by natural languages and the deep structures in
conceptual knowledge. In this talk we will introduce the building of the multi-level annotated
Chinese language resource, the ontology engineering based on encyclopedias and the Web,
and the construction of the mapping resource between conceptual relations and their natural
language expressions to link linguistic knowledge and the world knowledge together. The
ultimate goal is to lay resource foundation for Chinese language computing in the Web scale.
BIO: Zhifang Sui, Professor of Institute of Computational Linguistics, Peking University. Her
research focuses on computational linguistics, text mining and knowledge engineering. She
has won the National Prize for Progress in Science and Technology for the comprehensive
language knowledge base in 2011. Her work is supported by several grants from NSFC and
National Key Basic Research Program of China etc.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.96588">
2
</page>
<note confidence="0.5757425">
Proceedings of the Third CIPS-SIGHAN Joint Conference on Chinese Language Processing, page 2,
Wuhan, China, 20-21 October 2014
</note>
</variant>
</algorithm>
<algorithm name="ParsHed" version="110505">
<variant no="0" confidence="0.283911">
<title confidence="0.999346">The Construction of language Resource and Knowledge Base for Chinese Language Computing</title>
<author confidence="0.997553">Zhifang Sui</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.999987">Peking University,</affiliation>
<abstract confidence="0.960210684210526">szf@pku.edu.cn the urgent needs of enhancing the intelligence of the internet, Knowledge engineering is attracting high attention from both industry and academia. Different from the knowledge engineering (such as Dbpedia, Knowledge Graph, YAGO, etc.) based on structured knowledge resources, the task of textual knowledge engineering is to mine knowledge from unstructured natural language texts. One of the critical problems is, there is gap between the shallow structures expressed by natural languages and the deep structures in conceptual knowledge. In this talk we will introduce the building of the multi-level annotated Chinese language resource, the ontology engineering based on encyclopedias and the Web, and the construction of the mapping resource between conceptual relations and their natural language expressions to link linguistic knowledge and the world knowledge together. The ultimate goal is to lay resource foundation for Chinese language computing in the Web scale. Sui, Professor of Institute of Computational Linguistics, Peking University. Her research focuses on computational linguistics, text mining and knowledge engineering. She has won the National Prize for Progress in Science and Technology for the comprehensive language knowledge base in 2011. Her work is supported by several grants from NSFC and National Key Basic Research Program of China etc. 2 of the Third CIPS-SIGHAN Joint Conference on Chinese Language page</abstract>
<address confidence="0.511515">Wuhan, China, 20-21 October 2014</address>
</variant>
</algorithm>
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>