<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="SectLabel" version="110505">
<variant no="0" confidence="0.000000">
<note confidence="0.641213">
CLP 2014
</note>
<title confidence="0.5966862">
The Third CIPS-SIGHAN Joint Conference on
Chinese Language Processing
October 20-21, 2014
Wuhan, China
Production and Manufacturing by
</title>
<note confidence="0.95571775">
Chinese Information Processing Society of China
All rights reserved for hard copy production.
No.4 Zhongguancun South 4th Street
Haidian District, Beijing, China
</note>
<page confidence="0.763192">
ii
</page>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.358093">
Preface
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9998945">
As the vast emerging web users generate big data globally, Chinese language resources develop rapidly
accompanying with language-specific great interests in academic and industrial applications. CLP2014
targets to harness Chinese language content by reporting recent advancements in technical and linguistic
aspects, and drawing interests of global researchers to pursue Chinese processing techniques in this big
data age.
CLP2014 is the third conference jointly organized by the Chinese Language Processing Society of China
(CIPS) and the ACL Special Interest Group on Chinese Language Processing (SIGHAN). The first
conference, CLP-2010, was held on Aug 28-29, 2010 in Beijing, China, in conjunction with COLING
2010. The second conference, CLP2012, hosted by Tianjin University, was held on December 20-21,
2012 in Tianjin, China. CLP2014, hosted by the Central China Normal University, Wuhan, was held on
Oct 20-21, 2014.
The series of CLP conference provide a platform for researchers around the world to present their
research, share ideas, explore new research directions, and advance the state-of-the-art in Chinese
language processing. Continuous efforts of the conference received more and more attention on its
characteristics of Chinese language application and studies. The specialty of Chinese language poses
challenging task for both linguist and computer scientists, and raises a conference tradition of the
international bakeoffs. CLP2014 features four bakeoff tracks: Chinese word segmentation, Chinese
Spelling Check, Simplified Chinese parsing, and Personal Attributes Extraction in Chinese Text.
Of the 18 submissions, CLP2014 selected 11 papers through rigorous review process. CLP2014 bakeoffs
attract 18 groups to participate and submit 22 papers of both technical and overview papers.
We wish to thank everyone who showed interest and submitted a paper, all of the authors for their
contributions, the members of the Program Committee for their thoughtful reviews, the invited speakers
for sharing their perspectives on the topic, and all the attendees of the workshop. All of these factors
contribute to a truly enriching event!
</bodyText>
<author confidence="0.5615675">
Le Sun, Chengqing Zong CLP2014 General Co-Chairs
Min Zhang, Levow, Gina-Anne CLP2014 Program Co-Chairs
</author>
<page confidence="0.402947">
iii
</page>
<note confidence="0.711194">
Organizers
</note>
<author confidence="0.788792">
General Chairs:
</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.9663025">
Le Sun, Institute of Software, Chinese Academy of Sciences
Chengqing Zong, Institute of Automation, Chinese Academy of Sciences
</affiliation>
<author confidence="0.875268">
Program Chairs:
</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.9222415">
Min Zhang, Soochow University
Levow, Gina-Anne, University of Washington
</affiliation>
<author confidence="0.536822">
Program Committee Members:
</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.927379">
Hailong Cao, Harbin Institute of Technology
Baobao Chang, Peking University
Yidong Chen, Xiamen University
Guohong Fu, Heilongjiang University
Yanqing He, Institute of Scientific and Technical Information of China
Hongying Zang, Zhengzhou University
Yuexian Hou, Tianjin University
Xuanjing Huang, Fudan University
Shujian Huang, Nanjing University
Wenbin Jiang, Institute of Computing Technology, Chinese Academy of Sciences
Sujian Li, Peking University
Yang Liu, Tsinghua University
Zhiyuan Liu, Tsinghua University
</affiliation>
<author confidence="0.636917">
Haoliang Qi, Heilongjiang Institute of Technology (HIT)
</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.723341333333333">
Bing Qin, Harbin Institute of Technology
LikunQiu, Ludong University
Weiguang Qu, Nanjing Normal University
</affiliation>
<author confidence="0.594825">
Yanqiu Shao, Beijing Language and Culture University
</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.6287345">
Xiaodong Shi, Xiamen University
Wei Song, Capital Normal University
Jinsong Su, Xiamen University
Xiaojie Wang, Beijing University of Posts and Telecommunications
</affiliation>
<author confidence="0.458473">
Houfeng Wang, Peking University
</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.730249">
Bin Wang, Institute of Computing Technology, Chinese Academy of Sciences
</affiliation>
<author confidence="0.513875">
Mingwen Wang, Jiangxi Normal University
Zhimin Wang, Beijing City University
Ting Wang, The National University of Defense Technology
</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.8390937">
Yunfang Wu, Peking University
Yunqing Xia, Tsinghua University
Tong Xiao, Northeastern University
Xiaobing Zhao, Inner Mongolia Normal University
Jun Xie, Institute of Computing Technology, Chinese Academy of Sciences
DeyiXiong, Soochow University
Jinan Xu, Beijing Jiaotong University
Zhiming Xu, Harbin Institute of Technology
Ruifeng Xu, Harbin Institute of Technology
EndongXun, Beijing Language and Culture University
</affiliation>
<page confidence="0.532899">
V
</page>
<table confidence="0.882095542857143">
Erhong Yang, Beijing Language and Culture University
Muyun Yang, Harbin Institute of Technology
Tianfang Yao, Shanghai Jiao Tong University
Hong Yu, Soochow University
Weidong Zhan, Peking University
Jiajun Zhang, Institute of Automation, Chinese Academy of Sciences
Quan Zhang, Institute of Acoustics, Chinese Academy of Sciences
Min Zhang, Tsinghua University
HuaRui Zhang, Peking University
Zhichang Zhang, Northwest Normal University
Dakun Zhang, Toshiba China
Yujie Zhang, Beijing Jiaotong University
Yu Zhang, Harbin Institute of Technology
Yangsen Zhang, Beijing Information Science &amp; Technology University
Jun Zhao, Institute of Automation, Chinese Academy of Sciences
Tiejun Zhao, Harbin Institute of Technology
Shiqi Zhao, Baidu
Yanyan Zhao, Harbin Institute of Technology
Qiang Zhou, Tsinghua University
Yu Zhou, Institute of Automation, Chinese Academy of Sciences
Jingbo Zhu, Northeastern University
Yaohong Jin, Beijing Normal University
Bakeoff Chairs:
*Chinese Word Segmentation:
Huiming Duan, Peking University
Zhifang Sui, Peking University
*Chinese Spelling Check:
Liang-Chih Yu, Yuan Ze University
Lung-Hao Lee, National Taiwan Normal University
Yuen-Hsien Tseng, National Taiwan Normal University
Hsin-HisChen, National Taiwan Normal University
*Simplified Chinese Parsing:
Qiang Zhou, Tsinghua University
*Personal Attributes Extraction in Chinese Text:
Ruifeng Xu, Harbin Institute of Technology
</table>
<author confidence="0.302032">
Jian Xu, The Hong Kong Polytechnic University
Publications Chair:
</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.398679">
Xiangyu Duan, Soochow University
</affiliation>
<author confidence="0.515648">
Publicity Chair:
</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.905355">
Minhui Dong, Institute for Infocomm Research, Singapore
Xianpei Han, Institute of Software, Chinese Academy of Sciences
</affiliation>
<page confidence="0.719921">
vi
</page>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.713023">
Local Arrangements Chair:
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.755655">
Tingting He, Central China Normal University
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.655883">
vii
</page>
<tableCaption confidence="0.978268">
Table of Contents
</tableCaption>
<table confidence="0.764736545454546">
Invited Talks
Research on Chinese discourse rhetorical structure representation scheme and corpus annotation
Guodong Zhou 1
The Construction of language Resource and Knowledge Base for Chinese Language Computing
Zhifang Sui 2
Research Papers
COV Model and its Application in Chinese Part-of-Speech Tagging
Xing Fukun and Song Rou 3
Maximum Entropy for Chinese Comma Classification with Rich Linguistic Features
Xiaojuan Li, Hua Yang and JiangPing Huang 11
Improving Bilingual Lexicon Extraction Performance from Comparable Corpora via Optimizing Trans-
lation Candidate Lists
Shaoqi Wang, Miao Li, Zede Zhu, Zhenxin Yang and Shizhuang Weng 18
Ch2R: A Chinese Chatter Robot for Online Shopping Guide
Peijie Huang, Xianmao Lin, Zeqi Lian, De Yang, Xiaoling Tang, Li Huang, Qiang Huang, Xiupeng
Wu, Guisheng Wu and Xinrui Zhang 26
Improving Chinese Sentence Polarity Classification via Opinion Paraphrasing
Guohong Fu, Yu He, Jiaying Song and Chaoyue Wang 35
Problematic Situation Analysis and Automatic Recognition for Chinese Online Conversational System
Yang Xiang, Yaoyun Zhang, Xiaoqiang Zhou, Xiaolong Wang and Yang Qin 43
Segment-based Fine-grained Emotion Detection for Chinese Text
Odbal and Zengfu Wang 52
Bilingual Product Name Dictionary Construction Using a Two Stage Method
Yatian Shen and Xuanjing Huang 61
Detection on Inconsistency of Verb Phrase in TreeBank
Chaoqun Duan, Dequan Zheng, Conghui Zhu, Sheng Li and Hongye Tan 70
Local Phrase Reordering Model for Chinese-English Patent Machine Translation
Xiaodie Liu, Yun Zhu and Yaohong Jin 76
Sentence Alignment of Historical Classics based on Mode Prediction and Term Translation Pairs
Chao Che and Xiaojun Zheng 85
Bake-off Papers
The CIPS-SIGHAN CLP 2014 Chinese Word Segmentation Bake-off
Huiming Duan, Zhifang Sui and Tao Ge 90
</table>
<footnote confidence="0.8996065">
Word Segmenter for Chinese Micro-blogging Text Segmentation – Report for CIPS-SIGHAN’2014 Bake-
off
</footnote>
<note confidence="0.289885">
Lu Xiang, Xiaoqing Li and Yu Zhou 96
</note>
<page confidence="0.393619">
ix
</page>
<figure confidence="0.883474859999999">
Leveraging Rich Linguistic Features for Cross-domain Chinese Segmentation
Guohua Wu, Dezhu He, Keli Zhong, Xue Zhou and Caixia Yuan 101
Personal Attributes Extraction in Chinese Text Bakeoff in CLP 2014: Overview
Ruifeng Xu, Shuai Wang, Feng Shi and Jian Xu 108
Personal Attributes Extraction Based on the Combination of Trigger Words, Dictionary and Rules
Kailun Zhang, Mingyin Wang, Xiaoyue Cong, Fang Huang, Hongfa Xue, Lei Li and Zhiqiao Gao
114
An Introduction to BLCU Personal Attributes Extraction System
Dong YU, Cheng YU, Qin QU, Gongbo TANG, Chunhua LIU, Yue TIAN and Jing YI 120
Overview of SIGHAN 2014 Bake-offfor Chinese Spelling Check
Liang-Chih Yu, Lung-Hao Lee, Yuen-Hsien Tseng and Hsin-Hsi Chen 126
Extended HMM and Ranking Models for Chinese Spelling Correction
Jinhua Xiong, Qiao Zhang, Jianpeng Hou, Qianbo Wang, Yuanzhuo Wang and Xueqi Cheng.. 133
Chinese Word Spelling Correction Based on Rule Induction
Jui-Feng Yeh, Yun-Yun Lu, Chen-Hsien Lee, Yu-Hsiang Yu and Yong-Ting Chen 139
Evaluation Reportof the fourth Chinese Parsing Evaluation: CIPS-SIGHAN-ParsEval-2014
Qiang Zhou 146
Generative CCG Parsing with OOV Prediction
Huijia Wu 153
An Improved Graph Model for Chinese Spell Checking
Yang Xin, Hai Zhao, Yuzhu Wang and Zhongye Jia 157
Introduction to NJUPT Chinese Spelling Check Systems in CLP-2014 Bakeoff
Lei Gu, Yong Wang and Xitao Liang 167
Chinese Spelling Check System Based on Tri-gram Model
Qiang Huang, Peijie Huang, Xinrui Zhang, Weijian Xie, Kaiduo Hong, Bingzhou Chen and Lei
Huang 173
Introduction to BIT Chinese Spelling Correction System at CLP 2014 Bake-off
Min Liu, Ping Jian and Heyan Huang 179
A mixed approach for Chinese word segmentation
Zhen Wang 186
Extraction system for Personal Attributes Extraction of CLP2014
Zhen Wang 189
A Study on Personal Attributes Extraction Based on the Combination of Sentences Classifications and
Rules
Nan-chang Cheng, Cheng-qing Zong, Min Hou and Yong-lin Teng 192
Chinese Spell Checking Based on Noisy Channel Model
Hsun-wen Chiu, Jian-cheng Wu and Jason S. Chang 202
NTOU Chinese Spelling Check System in CLP Bake-off 2014
Wei-Cheng Chu and Chuan-Jie Lin 210
x
NCTU and NTUT’s Entry to CLP-2014 Chinese Spelling Check Evaluation
Yih-Ru Wang and Yuan-Fu Liao 216
Chinese Spelling Error Detection and Correction Based on Language Model, Pronunciation, and Shape
Junjie Yu and Zhenghua Li 220
xi
Conference Program
Saturday, October 20, 2014
8:30–8:40 Opening Ceremony
Invited Talks
8:40–9:35
Research on Chinese discourse rhetorical structure representation scheme and cor-
pus annotation
Guodong Zhou
9:30–10:30
The Construction of language Resource and Knowledge Base for Chinese Language
Computing
Zhifang Sui
Research Papers
10:45–11:10
COV Model and its Application in Chinese Part-of-Speech Tagging
Xing Fukun and Song Rou
11:10–11:35
Maximum Entropy for Chinese Comma Classification with Rich Linguistic Features
Xiaojuan Li, Hua Yang and JiangPing Huang
xiii
Saturday, October 20, 2014 (continued)
11:35–12:00
Improving Bilingual Lexicon Extraction Performance from Comparable Corpora
via Optimizing Translation Candidate Lists
Shaoqi Wang, Miao Li, Zede Zhu, Zhenxin Yang and Shizhuang Weng
13:30–13:55
Ch2R: A Chinese Chatter Robot for Online Shopping Guide
Peijie Huang, Xianmao Lin, Zeqi Lian, De Yang, Xiaoling Tang, Li Huang, Qiang
Huang, Xiupeng Wu, Guisheng Wu and Xinrui Zhang
13:55–14:20
Improving Chinese Sentence Polarity Classification via Opinion Paraphrasing
Guohong Fu, Yu He, Jiaying Song and Chaoyue Wang
14:20–14:45
Problematic Situation Analysis and Automatic Recognition for Chinese Online Con-
versational System
Yang Xiang, Yaoyun Zhang, Xiaoqiang Zhou, Xiaolong Wang and Yang Qin
xiv
Saturday, October 20, 2014 (continued)
14:45–15:10
Segment-based Fine-grained Emotion Detection for Chinese Text
Odbal and Zengfu Wang
15:35–16:00
Bilingual Product Name Dictionary Construction Using a Two Stage Method
Yatian Shen and Xuanjing Huang
16:00–16:25
Local Phrase Reordering Model for Chinese-English Patent Machine Translation
Xiaodie Liu, Yun Zhu and Yaohong Jin
xv
Saturday, October 20, 2014 (continued)
16:25–16:50
Sentence Alignment of Historical Classics based on Mode Prediction and Term
Translation Pairs
Chao Che and Xiaojun Zheng
Sunday, October 21, 2014
Bake-off Session 1 : Chinese Word Segmentation
8:40–9:05
The CIPS-SIGHAN CLP 2014 Chinese Word Segmentation Bake-off
Huiming Duan, Zhifang Sui and Tao Ge
9:05–9:30
Word Segmenter for Chinese Micro-blogging Text Segmentation – Report for CIPS-
SIGHAN’2014 Bakeoff
Lu Xiang, Xiaoqing Li and Yu Zhou
9:30–9:55
Leveraging Rich Linguistic Features for Cross-domain Chinese Segmentation
Guohua Wu, Dezhu He, Keli Zhong, Xue Zhou and Caixia Yuan
xvi
Sunday, October 21, 2014 (continued)
Bake-off Session 2 : Personal Attributes Extraction in Chinese Text Task
9:55–10:20
Personal Attributes Extraction in Chinese Text Bakeoff in CLP 2014: Overview
Ruifeng Xu, Shuai Wang, Feng Shi and Jian Xu
10:40–11:05
Personal Attributes Extraction Based on the Combination of Trigger Words, Dictio-
nary and Rules
Kailun Zhang, Mingyin Wang, Xiaoyue Cong, Fang Huang, Hongfa Xue, Lei Li
and Zhiqiao Gao
13:30–13:55
An Introduction to BLCU Personal Attributes Extraction System
Dong YU, Cheng YU, Qin QU, Gongbo TANG, Chunhua LIU, Yue TIAN and Jing
YI
Bake-off Session 3 : Chinese Spelling Check Task
xvii
Sunday, October 21, 2014 (continued)
13:55–14:20
Overview of SIGHAN 2014 Bake-offfor Chinese Spelling Check
Liang-Chih Yu, Lung-Hao Lee, Yuen-Hsien Tseng and Hsin-Hsi Chen
14:20–14:45
Extended HMM and Ranking Models for Chinese Spelling Correction
Jinhua Xiong, Qiao Zhang, Jianpeng Hou, Qianbo Wang, Yuanzhuo Wang and
Xueqi Cheng
15:10–15:35
Chinese Word Spelling Correction Based on Rule Induction
Jui-Feng Yeh, Yun-Yun Lu, Chen-Hsien Lee, Yu-Hsiang Yu and Yong-Ting Chen
Bake-off Session 4 : Simplified Chinese Parsing Task
15:35–16:00
Evaluation Reportof the fourth Chinese Parsing Evaluation: CIPS-SIGHAN-
ParsEval-2014
Qiang Zhou
xviii
Sunday, October 21, 2014 (continued)
16:00–16:25
Generative CCG Parsing with OOV Prediction
Huijia Wu
Bake-off Poster
11:05–12:05
</figure>
<reference confidence="0.964489592592592">
An Improved Graph Model for Chinese Spell Checking
Yang Xin, Hai Zhao, Yuzhu Wang and Zhongye Jia
Introduction to NJUPT Chinese Spelling Check Systems in CLP-2014 Bakeoff
Lei Gu, Yong Wang and Xitao Liang
Chinese Spelling Check System Based on Tri-gram Model
Qiang Huang, Peijie Huang, Xinrui Zhang, Weijian Xie, Kaiduo Hong, Bingzhou
Chen and Lei Huang
Introduction to BIT Chinese Spelling Correction System at CLP 2014 Bake-off
Min Liu, Ping Jian and Heyan Huang
A mixed approach for Chinese word segmentation
Zhen Wang
Extraction system for Personal Attributes Extraction of CLP2014
Zhen Wang
A Study on Personal Attributes Extraction Based on the Combination of Sentences
Classifications and Rules
Nan-chang Cheng, Cheng-qing Zong, Min Hou and Yong-lin Teng
Chinese Spell Checking Based on Noisy Channel Model
Hsun-wen Chiu, Jian-cheng Wu and Jason S. Chang
xix
Sunday, October 21, 2014 (continued)
NTOU Chinese Spelling Check System in CLP Bake-off 2014
Wei-Cheng Chu and Chuan-Jie Lin
NCTU and NTUT’s Entry to CLP-2014 Chinese Spelling Check Evaluation
Yih-Ru Wang and Yuan-Fu Liao
Chinese Spelling Error Detection and Correction Based on Language Model, Pro-
nunciation, and Shape
Junjie Yu and Zhenghua Li
</reference>
<page confidence="0.849978">
xx
</page>
</variant>
</algorithm>
<algorithm name="ParsHed" version="110505">
<variant no="0" confidence="0.000000">
<pubnum confidence="0.392016">CLP 2014</pubnum>
<title confidence="0.9415955">The Third CIPS-SIGHAN Joint Conference on Chinese Language Processing</title>
<date confidence="0.905586">October 20-21,</date>
<address confidence="0.8924">Wuhan, China</address>
<title confidence="0.326276">Production and Manufacturing by Chinese Information Processing Society of China</title>
<abstract confidence="0.876548689655172">All rights reserved for hard copy production. No.4 Zhongguancun South 4th Street Haidian District, Beijing, China ii Preface As the vast emerging web users generate big data globally, Chinese language resources develop rapidly accompanying with language-specific great interests in academic and industrial applications. CLP2014 targets to harness Chinese language content by reporting recent advancements in technical and linguistic aspects, and drawing interests of global researchers to pursue Chinese processing techniques in this big data age. CLP2014 is the third conference jointly organized by the Chinese Language Processing Society of China (CIPS) and the ACL Special Interest Group on Chinese Language Processing (SIGHAN). The first conference, CLP-2010, was held on Aug 28-29, 2010 in Beijing, China, in conjunction with COLING 2010. The second conference, CLP2012, hosted by Tianjin University, was held on December 20-21, 2012 in Tianjin, China. CLP2014, hosted by the Central China Normal University, Wuhan, was held on Oct 20-21, 2014. The series of CLP conference provide a platform for researchers around the world to present their research, share ideas, explore new research directions, and advance the state-of-the-art in Chinese language processing. Continuous efforts of the conference received more and more attention on its characteristics of Chinese language application and studies. The specialty of Chinese language poses challenging task for both linguist and computer scientists, and raises a conference tradition of the international bakeoffs. CLP2014 features four bakeoff tracks: Chinese word segmentation, Chinese Spelling Check, Simplified Chinese parsing, and Personal Attributes Extraction in Chinese Text. Of the 18 submissions, CLP2014 selected 11 papers through rigorous review process. CLP2014 bakeoffs attract 18 groups to participate and submit 22 papers of both technical and overview papers. We wish to thank everyone who showed interest and submitted a paper, all of the authors for their contributions, the members of the Program Committee for their thoughtful reviews, the invited speakers for sharing their perspectives on the topic, and all the attendees of the workshop. All of these factors contribute to a truly enriching event!</abstract>
<title confidence="0.6657325">Sun, Chengqing Zong General Co-Chairs Zhang, Levow, Gina-Anne Program Co-Chairs iii Organizers</title>
<author confidence="0.748782">General Chairs</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.972316851851852">Sun, of Software, Chinese Academy of Sciences Zong, of Automation, Chinese Academy of Sciences Program Chairs: Zhang, University Gina-Anne, of Washington Program Committee Members: Cao, Institute of Technology Chang, University Chen, University Fu, University He, of Scientific and Technical Information of China Zang, University Hou, University Huang, University Huang, University Jiang, of Computing Technology, Chinese Academy of Sciences Li, University Liu, University Liu, University Qi, Institute of Technology (HIT) Qin, Institute of Technology University Qu, Normal University Shao, Language and Culture University Shi, University Song, Normal University Su, University Wang, University of Posts and Telecommunications Wang, University Wang, of Computing Technology, Chinese Academy of Sciences Wang, Normal University Wang, City University Wang, National University of Defense Technology Wu, University Xia, University Xiao, University Zhao, Mongolia Normal University Xie, of Computing Technology, Chinese Academy of Sciences University Xu, Jiaotong University Xu, Institute of Technology Xu, Institute of Technology Language and Culture University V Yang, Language and Culture University Yang, Institute of Technology Yao, Jiao Tong University Yu, University Zhan, University Zhang, of Automation, Chinese Academy of Sciences Zhang, of Acoustics, Chinese Academy of Sciences Zhang, University Zhang, University Zhang, Normal University</affiliation>
<address confidence="0.892987">Zhang, China</address>
<affiliation confidence="0.983959727272727">Zhang, Jiaotong University Zhang, Institute of Technology Zhang, Information Science &amp; Technology University Zhao, of Automation, Chinese Academy of Sciences Zhao, Institute of Technology Zhao, Zhao, Institute of Technology Zhou, University Zhou, of Automation, Chinese Academy of Sciences Zhu, University Jin, Normal University</affiliation>
<title confidence="0.3854865">Bakeoff Chairs: *Chinese Word Segmentation:</title>
<affiliation confidence="0.954900785714286">Duan, University Sui, University *Chinese Spelling Check: Yu, Ze University Lee, Taiwan Normal University Tseng, Taiwan Normal University Taiwan Normal University *Simplified Chinese Parsing: Zhou, University *Personal Attributes Extraction in Chinese Text: Xu, Institute of Technology Xu, Hong Kong Polytechnic University Publications Chair: Duan, University</affiliation>
<title confidence="0.408921333333333">Publicity Chair: Dong, for Infocomm Research, Singapore Han, of Software, Chinese Academy of Sciences</title>
<author confidence="0.658737">vi</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.876233">Local Arrangements Chair: He, China Normal University</affiliation>
<email confidence="0.789603">vii</email>
<title confidence="0.846871366666667">Table of Contents Invited Talks Research on Chinese discourse rhetorical structure representation scheme and corpus annotation Zhou The Construction of language Resource and Knowledge Base for Chinese Language Computing Sui Research Papers COV Model and its Application in Chinese Part-of-Speech Tagging Fukun and Song Rou Maximum Entropy for Chinese Comma Classification with Rich Linguistic Features Li, Hua Yang and JiangPing Huang11 Improving Bilingual Lexicon Extraction Performance from Comparable Corpora via Optimizing Translation Candidate Lists Wang, Miao Li, Zede Zhu, Zhenxin Yang and Shizhuang Weng18 Ch2R: A Chinese Chatter Robot for Online Shopping Guide Peijie Huang, Xianmao Lin, Zeqi Lian, De Yang, Xiaoling Tang, Li Huang, Qiang Huang, Xiupeng Wu, Guisheng Wu and Xinrui Zhang 26 Improving Chinese Sentence Polarity Classification via Opinion Paraphrasing Fu, Yu He, Jiaying Song and Chaoyue Wang35 Problematic Situation Analysis and Automatic Recognition for Chinese Online Conversational System Xiang, Yaoyun Zhang, Xiaoqiang Zhou, Xiaolong Wang and Yang Qin43 Segment-based Fine-grained Emotion Detection for Chinese Text and Zengfu Wang52 Bilingual Product Name Dictionary Construction Using a Two Stage Method Shen and Xuanjing Huang61 Detection on Inconsistency of Verb Phrase in TreeBank Duan, Dequan Zheng, Conghui Zhu, Sheng Li and Hongye Tan70 Local Phrase Reordering Model for Chinese-English Patent Machine Translation Liu, Yun Zhu and Yaohong Jin76 Sentence Alignment of Historical Classics based on Mode Prediction and Term Translation Pairs</title>
<note confidence="0.559021916666667">Chao Che and Xiaojun Zheng 85 Bake-off Papers The CIPS-SIGHAN CLP 2014 Chinese Word Segmentation Bake-off Duan, Zhifang Sui and Tao Ge90 Word Segmenter for Chinese Micro-blogging Text Segmentation – Report for CIPS-SIGHAN’2014 Bakeoff Lu Xiang, Xiaoqing Li and Yu Zhou 96 ix Leveraging Rich Linguistic Features for Cross-domain Chinese Segmentation Wu, Dezhu He, Keli Zhong, Xue Zhou and Caixia Yuan 101 Personal Attributes Extraction in Chinese Text Bakeoff in CLP 2014: Overview Xu, Shuai Wang, Feng Shi and Jian Xu 108</note>
<title confidence="0.980669">Personal Attributes Extraction Based on the Combination of Trigger Words, Dictionary and Rules</title>
<author confidence="0.9693">Kailun Zhang</author>
<author confidence="0.9693">Mingyin Wang</author>
<author confidence="0.9693">Xiaoyue Cong</author>
<author confidence="0.9693">Fang Huang</author>
<author confidence="0.9693">Hongfa Xue</author>
<author confidence="0.9693">Lei Li</author>
<author confidence="0.9693">Zhiqiao Gao</author>
<address confidence="0.496599">114</address>
</variant>
</algorithm>
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="false">
<title>An Improved Graph Model for Chinese Spell Checking Yang Xin, Hai Zhao, Yuzhu Wang and Zhongye Jia</title>
<marker></marker>
<rawString>An Improved Graph Model for Chinese Spell Checking Yang Xin, Hai Zhao, Yuzhu Wang and Zhongye Jia</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<title>Introduction to NJUPT Chinese Spelling Check Systems in CLP-2014 Bakeoff Lei Gu, Yong Wang and Xitao Liang Chinese Spelling Check System Based on Tri-gram Model Qiang Huang, Peijie Huang, Xinrui Zhang, Weijian Xie, Kaiduo Hong, Bingzhou Chen and Lei Huang</title>
<marker></marker>
<rawString>Introduction to NJUPT Chinese Spelling Check Systems in CLP-2014 Bakeoff Lei Gu, Yong Wang and Xitao Liang Chinese Spelling Check System Based on Tri-gram Model Qiang Huang, Peijie Huang, Xinrui Zhang, Weijian Xie, Kaiduo Hong, Bingzhou Chen and Lei Huang</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<title>Introduction to BIT Chinese Spelling Correction System at CLP</title>
<date>2014</date>
<institution>Bake-off Min Liu, Ping Jian and Heyan Huang</institution>
<marker>2014</marker>
<rawString>Introduction to BIT Chinese Spelling Correction System at CLP 2014 Bake-off Min Liu, Ping Jian and Heyan Huang</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<title>A mixed approach for Chinese word segmentation Zhen Wang Extraction system for Personal Attributes Extraction of CLP2014</title>
<location>Zhen Wang</location>
<marker></marker>
<rawString>A mixed approach for Chinese word segmentation Zhen Wang Extraction system for Personal Attributes Extraction of CLP2014 Zhen Wang</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<title>A Study on Personal Attributes Extraction Based on the Combination of Sentences Classifications and Rules</title>
<marker></marker>
<rawString>A Study on Personal Attributes Extraction Based on the Combination of Sentences Classifications and Rules</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>Nan-chang Cheng</author>
</authors>
<title>Cheng-qing Zong, Min Hou and Yong-lin Teng Chinese Spell Checking Based on Noisy Channel Model Hsun-wen Chiu,</title>
<location>Jian-cheng Wu</location>
<note>Chang xix</note>
<marker>Cheng, </marker>
<rawString>Nan-chang Cheng, Cheng-qing Zong, Min Hou and Yong-lin Teng Chinese Spell Checking Based on Noisy Channel Model Hsun-wen Chiu, Jian-cheng Wu and Jason S. Chang xix</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Sunday</author>
</authors>
<title>(continued) NTOU Chinese Spelling Check System</title>
<date>2014</date>
<booktitle>in CLP Bake-off 2014 Wei-Cheng Chu and Chuan-Jie Lin</booktitle>
<marker>Sunday, 2014</marker>
<rawString>Sunday, October 21, 2014 (continued) NTOU Chinese Spelling Check System in CLP Bake-off 2014 Wei-Cheng Chu and Chuan-Jie Lin</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>NCTU</author>
</authors>
<title>NTUT’s Entry to CLP-2014 Chinese Spelling Check Evaluation Yih-Ru Wang and Yuan-Fu Liao Chinese Spelling Error Detection and Correction Based on Language Model, Pronunciation, and Shape</title>
<marker>NCTU, </marker>
<rawString>NCTU and NTUT’s Entry to CLP-2014 Chinese Spelling Check Evaluation Yih-Ru Wang and Yuan-Fu Liao Chinese Spelling Error Detection and Correction Based on Language Model, Pronunciation, and Shape</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<institution>Junjie Yu and Zhenghua Li</institution>
<marker></marker>
<rawString>Junjie Yu and Zhenghua Li</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>