<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="SectLabel" version="110505">
<variant no="0" confidence="0.003225">
<title confidence="0.847881">
GLANCE Visualizes Lexical Phenomena for Language Learning
</title>
<author confidence="0.698859">
Mei-Hua Chen*, Shih-Ting Huang+, Ting-Hui Kao+, Sun-Wen Chiu+, Tzu-His Yen+
</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.490897">
* Department of Foreign Languages and Literature, Hua Fan University, Taipei, Taiwan,
R.O.C. 22301
+ Department of Computer Science, National Tsing Hua University, HsinChu, Taiwan,
</affiliation>
<address confidence="0.603317">
R.O.C. 30013
</address>
<email confidence="0.994768">
{chen.meihua,koromiko1104,maxis1718,chiuhsunwen, joseph.yen}@gmail.com
</email>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.993827" genericHeader="abstract">
Abstract
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999808736842105">
Facilitating vocabulary knowledge is a
challenging aspect for language learners.
Although current corpus-based reference
tools provide authentic contextual clues, the
plain text format is not conducive to fully
illustrating some lexical phenomena. Thus,
this paper proposes GLANCE 1 , a text
visualization tool, to present a large amount
of lexical phenomena using charts and graphs,
aimed at helping language learners
understand a word quickly and intuitively. To
evaluate the effectiveness of the system, we
designed interfaces to allow comparison
between text and graphics presentation, and
conducted a preliminary user study with ESL
students. The results show that the visualized
display is of greater benefit to the
understanding of word characteristics than
textual display.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.998993" genericHeader="introduction">
1 Introduction
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998779176470588">
Vocabulary is a challenging aspect for language
learners to master. Extended word knowledge,
such as word polarity and position, is not widely
available in traditional dictionaries. Thus, for
most language learners, it is very difficult to
have a good command of such lexical phenome-
na.
Current linguistics software programs use
large corpus data to advance language learning.
The use of corpora exposes learners to authentic
contextual clues and lets them discover patterns
or collocations of words from contextual clues
(Partington, 1998). However, a huge amount of
data can be overwhelming and time-consuming
(Yeh et al., 2007) for language learners to induce
rules or patterns. On the other hand, some lexical
phenomena seem unable to be comprehended
</bodyText>
<footnote confidence="0.866832">
1 http://glance-it.herokuapp.com/
</footnote>
<bodyText confidence="0.999913107142857">
fast and directly in plain text format (Koo, 2006).
For example, in the British National Corpus
(2007), “however” seems more negative than
“but”. Also, compared with “but”, “however”
appears more frequently at the beginning of a
sentence.
With this in mind, we proposed GLANCE1, a
text visualization tool, which presents corpus
data using charts and graphs to help language
learners understand the lexical phenomena of a
word quickly and intuitively. In this paper, we
focused on five types of lexical phenomena: po-
larity, position, POS, form and discipline, which
will be detailed in the Section 3. Given a single
query word, the GLANCE system shows graph-
ical representations of its lexical phenomena se-
quentially within a single web page.
Additionally we believe that the use of
graphics also facilitates the understanding of the
differences between two words. Taking this into
consideration, we introduce a comparison mode
to help learners differentiate two words at a
glance. Allowing two word input, GLANCE
draws the individual representative graphs for
both words and presents these graphs in a two-
column view. The display of parallel graphs de-
picts the distinctions between the two words
clearly.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.999765" genericHeader="related work">
2 Related Work
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999400727272727">
Corpus-based language learning has widened the
perspectives in second and foreign language edu-
cation, such as vocabulary learning (Wood,
2001). In past decades, various corpus-based ref-
erence tools have been developed. For example,
WordSmith (Scott, 2000), Compleat Lexical Tu-
tor (Cobb, 2007), GRASP (Huang et al., 2011),
PREFER (Chen et al, 2012).
Recently, some interactive visualization tools
have been developed for the purpose of illustrat-
ing various linguistic phenomena. Three exam-
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.967459">
34
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.834096375">
Proceedings of the Workshop on Interactive Language Learning, Visualization, and Interfaces, pages 34–37,
Baltimore, Maryland, USA, June 27, 2014. @c 2014 Association for Computational Linguistics
ples are Word Tree, a visual concordance (Wat-
tenberg and i gas, 2008), WORDGRAPH, a
visual tool for context-sensitive word choice
(Riehmann et al., 2012) and Visual Thesaurus, a
3D interactive reference tool (ThinkMap Inc.,
2005).
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.893812" genericHeader="method">
3 Design of the GLANCE System
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9999790625">
The GLANCE system consists of several com-
ponents of corpus data visualization. We design
and implement these visualization modules sepa-
rately to ensure all graphs are simple and clear
enough for users to capture and understand the
lexical phenomena quickly.
In this paper, we use the d3.js (Data-Driven
Documents) (Bostock et al., 2011) to visualize
the data. The d3.js enables direct inspection and
manipulation of a standard document object
model (DOM) so that we are able to transform
numeric data into various types of graphs when
fitting these data to other visualization tools. In
this section, we describe the ways we extract the
data from the corpus and how we translate these
data into informative graphs.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.999183">
3.1 Data Preprocessing
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999989545454546">
We use the well-formed corpus, the BNC, to ex-
tract the data. In order to obtain the Part-of-
speech tags for each text, we use the GENIA
tagger (Tsuruoka et al., 2005) to analyze the sen-
tences of the BNC and build a list of &lt;POS-tag,
frequency&gt; pairs for each word in the BNC. Also
the BNC contains the classification code as-
signed to the text in a genre-based analysis car-
ried out at Lancaster University by Lee (2001).
For each word, the classification codes are ag-
gregated to a list of &lt;code, frequency&gt; pairs.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.999774">
3.2 Visualization of Lexical Phenomena
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.967507083333333">
Polarity
A word may carry different sentiment polarities
(i.e., positive, negative and objective). To help
users quickly determine the proper sentiment
polarity of a word, we introduce the sentiment
polarity information of SentiWordNet
(Baccianella et al., 2010) into our system. For
each synset of a word, GLANCE displays the
polarity in a bar with three different colors. The
individual length of the three parts in the bar cor-
responds to the polarity scores of a synset (Fig-
ure 1).
</bodyText>
<figureCaption confidence="0.999503">
Figure 1. Representation of sentiment polarity
</figureCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.936375888888889">
Position
The word position in a sentence is also an im-
portant lexical phenomenon. By calculating the
word position in each sentence, we then obtain
the location distribution. GLANCE visualizes the
distribution information of a word using a bar
chart. Figure 2 shows a plot of distribution of
word position on the x-axis against the word fre-
quency on the y-axis.
</bodyText>
<figureCaption confidence="0.999781">
Figure 2. Distribution of word position
</figureCaption>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.827621">
Part Of Speech (POS)
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999928555555555">
A lexical item may have more than one part of
speech. Knowing the distribution of POS helps
users quickly understand the general usage of a
word.
GLANCE displays a pie chart for each word
to differentiate between its parts of speech. We
use the maximum likelihood probability of a
POS tag for a word as the arc length of the pie
chart (Figure 3).
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997633">
35
</page>
<figureCaption confidence="0.998622">
Figure 3. POS representation
</figureCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.9851778">
Form
The levels of formality of written and spoken
language are different, which also confuse lan-
guage learners. Pie charts are used to illustrate
the proportion of written and spoken English of
individual words as shown in Figure 4.
We derive the frequencies of both forms from
the BNC classification code for each word. The
arc length of each sector is proportional to the
maximum likelihood probability of forms.
</bodyText>
<figureCaption confidence="0.975983">
Figure 4. Form representation
</figureCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.963271214285714">
Discipline
Similar to language form, the discipline infor-
mation (e.g., newspaper or fiction) was gathered
from the BNC classification code. The relations
of the disciplines of a word are presented using a
sunburst graph, a radial space-filling tree layout
implemented with prefuse (Heer et al., 2005). In
the sunburst graph (Figure 5.), each level corre-
sponds to the relation of the disciplines of a cer-
tain word. The farther the level is away from the
center, the more specific the discipline is. Each
level is given equal width, but the circular angle
swept out by a discipline corresponds to the fre-
quency of the disciplines.
</bodyText>
<figureCaption confidence="0.953554">
Figure 5. Discipline relations
</figureCaption>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.999724" genericHeader="evaluation">
4 Results
</sectionHeader>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.998475">
4.1 Experimental Setting
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999986777777778">
We performed a preliminary user study to assess
the efficiency of our system in assisting language
learners in grasping lexical phenomena. To ex-
amine the effectiveness of visualization, we built
a textual interface for comparison with the
graphical interface.
Ten pre-intermediate ESL college students
participated in the study. A total of six pairs of
similar words were listed on the worksheet. After
being introduced to GLANCE, all students were
randomly divided into two groups. One group
was required to consult the first three pairs using
the graphical interface and the second three pairs
the textual interface, and vice versa. The partici-
pants were allowed a maximum of one minute
per pair, which meets the goal of this study of
quickly glancing at the graphics and grasping the
concepts of words. Then a test sheet containing
the same six similar word pairs was used to ex-
amine the extent of students’ word understanding.
Note that during the test, no tool supports were
provided. The student scored one point if he gave
the correct answers to each question. In other
words he would be awarded 6 points (the highest
number of points) if he provided all the correct
answers. They also completed a questionnaire,
described below, evaluating the system.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.993013">
4.2 Experimental Results
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999987428571429">
To determine the effectiveness of visualization of
lexical phenomena, the students’ average scores
were used as performance indicators. Students
achieved the average score 61.9 and 45.0 out of
100.00 after consulting the graphic interface and
textual interface respectively. Overall, the visual-
ized display of word characteristics outper-
formed the textual version.
The questionnaire revealed that all the partici-
pants showed a positive attitude to visualized
word information. Further analyses showed that
all ten participants appreciated the position dis-
play and nine of them the polarity and form dis-
plays. In short, the graphical display of lexical
phenomena in GLANCE results in faster assimi-
lation and understanding of word information.
Moreover, the participants suggested several in-
teresting aspects for improving the GLANCE
system. For example, they preferred bilingual
environment, further information concerning an-
tonyms, more example sentences, and increased
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.995807">
36
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.9957425">
detail in the sunburst representation of disci-
plines.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.918005" genericHeader="conclusions">
5 Conclusion and Future Work
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999982388888889">
In this paper, we proposed GLANCE, a text vis-
ualization tool, which provides graphical display
of corpus data. Our goal is to assist language
learners in glancing at the graphics and grasping
the lexical knowledge quickly and intuitively. To
evaluate the efficiency and effectiveness of
GLANCE, we conducted a preliminary user
study with ten non-native ESL learners. The re-
sults revealed that visualization format outper-
formed plain text format.
Many avenues exist for future research and
improvement. We attempt to expand the single
word to phrase level. For example, the colloca-
tion behaviors are expected to be deduced and
displayed. Moreover, we are interested in sup-
porting more lexical phenomena, such as hypo-
nyms, to provide learners with more lexical rela-
tions of the word with other words.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.983547" genericHeader="references">
Reference
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.999821104477612">
Baccianella, S., Esuli, A., &amp; Sebastiani, F. (2010,
May). SentiWordNet 3.0: An Enhanced Lexical
Resource for Sentiment Analysis and Opinion Min-
ing. In LREC (Vol. 10, pp. 2200-2204).
Bostock, M., Ogievetsky, V., &amp; Heer, J. (2011). D3
data-driven documents. Visualization and Comput-
er Graphics, IEEE Transactions on, 17(12), 2301-
2309.
Chen, M. H., Huang, S. T., Huang, C. C., Liou, H. C.,
&amp; Chang, J. S. (2012, June). PREFER: using a
graph-based approach to generate paraphrases for
language learning. In Proceedings of the Seventh
Workshop on Building Educational Applications
Using NLP (pp. 80-85). Association for Computa-
tional Linguistics.
Cobb, T. (2007). The compleat lexical tutor. Retrieved
September, 22, 2009.
Heer, J., Card, S. K., &amp; Landay, J. A. (2005, April).
Prefuse: a toolkit for interactive information visual-
ization. In Proceedings of the SIGCHI conference
on Human factors in computing systems (pp. 421-
430). ACM.
Huang, C. C., Chen, M. H., Huang, S. T., Liou, H. C.,
&amp; Chang, J. S. (2011, June). GRASP: grammar-
and syntax-based pattern-finder in CALL.
In Proceedings of the 6th Workshop on Innovative
Use of NLP for Building Educational Applications
(pp. 96-104). Association for Computational Lin-
guistics.
Kyosung Koo (2006). Effects of using corpora and
online reference tools on foreign language writing:
a study of Korean learners of English as a second
language. PhD. dissertation, University of Iowa.
Lee, D. Y. (2001). Genres, registers, text types, do-
mains and styles: Clarifying the concepts and
nevigating a path through the BNC jungle.
Partington, A. (1998). Patterns and meanings: Using
corpora for English language research and teach-
ing (Vol. 2). John Benjamins Publishing.
Riehmann, P., Gruendl, H., Froehlich, B., Potthast, M.,
Trenkmann, M., &amp; Stein, B. (2011, March). The
NETSPEAK WORDGRAPH: Visualizing key-
words in context. In Pacific Visualization Sympo-
sium (PacificVis), 2011 IEEE (pp. 123-130). IEEE.
Scott, M. (2004). WordSmith tools version 4.
The British National Corpus, version 3 (BNC XML
Edition). 2007. Distributed by Oxford University
Computing Services on behalf of the BNC Consor-
tium. URL: http://www.natcorp.ox.ac.uk/
ThinkMap Inc. (2005). Thinkmap Visual Thesaurus.
Available from http:// www.visualthesaurus.com
Tsuruoka, Y., Tateishi, Y., Kim, J. D., Ohta, T.,
McNaught, J., Ananiadou, S., &amp; Tsujii, J. I. (2005).
Developing a robust part-of-speech tagger for bio-
medical text. In Advances in informatics (pp. 382-
392). Springer Berlin Heidelberg.
Wattenberg, M., &amp; Viégas, F. B. (2008). The word
tree, an interactive visual concord-
ance. Visualization and Computer Graphics, IEEE
Transactions on, 14(6), 1221-1228.
Wood, J. (2001). Can software support children’s
vocabulary development.Language Learning &amp;
Technology, 5(1), 166-201.
Yeh, Y., Liou, H. C., &amp; Li, Y. H. (2007). Online syn-
onym materials and concordancing for EFL college
writing. Computer Assisted Language Learning,
20(2), 131-152.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.999611">
37
</page>
</variant>
</algorithm>
<algorithm name="ParsHed" version="110505">
<variant no="0" confidence="0.237252">
<title confidence="0.774428">GLANCE Visualizes Lexical Phenomena for Language Learning Tzu-His</title>
<address confidence="0.7973315">of Foreign Languages and Literature, Hua Fan University, Taipei, Taiwan, R.O.C. 22301 of Computer Science, National Tsing Hua University, HsinChu, Taiwan, R.O.C. 30013</address>
<abstract confidence="0.998128">Facilitating vocabulary knowledge is a challenging aspect for language learners. Although current corpus-based reference tools provide authentic contextual clues, the plain text format is not conducive to fully illustrating some lexical phenomena. Thus, paper proposes GLANCE 1, a text visualization tool, to present a large amount of lexical phenomena using charts and graphs, aimed at helping language learners understand a word quickly and intuitively. To evaluate the effectiveness of the system, we designed interfaces to allow comparison between text and graphics presentation, and conducted a preliminary user study with ESL students. The results show that the visualized display is of greater benefit to the understanding of word characteristics than textual display.</abstract>
</variant>
</algorithm>
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>S Baccianella</author>
<author>A Esuli</author>
<author>F Sebastiani</author>
</authors>
<title>SentiWordNet 3.0: An Enhanced Lexical Resource for Sentiment Analysis and Opinion Mining.</title>
<date>2010</date>
<journal>In LREC</journal>
<volume>10</volume>
<pages>2200--2204</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="5713" citStr="Baccianella et al., 2010" startWordPosition="865" endWordPosition="868">es of the BNC and build a list of &lt;POS-tag, frequency&gt; pairs for each word in the BNC. Also the BNC contains the classification code assigned to the text in a genre-based analysis carried out at Lancaster University by Lee (2001). For each word, the classification codes are aggregated to a list of &lt;code, frequency&gt; pairs. 3.2 Visualization of Lexical Phenomena Polarity A word may carry different sentiment polarities (i.e., positive, negative and objective). To help users quickly determine the proper sentiment polarity of a word, we introduce the sentiment polarity information of SentiWordNet (Baccianella et al., 2010) into our system. For each synset of a word, GLANCE displays the polarity in a bar with three different colors. The individual length of the three parts in the bar corresponds to the polarity scores of a synset (Figure 1). Figure 1. Representation of sentiment polarity Position The word position in a sentence is also an important lexical phenomenon. By calculating the word position in each sentence, we then obtain the location distribution. GLANCE visualizes the distribution information of a word using a bar chart. Figure 2 shows a plot of distribution of word position on the x-axis against th</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Baccianella, Esuli, Sebastiani, 2010</marker>
<rawString>Baccianella, S., Esuli, A., &amp; Sebastiani, F. (2010, May). SentiWordNet 3.0: An Enhanced Lexical Resource for Sentiment Analysis and Opinion Mining. In LREC (Vol. 10, pp. 2200-2204).</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M Bostock</author>
<author>V Ogievetsky</author>
<author>J Heer</author>
</authors>
<title>D3 data-driven documents.</title>
<date>2011</date>
<journal>Visualization and Computer Graphics, IEEE Transactions on,</journal>
<volume>17</volume>
<issue>12</issue>
<pages>2301--2309</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="4498" citStr="Bostock et al., 2011" startWordPosition="662" endWordPosition="665">mputational Linguistics ples are Word Tree, a visual concordance (Wattenberg and i gas, 2008), WORDGRAPH, a visual tool for context-sensitive word choice (Riehmann et al., 2012) and Visual Thesaurus, a 3D interactive reference tool (ThinkMap Inc., 2005). 3 Design of the GLANCE System The GLANCE system consists of several components of corpus data visualization. We design and implement these visualization modules separately to ensure all graphs are simple and clear enough for users to capture and understand the lexical phenomena quickly. In this paper, we use the d3.js (Data-Driven Documents) (Bostock et al., 2011) to visualize the data. The d3.js enables direct inspection and manipulation of a standard document object model (DOM) so that we are able to transform numeric data into various types of graphs when fitting these data to other visualization tools. In this section, we describe the ways we extract the data from the corpus and how we translate these data into informative graphs. 3.1 Data Preprocessing We use the well-formed corpus, the BNC, to extract the data. In order to obtain the Part-ofspeech tags for each text, we use the GENIA tagger (Tsuruoka et al., 2005) to analyze the sentences of the </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Bostock, Ogievetsky, Heer, 2011</marker>
<rawString>Bostock, M., Ogievetsky, V., &amp; Heer, J. (2011). D3 data-driven documents. Visualization and Computer Graphics, IEEE Transactions on, 17(12), 2301-2309.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M H Chen</author>
<author>S T Huang</author>
<author>C C Huang</author>
<author>H C Liou</author>
<author>J S Chang</author>
</authors>
<title>PREFER: using a graph-based approach to generate paraphrases for language learning.</title>
<date>2012</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the Seventh Workshop on Building Educational Applications Using NLP</booktitle>
<pages>80--85</pages>
<institution>Association for Computational Linguistics.</institution>
<contexts>
<context position="3560" citStr="Chen et al, 2012" startWordPosition="522" endWordPosition="525">entiate two words at a glance. Allowing two word input, GLANCE draws the individual representative graphs for both words and presents these graphs in a twocolumn view. The display of parallel graphs depicts the distinctions between the two words clearly. 2 Related Work Corpus-based language learning has widened the perspectives in second and foreign language education, such as vocabulary learning (Wood, 2001). In past decades, various corpus-based reference tools have been developed. For example, WordSmith (Scott, 2000), Compleat Lexical Tutor (Cobb, 2007), GRASP (Huang et al., 2011), PREFER (Chen et al, 2012). Recently, some interactive visualization tools have been developed for the purpose of illustrating various linguistic phenomena. Three exam34 Proceedings of the Workshop on Interactive Language Learning, Visualization, and Interfaces, pages 34–37, Baltimore, Maryland, USA, June 27, 2014. @c 2014 Association for Computational Linguistics ples are Word Tree, a visual concordance (Wattenberg and i gas, 2008), WORDGRAPH, a visual tool for context-sensitive word choice (Riehmann et al., 2012) and Visual Thesaurus, a 3D interactive reference tool (ThinkMap Inc., 2005). 3 Design of the GLANCE Syste</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Chen, Huang, Huang, Liou, Chang, 2012</marker>
<rawString>Chen, M. H., Huang, S. T., Huang, C. C., Liou, H. C., &amp; Chang, J. S. (2012, June). PREFER: using a graph-based approach to generate paraphrases for language learning. In Proceedings of the Seventh Workshop on Building Educational Applications Using NLP (pp. 80-85). Association for Computational Linguistics.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>T Cobb</author>
</authors>
<title>The compleat lexical tutor.</title>
<date>2007</date>
<journal>Retrieved September,</journal>
<volume>22</volume>
<contexts>
<context position="3505" citStr="Cobb, 2007" startWordPosition="514" endWordPosition="515">troduce a comparison mode to help learners differentiate two words at a glance. Allowing two word input, GLANCE draws the individual representative graphs for both words and presents these graphs in a twocolumn view. The display of parallel graphs depicts the distinctions between the two words clearly. 2 Related Work Corpus-based language learning has widened the perspectives in second and foreign language education, such as vocabulary learning (Wood, 2001). In past decades, various corpus-based reference tools have been developed. For example, WordSmith (Scott, 2000), Compleat Lexical Tutor (Cobb, 2007), GRASP (Huang et al., 2011), PREFER (Chen et al, 2012). Recently, some interactive visualization tools have been developed for the purpose of illustrating various linguistic phenomena. Three exam34 Proceedings of the Workshop on Interactive Language Learning, Visualization, and Interfaces, pages 34–37, Baltimore, Maryland, USA, June 27, 2014. @c 2014 Association for Computational Linguistics ples are Word Tree, a visual concordance (Wattenberg and i gas, 2008), WORDGRAPH, a visual tool for context-sensitive word choice (Riehmann et al., 2012) and Visual Thesaurus, a 3D interactive reference t</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Cobb, 2007</marker>
<rawString>Cobb, T. (2007). The compleat lexical tutor. Retrieved September, 22, 2009.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>J Heer</author>
<author>S K Card</author>
<author>J A Landay</author>
</authors>
<title>Prefuse: a toolkit for interactive information visualization.</title>
<date>2005</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the SIGCHI conference on Human factors in computing systems</booktitle>
<pages>421--430</pages>
<publisher>ACM.</publisher>
<contexts>
<context position="7531" citStr="Heer et al., 2005" startWordPosition="1172" endWordPosition="1175">used to illustrate the proportion of written and spoken English of individual words as shown in Figure 4. We derive the frequencies of both forms from the BNC classification code for each word. The arc length of each sector is proportional to the maximum likelihood probability of forms. Figure 4. Form representation Discipline Similar to language form, the discipline information (e.g., newspaper or fiction) was gathered from the BNC classification code. The relations of the disciplines of a word are presented using a sunburst graph, a radial space-filling tree layout implemented with prefuse (Heer et al., 2005). In the sunburst graph (Figure 5.), each level corresponds to the relation of the disciplines of a certain word. The farther the level is away from the center, the more specific the discipline is. Each level is given equal width, but the circular angle swept out by a discipline corresponds to the frequency of the disciplines. Figure 5. Discipline relations 4 Results 4.1 Experimental Setting We performed a preliminary user study to assess the efficiency of our system in assisting language learners in grasping lexical phenomena. To examine the effectiveness of visualization, we built a textual </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Heer, Card, Landay, 2005</marker>
<rawString>Heer, J., Card, S. K., &amp; Landay, J. A. (2005, April). Prefuse: a toolkit for interactive information visualization. In Proceedings of the SIGCHI conference on Human factors in computing systems (pp. 421-430). ACM.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>C C Huang</author>
<author>M H Chen</author>
<author>S T Huang</author>
<author>H C Liou</author>
<author>J S Chang</author>
</authors>
<title>GRASP: grammarand syntax-based pattern-finder in CALL.</title>
<date>2011</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 6th Workshop on Innovative Use of NLP for Building Educational Applications</booktitle>
<pages>96--104</pages>
<institution>Association for Computational Linguistics.</institution>
<contexts>
<context position="3533" citStr="Huang et al., 2011" startWordPosition="517" endWordPosition="520"> mode to help learners differentiate two words at a glance. Allowing two word input, GLANCE draws the individual representative graphs for both words and presents these graphs in a twocolumn view. The display of parallel graphs depicts the distinctions between the two words clearly. 2 Related Work Corpus-based language learning has widened the perspectives in second and foreign language education, such as vocabulary learning (Wood, 2001). In past decades, various corpus-based reference tools have been developed. For example, WordSmith (Scott, 2000), Compleat Lexical Tutor (Cobb, 2007), GRASP (Huang et al., 2011), PREFER (Chen et al, 2012). Recently, some interactive visualization tools have been developed for the purpose of illustrating various linguistic phenomena. Three exam34 Proceedings of the Workshop on Interactive Language Learning, Visualization, and Interfaces, pages 34–37, Baltimore, Maryland, USA, June 27, 2014. @c 2014 Association for Computational Linguistics ples are Word Tree, a visual concordance (Wattenberg and i gas, 2008), WORDGRAPH, a visual tool for context-sensitive word choice (Riehmann et al., 2012) and Visual Thesaurus, a 3D interactive reference tool (ThinkMap Inc., 2005). 3</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Huang, Chen, Huang, Liou, Chang, 2011</marker>
<rawString>Huang, C. C., Chen, M. H., Huang, S. T., Liou, H. C., &amp; Chang, J. S. (2011, June). GRASP: grammarand syntax-based pattern-finder in CALL. In Proceedings of the 6th Workshop on Innovative Use of NLP for Building Educational Applications (pp. 96-104). Association for Computational Linguistics.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Kyosung Koo</author>
</authors>
<title>Effects of using corpora and online reference tools on foreign language writing: a study of Korean learners of English as a second language.</title>
<date>2006</date>
<institution>University of Iowa.</institution>
<note>PhD. dissertation,</note>
<contexts>
<context position="2044" citStr="Koo, 2006" startWordPosition="287" endWordPosition="288">fficult to have a good command of such lexical phenomena. Current linguistics software programs use large corpus data to advance language learning. The use of corpora exposes learners to authentic contextual clues and lets them discover patterns or collocations of words from contextual clues (Partington, 1998). However, a huge amount of data can be overwhelming and time-consuming (Yeh et al., 2007) for language learners to induce rules or patterns. On the other hand, some lexical phenomena seem unable to be comprehended 1 http://glance-it.herokuapp.com/ fast and directly in plain text format (Koo, 2006). For example, in the British National Corpus (2007), “however” seems more negative than “but”. Also, compared with “but”, “however” appears more frequently at the beginning of a sentence. With this in mind, we proposed GLANCE1, a text visualization tool, which presents corpus data using charts and graphs to help language learners understand the lexical phenomena of a word quickly and intuitively. In this paper, we focused on five types of lexical phenomena: polarity, position, POS, form and discipline, which will be detailed in the Section 3. Given a single query word, the GLANCE system shows</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Koo, 2006</marker>
<rawString>Kyosung Koo (2006). Effects of using corpora and online reference tools on foreign language writing: a study of Korean learners of English as a second language. PhD. dissertation, University of Iowa.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>D Y Lee</author>
</authors>
<title>Genres, registers, text types, domains and styles: Clarifying the concepts and nevigating a path through the BNC jungle.</title>
<date>2001</date>
<contexts>
<context position="5317" citStr="Lee (2001)" startWordPosition="809" endWordPosition="810">ese data to other visualization tools. In this section, we describe the ways we extract the data from the corpus and how we translate these data into informative graphs. 3.1 Data Preprocessing We use the well-formed corpus, the BNC, to extract the data. In order to obtain the Part-ofspeech tags for each text, we use the GENIA tagger (Tsuruoka et al., 2005) to analyze the sentences of the BNC and build a list of &lt;POS-tag, frequency&gt; pairs for each word in the BNC. Also the BNC contains the classification code assigned to the text in a genre-based analysis carried out at Lancaster University by Lee (2001). For each word, the classification codes are aggregated to a list of &lt;code, frequency&gt; pairs. 3.2 Visualization of Lexical Phenomena Polarity A word may carry different sentiment polarities (i.e., positive, negative and objective). To help users quickly determine the proper sentiment polarity of a word, we introduce the sentiment polarity information of SentiWordNet (Baccianella et al., 2010) into our system. For each synset of a word, GLANCE displays the polarity in a bar with three different colors. The individual length of the three parts in the bar corresponds to the polarity scores of a </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Lee, 2001</marker>
<rawString>Lee, D. Y. (2001). Genres, registers, text types, domains and styles: Clarifying the concepts and nevigating a path through the BNC jungle.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>A Partington</author>
</authors>
<title>Patterns and meanings: Using corpora for English language research and teaching</title>
<date>1998</date>
<volume>2</volume>
<publisher>John Benjamins Publishing.</publisher>
<contexts>
<context position="1745" citStr="Partington, 1998" startWordPosition="241" endWordPosition="242">e understanding of word characteristics than textual display. 1 Introduction Vocabulary is a challenging aspect for language learners to master. Extended word knowledge, such as word polarity and position, is not widely available in traditional dictionaries. Thus, for most language learners, it is very difficult to have a good command of such lexical phenomena. Current linguistics software programs use large corpus data to advance language learning. The use of corpora exposes learners to authentic contextual clues and lets them discover patterns or collocations of words from contextual clues (Partington, 1998). However, a huge amount of data can be overwhelming and time-consuming (Yeh et al., 2007) for language learners to induce rules or patterns. On the other hand, some lexical phenomena seem unable to be comprehended 1 http://glance-it.herokuapp.com/ fast and directly in plain text format (Koo, 2006). For example, in the British National Corpus (2007), “however” seems more negative than “but”. Also, compared with “but”, “however” appears more frequently at the beginning of a sentence. With this in mind, we proposed GLANCE1, a text visualization tool, which presents corpus data using charts and g</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Partington, 1998</marker>
<rawString>Partington, A. (1998). Patterns and meanings: Using corpora for English language research and teaching (Vol. 2). John Benjamins Publishing.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>P Riehmann</author>
<author>H Gruendl</author>
<author>B Froehlich</author>
<author>M Potthast</author>
<author>M Trenkmann</author>
<author>B Stein</author>
</authors>
<title>The NETSPEAK WORDGRAPH: Visualizing keywords in context.</title>
<date>2011</date>
<booktitle>In Pacific Visualization Symposium (PacificVis), 2011 IEEE</booktitle>
<pages>123--130</pages>
<publisher>IEEE.</publisher>
<marker>Riehmann, Gruendl, Froehlich, Potthast, Trenkmann, Stein, 2011</marker>
<rawString>Riehmann, P., Gruendl, H., Froehlich, B., Potthast, M., Trenkmann, M., &amp; Stein, B. (2011, March). The NETSPEAK WORDGRAPH: Visualizing keywords in context. In Pacific Visualization Symposium (PacificVis), 2011 IEEE (pp. 123-130). IEEE.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M Scott</author>
</authors>
<title>WordSmith tools version 4.</title>
<date>2004</date>
<marker>Scott, 2004</marker>
<rawString>Scott, M. (2004). WordSmith tools version 4.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<title>The British National Corpus, version 3 (BNC XML Edition).</title>
<date>2007</date>
<booktitle>Distributed by Oxford University Computing Services on behalf of the BNC Consortium. URL: http://www.natcorp.ox.ac.uk/</booktitle>
<contexts>
<context position="2096" citStr="(2007)" startWordPosition="296" endWordPosition="296">. Current linguistics software programs use large corpus data to advance language learning. The use of corpora exposes learners to authentic contextual clues and lets them discover patterns or collocations of words from contextual clues (Partington, 1998). However, a huge amount of data can be overwhelming and time-consuming (Yeh et al., 2007) for language learners to induce rules or patterns. On the other hand, some lexical phenomena seem unable to be comprehended 1 http://glance-it.herokuapp.com/ fast and directly in plain text format (Koo, 2006). For example, in the British National Corpus (2007), “however” seems more negative than “but”. Also, compared with “but”, “however” appears more frequently at the beginning of a sentence. With this in mind, we proposed GLANCE1, a text visualization tool, which presents corpus data using charts and graphs to help language learners understand the lexical phenomena of a word quickly and intuitively. In this paper, we focused on five types of lexical phenomena: polarity, position, POS, form and discipline, which will be detailed in the Section 3. Given a single query word, the GLANCE system shows graphical representations of its lexical phenomena </context>
</contexts>
<marker>2007</marker>
<rawString>The British National Corpus, version 3 (BNC XML Edition). 2007. Distributed by Oxford University Computing Services on behalf of the BNC Consortium. URL: http://www.natcorp.ox.ac.uk/</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>ThinkMap Inc</author>
</authors>
<title>Thinkmap Visual Thesaurus. Available from</title>
<date>2005</date>
<note>http:// www.visualthesaurus.com</note>
<marker>Inc, 2005</marker>
<rawString>ThinkMap Inc. (2005). Thinkmap Visual Thesaurus. Available from http:// www.visualthesaurus.com</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Y Tsuruoka</author>
<author>Y Tateishi</author>
<author>J D Kim</author>
<author>T Ohta</author>
<author>J McNaught</author>
<author>S Ananiadou</author>
<author>J I Tsujii</author>
</authors>
<title>Developing a robust part-of-speech tagger for biomedical text.</title>
<date>2005</date>
<booktitle>In Advances in informatics</booktitle>
<pages>382--392</pages>
<publisher>Springer</publisher>
<location>Berlin Heidelberg.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="5065" citStr="Tsuruoka et al., 2005" startWordPosition="760" endWordPosition="763">he d3.js (Data-Driven Documents) (Bostock et al., 2011) to visualize the data. The d3.js enables direct inspection and manipulation of a standard document object model (DOM) so that we are able to transform numeric data into various types of graphs when fitting these data to other visualization tools. In this section, we describe the ways we extract the data from the corpus and how we translate these data into informative graphs. 3.1 Data Preprocessing We use the well-formed corpus, the BNC, to extract the data. In order to obtain the Part-ofspeech tags for each text, we use the GENIA tagger (Tsuruoka et al., 2005) to analyze the sentences of the BNC and build a list of &lt;POS-tag, frequency&gt; pairs for each word in the BNC. Also the BNC contains the classification code assigned to the text in a genre-based analysis carried out at Lancaster University by Lee (2001). For each word, the classification codes are aggregated to a list of &lt;code, frequency&gt; pairs. 3.2 Visualization of Lexical Phenomena Polarity A word may carry different sentiment polarities (i.e., positive, negative and objective). To help users quickly determine the proper sentiment polarity of a word, we introduce the sentiment polarity inform</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Tsuruoka, Tateishi, Kim, Ohta, McNaught, Ananiadou, Tsujii, 2005</marker>
<rawString>Tsuruoka, Y., Tateishi, Y., Kim, J. D., Ohta, T., McNaught, J., Ananiadou, S., &amp; Tsujii, J. I. (2005). Developing a robust part-of-speech tagger for biomedical text. In Advances in informatics (pp. 382-392). Springer Berlin Heidelberg.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M Wattenberg</author>
<author>F B Viégas</author>
</authors>
<title>The word tree, an interactive visual concordance. Visualization and Computer Graphics,</title>
<date>2008</date>
<journal>IEEE Transactions on,</journal>
<volume>14</volume>
<issue>6</issue>
<pages>1221--1228</pages>
<marker>Wattenberg, Viégas, 2008</marker>
<rawString>Wattenberg, M., &amp; Viégas, F. B. (2008). The word tree, an interactive visual concordance. Visualization and Computer Graphics, IEEE Transactions on, 14(6), 1221-1228.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>J Wood</author>
</authors>
<title>Can software support children’s vocabulary development.Language Learning</title>
<date>2001</date>
<journal>Technology,</journal>
<volume>5</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<pages>166--201</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="3355" citStr="Wood, 2001" startWordPosition="492" endWordPosition="493">lly we believe that the use of graphics also facilitates the understanding of the differences between two words. Taking this into consideration, we introduce a comparison mode to help learners differentiate two words at a glance. Allowing two word input, GLANCE draws the individual representative graphs for both words and presents these graphs in a twocolumn view. The display of parallel graphs depicts the distinctions between the two words clearly. 2 Related Work Corpus-based language learning has widened the perspectives in second and foreign language education, such as vocabulary learning (Wood, 2001). In past decades, various corpus-based reference tools have been developed. For example, WordSmith (Scott, 2000), Compleat Lexical Tutor (Cobb, 2007), GRASP (Huang et al., 2011), PREFER (Chen et al, 2012). Recently, some interactive visualization tools have been developed for the purpose of illustrating various linguistic phenomena. Three exam34 Proceedings of the Workshop on Interactive Language Learning, Visualization, and Interfaces, pages 34–37, Baltimore, Maryland, USA, June 27, 2014. @c 2014 Association for Computational Linguistics ples are Word Tree, a visual concordance (Wattenberg a</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Wood, 2001</marker>
<rawString>Wood, J. (2001). Can software support children’s vocabulary development.Language Learning &amp; Technology, 5(1), 166-201.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Y Yeh</author>
<author>H C Liou</author>
<author>Y H Li</author>
</authors>
<title>Online synonym materials and concordancing for EFL college writing.</title>
<date>2007</date>
<journal>Computer Assisted Language Learning,</journal>
<volume>20</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<pages>131--152</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="1835" citStr="Yeh et al., 2007" startWordPosition="254" endWordPosition="257"> a challenging aspect for language learners to master. Extended word knowledge, such as word polarity and position, is not widely available in traditional dictionaries. Thus, for most language learners, it is very difficult to have a good command of such lexical phenomena. Current linguistics software programs use large corpus data to advance language learning. The use of corpora exposes learners to authentic contextual clues and lets them discover patterns or collocations of words from contextual clues (Partington, 1998). However, a huge amount of data can be overwhelming and time-consuming (Yeh et al., 2007) for language learners to induce rules or patterns. On the other hand, some lexical phenomena seem unable to be comprehended 1 http://glance-it.herokuapp.com/ fast and directly in plain text format (Koo, 2006). For example, in the British National Corpus (2007), “however” seems more negative than “but”. Also, compared with “but”, “however” appears more frequently at the beginning of a sentence. With this in mind, we proposed GLANCE1, a text visualization tool, which presents corpus data using charts and graphs to help language learners understand the lexical phenomena of a word quickly and int</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Yeh, Liou, Li, 2007</marker>
<rawString>Yeh, Y., Liou, H. C., &amp; Li, Y. H. (2007). Online synonym materials and concordancing for EFL college writing. Computer Assisted Language Learning, 20(2), 131-152.</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>