<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="SectLabel" version="110505">
<variant no="0" confidence="0.010063">
<note confidence="0.679779">
The Varitext platform and the Corpus des variétés nationales du français
</note>
<title confidence="0.9495835">
(CoVaNa-FR) as resources for the study of French from a pluricentric
perspective
</title>
<author confidence="0.990338">
Sascha Diwersy
</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.997209">
Institute of Romance Languages /
Centre de Recherche Interdisciplinaire sur la France et la Francophonie (CIFRA)
University of Cologne
</affiliation>
<email confidence="0.762942">
sascha.diwersy@uni-koeln.de
</email>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.989388" genericHeader="abstract">
Abstract
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999894">
This paper reports on the francophone corpus archive Corpus des variétés nationales du français
(CoVaNa-FR) and the lexico-statistical platform Varitext. It outlines the design and data format
of the samples as well as presenting various usage scenarios related to the applications featured
by the platform’s toolbox.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.99906" genericHeader="introduction">
1 Introduction
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999958571428571">
This contribution presents the francophone corpus archive Corpus des variétés nationales du français
(CoVaNa-FR) and its hosting platform Varitext.
The paper is structured as follows. Section 2 will outline the rationale behind the corpus archive, its
composition and its data format. In section 3, we will then introduce the toolbox implemented by the
Varitext platform, by illustrating some of its functionalities and giving brief sketches of corresponding
usage scenarios. Section 4 provides a brief summary and discusses possible directions for the future
development of the resources presented in this paper.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.995337" genericHeader="method">
2 The CoVaNa-FR corpus archive
</sectionHeader>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.996419">
2.1 Rationale and composition of the CoVaNa-FR
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.971196">
The creation of the Corpus des variétés nationales du français (CoVaNa-FR) is motivated by the aim of
offering a large-scale resource to researchers working on the French language from a pluricentric per-
spective. It is thus primarily designed to provide methodological support for investigations in the French
tradition of ‘lexicologie différentielle’ (‘variationist differential lexicography’) focusing on elements of
endonormative differentiation, i.e. the emergence of regionally specific norms compared to a supposed
metropolitan standard variety of French (for studies on various francophone regions, see Rézeau 2007,
Thibault 2008; for studies especially focusing on Subsaharan Africa and the Maghreb, cf. Queffélec
1997, Lafage 2002, Naffati and Queffélec 2004, Nzesse 2009, to mention just a few examples of a si-
zable body of literature). Alongside the lexico-statistical toolbox implemented by the Varitext platform
(cf. Section 3 below), the design of the CoVaNa-FR goes beyond the rather conventional lexicographic
rationale of the lexicological framework just mentioned and can be seen as a contribution to meeting
the desideratum, voiced by Stein (2003:14f), of carrying out large-scale investigations on Francophone
varieties using contemporary corpus linguistic methods. In this regard, the CoVaNa-FR differs from exis-
ting French corpora such as Frantext (cf. ATILF-CNRS), Québétext (cf. Trésor de la langue française au
Québec) and Suistext (cf. Trésor des Vocabulaires francophones Neuchâtel) in offering broad regional
coverage (bundling samples from Africa, Europe and North America), a wider range of query functiona-
lities and free access (large parts of Frantext not being accessible free of charge and Suistext only being
available locally at its hosting institution, cf. Thibault 2007:480). Apart from corpus linguistic uses, the
CoVaNa-FR could also be a valuable resource for research on the automatic classification of language
varieties, which has recently aroused considerable interest in the field of NLP (for relevant contributi-
ons see, amongst others, Ranaivo-Malancon 2006, Ljubeši´c et al. 2007, Tiedemann and Ljubeši´c 2012,
This work is licenced under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License. Page numbers and proceedings footer
are added by the organizers. License details: http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.987429">
48
</page>
<note confidence="0.9858745">
Proceedings of the First Workshop on Applying NLP Tools to Similar Languages, Varieties and Dialects, pages 48–57,
Dublin, Ireland, August 23 2014.
</note>
<bodyText confidence="0.9945630625">
Trieschnigg et al. 2012, Zampieri and Gebre 2012, Tan et al. 2014). It should be noted, though, that in
accordance with copyright restrictions, the CoVaNa-FR is not directly available for download and can
only be consulted via the GUI of the password-protected Varitext platform.
Due to its focus on endonormative differentiation, the CoVaNa-FR is less balanced with respect to
genre than similar corpora for other languages such as the International Corpus of English (ICE, cf.
Greenbaum 1996), the Corpus of Contemporary American English (COCA, cf. Davies 2009), the Cor-
pus de Referencia del Español Actual (CREA, cf. Real Academia Española), the Corpus del Español
(cf. Davies 2002) or the Corpus do Português (cf. Davies 2014).1 The initial version of the CoVaNa-FR,
accessible on the Varitext platform, is made up of journalistic texts published by national newspapers in
different Francophone countries in Africa, Europe and North America. The choice of national newspa-
pers as primary sources is based on the assumption made by Glessgen (2007:97) that these are parti-
cularly representative of contemporary standard varieties (“les grands journaux [...] reflètent assez bien
les variétés standard actuelles”). Work is also underway on the extension of the CoVaNa-FR, such that
future versions will include a subcorpus of fiction and academic texts. In its present state, the CoVaNa-
FR is divided into 11 samples collected across a span of at least two years and categorized by regional
parameters as listed in Table 1.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.9970952">
Sample code Country Sources Number of
word tokens2
DZA Algeria El Watan, La Tribune d’Alger 45,600,000
CAM Cameroon Cameroon Tribune, La Nouvelle Expression, 46,500,000
Mutations
CAN Canada (Québec) Le Devoir, Le Soleil 53,500,000
COD Congo (D.R.C.) Le Potentiel 27,300,000
FRA France Le Figaro, Le Monde 53,300,000
CIV Ivory Coast Fraternité Matin, Notre Voie 18,800,000
MLI Mali Aurore, L’Essor, L’Indépendant 25,100,000
MAR Morocco Aujourd’hui le Maroc, Le Matin du Sahara 43,600,000
SEN Senegal Le Soleil, Wal Fadjri 27,100,000
CHE Switzerland Le Temps, La Tribune de Genève 28,000,000
TUN Tunisia La Presse, Le Quotidien, Le Temps 50,900,000
Total 419,700,000
</table>
<tableCaption confidence="0.870074">
Tab. 1: Composition of the CoVaNa-FR (on-line version accessible via the Varitext platform).
</tableCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.999909833333333">
The compilation of the overall corpus archive outlined in Table 1 has been carried out according to
the requirement that each country be represented by a sample comprising at least two newspapers with
articles from the same (or similar) two years. It should be noted, though, that some samples do not
fully meet these guidelines, as is the case with the corpora representing Algeria and Canada (containing
two newspapers from single and different years) or the sample representing the Democratic Republic of
Congo (containing three years of only one newspaper).
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.999501">
2.2 Processing format of the CoVaNa-FR
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999868444444444">
All documents in the CoVaNa-FR corpus are formatted in eXtensible Markup Language (XML) with the
structural units (i) subcorpus, (ii) text, (iii) paragraph, and (iv) sentence. The texts are annotated with
(i) part-of-speech (PoS) tags, (ii) lemmas and (iii) dependency-parses using the commercially licensed
Connexor annotation tool (Tapanainen and Järvinen 1997). The corpus files are in standard CWB in-
put format (cf. Evert and Hardie 2011:5f) with XML tags and each token record (one surface form +
associated TAB-delimited token-level annotations) appearing on separate lines.
The set of XML tagged structural units is specified by the DTD given in Figure 1. Note that the top
level &lt;corpus&gt;...&lt;/corpus&gt; element defines one country related sample and that each subcorpus corre-
sponds to a one year newspaper volume. The element attributes which are provided inside the query
</bodyText>
<footnote confidence="0.99880625">
1See the projects’ web sites at http://ice-corpora.net/ICE/INDEX.HTM, http://corpus.byu.edu/
coca/, http://corpus.rae.es/creanet.html, http://www.corpusdelespanol.org and http://
www.corpusdoportugues.org respectively.
2Numbers are rounded down to the nearest 100,000.
</footnote>
<page confidence="0.999599">
49
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.9477265">
platform as metadata categories for corpus partitioning or the description of concordance extracts are
highlighted in boldface.
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.998882411764706">
&lt;!DOCTYPE varcorpus [
&lt;!-- country related sample --&gt;
&lt;!ELEMENT corpus (subcorpus)+&gt;
&lt;!-- one year newspaper volume --&gt;
&lt;!ELEMENT subcorpus (text)+&gt;
&lt;!-- newspaper article --&gt;
&lt;!ELEMENT text (p)+&gt;
&lt;!-- paragraph --&gt;
&lt;!ELEMENT p (s)+&gt;
&lt;!-- sentence --&gt;
&lt;!ELEMENT s (#PCDATA)&gt;
&lt;!ATTLIST corpus id CDATA #REQUIRED
name CDATA #REQUIRED
code CDATA #REQUIRED
geocode CDATA #REQUIRED
geoname CDATA #REQUIRED
&gt;
&lt;!ATTLIST subcorpus id CDATA #REQUIRED
name CDATA #REQUIRED
code CDATA #REQUIRED
source CDATA #REQUIRED
year CDATA #REQUIRED
&gt;
&lt;!ATTLIST text id CDATA #REQUIRED
title CDATA #REQUIRED
author CDATA #REQUIRED
date CDATA #REQUIRED
section CDATA #REQUIRED
&gt;
&lt;!ATTLIST p id CDATA #REQUIRED
type CDATA #IMPLIED
&gt;
&lt;!ATTLIST s id CDATA #REQUIRED&gt;
]&gt;
</figure>
<figureCaption confidence="0.999874">
Fig. 1: DTD specifying the structural elements of the country-related samples in the CoVaNa-FR corpus archive.
</figureCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.997667818181818">
As for the token rows, their core structure is basically defined according to the so-called CoNLL
format, introduced on the occasion of the correspondent 2007 shared task on dependency parsing (cf.
Nivre et al. 2007:916). For rather technical reasons, this structure has been extended by a number
of fields whose purpose is to optimize the processing of queries exploring the dependency relations
annotated in the corpus. The fields in question are marked by an asterisk in the following table, which
outlines the overall structure of the token records:
Field name Description
id sentence internal numerical token identifier (counter starting at 1 for each sentence)
word surface form or punctuation sign
lemma lemma corresponding to the surface form
cpos coarse grained part of speech (PoS)
pos fine grained PoS + morphological features
headid token identifier of the syntactic head
headoffset * distance between syntactic head and token
deprel syntactic function of the token in the dependency relation to its head
headword * surface form of the syntactic head
headlemma * lemma of the syntactic head
headcpos * coarse grained PoS of the syntactic head
headpos * fine grained PoS + morphological features of the syntactic head
pmarkword * surface form of the function word (adposition or conjunction) dependent on the token3
pmarklemma * lemma of the function word dependent on the token
pmarkcpos * PoS of the function word dependent on the token
</bodyText>
<tableCaption confidence="0.244486">
Tab. 2: Structure of the token records contained by the corpus files.
</tableCaption>
<page confidence="0.986883">
50
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999773">
The 11 country specific samples making up the present online version of the CoVaNa-FR (see Table 1
above) have been encoded by means of the IMS Open Corpus Workbench (CWB, cf. Evert and Hardie
2011; see also the project’s web site http://cwb.sourceforge.net/), the total size of the cor-
responding index files summing up to 58,4 GB of disk space. The components of CWB are integrated
as main query processing tools in the Varitext platform, which will be described in more detail in the
following section.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.998563" genericHeader="method">
3 The Varitext platform
</sectionHeader>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.999157">
3.1 Design and GUI
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999954666666667">
Varitext is a web-based platform (cf. http://syrah.uni-koeln.de/varitext/ and http:
//extranet-ldi.univ-paris13.fr/varitext/) providing free-of-charge access to the
CoVaNa-FR corpus archive presented in section 2. As is indicated by its name, it is open to host corpora
for other languages compiled according to the same rationale of large-scale variationist research in a
pluricentric perspective. Work has already been completed on the prototype of a hispanophone corpus
archive, which will be released via Varitext in the near future. There are also plans to compile similar
resources for Portuguese, Russian and Arabic.
The toolbox implemented by the Varitext platform is built upon three major software components:
CWB for query processing, the UCS toolkit version 0.6 (cf. Evert 2005, the software being available at
http://www.collocations.de/software.html) for cooccurrence analysis and R (R Core
Team 2014) for statistical computing and plotting.
The platform’s user interface allows fairly complex queries in terms of subsampling and the formula-
tion of search expressions. Using the menu options relating to the available metadata categories (such as
country code, newspaper volume or thematic section), it is possible to create subcorpora and partitions
with different degrees of granularity, as is shown by Fig. 2:
</bodyText>
<figureCaption confidence="0.9527705">
Fig. 2: Using menu options to build a partition defined by country on the basis of a subcorpus comprising the samples repre-
senting Cameroon and the Ivory Coast and filtered by the thematic section ’Sports’
</figureCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.99861325">
As for the formulation of query expressions, the interface integrates a sub-menu to set up search
constraints flexibly by combining several token properties (such as lemma, PoS or syntactic function;
see the data model outlined in table 2 above) and / or assembling sequences of various length (see Figure
3).
</bodyText>
<footnote confidence="0.93222">
3The annotation model of Connexor treats adpositions and conjunctions as markers dependent on content words (verbs,
nouns, adjectives, adverbs).
</footnote>
<page confidence="0.996312">
51
</page>
<figureCaption confidence="0.994171">
Fig. 3: Using the platform’s interface to build up a query expression matching the sequence en ville (“in town”)
</figureCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.9999354">
In its present state, the Varitext platform features as its standard applications a KWIC concordancer
and a set of tools for frequency computing, key word analysis and collocation processing, the latter of
which will be outlined in some detail below. Future releases of the platform will also include advanced
functionalities of statistical computing and plotting that are currently under development and testing and
which will be briefly sketched at the end of this section.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.9721655">
3.2 Usage Scenario: Sample Specific Frequencies and Lexical Differences
3.2.1 chaussure vs. soulier
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999752076923077">
One of the platform’s standard applications besides KWIC concordancing is the computation of sample
specific frequencies and key word analysis. In a corpus-based perspective, these methods can be used for
instance as diagnostics to test the results of ‘differential’ lexicology. Similar to Thibault’s (2007) study
on some lexical specificities of Canadian (Quebec), Swiss and metropolitan standard French, it would be
possible to analyze geographical lexical variants in terms of their frequency distribution. An example also
mentioned by Thibault (2007:468-475) is provided by the nouns chaussure and soulier (“shoe”), with
soulier being regarded as regional variant especially of Canadian French (cf. the reference dictionary Le
Petit Robert (Rey-Debove and Rey 2006) s.v. SOULIER). A key word analysis based on the samples
representing Canada/Quebec (geographical code: CAN), France (FRA) and Switzerland (CHE) yields
the log-likelihood ratio (LL) scores given by the following bar plots in Fig. 4 (for the use of the log
likelihood ratio in key word analysis see Rayson 2003). The computation has been carried out on a 2x2
basis, with one sample as the main corpus and the combination of the remaining two as the reference
corpus.
</bodyText>
<figureCaption confidence="0.929205">
Fig. 4: LL scores for the nouns chaussure and soulier in the samples representing Canada/Quebec, Switzerland and France
</figureCaption>
<page confidence="0.995139">
52
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.9999565">
These figures indicate that there are clear-cut distributional divergences, with the two nouns being
respectively under- and overrepresented in the samples related to Quebec and France. This seems to
suggest that soulier is still part of the French standard as it evolves in Quebec, or at least in its national
newspapers, which qualifies to some extent the findings of Thibault (2007:474), according to which
Quebec newspaper language is moving towards greater conformity with French metropolitan usage in
the case of chaussure and soulier. It should be noted that Thibault only considers the relative frequencies
of the two items within each national sample. Applying this approach to our corpus data would provide
no more than a confirmation of Thibault’s findings. In light of the aforementioned key word analysis,
though, there is sufficient evidence to conclude that, in Quebec French, the relationship between the
two variants is rather more complex and should be subjected to a more detailed analysis in terms of
collocational distribution. One promising approach in this respect would be Hoey’s (2005) lexical
priming theory.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.943686">
3.2.2 Quebec Specific Lexical Items
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999495">
At this point, it is worth noting that, although major national newspapers might reflect trends of standard
varieties quite faithfully (see our reference to Glessgen 2007 in section 2), the data obtained from these
sources should be handled with some caution (cf. also Thibault 2007:474). This is of particular import-
ance if we adopt a corpus-driven approach, which involves identifying the most characteristic features in
a sample by means of statistical techniques such as key word analysis.
This may be illustrated with the results of a key word analysis contrasting the Quebec subcorpus as a
whole with the sample representing France.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.993046473684211">
Lemma Frequency Frequency Rel. Freq.4 Rel. Freq. LL score Rank
CAN FRA CAN FRA
Québec 93269 828 ....... 15.53 ... 1
Montréal 44257 472 ....... 8.85 ... 2
Canada 43612 1808 ....... 33.9 ... 3
. .. .. .. ....... 0.08 ... .
chum 1191 4 ....... 0.02 ... 243
. .. .. .. 1740.4 0 120592.82 .
magasiner 183 1 825.83 0 56578.51 1987
. .. .. .. 813.8 47579.89 .
placoter 18 0 .. . 10744
. .. .. .. 22.22 1597.32 .
paqueter 13 0 .. . 13473
. .. .. .. 3.41 241.78 .
.. .
0.34 24.87
.. .
0.24 17.96
.. .
</table>
<tableCaption confidence="0.873343">
Tab. 3: Words specific to the Quebec sub-corpus in contrast with the sample representing France.
</tableCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.999111">
The data given in Table 3 show that the most specific items are proper nouns closely related to socio-
cultural context, whereas words which clearly qualify as Quebecisms, such as chum (“friend, pal”),
magasiner (“to go shopping”), placoter (“to chat”; cf. Poirier 1995:32) or paqueter (“to pack”; cf.
Poirier ibid) only come at lower ranks, their log-likelihood scores being nonetheless highly significant.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.999464">
3.3 Usage Scenario: Lexical Cooccurrences and Collocational Variation
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999802">
The second main application provided by the platform’s toolbox is collocation analysis. We will illustrate
this functionality by considering the example of the causative support verb occasionner (“to occasion
sth”) and the semantic associations instantiated by its most significant collocates within each of the
</bodyText>
<footnote confidence="0.929238">
4Figures are given in terms of token per million.
</footnote>
<page confidence="0.998824">
53
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.993777833333333">
samples making up the CoVaNa-Fr corpus archive.
The following cross table which is based on the lexicogram (defined as list of collocates specified by
association scores; see Tournier 1987) computed for occasionner displays some of the nouns in direct
object position significantly collocating with this verb in terms of the log-likelihood ratio (the use of
the latter as an association measure for collocation analysis having been proposed, amongst others, by
Dunning 1993).
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.979804222222222">
Collocate CAN5 CHE CIV CMR COD DZA FRA MAR MLI SEN TUN
accident - - - 67.8 - 65.4 - - 61.2 - -
accroissement - - - - 68.5 - - - - - -
augmentation - - - - 52.4 - - - - - -
baisse - - - - 41.7 - - - 59.5 - -
coût 90.3 - - - - - - - - - -
dégât - 87.6 - 91.8 268.5 1059.3 62.3 255.7 157.6 208.5 143.9
perte 298.8 109.4 267.8 178.0 208.8 381.4 64.9 134.1 492.9 170.5 129.7
problème 62.37 - - - - 23.1 - - - - 33.1
</table>
<tableCaption confidence="0.916251">
Tab. 4: Significant direct object noun collocates of occasionner across all the samples contained by the CoVaNa-FR.
</tableCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.999496916666667">
It is easy to see that the combinatorial profile of occasionner is essentially characterized by negative
semantic prosody throughout all the samples under investigation (for the concept of semantic prosody,
see Stubbs 1995 and Xiao and McEnery 2006). At the same time, however, it exhibits some degree of
regional variation; in the case of the sub-corpus representing the Congo (COD), for example, there is
an additional semantic feature in evidence which may be described as INTENSITY (cf. the collocates
accroissement [“increase, growth”], augmentation [“increase, rise”] and baisse [“decrease, fall”]).
A similar statement can be made with regard to the significant noun collocates of causer (“to cause”),
although in this case it is the Quebec sample which adds more neutral marked elements (surprise [“sur-
prise”]) to the overall picture. We illustrate this by a means of a plot generated by a correspondence
analysis (CA, see Lebart et al. 1998:47ff) performed on the sample specific lexicograms comprising the
direct object nouns significantly associated6 with the verb in question (further examples of using CA to
explore the CoVaNa-FR are given by Diwersy and Loiseau forthcoming):
</bodyText>
<figureCaption confidence="0.827611">
Fig. 5: Plot generated by a CA performed on the country specific lexicograms of causer.
</figureCaption>
<footnote confidence="0.995987">
5Sample name as translated to their corresponding ISO 3166-1 alpha-3 country codes (see the UN Statistic Division’s page
athttp://unstats.un.org/unsd/methods/m49/m49alpha.htm).
6The collocates used for further processing have been selected according to a frequency threshold of 20 and an LL score
threshold of 10.83.
</footnote>
<page confidence="0.998751">
54
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.9998092">
The CA plot7 given in Fig. 5 highlights in its main (horizontal) dimension the contrast between the
Quebec subcorpus and the remaining samples, this contrast being paralleled by the contrast between the
noun surprise and other items such as souci (“worry”) and dégât (“damage”).8
Correspondence analysis is a useful technique in providing a condensed view of divergences relating to
samples and lexical items. It will be included in the next release of the Varitext platform.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.991453" genericHeader="conclusions">
4 Conclusion
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999980444444444">
As the examples in the preceding section have shown, there is considerable scope for using corpus-related
techniques (beyond concordancing) to investigate geographical variation from a pluricentric perspective,
but researchers must exercise caution when working on the diverse sets of data which can be obtained
using the resources outlined in this paper. A major case in point is the composition of the corpus ar-
chive and its current restriction to journalistic texts, which may bring about phenomena related to the
socio-cultural context rather than the linguistic one (although, from the point of view of media discourse
analysis and communication studies, these thematic „side effects“ could be of quite some interest).
It should be obvious, then, that our present activities focus on diversifying the corpus resources, espe-
cially with regard to other written genres. At the same time, we are engaged in extending the overall
text archive to include corpora for different languages, the rationale being to apply the methodological
framework implemented by the Varitext platform to linguistic areas other than Francophonia.
This framework is itself undergoing considerable modifications which will lead to the integration of ad-
vanced statistical functionalities. At present, our main interest is to enhance the platform’s toolbox by
implementing several exploratory multivariate techniques, which will be tested in experimental settings
that, however, go beyond the narrow focus of this paper.
That said, the development of the corpus archive and of the platform is still in its infancy, and is set to
evolve further in various ways and directions. At least, this is what should happen if the community
makes good use of it.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.994588" genericHeader="acknowledgments">
Acknowledgements
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9999675">
The author wishes to thank the reviewers for their valuable comments which helped to clarify the main
points of the paper.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.997689" genericHeader="references">
References
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.997001266666667">
ATILF-CNRS. Base textuelle FRANTEXT. ATILF-CNRS Nancy &amp; Université de Lorraine. http://www.
frantext.fr/.
Mark Davies. 2002. Un corpus anotado de 100.000.000 palabras del español histórico y moderno. SEPLN 2002
(Sociedad Española para el Procesamiento del Lenguaje Natural), 21–27.
Mark Davies. 2009. The 385+ Million Word Corpus of Contemporary American English (1990-2008+): Design,
Architecture, and Linguistic Insights. International Journal of Corpus Linguistics, 14: 159–190.
Mark Davies. 2014. Creating and Using the Corpus do Português and the Frequency Dictionary of Portuguese.
Tony Berber Sardinha and Telma de Lurdes São Bento Ferreira (eds.): Working with Portuguese Corpora.
London: Bloomsbury Publishing, 89–110.
Sascha Diwersy and Sylvain Loiseau. Forthcoming. La différenciation du français dans l’espace francophone:
l’apport des statistiques lexicales. Kirsten A. Jeppesen Kragh, Jan Lindschouw and Lene Schøsler (eds.): Les
variations diasystématiques dans les langues romanes et leurs interdépendances. Société de Linguistique Ro-
mane.
Ted Dunning. 1993. Accurate methods for the statistics of surprise and coincidence. Computational Linguistics,
19(1): 61–74.
</reference>
<footnote confidence="0.99459">
7The given CA plot has been generated by means of the R package FactoMineR (cf. Husson et al. 2013).
8To be more precise, the main dimension (read from right to left) puts into contrast nouns opposed by the features (1)
’neutral’ vs. ’negative’ (affect) polarity (surprise vs. souci), (2) ’physical’ vs. ’material’ damage (lésion [“injury, lesion”] vs.
dégât / préjudice [“damage”]) and (3) ’non-lethal’ vs. ’lethal’ impact (lésion vs. mort [“death”]).
</footnote>
<page confidence="0.99837">
55
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.925037285714286">
Stefan Evert. 2005. Empirical research on association measures: The UCS toolkit. Software demonstration at
the Phraseology 2005 Conference, Louvain-la-Neuve, Belgium. [abstract available at http://purl.org/
stefan.evert/PUB/Evert2005phraseology.pdf]
Stefan Evert and Andrew Hardie. 2011. Twenty-first century corpus workbench: Updating a query architecture
for the new millennium. Proceedings of the Corpus Linguistics 2011 Conference, Birmingham, UK. [pdf versi-
on available for download at http://www.birmingham.ac.uk/documents/college-artslaw/
corpus/conference-archives/2011/Paper-153.pdf]
</bodyText>
<reference confidence="0.985236102564103">
Martin-Dietrich Glessgen. 2007. Linguistique romane, domaine et méthode – Domaines et méthodes en linguisti-
que française et romane. Paris: Armand Colin.
Sidney Greenbaum (ed.). 1996. Comparing English Worldwide: The International Corpus of English. Oxford:
Clarendon Press.
Michael Hoey. 2005. Lexical Priming: A New Theory of Words and Language. London: Routledge.
François Husson, Julie Josse, Sebastien Lê and Jeremy Mazet. 2013. FactoMineR: Multivariate Exploratory Data
Analysis and Data Mining with R. http://CRAN.R-project.org/package=FactoMineR.
Suzanne Lafage. 2002. Le lexique français de Côté-d’Ivoire (Appropriation et créativité). Nice: CNRS.
Ludovic Lebart, André Salem and Lisette Berry. 1998. Exploring Textual Data. Dordrecht: Springer.
Nikola Ljubeši´c, Nives Mikeli´c and Damir Boras. 2007. Language Identification: How to Distinguish Similar
Languages? Proceedings of the 29th International Conference on Information Technology Interfaces, Zagreb,
Croatia.
Habiba Naffati and Ambroise Queffélec. 2004. Le français en Tunisie. Nice: CNRS.
Joakim Nivre, Johan Hall, Sandra Kübler, Ryan Mcdonald, Jens Nilsson, Sebastian Riedel, Deniz Yuret. 2007.
The CoNLL 2007 Shared Task on Dependency Parsing. Proceedings of the CoNLL Shared Task Session of
EMNLP-CoNLL 2007, Prague, Czech Republic, 915–932.
Ladislas Nzesse. 2009. Le français au Cameroun: d’une crise sociopolitique à la vitalité de la langue française
(1990-2008). Nice: CNRS.
Claude Poirier. 1995. Les variantes topolectales du lexique français: propositions de classement à partir
d’exemples québécois. Michel Francard and Danièle Latin (eds.): Le régionalisme lexical. Louvain-la-Neuve:
De Boeck, 13–56.
Ambroise Queffélec. 1997. Le français en Centrafrique: lexique et société. Vanves: Editions Classiques
d’Expression Française (EDICEF).
Bali Ranaivo-Malancon. 2006. Automatic identification of close languages - case study: Malay and Indonesian.
ECTI Transactions on Computer and Information Technology (2): 126–134.
Paul Rayson. 2003. Matrix: A statistical method and software tool for linguistic analysis through corpus compa-
rison. Ph.D. thesis, Lancaster University. [pdf version available for download at http://ucrel.lancs.
ac.uk/people/paul/publications/phd2003.pdf]
R Core Team. 2014. R: A language and environment for statistical computing. R Foundation for Statistical
Computing, Vienna, Austria. [http://www.R-project.org/]
Real Academia Española. Corpus de referencia del español actual. http://www.rae.es.
Josette Rey-Debove and Alain Rey (eds.). 2006. Le Nouveau Petit Robert: Dictionnaire alphabétique et analogi-
que de la langue française. Paris: Dictionnaires Le Robert.
Pierre Rézeau (ed.). 2007. Richesse du français et géographie linguistique, volume 1. Louvain-la-Neuve: de
Boeck.
Achim Stein. 2003. Lexikalische Kookkurrenz im afrikanischen Französisch. Zeitschrift für französische Sprach-
und Literaturwissenschaft, 113: 1–17.
Michael Stubbs. 1995. Collocations and semantic profiles: On the cause of the trouble with quantitative studies.
Functions of Language, 2(1): 23–55.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.96486">
56
</page>
<reference confidence="0.999422083333333">
Liling Tan, Marcos Zampieri, Nikola Ljube&amp;quot;si´c and Jörg Tiedemann. 2014. Merging Comparable Data Sources for
the Discrimination of Similar Languages: The DSL Corpus Collection. Proceedings of the 7th Workshop on
Building and Using Comparable Corpora: Building Resources for Machine Translation Research, Reykjavik,
Iceland.
Pasi Tapanainen and Timo Järvinen. 1997. A non-projective dependency parser. Proceedings of the 5th Confe-
rence on Applied Natural Language Processing, Washington, DC, 64–74.
Andr6 Thibault. 2007. Banques de donn6es textuelles, r6gionalismes de fr6quence et r6gionalismes n6gatifs.
ACILPR XXIV, volume 1, 467–480.
Andr6 Thibault (ed.). 2008. Richesse du français et géographie linguistique, volume 2. Louvain-la-Neuve: de
Boeck.
Jörg Tiedemann and Nikola Ljube&amp;quot;si´c. 2012. Efficient discrimination between closely related languages. Procee-
dings of COLING 2012, Mumbai, India, 2619–2634.
Tr6sor de la langue française au Qu6bec. Base textuelle QUÉBÉTEXT. Universit6 Laval, D6partement de Langues,
linguistiqueettraduction. http://www.tlfq.ulaval.ca/quebetext/
Tr6sor des Vocabulaires francophones Neuchâtel. Base textuelle SUISTEXT. Universit6 de Neuchâtel, Centre de
dialectologie et d’6tude du français r6gional.
Dolf Trieschnigg, Djoerd Hiemstra, Mariët Theune, Franciska de Jong and Theo Meder. 2012. An exploration
of language identification techniques for the Dutch Folktale Database. Proceedings of LREC 2012, Istanbul,
Turkey.
Maurice Tournier. 1987. Cooccurrences autour de travail (1971-1976). Mots, 14: 89–123.
Richard Xiao and Tony McEnery. 2006. Collocation, semantic prosody, and near synonymy: A cross-linguistic
perspective. Applied linguistics, 27(1): 103–129.
Marcos Zampieri and Binyam Gebrekidan Gebre. 2012. Automatic Identification of Language Varieties: The
Case of Portuguese. Proceedings of KONVENS 2012, Vienna, Austria, 233–237.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.999145">
57
</page>
</variant>
</algorithm>
<algorithm name="ParsHed" version="110505">
<variant no="0" confidence="0.329066">
<title confidence="0.474337">and the des variétés nationales du (CoVaNa-FR) as resources for the study of French from a pluricentric perspective</title>
<author confidence="0.9487">Sascha</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.994475333333333">Institute of Romance Languages Centre de Recherche Interdisciplinaire sur la France et la Francophonie University of</affiliation>
<email confidence="0.964799">sascha.diwersy@uni-koeln.de</email>
<abstract confidence="0.9980892">paper reports on the francophone corpus archive des variétés nationales du français and the lexico-statistical platform It outlines the design and data format of the samples as well as presenting various usage scenarios related to the applications featured by the platform’s toolbox.</abstract>
</variant>
</algorithm>
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>Base textuelle FRANTEXT</author>
</authors>
<journal>ATILF-CNRS Nancy &amp; Université</journal>
<note>http://www. frantext.fr/.</note>
<marker>FRANTEXT, </marker>
<rawString>ATILF-CNRS. Base textuelle FRANTEXT. ATILF-CNRS Nancy &amp; Université de Lorraine. http://www. frantext.fr/.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Mark Davies</author>
</authors>
<title>Un corpus anotado de 100.000.000 palabras del español histórico y moderno.</title>
<date>2002</date>
<booktitle>SEPLN 2002 (Sociedad Española para el Procesamiento del Lenguaje Natural),</booktitle>
<pages>21--27</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="4573" citStr="Davies 2002" startWordPosition="658" endWordPosition="659">ould be noted, though, that in accordance with copyright restrictions, the CoVaNa-FR is not directly available for download and can only be consulted via the GUI of the password-protected Varitext platform. Due to its focus on endonormative differentiation, the CoVaNa-FR is less balanced with respect to genre than similar corpora for other languages such as the International Corpus of English (ICE, cf. Greenbaum 1996), the Corpus of Contemporary American English (COCA, cf. Davies 2009), the Corpus de Referencia del Español Actual (CREA, cf. Real Academia Española), the Corpus del Español (cf. Davies 2002) or the Corpus do Português (cf. Davies 2014).1 The initial version of the CoVaNa-FR, accessible on the Varitext platform, is made up of journalistic texts published by national newspapers in different Francophone countries in Africa, Europe and North America. The choice of national newspapers as primary sources is based on the assumption made by Glessgen (2007:97) that these are particularly representative of contemporary standard varieties (“les grands journaux [...] reflètent assez bien les variétés standard actuelles”). Work is also underway on the extension of the CoVaNa-FR, such that fut</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Davies, 2002</marker>
<rawString>Mark Davies. 2002. Un corpus anotado de 100.000.000 palabras del español histórico y moderno. SEPLN 2002 (Sociedad Española para el Procesamiento del Lenguaje Natural), 21–27.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Mark Davies</author>
</authors>
<title>The 385+ Million Word Corpus of Contemporary American English (1990-2008+): Design, Architecture, and Linguistic Insights.</title>
<date>2009</date>
<journal>International Journal of Corpus Linguistics,</journal>
<volume>14</volume>
<pages>159--190</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="4451" citStr="Davies 2009" startWordPosition="638" endWordPosition="639">s, pages 48–57, Dublin, Ireland, August 23 2014. Trieschnigg et al. 2012, Zampieri and Gebre 2012, Tan et al. 2014). It should be noted, though, that in accordance with copyright restrictions, the CoVaNa-FR is not directly available for download and can only be consulted via the GUI of the password-protected Varitext platform. Due to its focus on endonormative differentiation, the CoVaNa-FR is less balanced with respect to genre than similar corpora for other languages such as the International Corpus of English (ICE, cf. Greenbaum 1996), the Corpus of Contemporary American English (COCA, cf. Davies 2009), the Corpus de Referencia del Español Actual (CREA, cf. Real Academia Española), the Corpus del Español (cf. Davies 2002) or the Corpus do Português (cf. Davies 2014).1 The initial version of the CoVaNa-FR, accessible on the Varitext platform, is made up of journalistic texts published by national newspapers in different Francophone countries in Africa, Europe and North America. The choice of national newspapers as primary sources is based on the assumption made by Glessgen (2007:97) that these are particularly representative of contemporary standard varieties (“les grands journaux [...] refl</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Davies, 2009</marker>
<rawString>Mark Davies. 2009. The 385+ Million Word Corpus of Contemporary American English (1990-2008+): Design, Architecture, and Linguistic Insights. International Journal of Corpus Linguistics, 14: 159–190.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Mark Davies</author>
</authors>
<date>2014</date>
<booktitle>Creating and Using the Corpus do Português and the Frequency Dictionary of Portuguese. Tony Berber Sardinha and Telma de Lurdes São Bento Ferreira (eds.): Working with Portuguese Corpora.</booktitle>
<pages>89--110</pages>
<publisher>Bloomsbury Publishing,</publisher>
<location>London:</location>
<contexts>
<context position="4618" citStr="Davies 2014" startWordPosition="666" endWordPosition="667">h copyright restrictions, the CoVaNa-FR is not directly available for download and can only be consulted via the GUI of the password-protected Varitext platform. Due to its focus on endonormative differentiation, the CoVaNa-FR is less balanced with respect to genre than similar corpora for other languages such as the International Corpus of English (ICE, cf. Greenbaum 1996), the Corpus of Contemporary American English (COCA, cf. Davies 2009), the Corpus de Referencia del Español Actual (CREA, cf. Real Academia Española), the Corpus del Español (cf. Davies 2002) or the Corpus do Português (cf. Davies 2014).1 The initial version of the CoVaNa-FR, accessible on the Varitext platform, is made up of journalistic texts published by national newspapers in different Francophone countries in Africa, Europe and North America. The choice of national newspapers as primary sources is based on the assumption made by Glessgen (2007:97) that these are particularly representative of contemporary standard varieties (“les grands journaux [...] reflètent assez bien les variétés standard actuelles”). Work is also underway on the extension of the CoVaNa-FR, such that future versions will include a subcorpus of fict</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Davies, 2014</marker>
<rawString>Mark Davies. 2014. Creating and Using the Corpus do Português and the Frequency Dictionary of Portuguese. Tony Berber Sardinha and Telma de Lurdes São Bento Ferreira (eds.): Working with Portuguese Corpora. London: Bloomsbury Publishing, 89–110.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>Forthcoming</author>
</authors>
<title>La différenciation du français dans l’espace francophone: l’apport des statistiques lexicales.</title>
<booktitle>Lindschouw and Lene Schøsler (eds.): Les variations diasystématiques dans les langues romanes et leurs interdépendances. Société de Linguistique</booktitle>
<editor>Kirsten A. Jeppesen Kragh, Jan</editor>
<location>Romane.</location>
<marker>Forthcoming, </marker>
<rawString>Sascha Diwersy and Sylvain Loiseau. Forthcoming. La différenciation du français dans l’espace francophone: l’apport des statistiques lexicales. Kirsten A. Jeppesen Kragh, Jan Lindschouw and Lene Schøsler (eds.): Les variations diasystématiques dans les langues romanes et leurs interdépendances. Société de Linguistique Romane.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Ted Dunning</author>
</authors>
<title>Accurate methods for the statistics of surprise and coincidence.</title>
<date>1993</date>
<journal>Computational Linguistics,</journal>
<volume>19</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<pages>61--74</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="18726" citStr="Dunning 1993" startWordPosition="2841" endWordPosition="2842">antic associations instantiated by its most significant collocates within each of the 4Figures are given in terms of token per million. 53 samples making up the CoVaNa-Fr corpus archive. The following cross table which is based on the lexicogram (defined as list of collocates specified by association scores; see Tournier 1987) computed for occasionner displays some of the nouns in direct object position significantly collocating with this verb in terms of the log-likelihood ratio (the use of the latter as an association measure for collocation analysis having been proposed, amongst others, by Dunning 1993). Collocate CAN5 CHE CIV CMR COD DZA FRA MAR MLI SEN TUN accident - - - 67.8 - 65.4 - - 61.2 - - accroissement - - - - 68.5 - - - - - - augmentation - - - - 52.4 - - - - - - baisse - - - - 41.7 - - - 59.5 - - coût 90.3 - - - - - - - - - - dégât - 87.6 - 91.8 268.5 1059.3 62.3 255.7 157.6 208.5 143.9 perte 298.8 109.4 267.8 178.0 208.8 381.4 64.9 134.1 492.9 170.5 129.7 problème 62.37 - - - - 23.1 - - - - 33.1 Tab. 4: Significant direct object noun collocates of occasionner across all the samples contained by the CoVaNa-FR. It is easy to see that the combinatorial profile of occasionner is esse</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Dunning, 1993</marker>
<rawString>Ted Dunning. 1993. Accurate methods for the statistics of surprise and coincidence. Computational Linguistics, 19(1): 61–74.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Martin-Dietrich Glessgen</author>
</authors>
<title>Linguistique romane, domaine et méthode – Domaines et méthodes en linguistique française et romane.</title>
<date>2007</date>
<location>Paris: Armand Colin.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="4936" citStr="Glessgen (2007" startWordPosition="715" endWordPosition="716">he International Corpus of English (ICE, cf. Greenbaum 1996), the Corpus of Contemporary American English (COCA, cf. Davies 2009), the Corpus de Referencia del Español Actual (CREA, cf. Real Academia Española), the Corpus del Español (cf. Davies 2002) or the Corpus do Português (cf. Davies 2014).1 The initial version of the CoVaNa-FR, accessible on the Varitext platform, is made up of journalistic texts published by national newspapers in different Francophone countries in Africa, Europe and North America. The choice of national newspapers as primary sources is based on the assumption made by Glessgen (2007:97) that these are particularly representative of contemporary standard varieties (“les grands journaux [...] reflètent assez bien les variétés standard actuelles”). Work is also underway on the extension of the CoVaNa-FR, such that future versions will include a subcorpus of fiction and academic texts. In its present state, the CoVaNaFR is divided into 11 samples collected across a span of at least two years and categorized by regional parameters as listed in Table 1. Sample code Country Sources Number of word tokens2 DZA Algeria El Watan, La Tribune d’Alger 45,600,000 CAM Cameroon Cameroon </context>
<context position="16353" citStr="Glessgen 2007" startWordPosition="2447" endWordPosition="2448">n a confirmation of Thibault’s findings. In light of the aforementioned key word analysis, though, there is sufficient evidence to conclude that, in Quebec French, the relationship between the two variants is rather more complex and should be subjected to a more detailed analysis in terms of collocational distribution. One promising approach in this respect would be Hoey’s (2005) lexical priming theory. 3.2.2 Quebec Specific Lexical Items At this point, it is worth noting that, although major national newspapers might reflect trends of standard varieties quite faithfully (see our reference to Glessgen 2007 in section 2), the data obtained from these sources should be handled with some caution (cf. also Thibault 2007:474). This is of particular importance if we adopt a corpus-driven approach, which involves identifying the most characteristic features in a sample by means of statistical techniques such as key word analysis. This may be illustrated with the results of a key word analysis contrasting the Quebec subcorpus as a whole with the sample representing France. Lemma Frequency Frequency Rel. Freq.4 Rel. Freq. LL score Rank CAN FRA CAN FRA Québec 93269 828 ....... 15.53 ... 1 Montréal 44257 </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Glessgen, 2007</marker>
<rawString>Martin-Dietrich Glessgen. 2007. Linguistique romane, domaine et méthode – Domaines et méthodes en linguistique française et romane. Paris: Armand Colin.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Sidney Greenbaum</author>
</authors>
<date>1996</date>
<booktitle>Comparing English Worldwide: The International Corpus of English.</booktitle>
<publisher>Clarendon Press.</publisher>
<location>Oxford:</location>
<contexts>
<context position="4382" citStr="Greenbaum 1996" startWordPosition="628" endWordPosition="629">rkshop on Applying NLP Tools to Similar Languages, Varieties and Dialects, pages 48–57, Dublin, Ireland, August 23 2014. Trieschnigg et al. 2012, Zampieri and Gebre 2012, Tan et al. 2014). It should be noted, though, that in accordance with copyright restrictions, the CoVaNa-FR is not directly available for download and can only be consulted via the GUI of the password-protected Varitext platform. Due to its focus on endonormative differentiation, the CoVaNa-FR is less balanced with respect to genre than similar corpora for other languages such as the International Corpus of English (ICE, cf. Greenbaum 1996), the Corpus of Contemporary American English (COCA, cf. Davies 2009), the Corpus de Referencia del Español Actual (CREA, cf. Real Academia Española), the Corpus del Español (cf. Davies 2002) or the Corpus do Português (cf. Davies 2014).1 The initial version of the CoVaNa-FR, accessible on the Varitext platform, is made up of journalistic texts published by national newspapers in different Francophone countries in Africa, Europe and North America. The choice of national newspapers as primary sources is based on the assumption made by Glessgen (2007:97) that these are particularly representativ</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Greenbaum, 1996</marker>
<rawString>Sidney Greenbaum (ed.). 1996. Comparing English Worldwide: The International Corpus of English. Oxford: Clarendon Press.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Michael Hoey</author>
</authors>
<title>Lexical Priming: A New Theory of Words and Language.</title>
<date>2005</date>
<location>London: Routledge.</location>
<marker>Hoey, 2005</marker>
<rawString>Michael Hoey. 2005. Lexical Priming: A New Theory of Words and Language. London: Routledge.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>François Husson</author>
<author>Julie Josse</author>
<author>Sebastien Lê</author>
<author>Jeremy Mazet</author>
</authors>
<title>FactoMineR: Multivariate Exploratory Data Analysis and Data Mining with R. http://CRAN.R-project.org/package=FactoMineR. Suzanne Lafage.</title>
<date>2013</date>
<booktitle>Le lexique français de Côté-d’Ivoire (Appropriation et créativité). Nice: CNRS. Ludovic Lebart, André Salem</booktitle>
<publisher>Springer.</publisher>
<location>Dordrecht:</location>
<marker>Husson, Josse, Lê, Mazet, 2013</marker>
<rawString>François Husson, Julie Josse, Sebastien Lê and Jeremy Mazet. 2013. FactoMineR: Multivariate Exploratory Data Analysis and Data Mining with R. http://CRAN.R-project.org/package=FactoMineR. Suzanne Lafage. 2002. Le lexique français de Côté-d’Ivoire (Appropriation et créativité). Nice: CNRS. Ludovic Lebart, André Salem and Lisette Berry. 1998. Exploring Textual Data. Dordrecht: Springer.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Nikola Ljubeši´c</author>
</authors>
<title>Nives Mikeli´c and Damir Boras.</title>
<date>2007</date>
<booktitle>Proceedings of the 29th International Conference on Information Technology Interfaces,</booktitle>
<location>Zagreb, Croatia.</location>
<marker>Ljubeši´c, 2007</marker>
<rawString>Nikola Ljubeši´c, Nives Mikeli´c and Damir Boras. 2007. Language Identification: How to Distinguish Similar Languages? Proceedings of the 29th International Conference on Information Technology Interfaces, Zagreb, Croatia.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Habiba Naffati</author>
<author>Ambroise Queffélec</author>
</authors>
<title>Le français en Tunisie.</title>
<date>2004</date>
<publisher>CNRS.</publisher>
<location>Nice:</location>
<contexts>
<context position="2133" citStr="Naffati and Queffélec 2004" startWordPosition="298" endWordPosition="301">archers working on the French language from a pluricentric perspective. It is thus primarily designed to provide methodological support for investigations in the French tradition of ‘lexicologie différentielle’ (‘variationist differential lexicography’) focusing on elements of endonormative differentiation, i.e. the emergence of regionally specific norms compared to a supposed metropolitan standard variety of French (for studies on various francophone regions, see Rézeau 2007, Thibault 2008; for studies especially focusing on Subsaharan Africa and the Maghreb, cf. Queffélec 1997, Lafage 2002, Naffati and Queffélec 2004, Nzesse 2009, to mention just a few examples of a sizable body of literature). Alongside the lexico-statistical toolbox implemented by the Varitext platform (cf. Section 3 below), the design of the CoVaNa-FR goes beyond the rather conventional lexicographic rationale of the lexicological framework just mentioned and can be seen as a contribution to meeting the desideratum, voiced by Stein (2003:14f), of carrying out large-scale investigations on Francophone varieties using contemporary corpus linguistic methods. In this regard, the CoVaNa-FR differs from existing French corpora such as Frante</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Naffati, Queffélec, 2004</marker>
<rawString>Habiba Naffati and Ambroise Queffélec. 2004. Le français en Tunisie. Nice: CNRS.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Joakim Nivre</author>
<author>Johan Hall</author>
<author>Sandra Kübler</author>
<author>Ryan Mcdonald</author>
<author>Jens Nilsson</author>
<author>Sebastian Riedel</author>
<author>Deniz Yuret</author>
</authors>
<date>2007</date>
<booktitle>The CoNLL 2007 Shared Task on Dependency Parsing. Proceedings of the CoNLL Shared Task Session of EMNLP-CoNLL 2007,</booktitle>
<pages>915--932</pages>
<location>Prague, Czech Republic,</location>
<contexts>
<context position="9118" citStr="Nivre et al. 2007" startWordPosition="1328" endWordPosition="1331">#REQUIRED code CDATA #REQUIRED source CDATA #REQUIRED year CDATA #REQUIRED &gt; &lt;!ATTLIST text id CDATA #REQUIRED title CDATA #REQUIRED author CDATA #REQUIRED date CDATA #REQUIRED section CDATA #REQUIRED &gt; &lt;!ATTLIST p id CDATA #REQUIRED type CDATA #IMPLIED &gt; &lt;!ATTLIST s id CDATA #REQUIRED&gt; ]&gt; Fig. 1: DTD specifying the structural elements of the country-related samples in the CoVaNa-FR corpus archive. As for the token rows, their core structure is basically defined according to the so-called CoNLL format, introduced on the occasion of the correspondent 2007 shared task on dependency parsing (cf. Nivre et al. 2007:916). For rather technical reasons, this structure has been extended by a number of fields whose purpose is to optimize the processing of queries exploring the dependency relations annotated in the corpus. The fields in question are marked by an asterisk in the following table, which outlines the overall structure of the token records: Field name Description id sentence internal numerical token identifier (counter starting at 1 for each sentence) word surface form or punctuation sign lemma lemma corresponding to the surface form cpos coarse grained part of speech (PoS) pos fine grained PoS + </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Nivre, Hall, Kübler, Mcdonald, Nilsson, Riedel, Yuret, 2007</marker>
<rawString>Joakim Nivre, Johan Hall, Sandra Kübler, Ryan Mcdonald, Jens Nilsson, Sebastian Riedel, Deniz Yuret. 2007. The CoNLL 2007 Shared Task on Dependency Parsing. Proceedings of the CoNLL Shared Task Session of EMNLP-CoNLL 2007, Prague, Czech Republic, 915–932.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Ladislas Nzesse</author>
</authors>
<title>Le français au Cameroun: d’une crise sociopolitique à la vitalité de la langue française (1990-2008).</title>
<date>2009</date>
<publisher>CNRS.</publisher>
<location>Nice:</location>
<contexts>
<context position="2146" citStr="Nzesse 2009" startWordPosition="302" endWordPosition="303">h language from a pluricentric perspective. It is thus primarily designed to provide methodological support for investigations in the French tradition of ‘lexicologie différentielle’ (‘variationist differential lexicography’) focusing on elements of endonormative differentiation, i.e. the emergence of regionally specific norms compared to a supposed metropolitan standard variety of French (for studies on various francophone regions, see Rézeau 2007, Thibault 2008; for studies especially focusing on Subsaharan Africa and the Maghreb, cf. Queffélec 1997, Lafage 2002, Naffati and Queffélec 2004, Nzesse 2009, to mention just a few examples of a sizable body of literature). Alongside the lexico-statistical toolbox implemented by the Varitext platform (cf. Section 3 below), the design of the CoVaNa-FR goes beyond the rather conventional lexicographic rationale of the lexicological framework just mentioned and can be seen as a contribution to meeting the desideratum, voiced by Stein (2003:14f), of carrying out large-scale investigations on Francophone varieties using contemporary corpus linguistic methods. In this regard, the CoVaNa-FR differs from existing French corpora such as Frantext (cf. ATILF</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Nzesse, 2009</marker>
<rawString>Ladislas Nzesse. 2009. Le français au Cameroun: d’une crise sociopolitique à la vitalité de la langue française (1990-2008). Nice: CNRS.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Claude Poirier</author>
</authors>
<title>Les variantes topolectales du lexique français: propositions de classement à partir d’exemples québécois.</title>
<date>1995</date>
<booktitle>Michel Francard and Danièle Latin (eds.): Le régionalisme lexical. Louvain-la-Neuve: De Boeck,</booktitle>
<pages>13--56</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="17678" citStr="Poirier 1995" startWordPosition="2688" endWordPosition="2689">2 ... 243 . .. .. .. 1740.4 0 120592.82 . magasiner 183 1 825.83 0 56578.51 1987 . .. .. .. 813.8 47579.89 . placoter 18 0 .. . 10744 . .. .. .. 22.22 1597.32 . paqueter 13 0 .. . 13473 . .. .. .. 3.41 241.78 . .. . 0.34 24.87 .. . 0.24 17.96 .. . Tab. 3: Words specific to the Quebec sub-corpus in contrast with the sample representing France. The data given in Table 3 show that the most specific items are proper nouns closely related to sociocultural context, whereas words which clearly qualify as Quebecisms, such as chum (“friend, pal”), magasiner (“to go shopping”), placoter (“to chat”; cf. Poirier 1995:32) or paqueter (“to pack”; cf. Poirier ibid) only come at lower ranks, their log-likelihood scores being nonetheless highly significant. 3.3 Usage Scenario: Lexical Cooccurrences and Collocational Variation The second main application provided by the platform’s toolbox is collocation analysis. We will illustrate this functionality by considering the example of the causative support verb occasionner (“to occasion sth”) and the semantic associations instantiated by its most significant collocates within each of the 4Figures are given in terms of token per million. 53 samples making up the CoVa</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Poirier, 1995</marker>
<rawString>Claude Poirier. 1995. Les variantes topolectales du lexique français: propositions de classement à partir d’exemples québécois. Michel Francard and Danièle Latin (eds.): Le régionalisme lexical. Louvain-la-Neuve: De Boeck, 13–56.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Ambroise Queffélec</author>
</authors>
<title>Le français en Centrafrique: lexique et société. Vanves: Editions Classiques d’Expression Française (EDICEF).</title>
<date>1997</date>
<contexts>
<context position="2092" citStr="Queffélec 1997" startWordPosition="294" endWordPosition="295"> large-scale resource to researchers working on the French language from a pluricentric perspective. It is thus primarily designed to provide methodological support for investigations in the French tradition of ‘lexicologie différentielle’ (‘variationist differential lexicography’) focusing on elements of endonormative differentiation, i.e. the emergence of regionally specific norms compared to a supposed metropolitan standard variety of French (for studies on various francophone regions, see Rézeau 2007, Thibault 2008; for studies especially focusing on Subsaharan Africa and the Maghreb, cf. Queffélec 1997, Lafage 2002, Naffati and Queffélec 2004, Nzesse 2009, to mention just a few examples of a sizable body of literature). Alongside the lexico-statistical toolbox implemented by the Varitext platform (cf. Section 3 below), the design of the CoVaNa-FR goes beyond the rather conventional lexicographic rationale of the lexicological framework just mentioned and can be seen as a contribution to meeting the desideratum, voiced by Stein (2003:14f), of carrying out large-scale investigations on Francophone varieties using contemporary corpus linguistic methods. In this regard, the CoVaNa-FR differs fr</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Queffélec, 1997</marker>
<rawString>Ambroise Queffélec. 1997. Le français en Centrafrique: lexique et société. Vanves: Editions Classiques d’Expression Française (EDICEF).</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Bali Ranaivo-Malancon</author>
</authors>
<title>Automatic identification of close languages - case study: Malay and Indonesian.</title>
<date>2006</date>
<journal>ECTI Transactions on Computer and Information Technology</journal>
<volume>2</volume>
<pages>126--134</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="3470" citStr="Ranaivo-Malancon 2006" startWordPosition="495" endWordPosition="496">es francophones Neuchâtel) in offering broad regional coverage (bundling samples from Africa, Europe and North America), a wider range of query functionalities and free access (large parts of Frantext not being accessible free of charge and Suistext only being available locally at its hosting institution, cf. Thibault 2007:480). Apart from corpus linguistic uses, the CoVaNa-FR could also be a valuable resource for research on the automatic classification of language varieties, which has recently aroused considerable interest in the field of NLP (for relevant contributions see, amongst others, Ranaivo-Malancon 2006, Ljubeši´c et al. 2007, Tiedemann and Ljubeši´c 2012, This work is licenced under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License. Page numbers and proceedings footer are added by the organizers. License details: http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/ 48 Proceedings of the First Workshop on Applying NLP Tools to Similar Languages, Varieties and Dialects, pages 48–57, Dublin, Ireland, August 23 2014. Trieschnigg et al. 2012, Zampieri and Gebre 2012, Tan et al. 2014). It should be noted, though, that in accordance with copyright restrictions, the CoVaNa-FR is not directly availabl</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Ranaivo-Malancon, 2006</marker>
<rawString>Bali Ranaivo-Malancon. 2006. Automatic identification of close languages - case study: Malay and Indonesian. ECTI Transactions on Computer and Information Technology (2): 126–134.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Paul Rayson</author>
</authors>
<title>Matrix: A statistical method and software tool for linguistic analysis through corpus comparison.</title>
<date>2003</date>
<tech>Ph.D. thesis,</tech>
<institution>Lancaster University.</institution>
<contexts>
<context position="14733" citStr="Rayson 2003" startWordPosition="2194" endWordPosition="2195"> in terms of their frequency distribution. An example also mentioned by Thibault (2007:468-475) is provided by the nouns chaussure and soulier (“shoe”), with soulier being regarded as regional variant especially of Canadian French (cf. the reference dictionary Le Petit Robert (Rey-Debove and Rey 2006) s.v. SOULIER). A key word analysis based on the samples representing Canada/Quebec (geographical code: CAN), France (FRA) and Switzerland (CHE) yields the log-likelihood ratio (LL) scores given by the following bar plots in Fig. 4 (for the use of the log likelihood ratio in key word analysis see Rayson 2003). The computation has been carried out on a 2x2 basis, with one sample as the main corpus and the combination of the remaining two as the reference corpus. Fig. 4: LL scores for the nouns chaussure and soulier in the samples representing Canada/Quebec, Switzerland and France 52 These figures indicate that there are clear-cut distributional divergences, with the two nouns being respectively under- and overrepresented in the samples related to Quebec and France. This seems to suggest that soulier is still part of the French standard as it evolves in Quebec, or at least in its national newspapers</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Rayson, 2003</marker>
<rawString>Paul Rayson. 2003. Matrix: A statistical method and software tool for linguistic analysis through corpus comparison. Ph.D. thesis, Lancaster University. [pdf version available for download at http://ucrel.lancs. ac.uk/people/paul/publications/phd2003.pdf]</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>R Core Team</author>
</authors>
<title>R: A language and environment for statistical computing. R Foundation for Statistical Computing,</title>
<date>2014</date>
<location>Vienna,</location>
<note>http://www.rae.es.</note>
<contexts>
<context position="11889" citStr="Team 2014" startWordPosition="1761" endWordPosition="1762">ing to the same rationale of large-scale variationist research in a pluricentric perspective. Work has already been completed on the prototype of a hispanophone corpus archive, which will be released via Varitext in the near future. There are also plans to compile similar resources for Portuguese, Russian and Arabic. The toolbox implemented by the Varitext platform is built upon three major software components: CWB for query processing, the UCS toolkit version 0.6 (cf. Evert 2005, the software being available at http://www.collocations.de/software.html) for cooccurrence analysis and R (R Core Team 2014) for statistical computing and plotting. The platform’s user interface allows fairly complex queries in terms of subsampling and the formulation of search expressions. Using the menu options relating to the available metadata categories (such as country code, newspaper volume or thematic section), it is possible to create subcorpora and partitions with different degrees of granularity, as is shown by Fig. 2: Fig. 2: Using menu options to build a partition defined by country on the basis of a subcorpus comprising the samples representing Cameroon and the Ivory Coast and filtered by the thematic</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Team, 2014</marker>
<rawString>R Core Team. 2014. R: A language and environment for statistical computing. R Foundation for Statistical Computing, Vienna, Austria. [http://www.R-project.org/] Real Academia Española. Corpus de referencia del español actual. http://www.rae.es.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<title>Le Nouveau Petit Robert: Dictionnaire alphabétique et analogique de la langue française. Paris: Dictionnaires Le Robert.</title>
<date>2006</date>
<editor>Josette Rey-Debove and Alain Rey (eds.).</editor>
<marker>2006</marker>
<rawString>Josette Rey-Debove and Alain Rey (eds.). 2006. Le Nouveau Petit Robert: Dictionnaire alphabétique et analogique de la langue française. Paris: Dictionnaires Le Robert.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Pierre Rézeau</author>
</authors>
<title>Richesse du français et géographie linguistique, volume 1. Louvain-la-Neuve: de Boeck.</title>
<date>2007</date>
<contexts>
<context position="1987" citStr="Rézeau 2007" startWordPosition="279" endWordPosition="280">on of the Corpus des variétés nationales du français (CoVaNa-FR) is motivated by the aim of offering a large-scale resource to researchers working on the French language from a pluricentric perspective. It is thus primarily designed to provide methodological support for investigations in the French tradition of ‘lexicologie différentielle’ (‘variationist differential lexicography’) focusing on elements of endonormative differentiation, i.e. the emergence of regionally specific norms compared to a supposed metropolitan standard variety of French (for studies on various francophone regions, see Rézeau 2007, Thibault 2008; for studies especially focusing on Subsaharan Africa and the Maghreb, cf. Queffélec 1997, Lafage 2002, Naffati and Queffélec 2004, Nzesse 2009, to mention just a few examples of a sizable body of literature). Alongside the lexico-statistical toolbox implemented by the Varitext platform (cf. Section 3 below), the design of the CoVaNa-FR goes beyond the rather conventional lexicographic rationale of the lexicological framework just mentioned and can be seen as a contribution to meeting the desideratum, voiced by Stein (2003:14f), of carrying out large-scale investigations on Fra</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Rézeau, 2007</marker>
<rawString>Pierre Rézeau (ed.). 2007. Richesse du français et géographie linguistique, volume 1. Louvain-la-Neuve: de Boeck.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Achim Stein</author>
</authors>
<title>Lexikalische Kookkurrenz im afrikanischen Französisch. Zeitschrift für französische Sprachund Literaturwissenschaft,</title>
<date>2003</date>
<volume>113</volume>
<pages>1--17</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="2531" citStr="Stein (2003" startWordPosition="361" endWordPosition="362">French (for studies on various francophone regions, see Rézeau 2007, Thibault 2008; for studies especially focusing on Subsaharan Africa and the Maghreb, cf. Queffélec 1997, Lafage 2002, Naffati and Queffélec 2004, Nzesse 2009, to mention just a few examples of a sizable body of literature). Alongside the lexico-statistical toolbox implemented by the Varitext platform (cf. Section 3 below), the design of the CoVaNa-FR goes beyond the rather conventional lexicographic rationale of the lexicological framework just mentioned and can be seen as a contribution to meeting the desideratum, voiced by Stein (2003:14f), of carrying out large-scale investigations on Francophone varieties using contemporary corpus linguistic methods. In this regard, the CoVaNa-FR differs from existing French corpora such as Frantext (cf. ATILF-CNRS), Québétext (cf. Trésor de la langue française au Québec) and Suistext (cf. Trésor des Vocabulaires francophones Neuchâtel) in offering broad regional coverage (bundling samples from Africa, Europe and North America), a wider range of query functionalities and free access (large parts of Frantext not being accessible free of charge and Suistext only being available locally at </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Stein, 2003</marker>
<rawString>Achim Stein. 2003. Lexikalische Kookkurrenz im afrikanischen Französisch. Zeitschrift für französische Sprachund Literaturwissenschaft, 113: 1–17.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Michael Stubbs</author>
</authors>
<title>Collocations and semantic profiles: On the cause of the trouble with quantitative studies.</title>
<date>1995</date>
<journal>Functions of Language,</journal>
<volume>2</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<pages>23--55</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="19477" citStr="Stubbs 1995" startWordPosition="2999" endWordPosition="3000">entation - - - - 52.4 - - - - - - baisse - - - - 41.7 - - - 59.5 - - coût 90.3 - - - - - - - - - - dégât - 87.6 - 91.8 268.5 1059.3 62.3 255.7 157.6 208.5 143.9 perte 298.8 109.4 267.8 178.0 208.8 381.4 64.9 134.1 492.9 170.5 129.7 problème 62.37 - - - - 23.1 - - - - 33.1 Tab. 4: Significant direct object noun collocates of occasionner across all the samples contained by the CoVaNa-FR. It is easy to see that the combinatorial profile of occasionner is essentially characterized by negative semantic prosody throughout all the samples under investigation (for the concept of semantic prosody, see Stubbs 1995 and Xiao and McEnery 2006). At the same time, however, it exhibits some degree of regional variation; in the case of the sub-corpus representing the Congo (COD), for example, there is an additional semantic feature in evidence which may be described as INTENSITY (cf. the collocates accroissement [“increase, growth”], augmentation [“increase, rise”] and baisse [“decrease, fall”]). A similar statement can be made with regard to the significant noun collocates of causer (“to cause”), although in this case it is the Quebec sample which adds more neutral marked elements (surprise [“surprise”]) to </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Stubbs, 1995</marker>
<rawString>Michael Stubbs. 1995. Collocations and semantic profiles: On the cause of the trouble with quantitative studies. Functions of Language, 2(1): 23–55.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Liling Tan</author>
<author>Marcos Zampieri</author>
<author>Nikola Ljubesi´c</author>
<author>Jörg Tiedemann</author>
</authors>
<title>Merging Comparable Data Sources for the Discrimination of Similar Languages: The DSL Corpus Collection.</title>
<date>2014</date>
<booktitle>Proceedings of the 7th Workshop on Building and Using Comparable Corpora: Building Resources for Machine Translation Research,</booktitle>
<location>Reykjavik, Iceland.</location>
<marker>Tan, Zampieri, Ljubesi´c, Tiedemann, 2014</marker>
<rawString>Liling Tan, Marcos Zampieri, Nikola Ljube&amp;quot;si´c and Jörg Tiedemann. 2014. Merging Comparable Data Sources for the Discrimination of Similar Languages: The DSL Corpus Collection. Proceedings of the 7th Workshop on Building and Using Comparable Corpora: Building Resources for Machine Translation Research, Reykjavik, Iceland.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Pasi Tapanainen</author>
<author>Timo Järvinen</author>
</authors>
<title>A non-projective dependency parser.</title>
<date>1997</date>
<booktitle>Proceedings of the 5th Conference on Applied Natural Language Processing,</booktitle>
<pages>64--74</pages>
<location>Washington, DC,</location>
<contexts>
<context position="7133" citStr="Tapanainen and Järvinen 1997" startWordPosition="1045" endWordPosition="1048"> the case with the corpora representing Algeria and Canada (containing two newspapers from single and different years) or the sample representing the Democratic Republic of Congo (containing three years of only one newspaper). 2.2 Processing format of the CoVaNa-FR All documents in the CoVaNa-FR corpus are formatted in eXtensible Markup Language (XML) with the structural units (i) subcorpus, (ii) text, (iii) paragraph, and (iv) sentence. The texts are annotated with (i) part-of-speech (PoS) tags, (ii) lemmas and (iii) dependency-parses using the commercially licensed Connexor annotation tool (Tapanainen and Järvinen 1997). The corpus files are in standard CWB input format (cf. Evert and Hardie 2011:5f) with XML tags and each token record (one surface form + associated TAB-delimited token-level annotations) appearing on separate lines. The set of XML tagged structural units is specified by the DTD given in Figure 1. Note that the top level &lt;corpus&gt;...&lt;/corpus&gt; element defines one country related sample and that each subcorpus corresponds to a one year newspaper volume. The element attributes which are provided inside the query 1See the projects’ web sites at http://ice-corpora.net/ICE/INDEX.HTM, http://corpus.b</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Tapanainen, Järvinen, 1997</marker>
<rawString>Pasi Tapanainen and Timo Järvinen. 1997. A non-projective dependency parser. Proceedings of the 5th Conference on Applied Natural Language Processing, Washington, DC, 64–74.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Andr6 Thibault</author>
</authors>
<title>Banques de donn6es textuelles, r6gionalismes de fr6quence et r6gionalismes n6gatifs.</title>
<date>2007</date>
<journal>ACILPR XXIV,</journal>
<volume>1</volume>
<pages>467--480</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="3173" citStr="Thibault 2007" startWordPosition="453" endWordPosition="454">scale investigations on Francophone varieties using contemporary corpus linguistic methods. In this regard, the CoVaNa-FR differs from existing French corpora such as Frantext (cf. ATILF-CNRS), Québétext (cf. Trésor de la langue française au Québec) and Suistext (cf. Trésor des Vocabulaires francophones Neuchâtel) in offering broad regional coverage (bundling samples from Africa, Europe and North America), a wider range of query functionalities and free access (large parts of Frantext not being accessible free of charge and Suistext only being available locally at its hosting institution, cf. Thibault 2007:480). Apart from corpus linguistic uses, the CoVaNa-FR could also be a valuable resource for research on the automatic classification of language varieties, which has recently aroused considerable interest in the field of NLP (for relevant contributions see, amongst others, Ranaivo-Malancon 2006, Ljubeši´c et al. 2007, Tiedemann and Ljubeši´c 2012, This work is licenced under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License. Page numbers and proceedings footer are added by the organizers. License details: http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/ 48 Proceedings of the First Workshop</context>
<context position="14207" citStr="Thibault (2007" startWordPosition="2113" endWordPosition="2114">quencies and Lexical Differences 3.2.1 chaussure vs. soulier One of the platform’s standard applications besides KWIC concordancing is the computation of sample specific frequencies and key word analysis. In a corpus-based perspective, these methods can be used for instance as diagnostics to test the results of ‘differential’ lexicology. Similar to Thibault’s (2007) study on some lexical specificities of Canadian (Quebec), Swiss and metropolitan standard French, it would be possible to analyze geographical lexical variants in terms of their frequency distribution. An example also mentioned by Thibault (2007:468-475) is provided by the nouns chaussure and soulier (“shoe”), with soulier being regarded as regional variant especially of Canadian French (cf. the reference dictionary Le Petit Robert (Rey-Debove and Rey 2006) s.v. SOULIER). A key word analysis based on the samples representing Canada/Quebec (geographical code: CAN), France (FRA) and Switzerland (CHE) yields the log-likelihood ratio (LL) scores given by the following bar plots in Fig. 4 (for the use of the log likelihood ratio in key word analysis see Rayson 2003). The computation has been carried out on a 2x2 basis, with one sample as </context>
<context position="16465" citStr="Thibault 2007" startWordPosition="2466" endWordPosition="2467">icient evidence to conclude that, in Quebec French, the relationship between the two variants is rather more complex and should be subjected to a more detailed analysis in terms of collocational distribution. One promising approach in this respect would be Hoey’s (2005) lexical priming theory. 3.2.2 Quebec Specific Lexical Items At this point, it is worth noting that, although major national newspapers might reflect trends of standard varieties quite faithfully (see our reference to Glessgen 2007 in section 2), the data obtained from these sources should be handled with some caution (cf. also Thibault 2007:474). This is of particular importance if we adopt a corpus-driven approach, which involves identifying the most characteristic features in a sample by means of statistical techniques such as key word analysis. This may be illustrated with the results of a key word analysis contrasting the Quebec subcorpus as a whole with the sample representing France. Lemma Frequency Frequency Rel. Freq.4 Rel. Freq. LL score Rank CAN FRA CAN FRA Québec 93269 828 ....... 15.53 ... 1 Montréal 44257 472 ....... 8.85 ... 2 Canada 43612 1808 ....... 33.9 ... 3 . .. .. .. ....... 0.08 ... . chum 1191 4 ....... 0.</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Thibault, 2007</marker>
<rawString>Andr6 Thibault. 2007. Banques de donn6es textuelles, r6gionalismes de fr6quence et r6gionalismes n6gatifs. ACILPR XXIV, volume 1, 467–480.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<title>Richesse du français et géographie linguistique, volume 2. Louvain-la-Neuve: de Boeck.</title>
<date>2008</date>
<editor>Andr6 Thibault (ed.).</editor>
<marker>2008</marker>
<rawString>Andr6 Thibault (ed.). 2008. Richesse du français et géographie linguistique, volume 2. Louvain-la-Neuve: de Boeck.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Jörg Tiedemann</author>
<author>Nikola Ljubesi´c</author>
</authors>
<title>Efficient discrimination between closely related languages.</title>
<date>2012</date>
<booktitle>Proceedings of COLING 2012,</booktitle>
<pages>2619--2634</pages>
<location>Mumbai, India,</location>
<marker>Tiedemann, Ljubesi´c, 2012</marker>
<rawString>Jörg Tiedemann and Nikola Ljube&amp;quot;si´c. 2012. Efficient discrimination between closely related languages. Proceedings of COLING 2012, Mumbai, India, 2619–2634.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<title>Tr6sor de la langue française au</title>
<booktitle>Qu6bec. Base textuelle QUÉBÉTEXT. Universit6 Laval, D6partement de Langues, linguistiqueettraduction. http://www.tlfq.ulaval.ca/quebetext/</booktitle>
<marker></marker>
<rawString>Tr6sor de la langue française au Qu6bec. Base textuelle QUÉBÉTEXT. Universit6 Laval, D6partement de Langues, linguistiqueettraduction. http://www.tlfq.ulaval.ca/quebetext/</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<booktitle>Tr6sor des Vocabulaires francophones Neuchâtel. Base textuelle SUISTEXT. Universit6 de Neuchâtel, Centre de dialectologie et d’6tude du français r6gional.</booktitle>
<marker></marker>
<rawString>Tr6sor des Vocabulaires francophones Neuchâtel. Base textuelle SUISTEXT. Universit6 de Neuchâtel, Centre de dialectologie et d’6tude du français r6gional.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Dolf Trieschnigg</author>
<author>Djoerd Hiemstra</author>
<author>Mariët Theune</author>
<author>Franciska de Jong</author>
<author>Theo Meder</author>
</authors>
<title>An exploration of language identification techniques for the Dutch Folktale Database.</title>
<date>2012</date>
<journal>Mots,</journal>
<booktitle>Proceedings of LREC 2012,</booktitle>
<volume>14</volume>
<pages>89--123</pages>
<location>Istanbul, Turkey. Maurice Tournier.</location>
<marker>Trieschnigg, Hiemstra, Theune, de Jong, Meder, 2012</marker>
<rawString>Dolf Trieschnigg, Djoerd Hiemstra, Mariët Theune, Franciska de Jong and Theo Meder. 2012. An exploration of language identification techniques for the Dutch Folktale Database. Proceedings of LREC 2012, Istanbul, Turkey. Maurice Tournier. 1987. Cooccurrences autour de travail (1971-1976). Mots, 14: 89–123.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Richard Xiao</author>
<author>Tony McEnery</author>
</authors>
<title>Collocation, semantic prosody, and near synonymy: A cross-linguistic perspective.</title>
<date>2006</date>
<journal>Applied linguistics,</journal>
<volume>27</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<pages>103--129</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="19504" citStr="Xiao and McEnery 2006" startWordPosition="3002" endWordPosition="3005"> 52.4 - - - - - - baisse - - - - 41.7 - - - 59.5 - - coût 90.3 - - - - - - - - - - dégât - 87.6 - 91.8 268.5 1059.3 62.3 255.7 157.6 208.5 143.9 perte 298.8 109.4 267.8 178.0 208.8 381.4 64.9 134.1 492.9 170.5 129.7 problème 62.37 - - - - 23.1 - - - - 33.1 Tab. 4: Significant direct object noun collocates of occasionner across all the samples contained by the CoVaNa-FR. It is easy to see that the combinatorial profile of occasionner is essentially characterized by negative semantic prosody throughout all the samples under investigation (for the concept of semantic prosody, see Stubbs 1995 and Xiao and McEnery 2006). At the same time, however, it exhibits some degree of regional variation; in the case of the sub-corpus representing the Congo (COD), for example, there is an additional semantic feature in evidence which may be described as INTENSITY (cf. the collocates accroissement [“increase, growth”], augmentation [“increase, rise”] and baisse [“decrease, fall”]). A similar statement can be made with regard to the significant noun collocates of causer (“to cause”), although in this case it is the Quebec sample which adds more neutral marked elements (surprise [“surprise”]) to the overall picture. We ill</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Xiao, McEnery, 2006</marker>
<rawString>Richard Xiao and Tony McEnery. 2006. Collocation, semantic prosody, and near synonymy: A cross-linguistic perspective. Applied linguistics, 27(1): 103–129.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Marcos Zampieri</author>
<author>Binyam Gebrekidan Gebre</author>
</authors>
<title>Automatic Identification of Language Varieties: The Case of Portuguese.</title>
<date>2012</date>
<booktitle>Proceedings of KONVENS 2012,</booktitle>
<pages>233--237</pages>
<location>Vienna, Austria,</location>
<contexts>
<context position="3936" citStr="Zampieri and Gebre 2012" startWordPosition="557" endWordPosition="560">nguage varieties, which has recently aroused considerable interest in the field of NLP (for relevant contributions see, amongst others, Ranaivo-Malancon 2006, Ljubeši´c et al. 2007, Tiedemann and Ljubeši´c 2012, This work is licenced under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License. Page numbers and proceedings footer are added by the organizers. License details: http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/ 48 Proceedings of the First Workshop on Applying NLP Tools to Similar Languages, Varieties and Dialects, pages 48–57, Dublin, Ireland, August 23 2014. Trieschnigg et al. 2012, Zampieri and Gebre 2012, Tan et al. 2014). It should be noted, though, that in accordance with copyright restrictions, the CoVaNa-FR is not directly available for download and can only be consulted via the GUI of the password-protected Varitext platform. Due to its focus on endonormative differentiation, the CoVaNa-FR is less balanced with respect to genre than similar corpora for other languages such as the International Corpus of English (ICE, cf. Greenbaum 1996), the Corpus of Contemporary American English (COCA, cf. Davies 2009), the Corpus de Referencia del Español Actual (CREA, cf. Real Academia Española), the</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Zampieri, Gebre, 2012</marker>
<rawString>Marcos Zampieri and Binyam Gebrekidan Gebre. 2012. Automatic Identification of Language Varieties: The Case of Portuguese. Proceedings of KONVENS 2012, Vienna, Austria, 233–237.</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>