<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="SectLabel" version="110505">
<variant no="0" confidence="0.008365">
<title confidence="0.976283">
Developing further speech recognition resources for Welsh
</title>
<author confidence="0.88032">
Sarah Cooper
</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.871884666666667">
Language Technologies Unit
Canolfan Bedwyr
Bangor University
</affiliation>
<email confidence="0.992507">
s.cooper@bangor.ac.uk
</email>
<author confidence="0.48583">
Dewi Bryn Jones
</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.659025">
Language Technologies Unit
Canolfan Bedwyr
Bangor University
</affiliation>
<email confidence="0.991217">
d.b.jones@bangor.ac.uk
</email>
<author confidence="0.757542">
Delyth Prys
</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.805741">
Language Technologies Unit
Canolfan Bedwyr
Bangor University
</affiliation>
<email confidence="0.992593">
d.prys@bangor.ac.uk
</email>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.993759" genericHeader="abstract">
Abstract
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999751571428572">
This paper reports on ongoing research into developing large-vocabulary continuous speech
recognition (LVCSR) for the Welsh language. We address data design issues and the method
for data collection using a purposely designed application for mobile devices. We also discuss
the application of the data including the design and collection of a small speech corpus to cov-
er the commands used to control a robotic arm in Welsh on a Raspberry Pi computer the li-
censing of the project and our hopes for the application of the project resources to other lan-
guages.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.999267" genericHeader="introduction">
1 Introduction
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.994681392857143">
This paper presents an overview of the GALLU (Gwaith Adnabod Lleferydd Uwch- IPA: [ɡaɬɨ], trans-
lation: further speech recognition work) project to develop speech recognition technology for the
Welsh language. Wales has a population of around 3 million people, of whom around 20% speak
Welsh (Office for National Statistics, 2012). Lesser-resourced languages typically lag in digital inno-
vation, including in language technologies. However since 2012, the Welsh Government has updated
and revised a strategy for supporting Welsh-language technology. Emphasis is placed on “more tools
and resources ... to facilitate the use of Welsh, including in the digital environment” (Welsh Govern-
ment, 2012: 45) and “the development of new Welsh-language software applications and digital ser-
vices” (Welsh Government, 2013; 12). With funding from the Welsh Government and S4C (the Welsh
language television channel), the GALLU project aims to develop speech recognition technology for
the Welsh language. The resources will be available under a permissive open-source licence, and will
therefore be available for use in a broad spectrum of platforms and devices, including voice control for
smart televisions.
2 Previous speech technology for Welsh
Prior to the GALLU project, the most substantial work on Welsh speech technology was developed
under the WISPR (Welsh and Irish Speech Processing Resources) project (Prys et al., 2004). Previous
work on a diphone-based synthesiser (Williams, 1994; 1995) and also a small speech database for
Welsh (Williams, 1999) was built upon by the WISPR project. An improved synthetic Welsh voice
was developed as part of the WISPR project as well as an MSAPI interface to Festival for use in Mi-
crosoft Windows environments (Bangor University Text to Speech, [no date]). Following the release
of the WISPR resources under an open-source (BSD) licence, further work was facilitated to develop
commercial Welsh voices by the Language Technologies Unit at Bangor University, by the Finnish
company Bitlips (Bitlips Text to Speech, [no date]) and the Polish company Ivona (Ivona Text to
Speech, [no date]). A “Basic Welsh speech recognition&amp;quot; (Bangor University, [no date]) project at the
Language Technologies Unit at Bangor University in 2008-9 resulted in laboratory prototypes for a) a
“command and control” application for a PC where applications could be launched by voice control
and b) a simple voice-driven calculator. The GALLU project will build on this to develop further
Welsh speech recognition resources.
</bodyText>
<footnote confidence="0.563571">
This work is licenced under the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International Public License. Page numbers and proceed-
ings footer are added by the organisers. Licence details: http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/
</footnote>
<page confidence="0.992281">
55
</page>
<note confidence="0.8651185">
Proceedings of the First Celtic Language Technology Workshop, pages 55–59,
Dublin, Ireland, August 23 2014.
</note>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.91687" genericHeader="method">
3 Data design
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.966697181818182">
The Welsh language has up to 29 consonants and a large number of vowels: up to 13 monophthongs
and 13 diphthongs dependent on the variety (Awbery, 1984; Ball, 1984; Jones, 1984; Ball and Wil-
liams, 2001; Mayr and Davies, 2011; amongst others). In order to collect the appropriate data to train
an acoustic model within HTK ([no date]), a set of phonetically rich words has been designed for con-
tributors to read aloud. In designing the prompt set it was important to ensure that a small number of
prompts contain representations of all of the phonemes in the language. The WISPR project’s letter-to-
sound rules were rewritten based on data mining from a lexicon, and a list of the most common sounds
and words was extracted from a text corpus. The final prompt set will contain approximately 200
prompts (8 words per prompt) covering all of the phonemes in the language which may be recorded by
contributors across different sessions.
{&amp;quot;identifier&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;sample1&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;text&amp;quot;: u&amp;quot;lleuad, melyn, aelodau, siarad, ffordd, ymlaen, cefnogaeth, Helen&amp;quot;},
{&amp;quot;identifier&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;sample2&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;text&amp;quot;: u&amp;quot;gwraig, oren, diwrnod, gwaith, mewn, eisteddfod, disgownt, iddo&amp;quot;},
{&amp;quot;identifier&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;sample3&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;text&amp;quot;: u&amp;quot;oherwydd, Elliw, awdurdod, blynyddoedd, gwlad, tywysog, llyw, uwch&amp;quot;},
{&amp;quot;identifier&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;sample4&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;text&amp;quot;: u&amp;quot;rhybuddio, Elen, uwchraddio, hwnnw, beic, Cymru, rhoi, aelod&amp;quot;},
{&amp;quot;identifier&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;sample5&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;text&amp;quot;: u&amp;quot;rhai, steroid, cefnogaeth, felen, cau, garej, angau, ymhlith&amp;quot;},
{&amp;quot;identifier&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;sample6&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;text&amp;quot;: u&amp;quot;gwneud, iawn, un, dweud, llais, wedi, gyda, llyn&amp;quot;},
{&amp;quot;identifier&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;sample7&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;text&amp;quot;: u&amp;quot;lliw, yng Nghymru, gwneud, rownd, ychydig, wy, yn, llaes&amp;quot;},
{&amp;quot;identifier&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;sample8&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;text&amp;quot;: u&amp;quot;hyn, newyddion, ar, roedd, pan, llun, melin, sychu&amp;quot;},
{&amp;quot;identifier&amp;quot;: &amp;quot;sample9&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;text&amp;quot;: u&amp;quot;ychydig, glin, wrth, Huw, at, nhw, bod, bydd&amp;quot;}
Example 1: Display prompts within the Paldaruo application
A large pronunciation lexicon will be developed and used for speech recognition. The next steps for
the project involve further data collection and linguistic model development.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.88838" genericHeader="method">
4 Data collection: crowdsourcing and the Paldaruo Application
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9999344">
A large number of speakers are required in order to train the acoustic model which forms the basis of
the speech recognition system. Recruiting speakers to attend a recording session at a sound booth with
recording software can prove expensive and time consuming. In attempting to tackle this issue, a
crowdsourcing approach is being used as a method for collecting data. Crowdsourcing is a low-cost
and efficient way of collecting speech data.
A mobile application “Paldaruo” (Welsh for “chattering”) has been developed for iOS and Android
devices. Such devices, with inbuilt microphones and internet connectivity, provide a convenient
mechanism for many volunteers to contribute speech corpus data. The app is optimised for ease of use
in order to maximise potential contributions.
Each volunteer creates their own profile within the app providing metadata related to sex, age, lin-
guistic characteristics and geographical background. Following this, the volunteers explicitly agree to
their contributions being collected and used. The prompts, described above, are presented one at a time
and the volunteer records each one individually. The recording is replayed and the volunteer verifies
the quality or re-records. The user can stop and resume at any time. Prompts are provided to the volun-
teer in a random order; completed prompts will be included in the corpus even if the user does not rec-
ord the full set.
The app accesses the microphone of the user’s mobile device and records 48 kHz PCM files, which
are sent to a server developed and hosted by the Language Technologies Unit at Bangor University.
Uploads are queued in the background so that network speed issues do not interrupt the recording pro-
cess.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.948521">
56
</page>
<figure confidence="0.959529">
Translation:
Paldaruo
Crowdsourcing a Welsh speech recognition corpus
Help us to develop Welsh speech recognition.
Contribute your voice through nattering into this
app.
Funders:
S4C Welsh Government
Begin &gt;
More information...
</figure>
<figureCaption confidence="0.999915">
Figure 1: Welcome screen in the Paldaruo App
</figureCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.999441857142857">
The app was evaluated in a pilot application (see 5) and proved successful in obtaining a useful speech
corpus from invited volunteers. However issues were highlighted with regards to background noise
and recording volume levels. To address this, the app now includes background noise and volume lev-
el checks.
The official media launch of the app, with the final prompt set, will take place on 7th July 2014. There
will be television coverage on S4C with high-profile individuals including the First Minister of Wales
and celebrities providing endorsements and appeals for volunteers.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.997479" genericHeader="method">
5 Data Application
</sectionHeader>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.999339">
5.1 Pilot Data Application
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9998492">
To date a small pilot speech corpus has been collected with the Paldaruo app covering the phonemes
that appear in a vocabulary to control a robotic arm. 20 speakers contributed to this corpus and record-
ed 38 prompts (approx. 200 words) each, totalling around 4000 words. Certain commands, for instance
‘up’, exhibit dialect-dependent lexical variation, and in these cases every speaker recorded both re-
gional forms.
</bodyText>
<listItem confidence="0.608847">
Command: Translation:
</listItem>
<bodyText confidence="0.984681352941176">
light on
grip open
grip close
wrist up
wrist down
elbow up
elbow down
shoulder up
shoulder down
troi i’r dde turn to the right
troi i’r chwith turn to the left
This corpus has been used to develop a pilot speaker-independent Welsh-language speech recognition
system for controlling the robotic arm. The pilot system uses HTK ([no date]) and Julius ([no date]),
and follows the design of an existing English system (AonSquared, [no date]). It controls the robotic
arm from a Raspberry Pi (a credit card-sized computer, popular in schools and coding clubs, costing
around €35; see (Raspberry Pi Foundation, [No date]). The authors hope this simple demonstration
will be recreated in schools and coding clubs for children throughout Wales, fitting in with the Welsh
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.816246777777778">
golau ymlaen
gafael agor
gafael cau
arddwrn i fyny / arddwrn lan
arddwrn i lawr
penelin i fyny / penelin lan
penelin i lawr
ysgwydd i fyny / ysgwydd lan
ysgwydd i lawr
</figure>
<page confidence="0.995037">
57
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.994053">
Government’s aim to support initiatives aimed at encouraging and supporting young people to engage
“in the digital world in a Welsh-language context” (Welsh Government, 2013: 14).
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.999697">
5.2 Licensing
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999943666666667">
GALLU will follow the successful strategy of the WISPR project in using permissive open-source li-
censing. All outputs will be made available under the MIT licence (MIT, [No date]) which allows roy-
alty-free use in both open-source and proprietary systems, including desktop computer software, web
applications, mobile apps and embedded systems such as television set firmware.
This strategy allows the widest possible use of the project’s outputs, and the maximal availability of
Welsh speech recognition technology.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.998525">
5.3 Application to other languages
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999911">
The authors hope other lesser-resourced languages can harness the project’s outputs and experience.
The source code of the Paldaruo crowdsourcing app can easily be adapted for use in other languages.
The process for developing the LVCSR system has been documented and will be published in the
form of a tutorial. All project outputs, including the source code for the app, will be available under
the MIT licence.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.997923" genericHeader="references">
References
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.99633008">
AonSquared. [No date]. Speech recognition using the Raspberry Pi [Online]. Available at:
http://aonsquared.co.uk/raspi_voice_control [Accessed: 1 May 2014].
Bangor University [No date]. Bangor University Basic Welsh Speech Recognition Project [Online]. Available at:
http://www.bangor.ac.uk/canolfanbedwyr/adllefsyl.php.en [Accessed: 1 May 2014].
Bangor University Text to Speech [No date] Festival Demo voice [Online]. Available at: http://www.e-
gymraeg.org/siarad [Accessed: 1 May 2014].
Bitlips Text to Speeeh. [No date]. Welsh Text to Speech Demo [Online]. Available at: bitlips.fi/tts/demo-cy.cgi
[Accessed: 1 May 2014].
Briony Williams. 1994. Diphone synthesis for the Welsh language. Proceedings of the 1994 International Con-
ference on Spoken Language Processing, Yokohama, Japan: 739-742.
Briony Williams. 1995. Text-to-speech synthesis for Welsh and Welsh English. Proceedings of Eurospeech
1995, Madrid, Spain, 2: 1113-1116.
Briony Williams. 1999. A Welsh speech database: preliminary results. Proceedings of Eurospeech 1999, Buda-
pest, Hungary, 5: 2283-2286.
Delyth Prys, Briony Williams, Bill Hicks, Dewi Jones, Ailbhe Ní Chasaide, Christer Gobl, Julie Carson-
Berndsen, Fred Cummins, Máire Ní Chiosáin, John McKenna, Rónán Scaife and Elaine Uí Dhonnchadha.
2004. SALTMIL Workshop at LREC 2004: First Steps in Language Documentation for Minority Languages.
Glyn E. Jones. 1984. The distinctive vowels and consonants of Welsh. In Martin J. Ball and Glyn E. Jones (eds.).
Welsh phonology: Selected readings. University of Wales Press, Cardiff, UK: 40-64.
Gwenllian M. Awbery. 1984. Phonotactic constraints in Welsh. In Martin J. Ball and Glyn E. Jones (eds.). Welsh
phonology: Selected readings. University of Wales Press, Cardiff, UK. 65-104.
HTK. [No date]. Hidden Markov Toolkit [Online]. Available at: http://htk.eng.cam.ac.uk/ [Accessed: 1 May
2014].
Ivona Text to Speech. [No date]. Text to Speech Portfolio [Online]. Available at: http://www.ivona.com/en/ [Ac-
cessed: 1 May 2014].
</reference>
<page confidence="0.983563">
58
</page>
<reference confidence="0.999727277777778">
Julius. [No date]. Open-Source Large Vocabulary CSR Engine Julius [Online]. Available at:
http://julius.sourceforge.jp/en_index.php [Accessed: 1 May 2014].
Martin J. Ball and Briony Williams. 2001. Welsh phonetics. The Edwin Mellen Press, Lampeter, UK.
Martin J. Ball. 1984. Phonetics for phonology. In Martin J. Ball and Glyn E. Jones (eds.). Welsh phonology: Se-
lected readings. University of Wales Press, Cardiff, UK.
MIT. [No date]. The MIT License [Online]. Available at: http://opensource.org/licenses/mit-license.html [Ac-
cessed: 1 May 2014].
Office for National Statistics. 2012. 2011 Census: Welsh language profile, unitary authorities in Wales. Availa-
ble at: http://www.ons.gov.uk/ons/rel/census/2011-census/key-statistics-for-unitary-authorities-in-wales/rft-
table-ks208wa.xls [Accessed: 1 May 2014].
Robert Mayr and Hannah Davies. 2011. A cross-dialectal acoustic study of the monophthongs and diphthongs of
Welsh. Journal of the International Phonetic Association, 41(1): 1-25.
Raspberry Pi Foundation. [No date]. What is a Raspberry Pi? [Online]. Available at:
http://www.raspberrypi.org/help/what-is-a-raspberry-pi/ [Accessed: 1 May 2014].
Welsh Government. 2012. A living language, a language for living. Available at:
http://wales.gov.uk/docs/dcells/publications/122902wls201217en.pdf [Accessed: 1 May 2014].
Welsh Government. 2013. Welsh language Technology and Digital Media Action Plan. Available at:
http://wales.gov.uk/docs/dcells/publications/230513-action-plan-en.pdf [Accessed: 20 June 2014].
</reference>
<page confidence="0.99926">
59
</page>
</variant>
</algorithm>
<algorithm name="ParsHed" version="110505">
<variant no="0" confidence="0.263582">
<title confidence="0.998265">Developing further speech recognition resources for Welsh</title>
<author confidence="0.989696">Sarah Cooper</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.893659333333333">Language Technologies Unit Canolfan Bedwyr Bangor University</affiliation>
<email confidence="0.988934">s.cooper@bangor.ac.uk</email>
<author confidence="0.923034">Dewi Bryn Jones</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.708217">Language Technologies Unit Canolfan Bedwyr Bangor University</affiliation>
<email confidence="0.983556">d.b.jones@bangor.ac.uk</email>
<title confidence="0.8720675">Delyth Prys Language Technologies Unit</title>
<author confidence="0.912359">Canolfan Bedwyr</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.998485">Bangor University</affiliation>
<email confidence="0.995277">d.prys@bangor.ac.uk</email>
<abstract confidence="0.983183">This paper reports on ongoing research into developing large-vocabulary continuous speech recognition (LVCSR) for the Welsh language. We address data design issues and the method for data collection using a purposely designed application for mobile devices. We also discuss the application of the data including the design and collection of a small speech corpus to cover the commands used to control a robotic arm in Welsh on a Raspberry Pi computer the licensing of the project and our hopes for the application of the project resources to other languages.</abstract>
</variant>
</algorithm>
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>AonSquared</author>
</authors>
<title>[No date]. Speech recognition using the Raspberry Pi [Online]. Available at: http://aonsquared.co.uk/raspi_voice_control [Accessed: 1</title>
<date>2014</date>
<marker>AonSquared, 2014</marker>
<rawString>AonSquared. [No date]. Speech recognition using the Raspberry Pi [Online]. Available at: http://aonsquared.co.uk/raspi_voice_control [Accessed: 1 May 2014].</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<title>Basic Welsh Speech Recognition Project [Online]. Available at: http://www.bangor.ac.uk/canolfanbedwyr/adllefsyl.php.en [Accessed: 1</title>
<date>2014</date>
<institution>Bangor University [No date]. Bangor University</institution>
<marker>2014</marker>
<rawString>Bangor University [No date]. Bangor University Basic Welsh Speech Recognition Project [Online]. Available at: http://www.bangor.ac.uk/canolfanbedwyr/adllefsyl.php.en [Accessed: 1 May 2014].</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<title>Text to Speech [No date] Festival Demo voice [Online]. Available at: http://www.egymraeg.org/siarad [Accessed: 1</title>
<date>2014</date>
<institution>Bangor University</institution>
<marker>2014</marker>
<rawString>Bangor University Text to Speech [No date] Festival Demo voice [Online]. Available at: http://www.egymraeg.org/siarad [Accessed: 1 May 2014].</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<title>Bitlips Text to Speeeh. [No date]. Welsh Text to Speech Demo [Online]. Available at: bitlips.fi/tts/demo-cy.cgi [Accessed: 1</title>
<date>2014</date>
<marker>2014</marker>
<rawString>Bitlips Text to Speeeh. [No date]. Welsh Text to Speech Demo [Online]. Available at: bitlips.fi/tts/demo-cy.cgi [Accessed: 1 May 2014].</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Briony Williams</author>
</authors>
<title>Diphone synthesis for the Welsh language.</title>
<date>1994</date>
<booktitle>Proceedings of the 1994 International Conference on Spoken Language Processing,</booktitle>
<pages>739--742</pages>
<location>Yokohama, Japan:</location>
<contexts>
<context position="2413" citStr="Williams, 1994" startWordPosition="350" endWordPosition="351">Welsh language television channel), the GALLU project aims to develop speech recognition technology for the Welsh language. The resources will be available under a permissive open-source licence, and will therefore be available for use in a broad spectrum of platforms and devices, including voice control for smart televisions. 2 Previous speech technology for Welsh Prior to the GALLU project, the most substantial work on Welsh speech technology was developed under the WISPR (Welsh and Irish Speech Processing Resources) project (Prys et al., 2004). Previous work on a diphone-based synthesiser (Williams, 1994; 1995) and also a small speech database for Welsh (Williams, 1999) was built upon by the WISPR project. An improved synthetic Welsh voice was developed as part of the WISPR project as well as an MSAPI interface to Festival for use in Microsoft Windows environments (Bangor University Text to Speech, [no date]). Following the release of the WISPR resources under an open-source (BSD) licence, further work was facilitated to develop commercial Welsh voices by the Language Technologies Unit at Bangor University, by the Finnish company Bitlips (Bitlips Text to Speech, [no date]) and the Polish comp</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Williams, 1994</marker>
<rawString>Briony Williams. 1994. Diphone synthesis for the Welsh language. Proceedings of the 1994 International Conference on Spoken Language Processing, Yokohama, Japan: 739-742.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Briony Williams</author>
</authors>
<title>Text-to-speech synthesis for Welsh and Welsh English.</title>
<date>1995</date>
<booktitle>Proceedings of Eurospeech</booktitle>
<volume>2</volume>
<pages>1113--1116</pages>
<location>Madrid,</location>
<marker>Williams, 1995</marker>
<rawString>Briony Williams. 1995. Text-to-speech synthesis for Welsh and Welsh English. Proceedings of Eurospeech 1995, Madrid, Spain, 2: 1113-1116.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Briony Williams</author>
</authors>
<title>A Welsh speech database: preliminary results.</title>
<date>1999</date>
<booktitle>Proceedings of Eurospeech</booktitle>
<volume>5</volume>
<pages>2283--2286</pages>
<location>Budapest,</location>
<contexts>
<context position="2480" citStr="Williams, 1999" startWordPosition="361" endWordPosition="362">lop speech recognition technology for the Welsh language. The resources will be available under a permissive open-source licence, and will therefore be available for use in a broad spectrum of platforms and devices, including voice control for smart televisions. 2 Previous speech technology for Welsh Prior to the GALLU project, the most substantial work on Welsh speech technology was developed under the WISPR (Welsh and Irish Speech Processing Resources) project (Prys et al., 2004). Previous work on a diphone-based synthesiser (Williams, 1994; 1995) and also a small speech database for Welsh (Williams, 1999) was built upon by the WISPR project. An improved synthetic Welsh voice was developed as part of the WISPR project as well as an MSAPI interface to Festival for use in Microsoft Windows environments (Bangor University Text to Speech, [no date]). Following the release of the WISPR resources under an open-source (BSD) licence, further work was facilitated to develop commercial Welsh voices by the Language Technologies Unit at Bangor University, by the Finnish company Bitlips (Bitlips Text to Speech, [no date]) and the Polish company Ivona (Ivona Text to Speech, [no date]). A “Basic Welsh speech </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Williams, 1999</marker>
<rawString>Briony Williams. 1999. A Welsh speech database: preliminary results. Proceedings of Eurospeech 1999, Budapest, Hungary, 5: 2283-2286.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>Delyth Prys</author>
<author>Briony Williams</author>
<author>Bill Hicks</author>
</authors>
<title>Dewi Jones, Ailbhe Ní Chasaide, Christer Gobl, Julie CarsonBerndsen, Fred Cummins, Máire Ní Chiosáin,</title>
<booktitle>Scaife and Elaine Uí Dhonnchadha. 2004. SALTMIL Workshop at LREC 2004: First Steps in Language Documentation for Minority Languages.</booktitle>
<location>John McKenna, Rónán</location>
<marker>Prys, Williams, Hicks, </marker>
<rawString>Delyth Prys, Briony Williams, Bill Hicks, Dewi Jones, Ailbhe Ní Chasaide, Christer Gobl, Julie CarsonBerndsen, Fred Cummins, Máire Ní Chiosáin, John McKenna, Rónán Scaife and Elaine Uí Dhonnchadha. 2004. SALTMIL Workshop at LREC 2004: First Steps in Language Documentation for Minority Languages.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Glyn E Jones</author>
</authors>
<title>The distinctive vowels and consonants of Welsh. In</title>
<date>1984</date>
<pages>40--64</pages>
<editor>Martin J. Ball and Glyn E. Jones (eds.). Welsh</editor>
<publisher>University of Wales Press,</publisher>
<location>Cardiff, UK:</location>
<contexts>
<context position="3992" citStr="Jones, 1984" startWordPosition="593" endWordPosition="594"> GALLU project will build on this to develop further Welsh speech recognition resources. This work is licenced under the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International Public License. Page numbers and proceedings footer are added by the organisers. Licence details: http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/ 55 Proceedings of the First Celtic Language Technology Workshop, pages 55–59, Dublin, Ireland, August 23 2014. 3 Data design The Welsh language has up to 29 consonants and a large number of vowels: up to 13 monophthongs and 13 diphthongs dependent on the variety (Awbery, 1984; Ball, 1984; Jones, 1984; Ball and Williams, 2001; Mayr and Davies, 2011; amongst others). In order to collect the appropriate data to train an acoustic model within HTK ([no date]), a set of phonetically rich words has been designed for contributors to read aloud. In designing the prompt set it was important to ensure that a small number of prompts contain representations of all of the phonemes in the language. The WISPR project’s letter-tosound rules were rewritten based on data mining from a lexicon, and a list of the most common sounds and words was extracted from a text corpus. The final prompt set will contain </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Jones, 1984</marker>
<rawString>Glyn E. Jones. 1984. The distinctive vowels and consonants of Welsh. In Martin J. Ball and Glyn E. Jones (eds.). Welsh phonology: Selected readings. University of Wales Press, Cardiff, UK: 40-64.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Gwenllian M Awbery</author>
</authors>
<title>Phonotactic constraints in Welsh. In</title>
<date>1984</date>
<pages>65--104</pages>
<editor>Martin J. Ball and Glyn E. Jones (eds.). Welsh</editor>
<publisher>University of Wales Press,</publisher>
<location>Cardiff, UK.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="3967" citStr="Awbery, 1984" startWordPosition="589" endWordPosition="590">ice-driven calculator. The GALLU project will build on this to develop further Welsh speech recognition resources. This work is licenced under the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International Public License. Page numbers and proceedings footer are added by the organisers. Licence details: http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/ 55 Proceedings of the First Celtic Language Technology Workshop, pages 55–59, Dublin, Ireland, August 23 2014. 3 Data design The Welsh language has up to 29 consonants and a large number of vowels: up to 13 monophthongs and 13 diphthongs dependent on the variety (Awbery, 1984; Ball, 1984; Jones, 1984; Ball and Williams, 2001; Mayr and Davies, 2011; amongst others). In order to collect the appropriate data to train an acoustic model within HTK ([no date]), a set of phonetically rich words has been designed for contributors to read aloud. In designing the prompt set it was important to ensure that a small number of prompts contain representations of all of the phonemes in the language. The WISPR project’s letter-tosound rules were rewritten based on data mining from a lexicon, and a list of the most common sounds and words was extracted from a text corpus. The final</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Awbery, 1984</marker>
<rawString>Gwenllian M. Awbery. 1984. Phonotactic constraints in Welsh. In Martin J. Ball and Glyn E. Jones (eds.). Welsh phonology: Selected readings. University of Wales Press, Cardiff, UK. 65-104.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<title>Hidden Markov Toolkit [Online]. Available at: http://htk.eng.cam.ac.uk/</title>
<date>2014</date>
<journal>Accessed:</journal>
<volume>1</volume>
<marker>2014</marker>
<rawString>HTK. [No date]. Hidden Markov Toolkit [Online]. Available at: http://htk.eng.cam.ac.uk/ [Accessed: 1 May 2014].</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<title>Ivona Text to Speech. [No date]. Text to Speech Portfolio [Online]. Available at: http://www.ivona.com/en/</title>
<date>2014</date>
<journal>Accessed:</journal>
<volume>1</volume>
<marker>2014</marker>
<rawString>Ivona Text to Speech. [No date]. Text to Speech Portfolio [Online]. Available at: http://www.ivona.com/en/ [Accessed: 1 May 2014].</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Julius</author>
</authors>
<title>[No date]. Open-Source Large Vocabulary CSR Engine Julius [Online]. Available at: http://julius.sourceforge.jp/en_index.php [Accessed: 1</title>
<date>2014</date>
<marker>Julius, 2014</marker>
<rawString>Julius. [No date]. Open-Source Large Vocabulary CSR Engine Julius [Online]. Available at: http://julius.sourceforge.jp/en_index.php [Accessed: 1 May 2014].</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Martin J Ball</author>
<author>Briony Williams</author>
</authors>
<title>Welsh phonetics.</title>
<date>2001</date>
<publisher>The Edwin Mellen Press, Lampeter, UK.</publisher>
<contexts>
<context position="4017" citStr="Ball and Williams, 2001" startWordPosition="595" endWordPosition="599">t will build on this to develop further Welsh speech recognition resources. This work is licenced under the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International Public License. Page numbers and proceedings footer are added by the organisers. Licence details: http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/ 55 Proceedings of the First Celtic Language Technology Workshop, pages 55–59, Dublin, Ireland, August 23 2014. 3 Data design The Welsh language has up to 29 consonants and a large number of vowels: up to 13 monophthongs and 13 diphthongs dependent on the variety (Awbery, 1984; Ball, 1984; Jones, 1984; Ball and Williams, 2001; Mayr and Davies, 2011; amongst others). In order to collect the appropriate data to train an acoustic model within HTK ([no date]), a set of phonetically rich words has been designed for contributors to read aloud. In designing the prompt set it was important to ensure that a small number of prompts contain representations of all of the phonemes in the language. The WISPR project’s letter-tosound rules were rewritten based on data mining from a lexicon, and a list of the most common sounds and words was extracted from a text corpus. The final prompt set will contain approximately 200 prompts</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Ball, Williams, 2001</marker>
<rawString>Martin J. Ball and Briony Williams. 2001. Welsh phonetics. The Edwin Mellen Press, Lampeter, UK.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Martin J Ball</author>
</authors>
<title>Phonetics for phonology. In</title>
<date>1984</date>
<editor>Martin J. Ball and Glyn E. Jones (eds.). Welsh</editor>
<publisher>University of Wales Press,</publisher>
<location>Cardiff, UK.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="3979" citStr="Ball, 1984" startWordPosition="591" endWordPosition="592">culator. The GALLU project will build on this to develop further Welsh speech recognition resources. This work is licenced under the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International Public License. Page numbers and proceedings footer are added by the organisers. Licence details: http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/ 55 Proceedings of the First Celtic Language Technology Workshop, pages 55–59, Dublin, Ireland, August 23 2014. 3 Data design The Welsh language has up to 29 consonants and a large number of vowels: up to 13 monophthongs and 13 diphthongs dependent on the variety (Awbery, 1984; Ball, 1984; Jones, 1984; Ball and Williams, 2001; Mayr and Davies, 2011; amongst others). In order to collect the appropriate data to train an acoustic model within HTK ([no date]), a set of phonetically rich words has been designed for contributors to read aloud. In designing the prompt set it was important to ensure that a small number of prompts contain representations of all of the phonemes in the language. The WISPR project’s letter-tosound rules were rewritten based on data mining from a lexicon, and a list of the most common sounds and words was extracted from a text corpus. The final prompt set </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Ball, 1984</marker>
<rawString>Martin J. Ball. 1984. Phonetics for phonology. In Martin J. Ball and Glyn E. Jones (eds.). Welsh phonology: Selected readings. University of Wales Press, Cardiff, UK.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<title>The MIT License [Online]. Available at: http://opensource.org/licenses/mit-license.html [Accessed: 1</title>
<date>2014</date>
<marker>2014</marker>
<rawString>MIT. [No date]. The MIT License [Online]. Available at: http://opensource.org/licenses/mit-license.html [Accessed: 1 May 2014].</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<title>Office for National Statistics.</title>
<date>2012</date>
<marker>2012</marker>
<rawString>Office for National Statistics. 2012. 2011 Census: Welsh language profile, unitary authorities in Wales. Available at: http://www.ons.gov.uk/ons/rel/census/2011-census/key-statistics-for-unitary-authorities-in-wales/rfttable-ks208wa.xls [Accessed: 1 May 2014].</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Robert Mayr</author>
<author>Hannah Davies</author>
</authors>
<title>A cross-dialectal acoustic study of the monophthongs and diphthongs of Welsh.</title>
<date>2011</date>
<journal>Journal of the International Phonetic Association,</journal>
<volume>41</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<pages>1--25</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="4040" citStr="Mayr and Davies, 2011" startWordPosition="600" endWordPosition="603">evelop further Welsh speech recognition resources. This work is licenced under the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International Public License. Page numbers and proceedings footer are added by the organisers. Licence details: http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/ 55 Proceedings of the First Celtic Language Technology Workshop, pages 55–59, Dublin, Ireland, August 23 2014. 3 Data design The Welsh language has up to 29 consonants and a large number of vowels: up to 13 monophthongs and 13 diphthongs dependent on the variety (Awbery, 1984; Ball, 1984; Jones, 1984; Ball and Williams, 2001; Mayr and Davies, 2011; amongst others). In order to collect the appropriate data to train an acoustic model within HTK ([no date]), a set of phonetically rich words has been designed for contributors to read aloud. In designing the prompt set it was important to ensure that a small number of prompts contain representations of all of the phonemes in the language. The WISPR project’s letter-tosound rules were rewritten based on data mining from a lexicon, and a list of the most common sounds and words was extracted from a text corpus. The final prompt set will contain approximately 200 prompts (8 words per prompt) c</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Mayr, Davies, 2011</marker>
<rawString>Robert Mayr and Hannah Davies. 2011. A cross-dialectal acoustic study of the monophthongs and diphthongs of Welsh. Journal of the International Phonetic Association, 41(1): 1-25.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Raspberry Pi</author>
</authors>
<title>Foundation. [No date]. What is a Raspberry Pi? [Online]. Available at: http://www.raspberrypi.org/help/what-is-a-raspberry-pi/</title>
<date>2014</date>
<journal>Accessed:</journal>
<volume>1</volume>
<marker>Pi, 2014</marker>
<rawString>Raspberry Pi Foundation. [No date]. What is a Raspberry Pi? [Online]. Available at: http://www.raspberrypi.org/help/what-is-a-raspberry-pi/ [Accessed: 1 May 2014].</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Welsh Government</author>
</authors>
<title>A living language, a language for living. Available at: http://wales.gov.uk/docs/dcells/publications/122902wls201217en.pdf [Accessed: 1</title>
<date>2012</date>
<contexts>
<context position="1624" citStr="Government, 2012" startWordPosition="232" endWordPosition="234">PA: [ɡaɬɨ], translation: further speech recognition work) project to develop speech recognition technology for the Welsh language. Wales has a population of around 3 million people, of whom around 20% speak Welsh (Office for National Statistics, 2012). Lesser-resourced languages typically lag in digital innovation, including in language technologies. However since 2012, the Welsh Government has updated and revised a strategy for supporting Welsh-language technology. Emphasis is placed on “more tools and resources ... to facilitate the use of Welsh, including in the digital environment” (Welsh Government, 2012: 45) and “the development of new Welsh-language software applications and digital services” (Welsh Government, 2013; 12). With funding from the Welsh Government and S4C (the Welsh language television channel), the GALLU project aims to develop speech recognition technology for the Welsh language. The resources will be available under a permissive open-source licence, and will therefore be available for use in a broad spectrum of platforms and devices, including voice control for smart televisions. 2 Previous speech technology for Welsh Prior to the GALLU project, the most substantial work on </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Government, 2012</marker>
<rawString>Welsh Government. 2012. A living language, a language for living. Available at: http://wales.gov.uk/docs/dcells/publications/122902wls201217en.pdf [Accessed: 1 May 2014].</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Welsh Government</author>
</authors>
<title>Welsh language Technology and Digital Media Action Plan. Available at: http://wales.gov.uk/docs/dcells/publications/230513-action-plan-en.pdf [Accessed:</title>
<date>2013</date>
<contexts>
<context position="1740" citStr="Government, 2013" startWordPosition="249" endWordPosition="250">elsh language. Wales has a population of around 3 million people, of whom around 20% speak Welsh (Office for National Statistics, 2012). Lesser-resourced languages typically lag in digital innovation, including in language technologies. However since 2012, the Welsh Government has updated and revised a strategy for supporting Welsh-language technology. Emphasis is placed on “more tools and resources ... to facilitate the use of Welsh, including in the digital environment” (Welsh Government, 2012: 45) and “the development of new Welsh-language software applications and digital services” (Welsh Government, 2013; 12). With funding from the Welsh Government and S4C (the Welsh language television channel), the GALLU project aims to develop speech recognition technology for the Welsh language. The resources will be available under a permissive open-source licence, and will therefore be available for use in a broad spectrum of platforms and devices, including voice control for smart televisions. 2 Previous speech technology for Welsh Prior to the GALLU project, the most substantial work on Welsh speech technology was developed under the WISPR (Welsh and Irish Speech Processing Resources) project (Prys et</context>
<context position="10086" citStr="Government, 2013" startWordPosition="1529" endWordPosition="1530">redit card-sized computer, popular in schools and coding clubs, costing around €35; see (Raspberry Pi Foundation, [No date]). The authors hope this simple demonstration will be recreated in schools and coding clubs for children throughout Wales, fitting in with the Welsh golau ymlaen gafael agor gafael cau arddwrn i fyny / arddwrn lan arddwrn i lawr penelin i fyny / penelin lan penelin i lawr ysgwydd i fyny / ysgwydd lan ysgwydd i lawr 57 Government’s aim to support initiatives aimed at encouraging and supporting young people to engage “in the digital world in a Welsh-language context” (Welsh Government, 2013: 14). 5.2 Licensing GALLU will follow the successful strategy of the WISPR project in using permissive open-source licensing. All outputs will be made available under the MIT licence (MIT, [No date]) which allows royalty-free use in both open-source and proprietary systems, including desktop computer software, web applications, mobile apps and embedded systems such as television set firmware. This strategy allows the widest possible use of the project’s outputs, and the maximal availability of Welsh speech recognition technology. 5.3 Application to other languages The authors hope other lesse</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Government, 2013</marker>
<rawString>Welsh Government. 2013. Welsh language Technology and Digital Media Action Plan. Available at: http://wales.gov.uk/docs/dcells/publications/230513-action-plan-en.pdf [Accessed: 20 June 2014].</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>