<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="SectLabel" version="110505">
<variant no="0" confidence="0.001183">
<title confidence="0.9985955">
Building English-Vietnamese Named Entity Corpus
with Aligned Bilingual News Articles
</title>
<author confidence="0.995583">
Quoc Hung Ngo
</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.946907">
University of Information Technology
Vietnam National Universiry - HCM City
</affiliation>
<address confidence="0.583625">
Ho Chi Minh City, Vietnam
</address>
<email confidence="0.99053">
hungnq@uit.edu.vn
</email>
<author confidence="0.970376">
Dinh Dien
</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.7027325">
University of Sciences
Vietnam National Universiry - HCM City
</affiliation>
<address confidence="0.459284">
Ho Chi Minh City, Vietnam
</address>
<email confidence="0.978434">
ddien@fit.hcmus.edu.vn
</email>
<author confidence="0.998585">
Werner Winiwarter
</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.9331925">
University of Vienna
Research Group Data Analytics and Computing
</affiliation>
<address confidence="0.797741">
W¨ahringer Straße 29, 1090 Wien, Austria
</address>
<email confidence="0.99053">
werner.winiwarter@univie.ac.at
</email>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.995489" genericHeader="abstract">
Abstract
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999548">
Named entity recognition aims to classify words in a document into pre-defined target entity
classes. It is now considered to be fundamental for many natural language processing tasks such
as information retrieval, machine translation, information extraction and question answering.
This paper presents a workflow to build an English-Vietnamese named entity corpus from an
aligned bilingual corpus. The workflow is based on a state of the art named entity recognition
tool to identify English named entities and map them into Vietnamese text. The paper also
presents a detailed discussion about several mapping errors and differences between English and
Vietnamese sentences that affect this task.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.998986" genericHeader="keywords">
1 Introduction
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999579">
Named entity recognition (NER) is a basic task in natural language processing and one of the most
important subtasks in Information Extraction. It is really essential to identify objects and extract relations
between them. Moreover, recognizing proper names from news articles or newswires is also useful in
detecting events and monitoring them. The NER task aims to identify and classify certain proper nouns
into some pre-defined target entity classes such as person (PER), organization (ORG), location (LOC),
temporal expressions (TIME), monetary values (MON), and percentage (PCT).
Several previous works in NER have been done on languages such as English (J. Sun et al., 2002;
C.W. Shih et al., 2004), Japanese (R. Sasano and S. Kurohashi, 2008), Chinese (J. Sun et al., 2002;
C.W. Shih et al., 2004), and Vietnamese (N.C. Tu et al., 2005; T.X. T. Pham et al., 2007; Q.T. Tran et
al., 2007); and NER systems have been developed using supervised learning methods such as Decision
Tree, Maximum Entropy model (D. Nadeau and S. Sekine, 2007), and Support Vector Machine (Q.T.
Tran et al., 2007), which achieved high performance. Moreover, there are several studies for bilingual
named entity recognition (C.J. Lee et al., 2006; D. Feng et al., 2004; F. Huang and S. Vogel, 2002).
However, for the English-Vietnamese pair, this task still presents a significant challenge in a number of
important respects (R. Sasano and S. Kurohashi, 2008). Firstly, words in Vietnamese are not always
separated by spaces, so word segmentation is necessary and segmentation errors will affect the level
of NER performance. Secondly, some proper names of foreign persons and locations are loanwords or
represented by phonetic symbols, so we can expect wide variations in some Vietnamese terms. Thirdly,
there are considerably fewer available existing resources such as lexicons, parsers, word nets, etc. for
Vietnamese that have been used in previous studies.
</bodyText>
<footnote confidence="0.504402">
This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International Licence. Page numbers and proceedings footer
are added by the organisers. Licence details: http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/
</footnote>
<page confidence="0.995822">
85
</page>
<note confidence="0.696736">
Proceedings of the 5th Workshop on South and Southeast Asian NLP, 25th International Conference on Computational Linguistics, pages 85–93,
Dublin, Ireland, August 23-29 2014.
</note>
<bodyText confidence="0.999786444444444">
In this study, we suggest a process to build a bilingual named entity corpus from aligned news express
articles. In fact, this process is applied to build an English-Vietnamese Named Entity Corpus by using
available English named entity recognition to tag entities in the English text, and then map them into
Vietnamese text based on word alignments. The mapping results are also corrected manually by using a
visualization tool.
The remainder of this paper describes the details of our work. Firstly we address the data source for
building the corpus in Section 2. Next, we present a procedure to build an English-Vietnamese Named
Entity Corpus by using a bilingual corpus and mapping English entities into Vietnamese entity tags in
Section 3. Experimental results and conclusion appear in Sections 4 and 5, respectively.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.912941" genericHeader="introduction">
2 Tagset and Data Source
</sectionHeader>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.711055">
2.1 Tagset for Named Entities
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998046">
There are many tagsets for the NER task, such as the hierarchical named entity tagset with 150 types (S.
Sekine et al., 2002), the biological named entity tagset (Y. Tateisi et al., 2000; J-D Kim et al., 2003), or
common named entity tagsets with 3 types and 7 tags (N. Chinchor and P. Robinson, 1998). According
to the definition of the MUC-7 conference (N. Chinchor and P. Robinson, 1998), we will identify six
types of named entities:
</bodyText>
<listItem confidence="0.999959636363636">
• PERSON (PER): Person entities are limited to humans identified by name, nickname or alias.
• ORGANIZATION (ORG): Organization entities are limited to corporations, institutions, govern-
ment agencies and other groups of people defined by an established organizational structure.
• LOCATION (LOC): Location entities include names of politically or geographically defined
places (cities, provinces, countries, international regions, bodies of water, mountains, etc.). Lo-
cations also include man-made structures like airports, highways, streets, factories and monuments.
• TIME (TIM): Date/Time entities are complete or partial expressions of time of day, or date expres-
sions.
• PERCENTAGE (PCT): Percentage entities are percentage expressions, including percentage range
expressions.
• MONEY (MON): Money entities include monetary expressions.
</listItem>
<bodyText confidence="0.9980105">
We have developed a guide for bilingual named entity tagging and published it as EnVnNEguide at
http://code.google.com/p/evbcorpus/downloads/list.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.999156">
2.2 Data Source
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999956583333333">
The data source for building the English-Vietnamese named entity corpus is a part of the EVBCorpus1,
which consists of both original English text and its Vietnamese translations. It contains 1,000 news
articles defined as the EVBNews part of the EVBCorpus (as shown in Table 1) (Q.H. Ngo et al., 2013).
This corpus is also aligned semi-automatically at the word level.
In particular, each article was translated one to one at the whole article level, so we align sentence to
sentence. Then, sentences are aligned semi-automatically at the word level, including automatic align-
ment by class-based method (D. Dien et al., 2002) and use of the BiCAT tool (Q.H. Ngo and W. Wini-
warter, 2012) to correct the alignments manually. The details of the corpus are listed in Table 1.
Parallel documents are also chosen and classified into categories, such as economy, entertainment
(art and music), health, science, social, politics, and technology (percentage of each category is shown
in Table 2 and Figure 1). The wide range of categories ensures that named entities in the corpus are
diversified enough for other following tasks.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.994887">
86
</page>
<figureCaption confidence="0.924776">
Figure 1: The distribution of articles and sentences in each topic in EVBNews
</figureCaption>
<tableCaption confidence="0.580103">
Table 1: Characteristics of EVBNews part
</tableCaption>
<table confidence="0.929586666666667">
English Vietnamese
Files 1,000 1,000
Paragraphs 25,015 25,015
Sentences 45,531 45,531
Words 740,534 832,441
Words in Alignments 654,060 768,031
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.960361" genericHeader="method">
3 Building Named Entity Corpus
</sectionHeader>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.999965">
3.1 Model of Building EVNECorpus from EVBCorpus
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999635266666667">
Figure 2 shows the main modules of bilingual named entity corpus building, including three main mod-
ules: pre-processing, named entity recognition, bilingual entity mapping, and bilingual entity correction.
According to this workflow, the bilingual corpus will be tagged with named entities on the English text,
then, named entities are mapped from English to Vietnamese text. Finally, annotators will correct both
English and Vietnamese named entities by using the BiCAT tool (Q.H. Ngo and W. Winiwarter, 2012).
At the first stage, a Named Entity Recognition system is used to tag English entities in the English
sentence. Several Named Entity Recognition systems for English text are available online. For traditional
NER, the most popular publicly available systems are: OpenNLP NameFinder 2 , Illinois NER3 system
by Lev Ratinov (L. Ratinov and D. Roth, 2009), Stanford NER4 system by Jenny Rose Finkel (J.R.
Finkel et al., 3005), and Lingpipe NER5 system by Baldwin, B. and B. Carpenter (B. Carpenter, 2006).
The Stanford NER reports 86.86 F1 on the CoNLL03 NER shared task data. We chose the Stanford NER
to provide for the ability of our corpus for tagging with multi-type, such as 3 classes, 4 classes, and 7
classes.
The following example is the result of the Stanford NER for the English sentence “Prime Minister
Gordon Brown resigned as Britain ’s top politician on Tuesday evening, making way for Conservative
</bodyText>
<footnote confidence="0.999977">
1http://code.google.com/p/evbcorpus/
2http://sourceforge.net/apps/mediawiki/opennlp/
3http://cogcomp.cs.illinois.edu/page/software view/4
4http://nlp.stanford.edu/ner/index.shtml
5http://alias-i.com/lingpipe/index.html
</footnote>
<page confidence="0.999022">
87
</page>
<tableCaption confidence="0.996251">
Table 2: Number of files and sentences for each topic
</tableCaption>
<table confidence="0.999089272727273">
Topic File Sentence
Economy 125 4,326
Entertainment 11 365
Health 336 21,107
Politics 141 4,253
Science 34 1,692
Social 110 3,699
Sport 22 838
Technology 104 2,609
Misc 117 117
Total 1,000 45,531
</table>
<figureCaption confidence="0.97738">
Figure 2: Architecture of building EVNECorpus from EVBCorpus
leader David Cameron.” :
</figureCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.7984202">
Prime Minister [Gordon Brown]PER resigned as [Britain]LOC ’s top politician on [Tuesday]TIM
evening, making way for [Conservative]ORG leader [David Cameron]PER .
and its mapped named entities in the Vietnamese sentence:
Thu tiring [Gordon Brown]PER đã tU giã chic vu cao nhat trên chính tridng [Anh]LOC vào toi
[thi ba]TIM , nhidng cho cho [David Cameron]PER nhà lãnh đao [Đing Bao thu]ORG .
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.999577">
3.2 Mapping English to Vietnamese Named Entities
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.96389075">
At the next stage, every alignment will be mapped from English into Vietnamese tokens. Every named
entity tag on linked English words is mapped to Vietnamese tokens on the target sentence. Left and right
boundaries are also detected to re-build named entity chunks on the Vietnamese sentence (as shown in
Figure 3):
</bodyText>
<listItem confidence="0.999813">
• Remove all alignments which are not related to English named entity tokens
• Map English named entity tokens to Vietnamese text by using alignments
</listItem>
<page confidence="0.901544">
88
</page>
<listItem confidence="0.774782">
• Identify the boundaries of named entities and rebuild named entity script text.
</listItem>
<figureCaption confidence="0.998692">
Figure 3: Mapping named entities
</figureCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.999894666666667">
However, there is a difference between the number of tagged English named entities and mapped
Vietnamese named entities (as shown in Table 3). Several English entities in the English sentences are
not translated into the Vietnamese text, therefore, these entities are not mapped.
</bodyText>
<tableCaption confidence="0.997878">
Table 3: Number of entities at the first stage
</tableCaption>
<table confidence="0.998087125">
Tag Name Tagged English Entity Mapped Vietnamese Entity Unmapped Entity
LOC Location 10,418 10,354 64
ORG Organization 8,197 8,120 77
PER Person 7,217 7,153 64
TIM Time 4,474 4,437 37
MON Money 1,003 992 11
PCT Percent 1,201 1,193 8
Total 32,510 32,249 261
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.998865">
There are several common errors of the mapping stage. The most frequent error is caused by the
separation of entities from English text in Vietnamese. It means that there are several cases of one tagged
English named entity being separated into two distinct Vietnamese named entities in the Vietnamese
text. On the other hand, for example, the phrase “President [Bill Clinton]PER between [1994]TIM and
[1997]TIM” has one PER entity and two TIM entities whereas the Vietnamese translated text “Tong
thong [Bill Clinton]PER trong giai loan [1994-1997]TIM” has one PER entity and only one TIM entity.
Three common reasons which lead to mapping errors (these cases are discussed in the next section by
analysing unmatched cases) are:
</bodyText>
<listItem confidence="0.9966055">
• The differences between English and Vietnamese characteristics.
• The splitting of an English named entity to two Vietnamese entities.
• The entities are replaced by pronouns and possessive pronouns in the target sentences or the other
way around.
</listItem>
<page confidence="0.999194">
89
</page>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.999265">
3.3 Correcting Named Entities
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999694666666667">
As shown in Figure 4, we use the BiCAT tool (Q.H. Ngo and W. Winiwarter, 2012) for correcting named
entities in both English and Vietnamese sentences. The BiCAT tool is a visualization tool based on drag,
drop, and edit label operations (actions) to correct the sentence pairs. It is designed for annotators to
review whole phrase structures of English and Vietnamese sentences. They can compare the English
named entity result with the Vietnamese named entity result and correct them in both sentences. The
comparison is also used to detect incorrect named entities in both English and Vietnamese text.
</bodyText>
<figureCaption confidence="0.998373">
Figure 4: Screenshot of BiCAT with the named entity map
</figureCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.978559">
Moreover, several additional information, such as POS tagger, chunker, is also shown for building
further linguistic tags. Several features are implemented on the entity matrix at the right panel of the
BiCAT tool:
</bodyText>
<listItem confidence="0.9999475">
• Show the sentence where named entities occur.
• Highlight the pairs which have imbalance in number of entities between source sentence and target
sentence.
• Quick jump to the sentence pair on which the user clicks.
</listItem>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.513998" genericHeader="evaluation">
4 Experiment and Results
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999748166666667">
Named entities include six tags: Location (LOC), Person (PER), Organization (ORG), Time including
date tags (TIM), Money (MON), and Percentage (PCT). English text is tagged with English NER tags by
Stanford NER and then mapped to Vietnamese text. Next, Vietnamese entity tags are corrected manually.
In total, the English-Vietnamese Named Entity Corpus (EVNECorpus) has 32,454 English named
entities and 33,338 Vietnamese named entities in the EVBNews corpus (see Table 4 for details and its
comparison in Figure 5).
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998384">
90
</page>
<tableCaption confidence="0.999192">
Table 4: Number of entities in the EVNECorpus
</tableCaption>
<table confidence="0.99903225">
Tag Name English Entity Vietnamese Entity Unmatched Entity
LOC Location 10,406 11,343 998
ORG Organization 8,177 8,218 189
PER Person 7,201 7,205 199
TIM Time 4,408 4,417 136
MON Money 1,003 993 32
PCT Percent 1,194 1,170 27
Total 32,454 33,338 1,581
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.999559666666667">
There are several common unmatched named entities in English-Vietnamese named entity corpus: the
English-Vietnamese Named Entity Corpus (EVNECorpus) has 32,454 English named entities and 33,338
Vietnamese named entities in the EVBNews corpus (see Table 5). Moreover, to classify the unmatched
named entities, we also tag part-of-speech for English sentences by the POS Tagger6 of the Stanford
Natural Language Processing Group (K. Toutanova and C. D. Manning, 2000).
As shown in Table 5, a large number of English adjectives (tagged JJ tag) are not tagged as named en-
tities while their translations are tagged as locations. Most of them are coming from country names, such
as French, English, and Vietnamese, and they refer to people or languages. In the English text ”Cuban
missile crisis”, the word Cuban is not tagged as a location because Cuban is an adjective (”Cuban/JJ
missile/NN crisis/NN”), while, in its Vietnamese translation, ”Khung khoang tên lila [Cu Ba]LOC”, ”Cu
Ba” is tagged as a location. Moreover, there are several English named entities that are split into two
entities in the Vietnamese sentences. For example, ”[Thailand]LOC ’s [Ministry of Public Health]ORG”
has two entities while its translation is [Bo Y to Thái Lan]ORG. Finally, there are several named entities
that are replaced by pronouns and possessive pronouns (30 cases for PRP and 11 cases for PRP$) in the
translated sentences and the inverse direction (38 cases).
</bodyText>
<figureCaption confidence="0.94929">
Figure 5: English entities and Vietnamese entities in the EVNECorpus
</figureCaption>
<footnote confidence="0.968794">
6http://nlp.stanford.edu/software/tagger.shtml
</footnote>
<page confidence="0.996064">
91
</page>
<tableCaption confidence="0.95633">
Table 5: Common Unmatched Named Entities
</tableCaption>
<table confidence="0.998583">
Description/Examples POS Count
1 English named entities without alignments to Vietnamese words 190
2 Vietnamese named entities without alignments to English source words 106
English named entities with alignments to Vietnamese words rather than
3 NNP 38
Vietnamese entities
Vietnamese named entities with alignments to English words rather than
4
English entities
- Eurobond, NN 10
- Democrats, Eurobonds, Socialists NNS 45
- Kenyan, French, NNP 229
- Russians, Danish, Philippines NNPS 107
- They, he, she, it PRP 36
- Him, His, her, them PRP$ 11
- French, English, and Fuji-based JJ 797
- other cases Others 12
Total 1,581
</table>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.997821" genericHeader="conclusions">
5 Conclusion
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9999715">
In this paper, we have shown a workflow of building an English-Vietnamese named entity corpus. This
workflow is based on an aligned bilingual corpus. In addition, we built a Vietnamese word segmen-
tation corpus for training and evaluating the system. As result, the corpus is built semi-automatically
with over 45,000 sentences, and totally 32,454 English named entities and 33,338 Vietnamese named
entities. Moreover, we also pointed out several differences in named entity tagging between English and
Vietnamese text. These differences can be used to map named entity tags, linguistic information, and in
machine translation systems.
However, adding to the six common named entity types additional names (such as product, disease,
and event names) is also necessary, and we need further research for identifying them in bilingual corpora
because they affect the named entity recognition process as well as the corpus.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.998391" genericHeader="references">
References
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.996453111111111">
Bob Carpenter 2006. Character Language Models for Chinese Word Segmentation and Named Entity Recognition,
In Proceedings of the Fifth SIGHAN Workshop on Chinese Language Processing, pp. 169-172.
Chun-Jen Lee, Jason S. Chang, and Jyh-Shing R. Jang. 2006. Alignment of Bilingual Named Entities in Parallel
Corpora Using Statistical Models and Multiple Knowledge sources, ACM Transactions on Asian Language
Information Processing (TALIP) 5, no. 2 (2006): 121-145.
Cheng-Wei Shih, Tzong-Han Tsai, Shih-Hung Wu, Chiu-Chen Hsieh, and Wen-Lian Hsu. 2004. The Construction
of a Chinese Named Entity Tagged Corpus: CNEC1.0., In Proceedings of Conference on Computational Lin-
guistics and Speech Processing (ROCLING). Association for Computational Linguistics and Chinese Language
Processing (ACLCLP).
</reference>
<page confidence="0.971487">
92
</page>
<reference confidence="0.998298294117647">
Dinh Dien, Hoang Kiem, Thuy Ngan, Xuan Quang, Nguyen V. Toan, Hung Ngo, and Phu Hoi. 2002. Word Align-
ment in English – Vietnamese Bilingual Corpus, In Proceedings of the 2nd East Asian Language Processing
and Internet Information Technology (EALPIIT’02), pp. 3-11.
Donghui Feng, Yajuan L¨u, and Ming Zhou. 2004. A New Approach for English-Chinese Named Entity Align-
ment, In Proceedings of Conference of the European Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics
(EMNLP), vol. 2004, pp. 372-379. Association for Computational Linguistics.
David Nadeau, and Satoshi Sekine. 2007. A Survey of Named Entity Recognition and Classification, Lingvisticae
Investigationes 30, no. 1 (2007): 3-26.
Fei Huang, and Stephan Vogel. 2002. Improved Named Entity Translation and Bilingual Named Entity Extraction,
In Proceedings of the Fourth IEEE International Conference on Multimodal Interfaces, pp. 253-258. IEEE.
J-D Kim, Tomoko Ohta, Yuka Tateisi, and Jun’ichi Tsujii. 2003. GENIA Corpus - a Semantically Annotated
Corpus for Bio-Textmining, Bioinformatics 19 (suppl. 1), pp. 80-82. Oxford University Press.
Jenny R. Finkel, Trond Grenager, and Christopher Manning. 2005. Incorporating Non-local Information into
Information Extraction Systems by Gibbs Sampling, In Proceedings of the 43nd Annual Meeting of the Associ-
ation for Computational Linguistics (ACL 2005), pp. 363-370. Association for Computational Linguistics.
Jian Sun, Jianfeng Gao, Lei Zhang, Ming Zhou, and Changning Huang. 2002. Chinese Named Entity Identification
Using Class-based Language Model, In Proceedings of the 19th International Conference on Computational
Linguistics - Volume 1, pp. 1-7. Association for Computational Linguistics.
Kristina Toutanova, and Christopher D. Manning, 2000. Enriching the Knowledge Sources Used in a Maximum
Entropy Part-of-Speech Tagger, In Proceedings of the Joint SIGDAT Conference on Empirical Methods in
Natural Language Processing and Very Large Corpora (EMNLP/VLC-2000), pp. 63-70. Association for Com-
putational Linguistics.
Lev Ratinov, and Dan Roth. 2009. Design Challenges and Misconceptions in Named Entity Recognition, In
Proceedings of the Thirteenth Conference on Computational Natural Language Learning (CoNLL ’09), pp.
147-155. Association for Computational Linguistics.
Nguyen C. Tu, Tran T. Oanh, Phan X. Hieu, and Ho Q. Thuy. 2005. Named Entity Recognition in Vietnamese Free-
Text and Web Documents Using Conditional Random Fields, The 8th Conference on Some Selection Problems
of Information Technology and Telecommunication. Hai Phong, Vietnam.
Nancy Chinchor, and Patricia Robinson. 1997. MUC-7 named entity task definition, In Proceedings of the 7th
Conference on Message Understanding.
Quoc Hung Ngo, and Werner Winiwarter. 2012. A Visualizing Annotation Tool for Semi-Automatically Building a
Bilingual Corpus, In Proceedings of the 5th Workshop on Building and Using Comparable Corpora, LREC2012
Workshop, pp. 67-74. Association for Computational Linguistics.
Quoc Hung Ngo, Werner Winiwarter, and Bartholom¨aus Wloka. 2013. EVBCorpus - A Multi-Layer English-
Vietnamese Bilingual Corpus for Studying Tasks in Comparative Linguistics, In Proceedings of the 11th Work-
shop on Asian Language Resources (11th ALR within the IJCNLP2013), pp. 1-9. Asian Federation of Natural
Language Processing Associations.
Quoc Tri Tran, TX. Thao Pham, Quoc Hung Ngo, Dien Dinh, and Nigel Collier. 2007. Named Entity Recognition
in Vietnamese Documents, Progress in Informatics, No.4, March 2007, pp. 5-13.
Ryohei Sasano, and Sadao Kurohashi. 2008. Japanese Named Entity Recognition Using Structural Natural Lan-
guage Processing, In Proceedings of the International Joint Conference on Natural Language Processing (IJC-
NLP), pp. 607-612. Asian Federation of Natural Language Processing Associations.
Satoshi Sekine, Kiyoshi Sudo, and Chikashi Nobata. 2002. Extended Named Entity Hierarchy, In Proceedings of
the Language Resources and Evaluation Conference, pp. 1818-1824. Association for Computational Linguis-
tics.
TX. Thao Pham, Quoc Tri Tran, Dinh Dien, and Nigel Collier. 2007. Named Entity Recognition in Vietnamese Us-
ing Classifier Voting, ACM Transactions on Asian Language Information Processing (TALIP) 6, no. 4 (2007):
3.
Yuka Tateisi, Tomoko Ohta, Nigel Collier, Chikashi Nobata, and Jun-ichi Tsujii. 2000. Building an Annotated
Corpus in the Molecular-Biology Domain. In Proceedings of the COLING-2000 Workshop on Semantic Anno-
tation and Intelligent Content, pp. 28-36. Association for Computational Linguistics.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.999172">
93
</page>
</variant>
</algorithm>
<algorithm name="ParsHed" version="110505">
<variant no="0" confidence="0.409696">
<title confidence="0.9995085">Building English-Vietnamese Named Entity with Aligned Bilingual News Articles</title>
<author confidence="0.999663">Quoc Hung Ngo</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.988003">University of Information Technology Vietnam National Universiry - HCM City</affiliation>
<address confidence="0.902789">Ho Chi Minh City, Vietnam</address>
<email confidence="0.890689">hungnq@uit.edu.vn</email>
<author confidence="0.99538">Dinh Dien</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.9921955">University of Sciences Vietnam National Universiry - HCM City</affiliation>
<address confidence="0.943977">Ho Chi Minh City, Vietnam</address>
<email confidence="0.963863">ddien@fit.hcmus.edu.vn</email>
<author confidence="0.98461">Werner</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.862049666666667">University of Research Group Data Analytics and W¨ahringer Straße 29, 1090 Wien,</affiliation>
<email confidence="0.99511">werner.winiwarter@univie.ac.at</email>
<abstract confidence="0.993760111111111">Named entity recognition aims to classify words in a document into pre-defined target entity classes. It is now considered to be fundamental for many natural language processing tasks such as information retrieval, machine translation, information extraction and question answering. This paper presents a workflow to build an English-Vietnamese named entity corpus from an aligned bilingual corpus. The workflow is based on a state of the art named entity recognition tool to identify English named entities and map them into Vietnamese text. The paper also presents a detailed discussion about several mapping errors and differences between English and Vietnamese sentences that affect this task.</abstract>
</variant>
</algorithm>
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Bob Carpenter</author>
</authors>
<title>Character Language Models for Chinese Word Segmentation and Named Entity Recognition,</title>
<date>2006</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the Fifth SIGHAN Workshop on Chinese Language Processing,</booktitle>
<pages>169--172</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="8350" citStr="Carpenter, 2006" startWordPosition="1266" endWordPosition="1267"> will correct both English and Vietnamese named entities by using the BiCAT tool (Q.H. Ngo and W. Winiwarter, 2012). At the first stage, a Named Entity Recognition system is used to tag English entities in the English sentence. Several Named Entity Recognition systems for English text are available online. For traditional NER, the most popular publicly available systems are: OpenNLP NameFinder 2 , Illinois NER3 system by Lev Ratinov (L. Ratinov and D. Roth, 2009), Stanford NER4 system by Jenny Rose Finkel (J.R. Finkel et al., 3005), and Lingpipe NER5 system by Baldwin, B. and B. Carpenter (B. Carpenter, 2006). The Stanford NER reports 86.86 F1 on the CoNLL03 NER shared task data. We chose the Stanford NER to provide for the ability of our corpus for tagging with multi-type, such as 3 classes, 4 classes, and 7 classes. The following example is the result of the Stanford NER for the English sentence “Prime Minister Gordon Brown resigned as Britain ’s top politician on Tuesday evening, making way for Conservative 1http://code.google.com/p/evbcorpus/ 2http://sourceforge.net/apps/mediawiki/opennlp/ 3http://cogcomp.cs.illinois.edu/page/software view/4 4http://nlp.stanford.edu/ner/index.shtml 5http://ali</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Carpenter, 2006</marker>
<rawString>Bob Carpenter 2006. Character Language Models for Chinese Word Segmentation and Named Entity Recognition, In Proceedings of the Fifth SIGHAN Workshop on Chinese Language Processing, pp. 169-172.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Chun-Jen Lee</author>
<author>Jason S Chang</author>
<author>Jyh-Shing R Jang</author>
</authors>
<title>Alignment of Bilingual Named Entities in Parallel Corpora Using Statistical Models and Multiple Knowledge sources,</title>
<date>2006</date>
<journal>ACM Transactions on Asian Language Information Processing (TALIP)</journal>
<volume>5</volume>
<pages>121--145</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="2445" citStr="Lee et al., 2006" startWordPosition="362" endWordPosition="365">NER have been done on languages such as English (J. Sun et al., 2002; C.W. Shih et al., 2004), Japanese (R. Sasano and S. Kurohashi, 2008), Chinese (J. Sun et al., 2002; C.W. Shih et al., 2004), and Vietnamese (N.C. Tu et al., 2005; T.X. T. Pham et al., 2007; Q.T. Tran et al., 2007); and NER systems have been developed using supervised learning methods such as Decision Tree, Maximum Entropy model (D. Nadeau and S. Sekine, 2007), and Support Vector Machine (Q.T. Tran et al., 2007), which achieved high performance. Moreover, there are several studies for bilingual named entity recognition (C.J. Lee et al., 2006; D. Feng et al., 2004; F. Huang and S. Vogel, 2002). However, for the English-Vietnamese pair, this task still presents a significant challenge in a number of important respects (R. Sasano and S. Kurohashi, 2008). Firstly, words in Vietnamese are not always separated by spaces, so word segmentation is necessary and segmentation errors will affect the level of NER performance. Secondly, some proper names of foreign persons and locations are loanwords or represented by phonetic symbols, so we can expect wide variations in some Vietnamese terms. Thirdly, there are considerably fewer available ex</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Lee, Chang, Jang, 2006</marker>
<rawString>Chun-Jen Lee, Jason S. Chang, and Jyh-Shing R. Jang. 2006. Alignment of Bilingual Named Entities in Parallel Corpora Using Statistical Models and Multiple Knowledge sources, ACM Transactions on Asian Language Information Processing (TALIP) 5, no. 2 (2006): 121-145.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Cheng-Wei Shih</author>
<author>Tzong-Han Tsai</author>
<author>Shih-Hung Wu</author>
<author>Chiu-Chen Hsieh</author>
<author>Wen-Lian Hsu</author>
</authors>
<title>The Construction of a Chinese Named Entity Tagged Corpus: CNEC1.0.,</title>
<date>2004</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of Conference on Computational Linguistics and Speech Processing (ROCLING). Association for Computational Linguistics and Chinese Language Processing (ACLCLP).</booktitle>
<contexts>
<context position="1922" citStr="Shih et al., 2004" startWordPosition="275" endWordPosition="278">f the most important subtasks in Information Extraction. It is really essential to identify objects and extract relations between them. Moreover, recognizing proper names from news articles or newswires is also useful in detecting events and monitoring them. The NER task aims to identify and classify certain proper nouns into some pre-defined target entity classes such as person (PER), organization (ORG), location (LOC), temporal expressions (TIME), monetary values (MON), and percentage (PCT). Several previous works in NER have been done on languages such as English (J. Sun et al., 2002; C.W. Shih et al., 2004), Japanese (R. Sasano and S. Kurohashi, 2008), Chinese (J. Sun et al., 2002; C.W. Shih et al., 2004), and Vietnamese (N.C. Tu et al., 2005; T.X. T. Pham et al., 2007; Q.T. Tran et al., 2007); and NER systems have been developed using supervised learning methods such as Decision Tree, Maximum Entropy model (D. Nadeau and S. Sekine, 2007), and Support Vector Machine (Q.T. Tran et al., 2007), which achieved high performance. Moreover, there are several studies for bilingual named entity recognition (C.J. Lee et al., 2006; D. Feng et al., 2004; F. Huang and S. Vogel, 2002). However, for the Englis</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Shih, Tsai, Wu, Hsieh, Hsu, 2004</marker>
<rawString>Cheng-Wei Shih, Tzong-Han Tsai, Shih-Hung Wu, Chiu-Chen Hsieh, and Wen-Lian Hsu. 2004. The Construction of a Chinese Named Entity Tagged Corpus: CNEC1.0., In Proceedings of Conference on Computational Linguistics and Speech Processing (ROCLING). Association for Computational Linguistics and Chinese Language Processing (ACLCLP).</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Dinh Dien</author>
<author>Hoang Kiem</author>
<author>Thuy Ngan</author>
<author>Xuan Quang</author>
<author>Nguyen V Toan</author>
<author>Hung Ngo</author>
<author>Phu Hoi</author>
</authors>
<date>2002</date>
<booktitle>Word Alignment in English – Vietnamese Bilingual Corpus, In Proceedings of the 2nd East Asian Language Processing and Internet Information Technology (EALPIIT’02),</booktitle>
<pages>3--11</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="6497" citStr="Dien et al., 2002" startWordPosition="975" endWordPosition="978">a source for building the English-Vietnamese named entity corpus is a part of the EVBCorpus1, which consists of both original English text and its Vietnamese translations. It contains 1,000 news articles defined as the EVBNews part of the EVBCorpus (as shown in Table 1) (Q.H. Ngo et al., 2013). This corpus is also aligned semi-automatically at the word level. In particular, each article was translated one to one at the whole article level, so we align sentence to sentence. Then, sentences are aligned semi-automatically at the word level, including automatic alignment by class-based method (D. Dien et al., 2002) and use of the BiCAT tool (Q.H. Ngo and W. Winiwarter, 2012) to correct the alignments manually. The details of the corpus are listed in Table 1. Parallel documents are also chosen and classified into categories, such as economy, entertainment (art and music), health, science, social, politics, and technology (percentage of each category is shown in Table 2 and Figure 1). The wide range of categories ensures that named entities in the corpus are diversified enough for other following tasks. 86 Figure 1: The distribution of articles and sentences in each topic in EVBNews Table 1: Characteristi</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Dien, Kiem, Ngan, Quang, Toan, Ngo, Hoi, 2002</marker>
<rawString>Dinh Dien, Hoang Kiem, Thuy Ngan, Xuan Quang, Nguyen V. Toan, Hung Ngo, and Phu Hoi. 2002. Word Alignment in English – Vietnamese Bilingual Corpus, In Proceedings of the 2nd East Asian Language Processing and Internet Information Technology (EALPIIT’02), pp. 3-11.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Donghui Feng</author>
<author>Yajuan L¨u</author>
<author>Ming Zhou</author>
</authors>
<title>A New Approach for English-Chinese Named Entity Alignment,</title>
<date>2004</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of Conference of the European Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics (EMNLP),</booktitle>
<volume>vol.</volume>
<pages>372--379</pages>
<institution>Association for Computational Linguistics.</institution>
<marker>Feng, L¨u, Zhou, 2004</marker>
<rawString>Donghui Feng, Yajuan L¨u, and Ming Zhou. 2004. A New Approach for English-Chinese Named Entity Alignment, In Proceedings of Conference of the European Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics (EMNLP), vol. 2004, pp. 372-379. Association for Computational Linguistics.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>David Nadeau</author>
<author>Satoshi Sekine</author>
</authors>
<date>2007</date>
<journal>A Survey of Named Entity Recognition and Classification, Lingvisticae Investigationes</journal>
<volume>30</volume>
<pages>3--26</pages>
<marker>Nadeau, Sekine, 2007</marker>
<rawString>David Nadeau, and Satoshi Sekine. 2007. A Survey of Named Entity Recognition and Classification, Lingvisticae Investigationes 30, no. 1 (2007): 3-26.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Fei Huang</author>
<author>Stephan Vogel</author>
</authors>
<title>Improved Named Entity Translation and Bilingual Named Entity Extraction,</title>
<date>2002</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the Fourth IEEE International Conference on Multimodal Interfaces,</booktitle>
<pages>253--258</pages>
<publisher>IEEE.</publisher>
<marker>Huang, Vogel, 2002</marker>
<rawString>Fei Huang, and Stephan Vogel. 2002. Improved Named Entity Translation and Bilingual Named Entity Extraction, In Proceedings of the Fourth IEEE International Conference on Multimodal Interfaces, pp. 253-258. IEEE.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>J-D Kim</author>
<author>Tomoko Ohta</author>
<author>Yuka Tateisi</author>
<author>Jun’ichi Tsujii</author>
</authors>
<title>GENIA Corpus - a Semantically Annotated Corpus for Bio-Textmining,</title>
<date>2003</date>
<journal>Bioinformatics</journal>
<volume>19</volume>
<pages>80--82</pages>
<publisher>Oxford University Press.</publisher>
<contexts>
<context position="4638" citStr="Kim et al., 2003" startWordPosition="702" endWordPosition="705">e details of our work. Firstly we address the data source for building the corpus in Section 2. Next, we present a procedure to build an English-Vietnamese Named Entity Corpus by using a bilingual corpus and mapping English entities into Vietnamese entity tags in Section 3. Experimental results and conclusion appear in Sections 4 and 5, respectively. 2 Tagset and Data Source 2.1 Tagset for Named Entities There are many tagsets for the NER task, such as the hierarchical named entity tagset with 150 types (S. Sekine et al., 2002), the biological named entity tagset (Y. Tateisi et al., 2000; J-D Kim et al., 2003), or common named entity tagsets with 3 types and 7 tags (N. Chinchor and P. Robinson, 1998). According to the definition of the MUC-7 conference (N. Chinchor and P. Robinson, 1998), we will identify six types of named entities: • PERSON (PER): Person entities are limited to humans identified by name, nickname or alias. • ORGANIZATION (ORG): Organization entities are limited to corporations, institutions, government agencies and other groups of people defined by an established organizational structure. • LOCATION (LOC): Location entities include names of politically or geographically defined p</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Kim, Ohta, Tateisi, Tsujii, 2003</marker>
<rawString>J-D Kim, Tomoko Ohta, Yuka Tateisi, and Jun’ichi Tsujii. 2003. GENIA Corpus - a Semantically Annotated Corpus for Bio-Textmining, Bioinformatics 19 (suppl. 1), pp. 80-82. Oxford University Press.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Jenny R Finkel</author>
<author>Trond Grenager</author>
<author>Christopher Manning</author>
</authors>
<title>Incorporating Non-local Information into Information Extraction Systems by Gibbs Sampling,</title>
<date>2005</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 43nd Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL</booktitle>
<pages>363--370</pages>
<institution>Association for Computational Linguistics.</institution>
<marker>Finkel, Grenager, Manning, 2005</marker>
<rawString>Jenny R. Finkel, Trond Grenager, and Christopher Manning. 2005. Incorporating Non-local Information into Information Extraction Systems by Gibbs Sampling, In Proceedings of the 43nd Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL 2005), pp. 363-370. Association for Computational Linguistics.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Jian Sun</author>
<author>Jianfeng Gao</author>
<author>Lei Zhang</author>
<author>Ming Zhou</author>
<author>Changning Huang</author>
</authors>
<title>Chinese Named Entity Identification Using Class-based Language Model,</title>
<date>2002</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 19th International Conference on Computational Linguistics -</booktitle>
<volume>1</volume>
<pages>1--7</pages>
<institution>Association for Computational Linguistics.</institution>
<contexts>
<context position="1897" citStr="Sun et al., 2002" startWordPosition="270" endWordPosition="273">ge processing and one of the most important subtasks in Information Extraction. It is really essential to identify objects and extract relations between them. Moreover, recognizing proper names from news articles or newswires is also useful in detecting events and monitoring them. The NER task aims to identify and classify certain proper nouns into some pre-defined target entity classes such as person (PER), organization (ORG), location (LOC), temporal expressions (TIME), monetary values (MON), and percentage (PCT). Several previous works in NER have been done on languages such as English (J. Sun et al., 2002; C.W. Shih et al., 2004), Japanese (R. Sasano and S. Kurohashi, 2008), Chinese (J. Sun et al., 2002; C.W. Shih et al., 2004), and Vietnamese (N.C. Tu et al., 2005; T.X. T. Pham et al., 2007; Q.T. Tran et al., 2007); and NER systems have been developed using supervised learning methods such as Decision Tree, Maximum Entropy model (D. Nadeau and S. Sekine, 2007), and Support Vector Machine (Q.T. Tran et al., 2007), which achieved high performance. Moreover, there are several studies for bilingual named entity recognition (C.J. Lee et al., 2006; D. Feng et al., 2004; F. Huang and S. Vogel, 2002)</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Sun, Gao, Zhang, Zhou, Huang, 2002</marker>
<rawString>Jian Sun, Jianfeng Gao, Lei Zhang, Ming Zhou, and Changning Huang. 2002. Chinese Named Entity Identification Using Class-based Language Model, In Proceedings of the 19th International Conference on Computational Linguistics - Volume 1, pp. 1-7. Association for Computational Linguistics.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Kristina Toutanova</author>
<author>Christopher D Manning</author>
</authors>
<title>Enriching the Knowledge Sources Used in a Maximum Entropy Part-of-Speech Tagger,</title>
<date>2000</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the Joint SIGDAT Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing and Very Large Corpora (EMNLP/VLC-2000),</booktitle>
<pages>63--70</pages>
<institution>Association for Computational Linguistics.</institution>
<marker>Toutanova, Manning, 2000</marker>
<rawString>Kristina Toutanova, and Christopher D. Manning, 2000. Enriching the Knowledge Sources Used in a Maximum Entropy Part-of-Speech Tagger, In Proceedings of the Joint SIGDAT Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing and Very Large Corpora (EMNLP/VLC-2000), pp. 63-70. Association for Computational Linguistics.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Lev Ratinov</author>
<author>Dan Roth</author>
</authors>
<title>Design Challenges and Misconceptions in Named Entity Recognition,</title>
<date>2009</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the Thirteenth Conference on Computational Natural Language Learning (CoNLL ’09),</booktitle>
<pages>147--155</pages>
<institution>Association for Computational Linguistics.</institution>
<marker>Ratinov, Roth, 2009</marker>
<rawString>Lev Ratinov, and Dan Roth. 2009. Design Challenges and Misconceptions in Named Entity Recognition, In Proceedings of the Thirteenth Conference on Computational Natural Language Learning (CoNLL ’09), pp. 147-155. Association for Computational Linguistics.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Nguyen C Tu</author>
<author>Tran T Oanh</author>
<author>Phan X Hieu</author>
<author>Ho Q Thuy</author>
</authors>
<title>Named Entity Recognition in Vietnamese FreeText and Web Documents Using Conditional Random Fields,</title>
<date>2005</date>
<booktitle>The 8th Conference on Some Selection Problems of Information Technology and Telecommunication.</booktitle>
<location>Hai Phong, Vietnam.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="2060" citStr="Tu et al., 2005" startWordPosition="300" endWordPosition="303">ver, recognizing proper names from news articles or newswires is also useful in detecting events and monitoring them. The NER task aims to identify and classify certain proper nouns into some pre-defined target entity classes such as person (PER), organization (ORG), location (LOC), temporal expressions (TIME), monetary values (MON), and percentage (PCT). Several previous works in NER have been done on languages such as English (J. Sun et al., 2002; C.W. Shih et al., 2004), Japanese (R. Sasano and S. Kurohashi, 2008), Chinese (J. Sun et al., 2002; C.W. Shih et al., 2004), and Vietnamese (N.C. Tu et al., 2005; T.X. T. Pham et al., 2007; Q.T. Tran et al., 2007); and NER systems have been developed using supervised learning methods such as Decision Tree, Maximum Entropy model (D. Nadeau and S. Sekine, 2007), and Support Vector Machine (Q.T. Tran et al., 2007), which achieved high performance. Moreover, there are several studies for bilingual named entity recognition (C.J. Lee et al., 2006; D. Feng et al., 2004; F. Huang and S. Vogel, 2002). However, for the English-Vietnamese pair, this task still presents a significant challenge in a number of important respects (R. Sasano and S. Kurohashi, 2008). </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Tu, Oanh, Hieu, Thuy, 2005</marker>
<rawString>Nguyen C. Tu, Tran T. Oanh, Phan X. Hieu, and Ho Q. Thuy. 2005. Named Entity Recognition in Vietnamese FreeText and Web Documents Using Conditional Random Fields, The 8th Conference on Some Selection Problems of Information Technology and Telecommunication. Hai Phong, Vietnam.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Nancy Chinchor</author>
<author>Patricia Robinson</author>
</authors>
<title>MUC-7 named entity task definition,</title>
<date>1997</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 7th Conference on Message Understanding.</booktitle>
<marker>Chinchor, Robinson, 1997</marker>
<rawString>Nancy Chinchor, and Patricia Robinson. 1997. MUC-7 named entity task definition, In Proceedings of the 7th Conference on Message Understanding.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Quoc Hung Ngo</author>
<author>Werner Winiwarter</author>
</authors>
<title>A Visualizing Annotation Tool for Semi-Automatically Building a Bilingual Corpus,</title>
<date>2012</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 5th Workshop on Building and Using Comparable Corpora, LREC2012 Workshop,</booktitle>
<pages>67--74</pages>
<institution>Association for Computational Linguistics.</institution>
<marker>Ngo, Winiwarter, 2012</marker>
<rawString>Quoc Hung Ngo, and Werner Winiwarter. 2012. A Visualizing Annotation Tool for Semi-Automatically Building a Bilingual Corpus, In Proceedings of the 5th Workshop on Building and Using Comparable Corpora, LREC2012 Workshop, pp. 67-74. Association for Computational Linguistics.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Quoc Hung Ngo</author>
<author>Werner Winiwarter</author>
<author>Bartholom¨aus Wloka</author>
</authors>
<title>EVBCorpus - A Multi-Layer EnglishVietnamese Bilingual Corpus for Studying Tasks in Comparative Linguistics,</title>
<date>2013</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 11th Workshop on Asian Language Resources (11th ALR within the IJCNLP2013),</booktitle>
<pages>1--9</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="6173" citStr="Ngo et al., 2013" startWordPosition="924" endWordPosition="927">CT): Percentage entities are percentage expressions, including percentage range expressions. • MONEY (MON): Money entities include monetary expressions. We have developed a guide for bilingual named entity tagging and published it as EnVnNEguide at http://code.google.com/p/evbcorpus/downloads/list. 2.2 Data Source The data source for building the English-Vietnamese named entity corpus is a part of the EVBCorpus1, which consists of both original English text and its Vietnamese translations. It contains 1,000 news articles defined as the EVBNews part of the EVBCorpus (as shown in Table 1) (Q.H. Ngo et al., 2013). This corpus is also aligned semi-automatically at the word level. In particular, each article was translated one to one at the whole article level, so we align sentence to sentence. Then, sentences are aligned semi-automatically at the word level, including automatic alignment by class-based method (D. Dien et al., 2002) and use of the BiCAT tool (Q.H. Ngo and W. Winiwarter, 2012) to correct the alignments manually. The details of the corpus are listed in Table 1. Parallel documents are also chosen and classified into categories, such as economy, entertainment (art and music), health, scienc</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Ngo, Winiwarter, Wloka, 2013</marker>
<rawString>Quoc Hung Ngo, Werner Winiwarter, and Bartholom¨aus Wloka. 2013. EVBCorpus - A Multi-Layer EnglishVietnamese Bilingual Corpus for Studying Tasks in Comparative Linguistics, In Proceedings of the 11th Workshop on Asian Language Resources (11th ALR within the IJCNLP2013), pp. 1-9. Asian Federation of Natural Language Processing Associations.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Thao Pham</author>
<author>Quoc Hung Ngo</author>
<author>Dien Dinh</author>
<author>Nigel Collier</author>
</authors>
<date>2007</date>
<booktitle>Named Entity Recognition in Vietnamese Documents, Progress in Informatics, No.4,</booktitle>
<pages>5--13</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="2087" citStr="Pham et al., 2007" startWordPosition="306" endWordPosition="309">ames from news articles or newswires is also useful in detecting events and monitoring them. The NER task aims to identify and classify certain proper nouns into some pre-defined target entity classes such as person (PER), organization (ORG), location (LOC), temporal expressions (TIME), monetary values (MON), and percentage (PCT). Several previous works in NER have been done on languages such as English (J. Sun et al., 2002; C.W. Shih et al., 2004), Japanese (R. Sasano and S. Kurohashi, 2008), Chinese (J. Sun et al., 2002; C.W. Shih et al., 2004), and Vietnamese (N.C. Tu et al., 2005; T.X. T. Pham et al., 2007; Q.T. Tran et al., 2007); and NER systems have been developed using supervised learning methods such as Decision Tree, Maximum Entropy model (D. Nadeau and S. Sekine, 2007), and Support Vector Machine (Q.T. Tran et al., 2007), which achieved high performance. Moreover, there are several studies for bilingual named entity recognition (C.J. Lee et al., 2006; D. Feng et al., 2004; F. Huang and S. Vogel, 2002). However, for the English-Vietnamese pair, this task still presents a significant challenge in a number of important respects (R. Sasano and S. Kurohashi, 2008). Firstly, words in Vietnames</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Pham, Ngo, Dinh, Collier, 2007</marker>
<rawString>Quoc Tri Tran, TX. Thao Pham, Quoc Hung Ngo, Dien Dinh, and Nigel Collier. 2007. Named Entity Recognition in Vietnamese Documents, Progress in Informatics, No.4, March 2007, pp. 5-13.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Ryohei Sasano</author>
<author>Sadao Kurohashi</author>
</authors>
<title>Japanese Named Entity Recognition Using Structural Natural Language Processing,</title>
<date>2008</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the International Joint Conference on Natural Language Processing (IJCNLP),</booktitle>
<pages>607--612</pages>
<marker>Sasano, Kurohashi, 2008</marker>
<rawString>Ryohei Sasano, and Sadao Kurohashi. 2008. Japanese Named Entity Recognition Using Structural Natural Language Processing, In Proceedings of the International Joint Conference on Natural Language Processing (IJCNLP), pp. 607-612. Asian Federation of Natural Language Processing Associations.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Satoshi Sekine</author>
<author>Kiyoshi Sudo</author>
<author>Chikashi Nobata</author>
</authors>
<title>Extended Named Entity Hierarchy,</title>
<date>2002</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the Language Resources and Evaluation Conference,</booktitle>
<pages>1818--1824</pages>
<institution>Association for Computational Linguistics.</institution>
<contexts>
<context position="4554" citStr="Sekine et al., 2002" startWordPosition="687" endWordPosition="690">rected manually by using a visualization tool. The remainder of this paper describes the details of our work. Firstly we address the data source for building the corpus in Section 2. Next, we present a procedure to build an English-Vietnamese Named Entity Corpus by using a bilingual corpus and mapping English entities into Vietnamese entity tags in Section 3. Experimental results and conclusion appear in Sections 4 and 5, respectively. 2 Tagset and Data Source 2.1 Tagset for Named Entities There are many tagsets for the NER task, such as the hierarchical named entity tagset with 150 types (S. Sekine et al., 2002), the biological named entity tagset (Y. Tateisi et al., 2000; J-D Kim et al., 2003), or common named entity tagsets with 3 types and 7 tags (N. Chinchor and P. Robinson, 1998). According to the definition of the MUC-7 conference (N. Chinchor and P. Robinson, 1998), we will identify six types of named entities: • PERSON (PER): Person entities are limited to humans identified by name, nickname or alias. • ORGANIZATION (ORG): Organization entities are limited to corporations, institutions, government agencies and other groups of people defined by an established organizational structure. • LOCATI</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Sekine, Sudo, Nobata, 2002</marker>
<rawString>Satoshi Sekine, Kiyoshi Sudo, and Chikashi Nobata. 2002. Extended Named Entity Hierarchy, In Proceedings of the Language Resources and Evaluation Conference, pp. 1818-1824. Association for Computational Linguistics.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Thao Pham</author>
<author>Quoc Tri Tran</author>
<author>Dinh Dien</author>
<author>Nigel Collier</author>
</authors>
<title>Named Entity Recognition in Vietnamese Using Classifier Voting,</title>
<date>2007</date>
<journal>ACM Transactions on Asian Language Information Processing (TALIP)</journal>
<volume>6</volume>
<pages>3</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="2087" citStr="Pham et al., 2007" startWordPosition="306" endWordPosition="309">ames from news articles or newswires is also useful in detecting events and monitoring them. The NER task aims to identify and classify certain proper nouns into some pre-defined target entity classes such as person (PER), organization (ORG), location (LOC), temporal expressions (TIME), monetary values (MON), and percentage (PCT). Several previous works in NER have been done on languages such as English (J. Sun et al., 2002; C.W. Shih et al., 2004), Japanese (R. Sasano and S. Kurohashi, 2008), Chinese (J. Sun et al., 2002; C.W. Shih et al., 2004), and Vietnamese (N.C. Tu et al., 2005; T.X. T. Pham et al., 2007; Q.T. Tran et al., 2007); and NER systems have been developed using supervised learning methods such as Decision Tree, Maximum Entropy model (D. Nadeau and S. Sekine, 2007), and Support Vector Machine (Q.T. Tran et al., 2007), which achieved high performance. Moreover, there are several studies for bilingual named entity recognition (C.J. Lee et al., 2006; D. Feng et al., 2004; F. Huang and S. Vogel, 2002). However, for the English-Vietnamese pair, this task still presents a significant challenge in a number of important respects (R. Sasano and S. Kurohashi, 2008). Firstly, words in Vietnames</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Pham, Tran, Dien, Collier, 2007</marker>
<rawString>TX. Thao Pham, Quoc Tri Tran, Dinh Dien, and Nigel Collier. 2007. Named Entity Recognition in Vietnamese Using Classifier Voting, ACM Transactions on Asian Language Information Processing (TALIP) 6, no. 4 (2007): 3.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Yuka Tateisi</author>
<author>Tomoko Ohta</author>
<author>Nigel Collier</author>
<author>Chikashi Nobata</author>
<author>Jun-ichi Tsujii</author>
</authors>
<title>Building an Annotated Corpus in the Molecular-Biology Domain.</title>
<date>2000</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the COLING-2000 Workshop on Semantic Annotation and Intelligent Content,</booktitle>
<pages>28--36</pages>
<institution>Association for Computational Linguistics.</institution>
<contexts>
<context position="4615" citStr="Tateisi et al., 2000" startWordPosition="697" endWordPosition="700">of this paper describes the details of our work. Firstly we address the data source for building the corpus in Section 2. Next, we present a procedure to build an English-Vietnamese Named Entity Corpus by using a bilingual corpus and mapping English entities into Vietnamese entity tags in Section 3. Experimental results and conclusion appear in Sections 4 and 5, respectively. 2 Tagset and Data Source 2.1 Tagset for Named Entities There are many tagsets for the NER task, such as the hierarchical named entity tagset with 150 types (S. Sekine et al., 2002), the biological named entity tagset (Y. Tateisi et al., 2000; J-D Kim et al., 2003), or common named entity tagsets with 3 types and 7 tags (N. Chinchor and P. Robinson, 1998). According to the definition of the MUC-7 conference (N. Chinchor and P. Robinson, 1998), we will identify six types of named entities: • PERSON (PER): Person entities are limited to humans identified by name, nickname or alias. • ORGANIZATION (ORG): Organization entities are limited to corporations, institutions, government agencies and other groups of people defined by an established organizational structure. • LOCATION (LOC): Location entities include names of politically or g</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Tateisi, Ohta, Collier, Nobata, Tsujii, 2000</marker>
<rawString>Yuka Tateisi, Tomoko Ohta, Nigel Collier, Chikashi Nobata, and Jun-ichi Tsujii. 2000. Building an Annotated Corpus in the Molecular-Biology Domain. In Proceedings of the COLING-2000 Workshop on Semantic Annotation and Intelligent Content, pp. 28-36. Association for Computational Linguistics.</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>