<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="SectLabel" version="110505">
<variant no="0" confidence="0.000007">
<note confidence="0.909326">
ComAComA 2014
</note>
<title confidence="0.9924935">
Proceedings of the First Workshop on
Computational Approaches to Compound Analysis
</title>
<note confidence="0.5278935">
Held at the 25th International Conference on Computational Linguistics (COLING 2014)
Editors
</note>
<address confidence="0.433737142857143">
Ben Verhoeven
Walter Daelemans
Menno van Zaanen
Gerhard van Huyssteen
ISBN: 978-1-873769-43-0
August 24, 2014
Dublin, Ireland
</address>
<bodyText confidence="0.7529375">
All works in this volume are licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International
Licence. Licence details: http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.640793">
Publishers
</subsectionHeader>
<affiliation confidence="0.806652">
Dublin City University (DCU)
Glasnevin, Dublin 9, Ireland
Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL)
</affiliation>
<address confidence="0.62429">
Stroudsburg, PA, USA
</address>
<email confidence="0.524077">
http://aclweb.org/anthology/
</email>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.330908" genericHeader="abstract">
ISBN: 978-1-873769-43-0
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.586484">
ii
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.897382" genericHeader="introduction">
Introduction
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999962666666667">
The ComAComA workshop is an interdisciplinary platform for researchers working on compound
processing in different languages, to present recent and ongoing work.
The workshop has several related aims. Firstly, it brings together researchers from different backgrounds
(e.g., computational linguistics, linguistics, neurolinguistics, psycholinguistics, language technology) to
discuss and evaluate compound processing each from their own point of view. Secondly, based on the
interaction between the participants, the workshop provides an overview of existing and desired resources
for future research in this area. Finally, we expect that the interdisciplinary approach of the workshop
will result in better methodologies to evaluate compound processing systems from different perspectives.
Given the high productivity of compounding in a wide range of languages, compound processing
is an interesting subject in linguistics, computational linguistics, and other applied disciplines. For
example, for many language technology applications, compound processing remains a challenge (both
morphologically and semantically), since novel compounds are created and interpreted on the fly. In
order to deal with this productivity, systems that can analyse new compound forms and their meanings
need to be developed. From an interdisciplinary perspective, we also need to better understand the
process of compounding (as a cognitive process), in order to model its complexity.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.285059">
iii
</page>
<table confidence="0.898341692307692">
Workshop Organizers
Ben Verhoeven, University of Antwerp, Belgium
Walter Daelemans, University of Antwerp, Belgium
Menno van Zaanen, Tilburg University, The Netherlands
Gerhard van Huyssteen, North-West University, South Africa
Program Committee
Preslav Nakov, Qatar Computing Research Institute
Iris Hendrickx, Radboud University Nijmegen
Lonneke Van der Plas, University of Stuttgart
Helmut Schmid, Ludwig Maximilian University Munich
Roald Eiselen, North-West University
Pavol Štekauer, P.J. Safarik University
Diarmuid Ó Séaghdha, University of Cambridge
</table>
<affiliation confidence="0.711446142857143">
Rochelle Lieber, University of New Hampshire
Tony Veale, University College Dublin
Pius ten Hacken, University of Innsbruck
Anneke Neijt, Radboud University Nijmegen
Andrea Krott, Univerisity of Birmingham
Emmanuel Keuleers, Ghent University
Stan Szpakowicz, University of Ottawa
</affiliation>
<author confidence="0.251039">
Invited Speakers
</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.6209465">
Andrea Krott, University of Birmingham
Diarmuid Ó Séaghdha, University of Cambridge
</affiliation>
<page confidence="0.744566">
v
</page>
<tableCaption confidence="0.943272">
Table of Contents
</tableCaption>
<figure confidence="0.656850916666667">
Modelling Regular Subcategorization Changes in German Particle Verbs
Stefan Bott and Sabine Schulte im Walde 1
Splitting of Compound Terms in non-Prototypical Compounding Languages
Elizaveta Clouet and Béatrice Daille 11
Automatic Compound Processing: Compound Splitting and Semantic Analysis for Afrikaans and Dutch
Ben Verhoeven, Menno van Zaanen, Walter Daelemans and Gerhard Van Huyssteen 20
A Taxonomy for Afrikaans and Dutch Compounds
Gerhard Van Huyssteen and Ben Verhoeven 31
Electrophysiological correlates of noun-noun compound processing by non-native speakers of English
Cecile DeCat, Harald Baayen and Ekaterini Klepousniotou 41
A Comparative Study of Different Classification Methods for the Identification of Brazilian Portuguese
Multiword Expressions
</figure>
<reference confidence="0.942164714285714">
Alexsandro Fonseca and Fatiha Sadat 53
Wordsyoudontknow: Evaluation of lexicon-based decompounding with unknown handling
Karolina Owczarzak, Ferdinand de Haan, George Krupka and Don Hindle 63
Multiword noun compound bracketing using Wikipedia
Caroline Barriere and Pierre André Ménard 72
Distinguishing Degrees of Compositionality in Compound Splitting for Statistical Machine Translation
Marion Weller, Fabienne Cap, Stefan Müller, Sabine Schulte im Walde and Alexander Fraser...81
</reference>
<page confidence="0.746454">
vii
</page>
</variant>
</algorithm>
<algorithm name="ParsHed" version="110505">
<variant no="0" confidence="0.032748">
<note confidence="0.93127475">ComAComA 2014 Proceedings of the First Workshop Computational Approaches to Compound Analysis Held at the 25th International Conference on Computational Linguistics (COLING 2014)</note>
<title confidence="0.672339">Editors</title>
<author confidence="0.83903375">Ben Walter Menno van_Gerhard van_Huyssteen</author>
<note confidence="0.632463333333333">ISBN: 978-1-873769-43-0 August 24, Dublin, Ireland All works in this volume are licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International Licence details: Publishers</note>
<affiliation confidence="0.965002">Dublin City University (DCU)</affiliation>
<address confidence="0.968332">Glasnevin, Dublin 9, Ireland</address>
<affiliation confidence="0.892164">Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL)</affiliation>
<address confidence="0.995543">Stroudsburg, PA, USA</address>
<web confidence="0.997901">http://aclweb.org/anthology/</web>
<phone confidence="0.725011">ISBN: 978-1-873769-43-0</phone>
<intro confidence="0.701131">ii</intro>
</variant>
</algorithm>
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>Karolina Owczarzak</author>
<author>Ferdinand de Haan</author>
</authors>
<title>George Krupka and Don Hindle 63 Multiword noun compound bracketing using Wikipedia Caroline Barriere and Pierre André</title>
<journal>Ménard</journal>
<volume>72</volume>
<marker>Owczarzak, de Haan, </marker>
<rawString>Karolina Owczarzak, Ferdinand de Haan, George Krupka and Don Hindle 63 Multiword noun compound bracketing using Wikipedia Caroline Barriere and Pierre André Ménard 72</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<title>Distinguishing Degrees of Compositionality in Compound Splitting for Statistical Machine Translation Marion Weller, Fabienne Cap, Stefan Müller, Sabine Schulte im Walde and Alexander Fraser...81</title>
<marker></marker>
<rawString>Distinguishing Degrees of Compositionality in Compound Splitting for Statistical Machine Translation Marion Weller, Fabienne Cap, Stefan Müller, Sabine Schulte im Walde and Alexander Fraser...81</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>