<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="SectLabel" version="110505">
<variant no="0" confidence="0.100176">
<title confidence="0.9756125">
The Last 10 Metres: Using Visual Analysis and Verbal Communication in
Guiding Visually Impaired Smartphone Users to Entrances
</title>
<note confidence="0.38915">
Anja Belz Anil Bharath
Computing, Engineering and Maths Department of Bioengineering
University of Brighton Imperial College London
Lewes Road, Brighton BN2 4GJ, UK Prince Consort Road, London SW7 2BP, UK
</note>
<email confidence="0.885573">
a.s.belz@brighton.ac.uk a.bharath@imperial.ac.uk
</email>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.999271" genericHeader="abstract">
1 Introduction
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999588">
Blindness and partial sight are increasing, due to changing demographics and greater incidence of dis-
eases such as diabetes, at vast financial and human cost (WHO, 2013). Organisations for the visually
impaired stress the importance of independent living, of which safe and independent travel is an integral
part. While existing smartphone facilities such as Apple’s Siri are encouraging, the supporting localisa-
tion services are not sufficiently accurate or precise to enable navigation between e.g. a bus stop or taxi
rank and the entrance to a public space such as a hospital, supermarket or train station.
In this paper, we report plans and progress to date of research addressing ‘the problem of the Last 10
Metres.’ We are developing methods for safely guiding users not just to the general vicinity of a target
destination (as done by GPS-based services), but right up to the main entrance of the target destination,
by a combination of semantically and visually enriched maps, visual analysis, and language generation.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.991093" genericHeader="keywords">
2 Overview
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999995142857143">
The core task is to help users navigate approach paths to building entrances. Navigation guidance is
delivered via a smartphone app with voice and haptic output. The app uses detailed, semantically tagged
maps in which public buildings (museums, schools, hospitals, etc.) and the pavements, landmarks and
other visual cues found in the approaches to their entrances (See Figure 2) are annotated. The maps differ
from existing resources in that they have (i) more detailed information on pedestrian-relevant features,
including obstructions and hazards, and (ii) computational descriptions of ‘visual paths,’ i.e. information
about approach paths to entrances including image sequencess taken along the path (visual cues).
The navigation app provides guidance from the point where a GPS-based system drops the user: the-
oretically within 10m of a destination building, but in reality, anything up to a few hundred metres away
from the actual building entrance. Our research is focused on developing a novel pedestrian guidance sys-
tem that uses semantically and visually enriched maps, visual cues from user-generated live-feed video,
and verbal and haptic communication to guide visually impaired pedestrians during the last few metres
to the entrance of their destination, dropping them not just somewhere near, say, the British Museum, but
more precisely and much more challengingly, right in front of the museum’s main entrance.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.905647" genericHeader="introduction">
3 Usage Scenario
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.975200909090909">
The user employs their usual GPS-based app to get near a target destination, then our Last 10m app takes
over: (1) User requests guidance to an entrance to their target building; (2) System retrieves relevant
local map from server; (3) System converts guidance request to a specific target entrance T annotated
on map; (4) Given location of T on map, system determines location U of user on map; (5) System
computes approach path P from U to T; (6) System starts guiding user along P; at the same time
system carries out continuous monitoring of user behaviour and surroundings, interacting with user as
necessary: (a) System monitors that user stays on track; (b) System monitors path ahead to identify any
obstacles; (c) System issues warnings and update information as necessary, and deals with user requests,
e.g. information about an object detected by the user, location updates or output modality changes.
This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International Licence. Page numbers and proceedings footer
are added by the organisers. Licence details: http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.910408">
118
</page>
<note confidence="0.8685995">
Proceedings of the 25th International Conference on Computational Linguistics, pages 118–120,
Dublin, Ireland, August 23-29 2014.
</note>
<figureCaption confidence="0.999872">
Figure 1: Illustration of the navigational context that we are addressing.
</figureCaption>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.990588" genericHeader="method">
4 Key Challenges
</sectionHeader>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.999736">
4.1 Mapping Challenges
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999172857142857">
Semantically enriched local maps: Using OpenStreetMap,1 which already includes many different kinds
of relevant ‘urban’ tags such as ‘tree’, ‘bus stop’, ‘post box’, ‘traffic signals’, etc., as a starting point,
we are investigating ways of involving some of the 1.5 million volunteer mappers to create a new OSM
layer of highly fine-grained local information and snapshots of visual cues.
Computing path from U to T: Adapting methods developed for similar purposes (Zeng et al., 2008),
compute geometric paths from U to T; if necessary recompute these paths on the fly on the basis of
obstacles that have been detected (see below).
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.975848">
4.2 Vision Challenges
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999963833333333">
Locating user on map based on visual cues: The task is to locate the user precisely on the map (within
a given radius determined on the basis of GPS output) by identifying landmarks and visual cues in user-
generated live feed and matching these to the tags and images in the semantically enriched local maps.
In a pilot study (Rivera-Rubio et al., 2013), conducted within indoor, but highly ambiguous corridors, we
have found that with relatively modest processes, paths can be distinguished with reasonable certainty
using visual cues alone. In more extensive tests, verified with surveying equipment (Rivera-Rubio et al.,
2014), we found that user location on a path can be inferred from hand-held and wearable cameras.
Continuous route monitoring: (a) monitoring of path ahead to identify obstacles and other danger
using computer vision techniques and map information, (b) monitoring actual path against target path,
updating target path and adapting instructions to user as necessary. Monitoring is based on local maps, vi-
sual information obtained on the fly (Davison et al., 2007; Alcantarilla et al., 2010; Pradeep and Medioni,
2010) from smartphone camera live feeds, as well as information from inertial sensors, etc.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.999103">
4.3 Communication Challenges
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998413545454545">
While ‘smart canes’ are promising technological improvements for visually impaired (VI) navigation,
our research has shown that the VI community sharply divides into white cane users and guide dog
owners, with the latter category in particular objecting to the use of a white cane. For this reason we
are focusing on smartphone apps delivering verbal and haptic output (which is suitable for both types of
users). We view the main communication challenges to be the following.
Interaction Management: Managing (a) the interaction between user and system, including allowing
user interrupts and system alerts, and (b) any resulting changes to system behaviour. This includes
allowing the user to input navigation and configuration options for the route before or during the journey.
Communicating navigation guidance: In the absence of interrupts from the continuous route moni-
toring processes described above, the system communicates route guidance along the target path to the
user. We will carry out detailed requirements analyses to determine what kind of instructions and what
</bodyText>
<footnote confidence="0.997193">
1http://www.openstreetmap.org
</footnote>
<page confidence="0.99844">
119
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999808409090909">
level of detail are most useful. While the assumption is that most instructions are best communicated via
brief spoken outputs, a core question is what part of the guidance can be delivered by haptic output, e.g.
different types/locations of vibration indicating different direction/speed of movement.
Communicating warnings: The properties required of warnings differ from navigation guidance, in
that the nature of the danger and the required user reaction need to be conveyed as quickly and as effi-
ciently as possible, with information ordered in terms of urgency. It is likely that a larger proportion of
warnings (than of navigation instructions) are best conveyed by haptic and simple audio output.
Communicating uncertainty: If the system detects a hazard in the path ahead, identification of the
type of hazard and appropriate user action will come with a confidence measure &lt; 1. The degree of
uncertainty in what the system has identified must be conveyed to the user. E.g. if a postbox is tagged in
the map, and the continuous monitoring component has detected an object ahead that it has recognised
with high confidence as a postbox, then it may be enough to simply steer the user around it. However, if
the system detects an obstruction at head height which is not annotated in the map and which it classifies
with similar confidence levels as several things, then this uncertainty has to be expressed in the verbal
output, and the user may have to further investigate.
Communicating varying levels of detail: Similarly, when describing a hazard or verbalising route
guidance, not all the detail about objects and routes available to the system needs to be conveyed to the
user in every situation. For this purpose the system design incorporates a content selection component
(CSC) which decides the appropriate level of detail given the context.
A suitable way to generate verbal output in line with the above communication requirements is proba-
bilistic natural language generation (NLG) technology (Belz, 2008) which offers the possibility of auto-
matically training the verbal output generator to adapt to different user requirements and usage contexts.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.998919" genericHeader="method">
5 Current Work
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999944625">
We are currently in the early stages of developing the various components of the Last 10m system. We
have carried out preliminary experiments in indoors path recognition identification (Rivera-Rubio et al.,
2013; 2014), and conducted initial consultation sessions with VI people. The next step is to design
Wizard-of-Oz experiments in order to obtain sizeable corpora of example instructions (produced by
humans playing the role of the system) appropriate in a variety of contexts which is then used both for
training NLG components and for other aspects of system design. At the same time we are improving
the path computation algorithms (which provide important input to the CSC), using, for the time being,
a small number of semantically and visually enriched local maps of entrances at our universities.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.998584" genericHeader="references">
References
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.9945904375">
P. F. Alcantarilla, L. M. Bergasa, and F. Dellaert. 2010. Visual odometry priors for robust EKF-SLAM. In
Proceedings of the 2010 IEEE International Conference on Robotics and Automation, pages 3501–3506.
A. Belz. 2008. Automatic generation of weather forecast texts using comprehensive probabilistic generation-space
models. Natural Language Engineering, 14(4):431–455.
A. Davison, I. D. Reid, N. D. Molton, and O. Stasse. 2007. MonoSLAM: Real-time single camera SLAM. IEEE
Transactions on Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence, 29(6):1052–1067.
V. Pradeep and G. Medioni. 2010. Robot vision for the visually impaired. In Proceedings of the 2010 Computer
Vision and Pattern Recognition Workshop (CVPR), pages 15–22.
J. Rivera-Rubio, S. Idrees, I. Alexiou, L. Hadjilucas, and A.A. Bharath. 2013. Mobile visual assistive apps:
Benchmarks of vision algorithm performance. In New Trends in Image Analysis and Processing (ICIAP 2013),
volume 8158 of Lecture Notes in Computer Science, pages 30–40.
J. Rivera-Rubio, I. Alexiou, A.A. Bharath, R. Secoli, Dickens, and E. Lupu. 2014. Associating locations from
wearable cameras. In Proceedings of the 25th British Machine Vision Conference. To Appear.
WHO. 2013. Visual impairment and blindness. Fact Sheet No. 282, World Health Organization.
Q. Zeng, C. L. Teo, B. Rebsamen, and E. Burdet. 2008. Collaborative path planning for a robotic wheelchair.
Disability and Rehabilitation Assistive Technology, 3(6):315–324.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.996023">
120
</page>
</variant>
</algorithm>
<algorithm name="ParsHed" version="110505">
<variant no="0" confidence="0.589309">
<title confidence="0.9850455">The Last 10 Metres: Using Visual Analysis and Verbal Communication in Guiding Visually Impaired Smartphone Users to Entrances</title>
<author confidence="0.982253">Anja Anil Bharath</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.9988805">Computing, Engineering and Department of Bioengineering Imperial College London University of Prince Consort Road, London SW7 2BP,</affiliation>
<address confidence="0.904904">Lewes Road, Brighton BN2 4GJ, a.bharath@imperial.ac.uk</address>
<email confidence="0.66721">a.s.belz@brighton.ac.uk</email>
</variant>
</algorithm>
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>P F Alcantarilla</author>
<author>L M Bergasa</author>
<author>F Dellaert</author>
</authors>
<title>Visual odometry priors for robust EKF-SLAM.</title>
<date>2010</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 2010 IEEE International Conference on Robotics and Automation,</booktitle>
<pages>3501--3506</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="6019" citStr="Alcantarilla et al., 2010" startWordPosition="920" endWordPosition="923">shed with reasonable certainty using visual cues alone. In more extensive tests, verified with surveying equipment (Rivera-Rubio et al., 2014), we found that user location on a path can be inferred from hand-held and wearable cameras. Continuous route monitoring: (a) monitoring of path ahead to identify obstacles and other danger using computer vision techniques and map information, (b) monitoring actual path against target path, updating target path and adapting instructions to user as necessary. Monitoring is based on local maps, visual information obtained on the fly (Davison et al., 2007; Alcantarilla et al., 2010; Pradeep and Medioni, 2010) from smartphone camera live feeds, as well as information from inertial sensors, etc. 4.3 Communication Challenges While ‘smart canes’ are promising technological improvements for visually impaired (VI) navigation, our research has shown that the VI community sharply divides into white cane users and guide dog owners, with the latter category in particular objecting to the use of a white cane. For this reason we are focusing on smartphone apps delivering verbal and haptic output (which is suitable for both types of users). We view the main communication challenges </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Alcantarilla, Bergasa, Dellaert, 2010</marker>
<rawString>P. F. Alcantarilla, L. M. Bergasa, and F. Dellaert. 2010. Visual odometry priors for robust EKF-SLAM. In Proceedings of the 2010 IEEE International Conference on Robotics and Automation, pages 3501–3506.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>A Belz</author>
</authors>
<title>Automatic generation of weather forecast texts using comprehensive probabilistic generation-space models.</title>
<date>2008</date>
<journal>Natural Language Engineering,</journal>
<volume>14</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<contexts>
<context position="9302" citStr="Belz, 2008" startWordPosition="1433" endWordPosition="1434"> in the verbal output, and the user may have to further investigate. Communicating varying levels of detail: Similarly, when describing a hazard or verbalising route guidance, not all the detail about objects and routes available to the system needs to be conveyed to the user in every situation. For this purpose the system design incorporates a content selection component (CSC) which decides the appropriate level of detail given the context. A suitable way to generate verbal output in line with the above communication requirements is probabilistic natural language generation (NLG) technology (Belz, 2008) which offers the possibility of automatically training the verbal output generator to adapt to different user requirements and usage contexts. 5 Current Work We are currently in the early stages of developing the various components of the Last 10m system. We have carried out preliminary experiments in indoors path recognition identification (Rivera-Rubio et al., 2013; 2014), and conducted initial consultation sessions with VI people. The next step is to design Wizard-of-Oz experiments in order to obtain sizeable corpora of example instructions (produced by humans playing the role of the syste</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Belz, 2008</marker>
<rawString>A. Belz. 2008. Automatic generation of weather forecast texts using comprehensive probabilistic generation-space models. Natural Language Engineering, 14(4):431–455.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>A Davison</author>
<author>I D Reid</author>
<author>N D Molton</author>
<author>O Stasse</author>
</authors>
<title>MonoSLAM: Real-time single camera SLAM.</title>
<date>2007</date>
<journal>IEEE Transactions on Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence,</journal>
<volume>29</volume>
<issue>6</issue>
<contexts>
<context position="5992" citStr="Davison et al., 2007" startWordPosition="916" endWordPosition="919">paths can be distinguished with reasonable certainty using visual cues alone. In more extensive tests, verified with surveying equipment (Rivera-Rubio et al., 2014), we found that user location on a path can be inferred from hand-held and wearable cameras. Continuous route monitoring: (a) monitoring of path ahead to identify obstacles and other danger using computer vision techniques and map information, (b) monitoring actual path against target path, updating target path and adapting instructions to user as necessary. Monitoring is based on local maps, visual information obtained on the fly (Davison et al., 2007; Alcantarilla et al., 2010; Pradeep and Medioni, 2010) from smartphone camera live feeds, as well as information from inertial sensors, etc. 4.3 Communication Challenges While ‘smart canes’ are promising technological improvements for visually impaired (VI) navigation, our research has shown that the VI community sharply divides into white cane users and guide dog owners, with the latter category in particular objecting to the use of a white cane. For this reason we are focusing on smartphone apps delivering verbal and haptic output (which is suitable for both types of users). We view the mai</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Davison, Reid, Molton, Stasse, 2007</marker>
<rawString>A. Davison, I. D. Reid, N. D. Molton, and O. Stasse. 2007. MonoSLAM: Real-time single camera SLAM. IEEE Transactions on Pattern Analysis and Machine Intelligence, 29(6):1052–1067.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>V Pradeep</author>
<author>G Medioni</author>
</authors>
<title>Robot vision for the visually impaired.</title>
<date>2010</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 2010 Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition Workshop (CVPR),</booktitle>
<pages>15--22</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="6047" citStr="Pradeep and Medioni, 2010" startWordPosition="924" endWordPosition="927">nty using visual cues alone. In more extensive tests, verified with surveying equipment (Rivera-Rubio et al., 2014), we found that user location on a path can be inferred from hand-held and wearable cameras. Continuous route monitoring: (a) monitoring of path ahead to identify obstacles and other danger using computer vision techniques and map information, (b) monitoring actual path against target path, updating target path and adapting instructions to user as necessary. Monitoring is based on local maps, visual information obtained on the fly (Davison et al., 2007; Alcantarilla et al., 2010; Pradeep and Medioni, 2010) from smartphone camera live feeds, as well as information from inertial sensors, etc. 4.3 Communication Challenges While ‘smart canes’ are promising technological improvements for visually impaired (VI) navigation, our research has shown that the VI community sharply divides into white cane users and guide dog owners, with the latter category in particular objecting to the use of a white cane. For this reason we are focusing on smartphone apps delivering verbal and haptic output (which is suitable for both types of users). We view the main communication challenges to be the following. Interac</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Pradeep, Medioni, 2010</marker>
<rawString>V. Pradeep and G. Medioni. 2010. Robot vision for the visually impaired. In Proceedings of the 2010 Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition Workshop (CVPR), pages 15–22.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>J Rivera-Rubio</author>
<author>S Idrees</author>
<author>I Alexiou</author>
<author>L Hadjilucas</author>
<author>A A Bharath</author>
</authors>
<title>Mobile visual assistive apps: Benchmarks of vision algorithm performance.</title>
<date>2013</date>
<booktitle>In New Trends in Image Analysis and Processing (ICIAP 2013),</booktitle>
<volume>8158</volume>
<pages>30--40</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="5260" citStr="Rivera-Rubio et al., 2013" startWordPosition="807" endWordPosition="810">al cues. Computing path from U to T: Adapting methods developed for similar purposes (Zeng et al., 2008), compute geometric paths from U to T; if necessary recompute these paths on the fly on the basis of obstacles that have been detected (see below). 4.2 Vision Challenges Locating user on map based on visual cues: The task is to locate the user precisely on the map (within a given radius determined on the basis of GPS output) by identifying landmarks and visual cues in usergenerated live feed and matching these to the tags and images in the semantically enriched local maps. In a pilot study (Rivera-Rubio et al., 2013), conducted within indoor, but highly ambiguous corridors, we have found that with relatively modest processes, paths can be distinguished with reasonable certainty using visual cues alone. In more extensive tests, verified with surveying equipment (Rivera-Rubio et al., 2014), we found that user location on a path can be inferred from hand-held and wearable cameras. Continuous route monitoring: (a) monitoring of path ahead to identify obstacles and other danger using computer vision techniques and map information, (b) monitoring actual path against target path, updating target path and adaptin</context>
<context position="9672" citStr="Rivera-Rubio et al., 2013" startWordPosition="1487" endWordPosition="1490">election component (CSC) which decides the appropriate level of detail given the context. A suitable way to generate verbal output in line with the above communication requirements is probabilistic natural language generation (NLG) technology (Belz, 2008) which offers the possibility of automatically training the verbal output generator to adapt to different user requirements and usage contexts. 5 Current Work We are currently in the early stages of developing the various components of the Last 10m system. We have carried out preliminary experiments in indoors path recognition identification (Rivera-Rubio et al., 2013; 2014), and conducted initial consultation sessions with VI people. The next step is to design Wizard-of-Oz experiments in order to obtain sizeable corpora of example instructions (produced by humans playing the role of the system) appropriate in a variety of contexts which is then used both for training NLG components and for other aspects of system design. At the same time we are improving the path computation algorithms (which provide important input to the CSC), using, for the time being, a small number of semantically and visually enriched local maps of entrances at our universities. Ref</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Rivera-Rubio, Idrees, Alexiou, Hadjilucas, Bharath, 2013</marker>
<rawString>J. Rivera-Rubio, S. Idrees, I. Alexiou, L. Hadjilucas, and A.A. Bharath. 2013. Mobile visual assistive apps: Benchmarks of vision algorithm performance. In New Trends in Image Analysis and Processing (ICIAP 2013), volume 8158 of Lecture Notes in Computer Science, pages 30–40.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>J Rivera-Rubio</author>
<author>I Alexiou</author>
<author>A A Bharath</author>
<author>R Secoli</author>
<author>Dickens</author>
<author>E Lupu</author>
</authors>
<title>Associating locations from wearable cameras.</title>
<date>2014</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 25th British Machine Vision Conference. To Appear. WHO.</booktitle>
<contexts>
<context position="5536" citStr="Rivera-Rubio et al., 2014" startWordPosition="845" endWordPosition="848">cating user on map based on visual cues: The task is to locate the user precisely on the map (within a given radius determined on the basis of GPS output) by identifying landmarks and visual cues in usergenerated live feed and matching these to the tags and images in the semantically enriched local maps. In a pilot study (Rivera-Rubio et al., 2013), conducted within indoor, but highly ambiguous corridors, we have found that with relatively modest processes, paths can be distinguished with reasonable certainty using visual cues alone. In more extensive tests, verified with surveying equipment (Rivera-Rubio et al., 2014), we found that user location on a path can be inferred from hand-held and wearable cameras. Continuous route monitoring: (a) monitoring of path ahead to identify obstacles and other danger using computer vision techniques and map information, (b) monitoring actual path against target path, updating target path and adapting instructions to user as necessary. Monitoring is based on local maps, visual information obtained on the fly (Davison et al., 2007; Alcantarilla et al., 2010; Pradeep and Medioni, 2010) from smartphone camera live feeds, as well as information from inertial sensors, etc. 4.</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Rivera-Rubio, Alexiou, Bharath, Secoli, Dickens, Lupu, 2014</marker>
<rawString>J. Rivera-Rubio, I. Alexiou, A.A. Bharath, R. Secoli, Dickens, and E. Lupu. 2014. Associating locations from wearable cameras. In Proceedings of the 25th British Machine Vision Conference. To Appear. WHO. 2013. Visual impairment and blindness. Fact Sheet No. 282, World Health Organization.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Q Zeng</author>
<author>C L Teo</author>
<author>B Rebsamen</author>
<author>E Burdet</author>
</authors>
<title>Collaborative path planning for a robotic wheelchair. Disability and Rehabilitation Assistive Technology,</title>
<date>2008</date>
<pages>3--6</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="4738" citStr="Zeng et al., 2008" startWordPosition="715" endWordPosition="718">August 23-29 2014. Figure 1: Illustration of the navigational context that we are addressing. 4 Key Challenges 4.1 Mapping Challenges Semantically enriched local maps: Using OpenStreetMap,1 which already includes many different kinds of relevant ‘urban’ tags such as ‘tree’, ‘bus stop’, ‘post box’, ‘traffic signals’, etc., as a starting point, we are investigating ways of involving some of the 1.5 million volunteer mappers to create a new OSM layer of highly fine-grained local information and snapshots of visual cues. Computing path from U to T: Adapting methods developed for similar purposes (Zeng et al., 2008), compute geometric paths from U to T; if necessary recompute these paths on the fly on the basis of obstacles that have been detected (see below). 4.2 Vision Challenges Locating user on map based on visual cues: The task is to locate the user precisely on the map (within a given radius determined on the basis of GPS output) by identifying landmarks and visual cues in usergenerated live feed and matching these to the tags and images in the semantically enriched local maps. In a pilot study (Rivera-Rubio et al., 2013), conducted within indoor, but highly ambiguous corridors, we have found that </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Zeng, Teo, Rebsamen, Burdet, 2008</marker>
<rawString>Q. Zeng, C. L. Teo, B. Rebsamen, and E. Burdet. 2008. Collaborative path planning for a robotic wheelchair. Disability and Rehabilitation Assistive Technology, 3(6):315–324.</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>