<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="SectLabel" version="110505">
<variant no="0" confidence="0.000164">
<title confidence="0.996117">
Adapting Predicate Frames for Urdu PropBanking
</title>
<author confidence="0.9338765">
Riyaz Ahmad Bhat4, Naman Jain4, Dipti Misra Sharma4, Ashwini Vaidya*,
Martha Palmer*, James Babani* and Tafseer Ahmed*
</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.926992666666667">
LTRC, IIIT-H, Hyderabad, India4
University of Colorado, Boulder, CO 80309 USA&apos;s
DHA Suffa University, Karachi, Pakistan*
</affiliation>
<email confidence="0.9205515">
{riyaz.bhat, naman.jain}@research.iiit.ac.in, dipti@iiit.ac.in,
{vaidyaa, mpalmer, james.babani}@colorado.edu, tafseer@dsu.edu.pk
</email>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.993517" genericHeader="abstract">
Abstract
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999871380952381">
Hindi and Urdu are two standardized reg-
isters of what has been called the Hindus-
tani language, which belongs to the Indo-
Aryan language family. Although, both
the varieties share a common grammar,
they differ significantly in their vocabulary
to an extent where both become mutually
incomprehensible (Masica, 1993). Hindi
draws its vocabulary from Sanskrit while
Urdu draws its vocabulary from Persian,
Arabic and even Turkish. In this paper,
we present our efforts to adopt frames of
nominal and verbal predicates that Urdu
shares with either Hindi or Arabic for
Urdu PropBanking. We discuss the fea-
sibility of porting such frames from either
of the sources (Arabic or Hindi) and also
present a simple and reasonably accurate
method to automatically identify the ori-
gin of Urdu words which is a necessary
step in the process of porting such frames.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.998985" genericHeader="keywords">
1 Introduction
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999885981818182">
Hindi and Urdu, spoken primarily in northern In-
dia and Pakistan, are socially and even officially
considered two different language varieties. How-
ever, such a division between the two is not es-
tablished linguistically. They are two standard-
ized registers of what has been called the Hindus-
tani language, which belongs to the Indo-Aryan
language family. Masica (1993) explains that,
while they are different languages officially, they
are not even different dialects or sub-dialects in
a linguistic sense; rather, they are different liter-
ary styles based on the same linguistically defined
sub-dialect. He further explains that at the collo-
quial level, Hindi and Urdu are nearly identical,
both in terms of core vocabulary and grammar.
However, at formal and literary levels, vocabu-
lary differences begin to loom much larger (Hindi
drawing its higher lexicon from Sanskrit and Urdu
from Persian and Arabic) to the point where the
two styles/languages become mutually unintelligi-
ble. In written form, not only the vocabulary but
the way Urdu and Hindi are written makes one be-
lieve that they are two separate languages. They
are written in separate orthographies, Hindi be-
ing written in Devanagari, and Urdu in a modi-
fied Persio-Arabic script. Given such (apparent)
divergences between the two varieties, two paral-
lel treebanks are being built under The Hindi-Urdu
treebanking Project (Bhatt et al., 2009; Xia et al.,
2009). Both the treebanks follow a multi-layered
and multi-representational framework which fea-
tures Dependency, PropBank and Phrase Structure
annotations. Among the two treebanks the Hindi
treebank is ahead of the Urdu treebank across all
layers. In the case of PropBanking, the Hindi tree-
bank has made considerable progress while Urdu
PropBanking has just started.
The creation of predicate frames is the first step
in PropBanking, which is followed by the actual
annotation of verb instances in corpora. In this
paper, we look at the possibility of porting re-
lated frames from Arabic and Hindi PropBanks for
Urdu PropBanking. Given that Urdu shares its vo-
cabulary with Arabic, Hindi and Persian, we look
at verbal and nominal predicates that Urdu shares
with these languages and try to port and adapt their
frames from the respective PropBanks instead of
creating them afresh. This implies that identifi-
cation of the source of Urdu predicates becomes
a necessary step in this process. Thus, in order
to port the relevant frames, we need to first iden-
tify the source of Urdu predicates and then extract
their frames from the related PropBanks. To state
briefly, we present the following as contributions
of this paper:
</bodyText>
<listItem confidence="0.991337">
• Automatic identification of origin or source
of Urdu vocabulary.
</listItem>
<page confidence="0.983053">
47
</page>
<note confidence="0.5386405">
Language Technology for Closely Related Languages and Language Variants (LT4CloseLang), pages 47–55,
October 29, 2014, Doha, Qatar. (c 2014 Association for Computational Linguistics
</note>
<listItem confidence="0.931113666666667">
• Porting and adapting nominal and verbal
predicate frames from the PropBanks of re-
lated languages.
</listItem>
<bodyText confidence="0.999715111111111">
The rest of the paper is organised as follows: In
the next Section we discuss the Hindi-Urdu tree-
banking project with the focus on PropBanking.
In Section 3, we discuss our efforts to automati-
cally identify the source of Urdu vocabulary and
in Section 4, we discuss the process of adapting
and porting Arabic and Hindi frames for Urdu
PropBanking. Finally we conclude with some
future directions in Section 5.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.8114815" genericHeader="introduction">
2 A multi-layered,
multi-representational treebank
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999838166666667">
Compared to other existing treebanks, Hindi/Urdu
Treebanks (HTB/UTB) are unusual in that they are
multi-layered. They contain three layers of anno-
tation: dependency structure (DS) for annotation
of modified-modifier relations, PropBank-style
annotation (PropBank) for predicate-argument
structure, and an independently motivated phrase-
structure (PS). Each layer has its own framework,
annotation scheme, and detailed annotation guide-
lines. Due to lack of space and relevance to our
work, we only look at PropBanking with reference
to Hindi PropBank, here.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.990566">
2.1 PropBank Annotation
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999941058823529">
The first PropBank, the English PropBank (Kings-
bury and Palmer, 2002), originated as a one-
million word subset of the Wall Street Journal
(WSJ) portion of Penn Treebank II (an English
phrase structure treebank). The verbs in the Prop-
Bank are annotated with predicate-argument struc-
tures and provide semantic role labels for each
syntactic argument of a verb. Although these
were deliberately chosen to be generic and theory-
neutral (e.g., ARG0, ARG1), they are intended
to consistently annotate the same semantic role
across syntactic variations. For example, in both
the sentences John broke the window and The win-
dow broke, ‘the window’ is annotated as ARG1
and as bearing the role of ‘Patient’. This reflects
the fact that this argument bears the same seman-
tic role in both the cases, even though it is realized
as the structural subject in one sentence and as the
object in the other. This is the primary difference
between PropBank’s approach to semantic role la-
bels and the Paninian approach to karaka labels,
which it otherwise resembles closely. PropBank’s
ARG0 and ARG1 can be thought of as similar
to Dowty’s prototypical ‘Agent’ and ‘Patient’
(Dowty, 1991). PropBank provides, for each sense
of each annotated verb, its “roleset”, i.e., the possi-
ble arguments of the predicate, their labels and all
possible syntactic realizations. The primary goal
of PropBank is to supply consistent, simple, gen-
eral purpose labeling of semantic roles for a large
quantity of coherent text that can provide training
data for supervised machine learning algorithms,
in the same way that the Penn Treebank supported
the training of statistical syntactic parsers.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.718378">
2.1.1 Hindi PropBank
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999972739130435">
The Hindi PropBank project has differed signif-
icantly from other PropBank projects in that the
semantic role labels are annotated on dependency
trees rather than on phrase structure trees. How-
ever, it is similar in that semantic roles are defined
on a verb-by-verb basis and the description at
the verb-specific level is fine-grained; e.g., a
verb like ‘hit’ will have ‘hitter’ and ‘hittee’.
These verb-specific roles are then grouped into
broader categories using numbered arguments
(ARG). Each verb can also have a set of modifiers
not specific to the verb (ARGM). In Table 1,
PropBank-style semantic roles are listed for
the simple verb de ‘to give’. In the table, the
numbered arguments correspond to the giver,
thing given and recipient. Frame file definitions
are created manually and include role information
as well as a unique roleset ID (e.g. de.01 in Table
1), which is assigned to every sense of a verb. In
addition, for Hindi the frame file also includes the
transitive and causative forms of the verb (if any).
Thus, the frame file for de ‘give’ will include
dilvaa ‘cause to give’.
</bodyText>
<footnote confidence="0.278522">
de.01 to give
Arg0 the giver
Arg1 thing given
Arg2 recipient
</footnote>
<tableCaption confidence="0.984112">
Table 1: A Frame File
</tableCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.999699">
The annotation process for the PropBank takes
place in two stages: the creation of frame files for
individual verb types, and the annotation of pred-
icate argument structures for each verb instance.
The annotation for each predicate in the corpus
is carried out based on its frame file definitions.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.998554">
48
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999941777777778">
The PropBank makes use of two annotation tools
viz. Jubilee (Choi et al., 2010b) and Cornerstone
(Choi et al., 2010a) for PropBank instance annota-
tion and PropBank frame file creation respectively.
For annotation of the Hindi and Urdu PropBank,
the Jubilee annotation tool had to be modified to
display dependency trees and also to provide ad-
ditional labels for the annotation of empty argu-
ments.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.982754" genericHeader="method">
3 Identifying the source of Urdu
Vocabulary
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999893527777778">
Predicting the source of a word is similar to lan-
guage identification where the task is to identify
the language a given document is written in. How-
ever, language identification at word level is more
challenging than a typical document level lan-
guage identification problem. The number of fea-
tures available at document level is much higher
than at word level. The available features for word
level identification are word morphology, syllable
structure and phonemic (letter) inventory of the
language(s).
In the case of Urdu, the problem is even more
complex as the borrowed words don’t necessarily
carry the inflections of their source language and
don’t retain their identity as such (they undergo
phonetic changes as well). For example, khabar
‘news’ which is an Arabic word declines as per
the morphological paradigm of feminine nom-
inals in Hindi and Urdu as shown in Table (2).
However, despite such challenges, if we look at
the character histogram in Figure (1), we can still
identify the source of a sufficiently large portion
of Urdu vocabulary just by using letter-based
heuristics. For example neither Arabic nor Persian
has aspirated consonants like bfi, ph Aspirated
Bilabial Plosives; tfh, d3fi Aspirated Alveolar
Fricatives; (fi Aspirated Retroflex Plosive; 9fi, kh
Aspirated Velar Plosives etc. while Hindi does.
Similarly, the following sounds occur only in
Arabic and Persian: 3 Fricative Postalveolar; 0,
d Fricative Dental; h Fricative Pharyngeal; X
Fricative Uvular etc. Using these heuristics we
could identify 2,682 types as Indic, and 3,968
as either Persian or Arabic out of 12,223 unique
types in the Urdu treebank (Bhat and Sharma,
2012).
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.598678">
Singular Plural
Direct khabar
Oblique khabar
</figure>
<tableCaption confidence="0.906768">
Table 2: Morphological Paradigm of khabar
</tableCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.9999685">
This explains the efficiency of n-gram based ap-
proaches to either document level or word level
language identification tasks as reported in the re-
cent literature on the problem (Dunning, 1994;
Elfardy and Diab, 2012; King and Abney, 2013;
Nguyen and Dogruoz, 2014; Lui et al., 2014).
In order to predict the source of an Urdu word,
we frame two classification tasks: (1) binary clas-
sification into Indic and Persio-Arabic and, (2) tri-
class classification into Arabic, Indic and Persian.
Both the problems are modeled using smoothed n-
gram based language models.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.999027">
3.1 N-gram Language Models
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999268666666667">
Given a word w to classify into one of k classes
c1, c2, ... , ck, we will choose the class with the
maximum conditional probability:
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.99095525">
c∗ = arg max
= arg max
ci
ci p(w|ci) ∗ p(ci) (1)
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.999562222222222">
The prior distribution p(c) of a class is esti-
mated from the respective training sets shown in
Table (3). Each training set is used to train a
separate letter-based language model to estimate
the probability of word w. The language model
p(w) is implemented as an n-gram model using
the IRSTLM-Toolkit (Federico et al., 2008) with
Kneser-Ney smoothing. The language model is
defined as:
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.9784705">
p(li|li−1
i−k) (2)
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.999201666666667">
where, l is a letter and k is a parameter indicat-
ing the amount of context used (e.g., k = 4 means
5-gram model).
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.99933">
3.2 Etymological Data
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999879">
In order to prepare training and testing data
marked with etymological information for our
classification experiments, we used the Online
</bodyText>
<footnote confidence="0.970024">
1http://www.langsci.ucl.ac.uk/ipa/IPA chart %28C%
292005.pdf
</footnote>
<equation confidence="0.959125">
khabarain
khabaron
p(ci|w)
n
p(w) =
i=1
</equation>
<page confidence="0.996943">
49
</page>
<figure confidence="0.999373266666667">
Relative Frequency
5 · 10−2
0.35
0.25
0.15
0.3
0.2
0.1
0
Arabic
Hindi
Persian
Urdu
bfi 3 T è X D sQ tQ dQ Q DQ G f tSh q ãfi gfi khd3fi N rl ph S ù th t”h d”fi tS b d g fi k d3 m l n p s r t t” U j d”
Alphabets in IPA1
</figure>
<figureCaption confidence="0.999934">
Figure 1: Relative Distribution of Arabic, Hindi, Persian and Urdu Alphabets (Consonants only)
</figureCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.998627571428571">
Urdu Dictionary2 (henceforth OUD). OUD has
been prepared under the supervision of the e-
government Directorate of Pakistan3. Apart from
basic definition and meaning, it provides etymo-
logical information for more than 120K Urdu
words. Since the dictionary is freely4 available
and requires no expertise for extraction of word
etymology which is usually the case with manual
annotation, we could mark the etymological infor-
mation on a reasonably sized word list in a limited
time frame. The statistics are provided in Table
(3). We use Indic as a cover term for all the words
that are either from Sanskrit, Prakrit, Hindi or lo-
cal languages.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.998035">
Language Data Size Average Token Length
Arabic 6,524 6.8
Indic 3,002 5.5
Persian 4,613 6.5
</table>
<tableCaption confidence="0.999673">
Table 3: Statistics of Etymological Data
</tableCaption>
<footnote confidence="0.999258333333333">
2http://182.180.102.251:8081/oud/default.aspx
3www.e-government.gov.pk
4We are not aware of an offline version of OUD.
</footnote>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.95628">
3.3 Experiments
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999977826086957">
We carried out a number of experiments in order
to explore the effect of data size and the order of
n-gram models on the classification performance.
By varying the size of training data, we wanted to
identify the lower bound on the training size with
respect to the classification performance. We var-
ied the training size per training iteration by 1%
for n-grams in the order 1-5 for both the classifi-
cation problems. For each n-gram order 100 ex-
periments were carried out, i.e overall 800 exper-
iments for binary and tri-class classification. The
impact of training size on the classification perfor-
mance is shown in Figures (2) and (3) for binary
and tri-class classification respectively. As ex-
pected, at every iteration the additional data points
introduced into the training data increased the per-
formance of the model. With a mere 3% of the
training data, we could reach a reasonable accu-
racy of 0.85 in terms of F-score for binary classi-
fication and for tri-class classification we reached
the same accuracy with 6% of the data.
Similarly, we tried different order n-gram mod-
els to quantify the effect of character context on
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.980091">
50
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.9999815">
the classification performance. As with the in-
crease in data size, increasing the n-gram order
profoundly improved the results. In both the clas-
sification tasks, unigram based models converge
faster than the higher order n-gram based models.
The obvious reason for it is the small, finite set of
characters that a language operates with (- 37 in
Arabic, - 39 in Persian and - 48 in Hindi). A
small set of words (unique in our case) is probably
enough to capture at least a single instance of each
character. As no new n-gram is introduced with
subsequent additions of new tokens in the training
data, the accuracy stabilizes. However, the accu-
racy with higher order n-grams kept on increas-
ing with an increase in the data size, though it was
marginal after 5-grams. The abrupt increase after
8,000 training instances is probably due to the ad-
dition of an unknown bigram sequence(s) to the
training data. In particular, the Recall of Persio-
Arabic increased by 2.2%.
</bodyText>
<figureCaption confidence="0.9213035">
Figure 2: Learning Curves for Binary Classifica-
tion of Urdu Vocabulary
</figureCaption>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.834602" genericHeader="method">
3.4 Results
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999947625">
We performed 10-fold cross validation over all the
instances of the etymological data for both the bi-
nary and tri-class classification tasks. We split the
data into training and testing sets with a ratio of
80:20 using the stratified sampling. Stratified sam-
pling distributes the samples of each class in train-
ing and testing sets with the same percentage as in
the complete set. For all the 10-folds, the order of
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.99675875">
1
0.9
0.8
F-Score 0.7
0.6
0.5
0 0.2 0.4 0.6 0.8 1 1.2
Training Data Size ·104
</figure>
<figureCaption confidence="0.992583">
Figure 3: Learning Curves for Tri-class Classifi-
cation of Urdu Vocabulary
</figureCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.995995125">
n-gram was varied again from 1-5. Tables (4) and
(5) show the consolidated results for these tasks
with a frequency based baseline to evaluate the
classification performance. In both the tasks, we
achieved highest accuracy with language models
trained with 5-gram letter sequence context. The
best results in terms of F-score are 0.96 and 0.93
for binary and tri-class classification respectively.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.999603571428571">
Type Precision (P) Recall (R) F1-Score (F)
Baseline 0.40 0.50 0.40
1-gram 0.89 0.89 0.89
2-gram 0.95 0.95 0.95
3-gram 0.96 0.96 0.96
4-gram 0.96 0.96 0.96
5-gram 0.96 0.96 0.96
</table>
<tableCaption confidence="0.959372">
Table 4: Results of 10-fold Cross Validation on
Binary Classification
</tableCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.999774909090909">
Although, we have achieved quite reasonable
accuracies in both the tasks, a closer look at the
confusion matrices shown in Tables (6) and (7)
show that we can still improve the accuracies by
balancing the size of data across classes. In binary
classification our model is more biased towards
Persio-Arabic as the data is highly imbalanced.
Our binary classifier misclassifies 0.86% of Indic
tokens as Persio-Arabic since the prior probability
of the latter is much higher than that of the former.
While in the case of tri-class classification, using
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.999260764705882">
0 0.2 0.4 0.6 0.8 1 1.2
Training Data Size ·104
F-Score
0.9
0.8
0.7
0.6
0.5
1
1-gram
2-gram
3-gram
4-gram
1-gram
2-gram
3-gram
4-gram
</figure>
<page confidence="0.99246">
51
</page>
<table confidence="0.999673">
Type Precision (P) Recall (R) F1-Score (F)
Baseline 0.15 0.33 0.21
1-gram 0.83 0.83 0.83
2-gram 0.89 0.89 0.89
3-gram 0.91 0.91 0.91
4-gram 0.93 0.93 0.93
5-gram 0.93 0.93 0.93
</table>
<tableCaption confidence="0.9885935">
Table 5: Results of 10-fold Cross Validation on
Tri-Class Classification
</tableCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.9197424">
higher order n-gram models can resolve the
prominent confusion between Arabic and Persian.
Since both Arabic and Persian share almost the
same phonetic inventory, working with lower
order n-gram models doesn’t seem ideal.
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.389565">
Class Indic Persio-Arabic
Indic 235 60
Persio-Arabic 15 1,057
</figure>
<tableCaption confidence="0.833664">
Table 6: Confusion Matrix of Binary Classifica-
tion
</tableCaption>
<table confidence="0.99973275">
Class Arabic Indic Persian
Arabic 605 5 26
Indic 11 268 18
Persian 22 9 415
</table>
<tableCaption confidence="0.9165455">
Table 7: Confusion Matrix of Tri-class Classifica-
tion
</tableCaption>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.7709135" genericHeader="method">
4 Adapting Frames from Arabic and
Hindi PropBanks
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999913105263158">
As discussed in Section 2.1.1, the creation of pred-
icate frames precedes the actual annotation of verb
instances in a given corpus. In this section, we de-
scribe our approach towards the first stage of Urdu
PropBanking by adapting related predicate frames
from Arabic and Hindi PropBanks (Palmer et al.,
2008; Vaidya et al., 2011). Since a PropBank
is not available for Persian, we could only adapt
those predicate frames which are shared with Ara-
bic and Hindi.
Although, Urdu shares or borrows most of its
literary vocabulary from Arabic and Persian, it re-
tains its simple verb (as opposed to compound or
complex verbs) inventory from Indo-Aryan ances-
try. Verbs from Arabic and Persian are borrowed
less frequently, although there are examples such
as ‘khariid’ buy, ‘farma’ say etc.5 This over-
lap in the verb inventory between Hindi and Urdu
might explain the fact that they share the same
grammar.
The fact that Urdu shares its lexicon with these
languages, prompted us towards exploring the
possibility of using their resources for Urdu Prop-
Banking. We are in the process of adapting frames
for those Urdu predicates that are shared with ei-
ther Arabic or Hindi.
Urdu frame file creation must be carried out for
both simple verbs and complex predicates. Since
Urdu differs very little in simple verb inventory
from Hindi, this simplifies the development pro-
cess as the frames could be ported easily. How-
ever, this is not the case with nominal predicates.
In Urdu, many nominal predicates are borrowed
from Arabic or Persian as shown in Table (8).
Given that a PropBank for Persian is not available,
the task of creating the frames for nominal predi-
cates in Urdu would have been fairly daunting in
the paucity of the Arabic PropBank, as well.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.999450833333333">
Simple Verbs Nominal Predicates
Language Total Unique Total Unique
Arabic 12 1 6,780 765
Hindi 7,332 441 1,203 258
Persian 69 3 2,276 352
Total 7,413 445 10,259 1,375
</table>
<tableCaption confidence="0.998919">
Table 8: Urdu Treebank Predicate Statistics
</tableCaption>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.998754">
4.1 Simple Verbs
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999715866666667">
The simple verb inventory of Urdu and Hindi is
almost similar, so the main task was to locate and
extract the relevant frames from Hindi frame files.
Fortunately, with the exception of farmaa ‘say’,
all the other simple verbs which Urdu borrows
from Persian or Arabic (cf. Table (8)) were also
borrowed by Hindi. Therefore, the Hindi sim-
ple verb frame files sufficed for porting frames for
Urdu simple verbs.
There were no significant differences found be-
tween the Urdu and Hindi rolesets, which describe
either semantic variants of the same verb or its
causative forms. Further, in order to name the
frame files with their corresponding Urdu lemmas,
we used Konstanz’s Urdu transliteration scheme
</bodyText>
<footnote confidence="0.997694333333333">
5Borrowed verbs often do not function as simple verbs
rather they are used like nominals in complex predicate con-
structions such as mehsoos in ‘mehsoos karnaa’ to feel.
</footnote>
<page confidence="0.998467">
52
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999418304347826">
(Malik et al., 2010) to convert a given lemma into
its romanized form. Since the Hindi frame files
use the WX transliteration scheme6, which is not
appropriate for Urdu due to lack of coverage for
Persio-Arabic phonemes or sounds like dQ ‘pha-
ryngealized voiced alveolar stop’. The frame files
also contain example sentences for each predicate,
in order to make the PropBank annotation task eas-
ier. While adapting the frame files from Hindi
to Urdu, simply transliterating such examples for
Urdu predicates was not always an option, because
sentences consisting of words with Sanskrit origin
may not be understood by Urdu speakers. Hence,
all the examples in the ported frames have been
replaced with Urdu sentences by an Urdu expert.
In general we find that the Urdu verbs are quite
similar to Hindi verbs, and this simplified our task
of adapting the frames for simple verbs. The
nouns, however, show more variation. Since a
large proportion (up to 50%) of Urdu predicates
are expressed using verb-noun complex predi-
cates, nominal predicates play a crucial role in our
annotation process and must be accounted for.
</bodyText>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.993877">
4.2 Complex Predicates
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99974425">
In the Urdu treebank, there are 17,672 predicates,
of which more than half have been identified as
noun-verb complex predicates (NVC) at the de-
pendency level. Typically, a noun-verb complex
predicate chorii ‘theft’ karnaa ‘to do’ has two
components: a noun chorii and a light verb karnaa
giving us the meaning ‘steal’. The verbal compo-
nent in NVCs has reduced predicating power (al-
though it is inflected for person, number, and gen-
der agreement as well as tense, aspect and mood)
and its nominal complement is considered the true
predicate. In our annotation of NVCs, we fol-
low a procedure common to all PropBanks, where
we create frame files for the nominal or the ‘true’
predicate (Hwang et al., 2010). An example of a
frame file for a noun such as chorii is described in
Table (9).
The creation of a frame file for the set of
true predicates that occur in an NVC is impor-
tant from the point of view of linguistic annota-
tion. Given the large number of NVCs, a semi-
automatic method has been proposed for creating
Hindi nominal frame files, which saves the man-
ual effort required for creating frames for nearly
</bodyText>
<footnote confidence="0.982201">
6http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/WX notation
</footnote>
<table confidence="0.930355857142857">
Frame file for chorii-n(oun)
chorii.01: theft-n light verb: kar‘do; to steal’
Arg0 person who steals
Arg1 thing stolen
chorii.02 : theft-n light verb: ho ‘be/become; to
get stolen’
Arg1 thing stolen
</table>
<tableCaption confidence="0.960563">
Table 9: Frame file for predicate noun chorii
</tableCaption>
<bodyText confidence="0.965496648648649">
‘theft’ with two frequently occurring light verbs
ho and kar. If other light verbs are found to occur,
they are added as additional rolesets as chorii.03,
chorii.04 and so on.
3,015 unique Hindi noun and light verb combina-
tions (Vaidya et al., 2013).
For Urdu, the process of nominal frame file cre-
ation is preceded by the identification of the ety-
mological origin for each nominal. If that nomi-
nal has an Indic or Arabic origin, relevant frames
from Arabic or Hindi PropBanks were adapted for
Urdu. On the other hand, if the Urdu nominal orig-
inates from Persian, then frame creation will be
done either manually or using other available Per-
sian language resources, in the future.
In Table (8), there are around 258 nominal pred-
icates that are common in Hindi and Urdu, so we
directly ported their frames from Hindi PropBank
with minor changes as was done for simple verb
frames. Out of 765 nominal predicates shared with
Arabic, 308 nominal predicate frames have been
ported to Urdu. 98 of these nominal predicate
frames were already present in the Arabic Prop-
Bank and were ported as such. However, for the
remaining 667 unique predicates, frames are be-
ing created manually by Arabic PropBanking ex-
perts and will be ported to Urdu once they become
available.
Porting of Arabic frames to Urdu is not that triv-
ial. We observed that while Urdu borrows vocabu-
lary from Arabic it does not borrow all the senses
for some words. In such cases, the rolesets that are
irrelevant to Urdu have to be discarded manually.
The example sentences for all the frames ported
from Arabic PropBank have to be sourced from
either the web or manually created by an Urdu ex-
pert, as was the case with Hindi simple verbs.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.999256" genericHeader="conclusions">
5 Conclusion
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.995537666666667">
In this paper we have exploited the overlap be-
tween the lexicon of Urdu, Arabic and Hindi for
the creation of predicate frames for Urdu Prop-
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.995611">
53
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999599588235294">
Banking. We presented a simple and accurate clas-
sifier for the identification of source or origin of
Urdu vocabulary which is a necessary step in the
overall process of extraction of predicate frames
from the related PropBanks. In the case of sim-
ple verbs that occur in the Urdu treebank, we have
extracted all the frames from the Hindi PropBank
and adapted them for Urdu PropBanking. Simi-
larly for complex predicates, frames for Urdu tree-
bank nominal predicates are extracted from Hindi
as well as from Arabic PropBanks. Since a Prop-
Bank is not available for Persian, the creation
of frames for shared predicates with Persian is a
prospect for future work. We plan to create these
frames either manually or semi-automatically, us-
ing the available Persian Dependency treebanks
(Rasooli et al., 2011; Rasooli et al., 2013).
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.998561" genericHeader="acknowledgments">
Acknowledgments
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9975415">
We would like to thank Himani Chaudhry for her
valuable comments that helped to improve the
quality of this paper.
The work reported in this paper is supported by
the NSF grant (Award Number: CNS 0751202;
CFDA Number: 47.070)7.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.995804" genericHeader="references">
References
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.988521217948718">
Riyaz Ahmad Bhat and Dipti Misra Sharma. 2012.
A dependency treebank of urdu and its evaluation.
In Proceedings of the Sixth Linguistic Annotation
Workshop, pages 157–165. Association for Compu-
tational Linguistics.
Rajesh Bhatt, Bhuvana Narasimhan, Martha Palmer,
Owen Rambow, Dipti Misra Sharma, and Fei Xia.
2009. A multi-representational and multi-layered
treebank for hindi/urdu. In Proceedings of the Third
Linguistic Annotation Workshop, pages 186–189.
Association for Computational Linguistics.
Jinho D Choi, Claire Bonial, and Martha Palmer.
2010a. Propbank frameset annotation guidelines us-
ing a dedicated editor, cornerstone. In LREC.
Jinho D Choi, Claire Bonial, and Martha Palmer.
2010b. Propbank instance annotation guidelines us-
ing a dedicated editor, jubilee. In LREC.
David Dowty. 1991. Thematic proto-roles and argu-
ment selection. Language, 67(3):547–619.
7Any opinions, findings, and conclusions or recommen-
dations expressed in this material are those of the author(s)
and do not necessarily reflect the views of the National Sci-
ence Foundation.
Ted Dunning. 1994. Statistical identification of lan-
guage. Computing Research Laboratory, New Mex-
ico State University.
Heba Elfardy and Mona T Diab. 2012. Token level
identification of linguistic code switching. In COL-
ING (Posters), pages 287–296.
Marcello Federico, Nicola Bertoldi, and Mauro Cet-
tolo. 2008. Irstlm: an open source toolkit for han-
dling large scale language models. In Interspeech,
pages 1618–1621.
Jena D Hwang, Archna Bhatia, Clare Bonial, Aous
Mansouri, Ashwini Vaidya, Nianwen Xue, and
Martha Palmer. 2010. Propbank annotation of mul-
tilingual light verb constructions. In Proceedings of
the Fourth Linguistic Annotation Workshop, pages
82–90. Association for Computational Linguistics.
Ben King and Steven P Abney. 2013. Labeling the
languages of words in mixed-language documents
using weakly supervised methods. In HLT-NAACL,
pages 1110–1119.
Paul Kingsbury and Martha Palmer. 2002. From tree-
bank to propbank. In LREC. Citeseer.
Marco Lui, Jey Han Lau, and Timothy Baldwin. 2014.
Automatic detection and language identification of
multilingual documents. Transactions of the Asso-
ciation for Computational Linguistics, 2:27–40.
Muhammad Kamran Malik, Tafseer Ahmed, Sebastian
Sulger, Tina B¨ogel, Atif Gulzar, Ghulam Raza, Sar-
mad Hussain, and Miriam Butt. 2010. Transliterat-
ing urdu for a broad-coverage urdu/hindi lfg gram-
mar. In LREC.
Colin P Masica. 1993. The Indo-Aryan Languages.
Cambridge University Press.
Dong Nguyen and A Seza Dogruoz. 2014. Word
level language identification in online multilingual
communication. In Proceedings of the 2013 Con-
ference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language
Processing.
Martha Palmer, Olga Babko-Malaya, Ann Bies,
Mona T Diab, Mohamed Maamouri, Aous Man-
souri, and Wajdi Zaghouani. 2008. A pilot arabic
propbank. In LREC.
Mohammad Sadegh Rasooli, Amirsaeid Moloodi,
Manouchehr Kouhestani, and Behrouz Minaei-
Bidgoli. 2011. A syntactic valency lexicon for
persian verbs: The first steps towards persian de-
pendency treebank. In 5th Language &amp; Technology
Conference (LTC): Human Language Technologies
as a Challenge for Computer Science and Linguis-
tics, pages 227–231.
Mohammad Sadegh Rasooli, Manouchehr Kouhestani,
and Amirsaeid Moloodi. 2013. Development of a
persian syntactic dependency treebank. In Proceed-
ings of the 2013 Conference of the North Ameri-
can Chapter of the Association for Computational
</reference>
<page confidence="0.979304">
54
</page>
<reference confidence="0.998977176470588">
Linguistics: Human Language Technologies, pages
306–314.
Ashwini Vaidya, Jinho D Choi, Martha Palmer, and
Bhuvana Narasimhan. 2011. Analysis of the hindi
proposition bank using dependency structure. In
Proceedings of the 5th Linguistic Annotation Work-
shop, pages 21–29. Association for Computational
Linguistics.
Ashwini Vaidya, Martha Palmer, and Bhuvana
Narasimhan. 2013. Semantic roles for nominal
predicates: Building a lexical resource. NAACL
HLT 2013, 13:126.
Fei Xia, Owen Rambow, Rajesh Bhatt, Martha Palmer,
and Dipti Misra Sharma. 2009. Towards a multi-
representational treebank. In The 7th International
Workshop on Treebanks and Linguistic Theories.
Groningen, Netherlands.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.999055">
55
</page>
</variant>
</algorithm>
<algorithm name="ParsHed" version="110505">
<variant no="0" confidence="0.428456">
<title confidence="0.999946">Adapting Predicate Frames for Urdu PropBanking</title>
<author confidence="0.866379">Ahmad Naman Dipti Misra Ashwini James</author>
<author confidence="0.866379">Tafseer</author>
<address confidence="0.853886">IIIT-H, Hyderabad, of Colorado, Boulder, CO 80309</address>
<affiliation confidence="0.96287">Suffa University, Karachi,</affiliation>
<email confidence="0.961319">mpalmer,</email>
<abstract confidence="0.999237590909091">Hindi and Urdu are two standardized registers of what has been called the Hindustani language, which belongs to the Indo- Aryan language family. Although, both the varieties share a common grammar, they differ significantly in their vocabulary to an extent where both become mutually incomprehensible (Masica, 1993). Hindi draws its vocabulary from Sanskrit while Urdu draws its vocabulary from Persian, Arabic and even Turkish. In this paper, we present our efforts to adopt frames of nominal and verbal predicates that Urdu shares with either Hindi or Arabic for Urdu PropBanking. We discuss the feasibility of porting such frames from either of the sources (Arabic or Hindi) and also present a simple and reasonably accurate method to automatically identify the origin of Urdu words which is a necessary step in the process of porting such frames.</abstract>
</variant>
</algorithm>
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Riyaz Ahmad Bhat</author>
<author>Dipti Misra Sharma</author>
</authors>
<title>A dependency treebank of urdu and its evaluation.</title>
<date>2012</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the Sixth Linguistic Annotation Workshop,</booktitle>
<pages>157--165</pages>
<publisher>Association</publisher>
<institution>for Computational Linguistics.</institution>
<contexts>
<context position="10583" citStr="Bhat and Sharma, 2012" startWordPosition="1668" endWordPosition="1671"> vocabulary just by using letter-based heuristics. For example neither Arabic nor Persian has aspirated consonants like bfi, ph Aspirated Bilabial Plosives; tfh, d3fi Aspirated Alveolar Fricatives; (fi Aspirated Retroflex Plosive; 9fi, kh Aspirated Velar Plosives etc. while Hindi does. Similarly, the following sounds occur only in Arabic and Persian: 3 Fricative Postalveolar; 0, d Fricative Dental; h Fricative Pharyngeal; X Fricative Uvular etc. Using these heuristics we could identify 2,682 types as Indic, and 3,968 as either Persian or Arabic out of 12,223 unique types in the Urdu treebank (Bhat and Sharma, 2012). Singular Plural Direct khabar Oblique khabar Table 2: Morphological Paradigm of khabar This explains the efficiency of n-gram based approaches to either document level or word level language identification tasks as reported in the recent literature on the problem (Dunning, 1994; Elfardy and Diab, 2012; King and Abney, 2013; Nguyen and Dogruoz, 2014; Lui et al., 2014). In order to predict the source of an Urdu word, we frame two classification tasks: (1) binary classification into Indic and Persio-Arabic and, (2) triclass classification into Arabic, Indic and Persian. Both the problems are mo</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Bhat, Sharma, 2012</marker>
<rawString>Riyaz Ahmad Bhat and Dipti Misra Sharma. 2012. A dependency treebank of urdu and its evaluation. In Proceedings of the Sixth Linguistic Annotation Workshop, pages 157–165. Association for Computational Linguistics.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Rajesh Bhatt</author>
<author>Bhuvana Narasimhan</author>
<author>Martha Palmer</author>
<author>Owen Rambow</author>
<author>Dipti Misra Sharma</author>
<author>Fei Xia</author>
</authors>
<title>A multi-representational and multi-layered treebank for hindi/urdu.</title>
<date>2009</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the Third Linguistic Annotation Workshop,</booktitle>
<pages>186--189</pages>
<publisher>Association</publisher>
<institution>for Computational Linguistics.</institution>
<contexts>
<context position="2692" citStr="Bhatt et al., 2009" startWordPosition="406" endWordPosition="409">y differences begin to loom much larger (Hindi drawing its higher lexicon from Sanskrit and Urdu from Persian and Arabic) to the point where the two styles/languages become mutually unintelligible. In written form, not only the vocabulary but the way Urdu and Hindi are written makes one believe that they are two separate languages. They are written in separate orthographies, Hindi being written in Devanagari, and Urdu in a modified Persio-Arabic script. Given such (apparent) divergences between the two varieties, two parallel treebanks are being built under The Hindi-Urdu treebanking Project (Bhatt et al., 2009; Xia et al., 2009). Both the treebanks follow a multi-layered and multi-representational framework which features Dependency, PropBank and Phrase Structure annotations. Among the two treebanks the Hindi treebank is ahead of the Urdu treebank across all layers. In the case of PropBanking, the Hindi treebank has made considerable progress while Urdu PropBanking has just started. The creation of predicate frames is the first step in PropBanking, which is followed by the actual annotation of verb instances in corpora. In this paper, we look at the possibility of porting related frames from Arabic</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Bhatt, Narasimhan, Palmer, Rambow, Sharma, Xia, 2009</marker>
<rawString>Rajesh Bhatt, Bhuvana Narasimhan, Martha Palmer, Owen Rambow, Dipti Misra Sharma, and Fei Xia. 2009. A multi-representational and multi-layered treebank for hindi/urdu. In Proceedings of the Third Linguistic Annotation Workshop, pages 186–189. Association for Computational Linguistics.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Jinho D Choi</author>
<author>Claire Bonial</author>
<author>Martha Palmer</author>
</authors>
<title>Propbank frameset annotation guidelines using a dedicated editor, cornerstone.</title>
<date>2010</date>
<booktitle>In LREC.</booktitle>
<contexts>
<context position="8555" citStr="Choi et al., 2010" startWordPosition="1345" endWordPosition="1348"> frame file also includes the transitive and causative forms of the verb (if any). Thus, the frame file for de ‘give’ will include dilvaa ‘cause to give’. de.01 to give Arg0 the giver Arg1 thing given Arg2 recipient Table 1: A Frame File The annotation process for the PropBank takes place in two stages: the creation of frame files for individual verb types, and the annotation of predicate argument structures for each verb instance. The annotation for each predicate in the corpus is carried out based on its frame file definitions. 48 The PropBank makes use of two annotation tools viz. Jubilee (Choi et al., 2010b) and Cornerstone (Choi et al., 2010a) for PropBank instance annotation and PropBank frame file creation respectively. For annotation of the Hindi and Urdu PropBank, the Jubilee annotation tool had to be modified to display dependency trees and also to provide additional labels for the annotation of empty arguments. 3 Identifying the source of Urdu Vocabulary Predicting the source of a word is similar to language identification where the task is to identify the language a given document is written in. However, language identification at word level is more challenging than a typical document l</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Choi, Bonial, Palmer, 2010</marker>
<rawString>Jinho D Choi, Claire Bonial, and Martha Palmer. 2010a. Propbank frameset annotation guidelines using a dedicated editor, cornerstone. In LREC.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Jinho D Choi</author>
<author>Claire Bonial</author>
<author>Martha Palmer</author>
</authors>
<title>Propbank instance annotation guidelines using a dedicated editor, jubilee.</title>
<date>2010</date>
<booktitle>In LREC.</booktitle>
<contexts>
<context position="8555" citStr="Choi et al., 2010" startWordPosition="1345" endWordPosition="1348"> frame file also includes the transitive and causative forms of the verb (if any). Thus, the frame file for de ‘give’ will include dilvaa ‘cause to give’. de.01 to give Arg0 the giver Arg1 thing given Arg2 recipient Table 1: A Frame File The annotation process for the PropBank takes place in two stages: the creation of frame files for individual verb types, and the annotation of predicate argument structures for each verb instance. The annotation for each predicate in the corpus is carried out based on its frame file definitions. 48 The PropBank makes use of two annotation tools viz. Jubilee (Choi et al., 2010b) and Cornerstone (Choi et al., 2010a) for PropBank instance annotation and PropBank frame file creation respectively. For annotation of the Hindi and Urdu PropBank, the Jubilee annotation tool had to be modified to display dependency trees and also to provide additional labels for the annotation of empty arguments. 3 Identifying the source of Urdu Vocabulary Predicting the source of a word is similar to language identification where the task is to identify the language a given document is written in. However, language identification at word level is more challenging than a typical document l</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Choi, Bonial, Palmer, 2010</marker>
<rawString>Jinho D Choi, Claire Bonial, and Martha Palmer. 2010b. Propbank instance annotation guidelines using a dedicated editor, jubilee. In LREC.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>David Dowty</author>
</authors>
<title>Thematic proto-roles and argument selection. Language, 67(3):547–619. 7Any opinions, findings, and conclusions or recommendations expressed in this material are those of the author(s) and do not necessarily reflect the views of the National Science Foundation.</title>
<date>1991</date>
<contexts>
<context position="6485" citStr="Dowty, 1991" startWordPosition="1006" endWordPosition="1007">ple, in both the sentences John broke the window and The window broke, ‘the window’ is annotated as ARG1 and as bearing the role of ‘Patient’. This reflects the fact that this argument bears the same semantic role in both the cases, even though it is realized as the structural subject in one sentence and as the object in the other. This is the primary difference between PropBank’s approach to semantic role labels and the Paninian approach to karaka labels, which it otherwise resembles closely. PropBank’s ARG0 and ARG1 can be thought of as similar to Dowty’s prototypical ‘Agent’ and ‘Patient’ (Dowty, 1991). PropBank provides, for each sense of each annotated verb, its “roleset”, i.e., the possible arguments of the predicate, their labels and all possible syntactic realizations. The primary goal of PropBank is to supply consistent, simple, general purpose labeling of semantic roles for a large quantity of coherent text that can provide training data for supervised machine learning algorithms, in the same way that the Penn Treebank supported the training of statistical syntactic parsers. 2.1.1 Hindi PropBank The Hindi PropBank project has differed significantly from other PropBank projects in tha</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Dowty, 1991</marker>
<rawString>David Dowty. 1991. Thematic proto-roles and argument selection. Language, 67(3):547–619. 7Any opinions, findings, and conclusions or recommendations expressed in this material are those of the author(s) and do not necessarily reflect the views of the National Science Foundation.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Ted Dunning</author>
</authors>
<title>Statistical identification of language.</title>
<date>1994</date>
<institution>Computing Research Laboratory, New Mexico State University.</institution>
<contexts>
<context position="10863" citStr="Dunning, 1994" startWordPosition="1713" endWordPosition="1714">milarly, the following sounds occur only in Arabic and Persian: 3 Fricative Postalveolar; 0, d Fricative Dental; h Fricative Pharyngeal; X Fricative Uvular etc. Using these heuristics we could identify 2,682 types as Indic, and 3,968 as either Persian or Arabic out of 12,223 unique types in the Urdu treebank (Bhat and Sharma, 2012). Singular Plural Direct khabar Oblique khabar Table 2: Morphological Paradigm of khabar This explains the efficiency of n-gram based approaches to either document level or word level language identification tasks as reported in the recent literature on the problem (Dunning, 1994; Elfardy and Diab, 2012; King and Abney, 2013; Nguyen and Dogruoz, 2014; Lui et al., 2014). In order to predict the source of an Urdu word, we frame two classification tasks: (1) binary classification into Indic and Persio-Arabic and, (2) triclass classification into Arabic, Indic and Persian. Both the problems are modeled using smoothed ngram based language models. 3.1 N-gram Language Models Given a word w to classify into one of k classes c1, c2, ... , ck, we will choose the class with the maximum conditional probability: c∗ = arg max = arg max ci ci p(w|ci) ∗ p(ci) (1) The prior distributi</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Dunning, 1994</marker>
<rawString>Ted Dunning. 1994. Statistical identification of language. Computing Research Laboratory, New Mexico State University.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Heba Elfardy</author>
<author>Mona T Diab</author>
</authors>
<title>Token level identification of linguistic code switching.</title>
<date>2012</date>
<booktitle>In COLING (Posters),</booktitle>
<pages>287--296</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="10887" citStr="Elfardy and Diab, 2012" startWordPosition="1715" endWordPosition="1718">llowing sounds occur only in Arabic and Persian: 3 Fricative Postalveolar; 0, d Fricative Dental; h Fricative Pharyngeal; X Fricative Uvular etc. Using these heuristics we could identify 2,682 types as Indic, and 3,968 as either Persian or Arabic out of 12,223 unique types in the Urdu treebank (Bhat and Sharma, 2012). Singular Plural Direct khabar Oblique khabar Table 2: Morphological Paradigm of khabar This explains the efficiency of n-gram based approaches to either document level or word level language identification tasks as reported in the recent literature on the problem (Dunning, 1994; Elfardy and Diab, 2012; King and Abney, 2013; Nguyen and Dogruoz, 2014; Lui et al., 2014). In order to predict the source of an Urdu word, we frame two classification tasks: (1) binary classification into Indic and Persio-Arabic and, (2) triclass classification into Arabic, Indic and Persian. Both the problems are modeled using smoothed ngram based language models. 3.1 N-gram Language Models Given a word w to classify into one of k classes c1, c2, ... , ck, we will choose the class with the maximum conditional probability: c∗ = arg max = arg max ci ci p(w|ci) ∗ p(ci) (1) The prior distribution p(c) of a class is es</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Elfardy, Diab, 2012</marker>
<rawString>Heba Elfardy and Mona T Diab. 2012. Token level identification of linguistic code switching. In COLING (Posters), pages 287–296.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Marcello Federico</author>
<author>Nicola Bertoldi</author>
<author>Mauro Cettolo</author>
</authors>
<title>Irstlm: an open source toolkit for handling large scale language models.</title>
<date>2008</date>
<booktitle>In Interspeech,</booktitle>
<pages>1618--1621</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="11768" citStr="Federico et al., 2008" startWordPosition="1870" endWordPosition="1873">and Persian. Both the problems are modeled using smoothed ngram based language models. 3.1 N-gram Language Models Given a word w to classify into one of k classes c1, c2, ... , ck, we will choose the class with the maximum conditional probability: c∗ = arg max = arg max ci ci p(w|ci) ∗ p(ci) (1) The prior distribution p(c) of a class is estimated from the respective training sets shown in Table (3). Each training set is used to train a separate letter-based language model to estimate the probability of word w. The language model p(w) is implemented as an n-gram model using the IRSTLM-Toolkit (Federico et al., 2008) with Kneser-Ney smoothing. The language model is defined as: p(li|li−1 i−k) (2) where, l is a letter and k is a parameter indicating the amount of context used (e.g., k = 4 means 5-gram model). 3.2 Etymological Data In order to prepare training and testing data marked with etymological information for our classification experiments, we used the Online 1http://www.langsci.ucl.ac.uk/ipa/IPA chart %28C% 292005.pdf khabarain khabaron p(ci|w) n p(w) = i=1 49 Relative Frequency 5 · 10−2 0.35 0.25 0.15 0.3 0.2 0.1 0 Arabic Hindi Persian Urdu bfi 3 T è X D sQ tQ dQ Q DQ G f tSh q ãfi gfi khd3fi N rl </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Federico, Bertoldi, Cettolo, 2008</marker>
<rawString>Marcello Federico, Nicola Bertoldi, and Mauro Cettolo. 2008. Irstlm: an open source toolkit for handling large scale language models. In Interspeech, pages 1618–1621.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Jena D Hwang</author>
<author>Archna Bhatia</author>
<author>Clare Bonial</author>
<author>Aous Mansouri</author>
<author>Ashwini Vaidya</author>
<author>Nianwen Xue</author>
<author>Martha Palmer</author>
</authors>
<title>Propbank annotation of multilingual light verb constructions.</title>
<date>2010</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the Fourth Linguistic Annotation Workshop,</booktitle>
<pages>82--90</pages>
<publisher>Association</publisher>
<institution>for Computational Linguistics.</institution>
<contexts>
<context position="22978" citStr="Hwang et al., 2010" startWordPosition="3756" endWordPosition="3759"> identified as noun-verb complex predicates (NVC) at the dependency level. Typically, a noun-verb complex predicate chorii ‘theft’ karnaa ‘to do’ has two components: a noun chorii and a light verb karnaa giving us the meaning ‘steal’. The verbal component in NVCs has reduced predicating power (although it is inflected for person, number, and gender agreement as well as tense, aspect and mood) and its nominal complement is considered the true predicate. In our annotation of NVCs, we follow a procedure common to all PropBanks, where we create frame files for the nominal or the ‘true’ predicate (Hwang et al., 2010). An example of a frame file for a noun such as chorii is described in Table (9). The creation of a frame file for the set of true predicates that occur in an NVC is important from the point of view of linguistic annotation. Given the large number of NVCs, a semiautomatic method has been proposed for creating Hindi nominal frame files, which saves the manual effort required for creating frames for nearly 6http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/WX notation Frame file for chorii-n(oun) chorii.01: theft-n light verb: kar‘do; to steal’ Arg0 person who steals Arg1 thing stolen chorii.02 : theft-n light verb:</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Hwang, Bhatia, Bonial, Mansouri, Vaidya, Xue, Palmer, 2010</marker>
<rawString>Jena D Hwang, Archna Bhatia, Clare Bonial, Aous Mansouri, Ashwini Vaidya, Nianwen Xue, and Martha Palmer. 2010. Propbank annotation of multilingual light verb constructions. In Proceedings of the Fourth Linguistic Annotation Workshop, pages 82–90. Association for Computational Linguistics.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Ben King</author>
<author>Steven P Abney</author>
</authors>
<title>Labeling the languages of words in mixed-language documents using weakly supervised methods.</title>
<date>2013</date>
<booktitle>In HLT-NAACL,</booktitle>
<pages>1110--1119</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="10909" citStr="King and Abney, 2013" startWordPosition="1719" endWordPosition="1722">y in Arabic and Persian: 3 Fricative Postalveolar; 0, d Fricative Dental; h Fricative Pharyngeal; X Fricative Uvular etc. Using these heuristics we could identify 2,682 types as Indic, and 3,968 as either Persian or Arabic out of 12,223 unique types in the Urdu treebank (Bhat and Sharma, 2012). Singular Plural Direct khabar Oblique khabar Table 2: Morphological Paradigm of khabar This explains the efficiency of n-gram based approaches to either document level or word level language identification tasks as reported in the recent literature on the problem (Dunning, 1994; Elfardy and Diab, 2012; King and Abney, 2013; Nguyen and Dogruoz, 2014; Lui et al., 2014). In order to predict the source of an Urdu word, we frame two classification tasks: (1) binary classification into Indic and Persio-Arabic and, (2) triclass classification into Arabic, Indic and Persian. Both the problems are modeled using smoothed ngram based language models. 3.1 N-gram Language Models Given a word w to classify into one of k classes c1, c2, ... , ck, we will choose the class with the maximum conditional probability: c∗ = arg max = arg max ci ci p(w|ci) ∗ p(ci) (1) The prior distribution p(c) of a class is estimated from the respe</context>
</contexts>
<marker>King, Abney, 2013</marker>
<rawString>Ben King and Steven P Abney. 2013. Labeling the languages of words in mixed-language documents using weakly supervised methods. In HLT-NAACL, pages 1110–1119.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Paul Kingsbury</author>
<author>Martha Palmer</author>
</authors>
<title>From treebank to propbank.</title>
<date>2002</date>
<booktitle>In LREC. Citeseer.</booktitle>
<contexts>
<context position="5389" citStr="Kingsbury and Palmer, 2002" startWordPosition="822" endWordPosition="826">ting treebanks, Hindi/Urdu Treebanks (HTB/UTB) are unusual in that they are multi-layered. They contain three layers of annotation: dependency structure (DS) for annotation of modified-modifier relations, PropBank-style annotation (PropBank) for predicate-argument structure, and an independently motivated phrasestructure (PS). Each layer has its own framework, annotation scheme, and detailed annotation guidelines. Due to lack of space and relevance to our work, we only look at PropBanking with reference to Hindi PropBank, here. 2.1 PropBank Annotation The first PropBank, the English PropBank (Kingsbury and Palmer, 2002), originated as a onemillion word subset of the Wall Street Journal (WSJ) portion of Penn Treebank II (an English phrase structure treebank). The verbs in the PropBank are annotated with predicate-argument structures and provide semantic role labels for each syntactic argument of a verb. Although these were deliberately chosen to be generic and theoryneutral (e.g., ARG0, ARG1), they are intended to consistently annotate the same semantic role across syntactic variations. For example, in both the sentences John broke the window and The window broke, ‘the window’ is annotated as ARG1 and as bear</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Kingsbury, Palmer, 2002</marker>
<rawString>Paul Kingsbury and Martha Palmer. 2002. From treebank to propbank. In LREC. Citeseer.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Marco Lui</author>
<author>Jey Han Lau</author>
<author>Timothy Baldwin</author>
</authors>
<title>Automatic detection and language identification of multilingual documents.</title>
<date>2014</date>
<journal>Transactions of the Association for Computational Linguistics,</journal>
<pages>2--27</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="10954" citStr="Lui et al., 2014" startWordPosition="1727" endWordPosition="1730">r; 0, d Fricative Dental; h Fricative Pharyngeal; X Fricative Uvular etc. Using these heuristics we could identify 2,682 types as Indic, and 3,968 as either Persian or Arabic out of 12,223 unique types in the Urdu treebank (Bhat and Sharma, 2012). Singular Plural Direct khabar Oblique khabar Table 2: Morphological Paradigm of khabar This explains the efficiency of n-gram based approaches to either document level or word level language identification tasks as reported in the recent literature on the problem (Dunning, 1994; Elfardy and Diab, 2012; King and Abney, 2013; Nguyen and Dogruoz, 2014; Lui et al., 2014). In order to predict the source of an Urdu word, we frame two classification tasks: (1) binary classification into Indic and Persio-Arabic and, (2) triclass classification into Arabic, Indic and Persian. Both the problems are modeled using smoothed ngram based language models. 3.1 N-gram Language Models Given a word w to classify into one of k classes c1, c2, ... , ck, we will choose the class with the maximum conditional probability: c∗ = arg max = arg max ci ci p(w|ci) ∗ p(ci) (1) The prior distribution p(c) of a class is estimated from the respective training sets shown in Table (3). Each </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Lui, Lau, Baldwin, 2014</marker>
<rawString>Marco Lui, Jey Han Lau, and Timothy Baldwin. 2014. Automatic detection and language identification of multilingual documents. Transactions of the Association for Computational Linguistics, 2:27–40.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Muhammad Kamran Malik</author>
<author>Tafseer Ahmed</author>
<author>Sebastian Sulger</author>
<author>Tina B¨ogel</author>
<author>Atif Gulzar</author>
<author>Ghulam Raza</author>
<author>Sarmad Hussain</author>
<author>Miriam Butt</author>
</authors>
<title>Transliterating urdu for a broad-coverage urdu/hindi lfg grammar.</title>
<date>2010</date>
<booktitle>In LREC.</booktitle>
<marker>Malik, Ahmed, Sulger, B¨ogel, Gulzar, Raza, Hussain, Butt, 2010</marker>
<rawString>Muhammad Kamran Malik, Tafseer Ahmed, Sebastian Sulger, Tina B¨ogel, Atif Gulzar, Ghulam Raza, Sarmad Hussain, and Miriam Butt. 2010. Transliterating urdu for a broad-coverage urdu/hindi lfg grammar. In LREC.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Colin P Masica</author>
</authors>
<title>The Indo-Aryan Languages.</title>
<date>1993</date>
<publisher>Cambridge University Press.</publisher>
<contexts>
<context position="739" citStr="Masica, 1993" startWordPosition="94" endWordPosition="95">lmer*, James Babani* and Tafseer Ahmed* LTRC, IIIT-H, Hyderabad, India4 University of Colorado, Boulder, CO 80309 USA&apos;s DHA Suffa University, Karachi, Pakistan* {riyaz.bhat, naman.jain}@research.iiit.ac.in, dipti@iiit.ac.in, {vaidyaa, mpalmer, james.babani}@colorado.edu, tafseer@dsu.edu.pk Abstract Hindi and Urdu are two standardized registers of what has been called the Hindustani language, which belongs to the IndoAryan language family. Although, both the varieties share a common grammar, they differ significantly in their vocabulary to an extent where both become mutually incomprehensible (Masica, 1993). Hindi draws its vocabulary from Sanskrit while Urdu draws its vocabulary from Persian, Arabic and even Turkish. In this paper, we present our efforts to adopt frames of nominal and verbal predicates that Urdu shares with either Hindi or Arabic for Urdu PropBanking. We discuss the feasibility of porting such frames from either of the sources (Arabic or Hindi) and also present a simple and reasonably accurate method to automatically identify the origin of Urdu words which is a necessary step in the process of porting such frames. 1 Introduction Hindi and Urdu, spoken primarily in northern Indi</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Masica, 1993</marker>
<rawString>Colin P Masica. 1993. The Indo-Aryan Languages. Cambridge University Press.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Dong Nguyen</author>
<author>A Seza Dogruoz</author>
</authors>
<title>Word level language identification in online multilingual communication.</title>
<date>2014</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 2013 Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing.</booktitle>
<contexts>
<context position="10935" citStr="Nguyen and Dogruoz, 2014" startWordPosition="1723" endWordPosition="1726">n: 3 Fricative Postalveolar; 0, d Fricative Dental; h Fricative Pharyngeal; X Fricative Uvular etc. Using these heuristics we could identify 2,682 types as Indic, and 3,968 as either Persian or Arabic out of 12,223 unique types in the Urdu treebank (Bhat and Sharma, 2012). Singular Plural Direct khabar Oblique khabar Table 2: Morphological Paradigm of khabar This explains the efficiency of n-gram based approaches to either document level or word level language identification tasks as reported in the recent literature on the problem (Dunning, 1994; Elfardy and Diab, 2012; King and Abney, 2013; Nguyen and Dogruoz, 2014; Lui et al., 2014). In order to predict the source of an Urdu word, we frame two classification tasks: (1) binary classification into Indic and Persio-Arabic and, (2) triclass classification into Arabic, Indic and Persian. Both the problems are modeled using smoothed ngram based language models. 3.1 N-gram Language Models Given a word w to classify into one of k classes c1, c2, ... , ck, we will choose the class with the maximum conditional probability: c∗ = arg max = arg max ci ci p(w|ci) ∗ p(ci) (1) The prior distribution p(c) of a class is estimated from the respective training sets shown </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Nguyen, Dogruoz, 2014</marker>
<rawString>Dong Nguyen and A Seza Dogruoz. 2014. Word level language identification in online multilingual communication. In Proceedings of the 2013 Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Martha Palmer</author>
<author>Olga Babko-Malaya</author>
<author>Ann Bies</author>
<author>Mona T Diab</author>
<author>Mohamed Maamouri</author>
<author>Aous Mansouri</author>
<author>Wajdi Zaghouani</author>
</authors>
<title>A pilot arabic propbank.</title>
<date>2008</date>
<booktitle>In LREC.</booktitle>
<contexts>
<context position="18601" citStr="Palmer et al., 2008" startWordPosition="3022" endWordPosition="3025">oesn’t seem ideal. Class Indic Persio-Arabic Indic 235 60 Persio-Arabic 15 1,057 Table 6: Confusion Matrix of Binary Classification Class Arabic Indic Persian Arabic 605 5 26 Indic 11 268 18 Persian 22 9 415 Table 7: Confusion Matrix of Tri-class Classification 4 Adapting Frames from Arabic and Hindi PropBanks As discussed in Section 2.1.1, the creation of predicate frames precedes the actual annotation of verb instances in a given corpus. In this section, we describe our approach towards the first stage of Urdu PropBanking by adapting related predicate frames from Arabic and Hindi PropBanks (Palmer et al., 2008; Vaidya et al., 2011). Since a PropBank is not available for Persian, we could only adapt those predicate frames which are shared with Arabic and Hindi. Although, Urdu shares or borrows most of its literary vocabulary from Arabic and Persian, it retains its simple verb (as opposed to compound or complex verbs) inventory from Indo-Aryan ancestry. Verbs from Arabic and Persian are borrowed less frequently, although there are examples such as ‘khariid’ buy, ‘farma’ say etc.5 This overlap in the verb inventory between Hindi and Urdu might explain the fact that they share the same grammar. The fac</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Palmer, Babko-Malaya, Bies, Diab, Maamouri, Mansouri, Zaghouani, 2008</marker>
<rawString>Martha Palmer, Olga Babko-Malaya, Ann Bies, Mona T Diab, Mohamed Maamouri, Aous Mansouri, and Wajdi Zaghouani. 2008. A pilot arabic propbank. In LREC.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Mohammad Sadegh Rasooli</author>
<author>Amirsaeid Moloodi</author>
<author>Manouchehr Kouhestani</author>
<author>Behrouz MinaeiBidgoli</author>
</authors>
<title>A syntactic valency lexicon for persian verbs: The first steps towards persian dependency treebank.</title>
<date>2011</date>
<booktitle>In 5th Language &amp; Technology Conference (LTC): Human Language Technologies as a Challenge for Computer Science and Linguistics,</booktitle>
<pages>227--231</pages>
<marker>Rasooli, Moloodi, Kouhestani, MinaeiBidgoli, 2011</marker>
<rawString>Mohammad Sadegh Rasooli, Amirsaeid Moloodi, Manouchehr Kouhestani, and Behrouz MinaeiBidgoli. 2011. A syntactic valency lexicon for persian verbs: The first steps towards persian dependency treebank. In 5th Language &amp; Technology Conference (LTC): Human Language Technologies as a Challenge for Computer Science and Linguistics, pages 227–231.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Mohammad Sadegh Rasooli</author>
<author>Manouchehr Kouhestani</author>
<author>Amirsaeid Moloodi</author>
</authors>
<title>Development of a persian syntactic dependency treebank.</title>
<date>2013</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 2013 Conference of the North American Chapter of the Association for Computational</booktitle>
<marker>Rasooli, Kouhestani, Moloodi, 2013</marker>
<rawString>Mohammad Sadegh Rasooli, Manouchehr Kouhestani, and Amirsaeid Moloodi. 2013. Development of a persian syntactic dependency treebank. In Proceedings of the 2013 Conference of the North American Chapter of the Association for Computational</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<title>Linguistics: Human Language Technologies,</title>
<pages>306--314</pages>
<marker></marker>
<rawString>Linguistics: Human Language Technologies, pages 306–314.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Ashwini Vaidya</author>
<author>Jinho D Choi</author>
<author>Martha Palmer</author>
<author>Bhuvana Narasimhan</author>
</authors>
<title>Analysis of the hindi proposition bank using dependency structure.</title>
<date>2011</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 5th Linguistic Annotation Workshop,</booktitle>
<pages>21--29</pages>
<publisher>Association</publisher>
<institution>for Computational Linguistics.</institution>
<contexts>
<context position="18623" citStr="Vaidya et al., 2011" startWordPosition="3026" endWordPosition="3029">ass Indic Persio-Arabic Indic 235 60 Persio-Arabic 15 1,057 Table 6: Confusion Matrix of Binary Classification Class Arabic Indic Persian Arabic 605 5 26 Indic 11 268 18 Persian 22 9 415 Table 7: Confusion Matrix of Tri-class Classification 4 Adapting Frames from Arabic and Hindi PropBanks As discussed in Section 2.1.1, the creation of predicate frames precedes the actual annotation of verb instances in a given corpus. In this section, we describe our approach towards the first stage of Urdu PropBanking by adapting related predicate frames from Arabic and Hindi PropBanks (Palmer et al., 2008; Vaidya et al., 2011). Since a PropBank is not available for Persian, we could only adapt those predicate frames which are shared with Arabic and Hindi. Although, Urdu shares or borrows most of its literary vocabulary from Arabic and Persian, it retains its simple verb (as opposed to compound or complex verbs) inventory from Indo-Aryan ancestry. Verbs from Arabic and Persian are borrowed less frequently, although there are examples such as ‘khariid’ buy, ‘farma’ say etc.5 This overlap in the verb inventory between Hindi and Urdu might explain the fact that they share the same grammar. The fact that Urdu shares its</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Vaidya, Choi, Palmer, Narasimhan, 2011</marker>
<rawString>Ashwini Vaidya, Jinho D Choi, Martha Palmer, and Bhuvana Narasimhan. 2011. Analysis of the hindi proposition bank using dependency structure. In Proceedings of the 5th Linguistic Annotation Workshop, pages 21–29. Association for Computational Linguistics.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Ashwini Vaidya</author>
<author>Martha Palmer</author>
<author>Bhuvana Narasimhan</author>
</authors>
<title>Semantic roles for nominal predicates: Building a lexical resource. NAACL HLT</title>
<date>2013</date>
<pages>13--126</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="23922" citStr="Vaidya et al., 2013" startWordPosition="3917" endWordPosition="3920"> frame files, which saves the manual effort required for creating frames for nearly 6http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/WX notation Frame file for chorii-n(oun) chorii.01: theft-n light verb: kar‘do; to steal’ Arg0 person who steals Arg1 thing stolen chorii.02 : theft-n light verb: ho ‘be/become; to get stolen’ Arg1 thing stolen Table 9: Frame file for predicate noun chorii ‘theft’ with two frequently occurring light verbs ho and kar. If other light verbs are found to occur, they are added as additional rolesets as chorii.03, chorii.04 and so on. 3,015 unique Hindi noun and light verb combinations (Vaidya et al., 2013). For Urdu, the process of nominal frame file creation is preceded by the identification of the etymological origin for each nominal. If that nominal has an Indic or Arabic origin, relevant frames from Arabic or Hindi PropBanks were adapted for Urdu. On the other hand, if the Urdu nominal originates from Persian, then frame creation will be done either manually or using other available Persian language resources, in the future. In Table (8), there are around 258 nominal predicates that are common in Hindi and Urdu, so we directly ported their frames from Hindi PropBank with minor changes as wa</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Vaidya, Palmer, Narasimhan, 2013</marker>
<rawString>Ashwini Vaidya, Martha Palmer, and Bhuvana Narasimhan. 2013. Semantic roles for nominal predicates: Building a lexical resource. NAACL HLT 2013, 13:126.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Fei Xia</author>
<author>Owen Rambow</author>
<author>Rajesh Bhatt</author>
<author>Martha Palmer</author>
<author>Dipti Misra Sharma</author>
</authors>
<title>Towards a multirepresentational treebank.</title>
<date>2009</date>
<booktitle>In The 7th International Workshop on Treebanks and Linguistic Theories.</booktitle>
<location>Groningen, Netherlands.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="2711" citStr="Xia et al., 2009" startWordPosition="410" endWordPosition="413">to loom much larger (Hindi drawing its higher lexicon from Sanskrit and Urdu from Persian and Arabic) to the point where the two styles/languages become mutually unintelligible. In written form, not only the vocabulary but the way Urdu and Hindi are written makes one believe that they are two separate languages. They are written in separate orthographies, Hindi being written in Devanagari, and Urdu in a modified Persio-Arabic script. Given such (apparent) divergences between the two varieties, two parallel treebanks are being built under The Hindi-Urdu treebanking Project (Bhatt et al., 2009; Xia et al., 2009). Both the treebanks follow a multi-layered and multi-representational framework which features Dependency, PropBank and Phrase Structure annotations. Among the two treebanks the Hindi treebank is ahead of the Urdu treebank across all layers. In the case of PropBanking, the Hindi treebank has made considerable progress while Urdu PropBanking has just started. The creation of predicate frames is the first step in PropBanking, which is followed by the actual annotation of verb instances in corpora. In this paper, we look at the possibility of porting related frames from Arabic and Hindi PropBank</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Xia, Rambow, Bhatt, Palmer, Sharma, 2009</marker>
<rawString>Fei Xia, Owen Rambow, Rajesh Bhatt, Martha Palmer, and Dipti Misra Sharma. 2009. Towards a multirepresentational treebank. In The 7th International Workshop on Treebanks and Linguistic Theories. Groningen, Netherlands.</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>