<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="SectLabel" version="110505">
<variant no="0" confidence="0.000000">
<note confidence="0.49493">
Obituary
Charles J. Fillmore
</note>
<author confidence="0.914861">
Dan Jurafsky
</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.836018">
Stanford University
</affiliation>
<note confidence="0.552459">
Charles J. Fillmore died at his home in San Francisco on February 13, 2014, of brain
</note>
<bodyText confidence="0.994759705882353">
cancer. He was 84 years old. Fillmore was one of the world’s pre-eminent scholars of
lexical meaning and its relationship with context, grammar, corpora, and computation,
and his work had an enormous impact on computational linguistics. His early theoret-
ical work in the 1960s, 1970s, and 1980s on case grammar and then frame semantics
significantly influenced computational linguistics, AI, and knowledge representation.
More recent work in the last two decades on FrameNet, a computational lexicon and
annotated corpus, influenced corpus linguistics and computational lexicography, and
led to modern natural language understanding tasks like semantic role labeling.
Fillmore was born and raised in St. Paul, Minnesota, and studied linguistics at the
University of Minnesota. As an undergraduate he worked on a pre-computational Latin
corpus linguistics project, alphabetizing index cards and building concordances. During
his service in the Army in the early 1950s he was stationed for three years in Japan.
After his service he became the first US soldier to be discharged locally in Japan, and
stayed for three years studying Japanese. He supported himself by teaching English,
pioneering a way to make ends meet that afterwards became popular with generations
of young Americans abroad. In 1957 he moved back to the United States to attend
graduate school at the University of Michigan.
At Michigan, Fillmore worked on phonetics, phonology, and syntax, first in the
American Structuralist tradition of developing what were called “discovery proce-
dures” for linguistic analysis, algorithms for inducing phones or parts of speech. Dis-
covery procedures were thought of as a methodological tool, a formal procedure that
linguists could apply to data to discover linguistic structure, for example inducing parts
of speech from the slots in “sentence frames” informed by the distribution of surround-
ing words. Like many linguistic graduate students of the period, he also worked partly
on machine translation, and was interviewed at the time by Yehoshua Bar-Hillel, who
was touring US machine translation laboratories in preparation for his famous report
on the state of MT (Bar-Hillel 1960).
Early in his graduate career, however, Fillmore read Noam Chomsky’s Syntactic
Structures and became an immediate proponent of the new transformational grammar.
He graduated with his PhD in 1962 and moved to the linguistics department at Ohio
State University. In his early work there Fillmore developed a number of early formal
properties of generative grammar, such as the idea that rules would re-apply to repre-
sentations in iterative stages called cycles (Fillmore 1963), a formal mechanism that still
plays a role in modern theories of generative grammar.
</bodyText>
<note confidence="0.7912">
doi:10.1162/COLI a 00201
© 2014 Association for Computational Linguistics
Computational Linguistics Volume 40, Number 3
</note>
<bodyText confidence="0.941637608695652">
But his greatest impact on computational linguistics came from the line of research
that began with his early work on case grammar (Fillmore 1966, 1968, 1971, 1977a).
Fillmore had become interested in argument structure by studying Lucien Tesni`ere’s
groundbreaking ´El´ements de Syntaxe Structurale (Tesni`ere 1959) in which the term
‘dependency’ was introduced and the foundations were laid for dependency grammar.
Like many transformational grammarians of the time, Fillmore began by trying to
capture the relationships between distinct formal patterns with systematically related
meanings; and he became interested in the different ways of expressing the object
and recipient of transfer in sentences like “He gave a book to me” and “He gave me
a book” (Fillmore 1962, 1965), a phenomenon that became known as dative movement.
He then expanded to the more general goal of representing how the participants in
an event are expressed syntactically, as in these two sentences about an event of
opening:
a. The janitor will open the door with this key
b. This key will open the door
Fillmore noticed that despite the differing syntactic structure, in both sentences key
plays the role of the instrument of the action and door the role of the object, patient,
or theme, and suggested that such abstract roles could constitute a shallow level of
meaning representation. Following Tesni`ere’s terminology, Fillmore first referred to
these argument roles as actants (Fillmore 1966) but quickly switched to the term case,
(see Fillmore (2003)) and proposed a universal list of semantic roles or cases (Agent,
Patient, Instrument, etc.), that could be taken on by the arguments of predicates. Verbs
would be listed in the lexicon with their ‘case frame’, the list of obligatory (or optional)
case arguments.
The idea that semantic roles could provide an intermediate level of semantic
representation that could help map from syntactic parse structures to deeper,
more fully-specified representations of meaning was quickly adopted in natural
language processing, and systems for extracting case frames were created for machine
translation (Wilks 1973), question-answering (Hendrix, Thompson, and Slocum 1973),
spoken-language understanding (Nash-Webber 1975), and dialogue systems (Bobrow
et al. 1977). General-purpose semantic role labelers were developed to map to case
representations via ATNs (Simmons 1973) or, from parse trees, by using dictionaries
with verb-specific case frames (Levin 1977; Marcus 1980). By 1977 case representation
was widely used and taught in natural language processing and artificial intelligence,
and was described as a standard component of natural language understanding in the
first edition of Winston’s (1977) textbook Artificial Intelligence.
In 1971 Fillmore joined the linguistics faculty at the University of California,
Berkeley, and by the mid-1970s he began to expand his ideas on case. He arrived at
a more general model of semantic representation, one that expressed the background
contexts or perspectives by which a word or a case role could be defined. He called this
new representation a frame, and later described the intuition as follows:
“The idea behind frame semantics is that speakers are aware of possibly quite complex
situation types, packages of connected expectations, that go by various names—frames,
schemas, scenarios, scripts, cultural narratives, memes—and the words in our language
are understood with such frames as their presupposed background.” (Fillmore 2012,
p. 712)
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.990141">
726
</page>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.286259">
Jurafsky Obituary
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9964135">
He described the name as coming from “the pre-transformationalist view of sentence
structure as consisting of a frame and a substitution list,” but the word frame seemed to
be in the air for a suite of related notions proposed at about the same time by Minsky
(1974), Hymes (1974), and Goffman (1974), as well as related notions with other names
like scripts (Schank and Abelson 1975) and schemata (Bobrow and Norman 1975) (see
Tannen [1979] for a comparison). Fillmore was also influenced by the semantic field
theorists and by a visit to the Yale AI lab where he took notice of the lists of slots and
fillers used by early information extraction systems like DeJong (1982) and Schank and
Abelson (1977).
Fillmore’s version of this new idea—more linguistic than other manifestations,
focusing on the way that words are associated with frames—was expressed in a series
of papers starting in the mid-1970’s (Fillmore 1975a, 1976, 1977b, 1982, 1985). His
motivating example was the Commercial Event frame, in which a seller sells goods
to a buyer, the buyer thus buying the goods that cost a certain amount by paying a
price charged by the seller. The definition of each of these verbs (buy, sell, cost, pay,
charge), is interrelated by virtue of their joint association with a single kind of event
or scenario. The meaning of each word draws in the entire frame, and by using (or
hearing) the word, a language user necessarily activates the entire frame. As Fillmore
put it:
If I tell you that I bought a new pair of shoes, you do not know where I bought them or
how much they cost, but you know, by virtue of the frame I have introduced into our
discourse, that there have got to be answers to those questions. (Fillmore 1976, p. 29)
Fillmore also emphasized the way that frames could represent perspectives on events,
such that verbs like sell or pay emphasize different aspects of the same event, or that the
differences between alternative senses of the same word might come from their drawing
on different frames. Fillmore’s linguistic interpretation of frames influenced work in
artificial intelligence on knowledge representation like KRL (Bobrow and Winograd
1977), and the perspective-taking aspect of frames had a strong influence on work on
framing in linguistics and politics (Lakoff 2010).
In 1988 Fillmore taught at the computational linguistics summer school in Pisa run
by the late Antonio Zampolli and met the lexicographer Beryl T. Atkins. The two began
a collaboration to produce a frame description for the verb risk based on corpus evidence
(Fillmore and Atkins 1992). This work, including an invited talk at ACL 1991 (Fillmore
and Atkins 1991), influenced the development of other projects in corpus-based lexical
semantics (Kipper, Dang, and Palmer 2000; Kipper et al. 2008).
Fillmore became interested in this idea that corpus linguistics, lexicography, and
lexical semantics could fruitfully be combined (Fillmore 1992) and when he officially
retired from UC Berkeley in 1995 he moved to the International Computer Science
Institute (ICSI) in Berkeley (although still teaching at UC Berkeley part-time) and began
work on the FrameNet project of computational corpus lexicography that combined his
early ideas on semantic roles with his later work on frames and his recent interest in
corpus lexicography.
The idea of FrameNet was to build a large set of frames, each of which consisted
of lists of constitutive roles or “frame elements”: sets of words that evoke the frame,
grammatical information expressing how each frame element is realized in the sentence,
and semantic relations between frames and between frame elements. Corpora were
annotated with the evoking words, frames, and frame elements (Baker, Fillmore, and
Lowe 1998; Fillmore, Johnson, and Petruck 2003; Fillmore and Baker 2009).
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.949755">
727
</page>
<note confidence="0.315727">
Computational Linguistics Volume 40, Number 3
</note>
<bodyText confidence="0.999626708333333">
Over the next 20 years until his death, Fillmore and his students and colleagues,
especially under the direction of Collin Baker, proceeded to create the frames and hand-
annotate the corpora. This period of his career was a productive and enjoyable one for
Fillmore. In an interview for the ICSI Newsletter, he said
“The happiest time of my career has been here at ICSI, where FrameNet has made it
possible for me to work with a team of bright young people on a continuing basis
doing work that I’ll never lose interest in.”
The combination of rich linguistic annotation and corpus-based approach
instantiated in FrameNet, together with the PropBank semantic-role-labeled corpus
created soon afterwards by Martha Palmer and colleagues (Palmer, Kingsbury, and
Gildea 2005), led to a revival of automatic approaches to semantic role labeling, first
on FrameNet (Gildea and Jurafsky 2000) and then on PropBank data (Gildea and
Palmer 2002, inter alia). The problem first addressed in the 1970s by hand-written rules
was thus now generally recast as one of supervised machine learning. The resulting
plethora of systems for performing automatic semantic role labeling (see the surveys
in Palmer, Gildea, and Xue (2010) and M`arquez et al. (2008)) have been applied widely
to improve the state of the art in tasks across NLP such as question answering (Shen
and Lapata 2007; Surdeanu, Ciaramita, and Zaragoza 2011) and machine translation
(Liu and Gildea 2010; Lo et al. 2013). Fillmore’s FrameNet project also led to the
development of FrameNets for many other languages including Spanish, German,
Japanese, Portuguese, Italian, and Chinese. And in a perhaps appropriate return to the
discovery procedures that first inspired Fillmore, modern work has focused on ways
to induce semantic roles from corpora without role annotation (Swier and Stevenson
2004; Chambers and Jurafsky 2009, 2011; Lang and Lapata 2014).
In addition to his work in semantics, Fillmore had significant contributions to
syntax and pragmatics, including the influential Santa Cruz Lectures on Deixis (Fillmore
1975b) and a long-standing research project in developing Construction Grammar, a
theory—or perhaps more accurately family of theories—that represented a grammar
as a collection of constructions, pairings of meaning, and form (Fillmore, Kay, and
O’Connor 1988). He also contributed to the application of linguistics to other disciplines
including cognitive science, education, and law. Ackerman, Kay, and O’Connor (2014)
offer more discussion of these aspects of Fillmore’s work.
Fillmore was much honored during his career; he was a fellow of the American
Academy of Arts and Sciences, served as president of the Linguistic Society of America,
was awarded an honorary doctorate from the University of Chicago, had festschrifts
and conferences in his honor, received the ACL lifetime achievement award in 2012 (see
the text of his acceptance speech in Fillmore [2012]) and, together with Collin Baker,
the Antonio Zampolli Prize from ELRA in 2012. Nonetheless, he was unpretentious
(universally referred to even by his undergraduates as “Chuck”), modest, embarrassed
by compliments, and generally referred to himself light-heartedly as an Ordinary Work-
ing Linguist. His Minnesota background (he was Norwegian on his mother’s side)
always led to Lake Wobegon comparisons, especially given his often bemused smile and
wry deadpan wit. His colleague George Lakoff tells the story: “When he first came to
Berkeley in 1971, he encountered a culture defined by the then-commonplace expres-
sion, ‘Let it all hang out.’ His response was to wear a button saying, ‘Tuck it all back in.’”
Fillmore was also a favorite teacher and mentor who enjoyed working with what
he often capitalized as “Young People”; and was deeply respected for his brilliance,
careful attention to detail, and encyclopedic knowledge of language, and universally
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.958769">
728
</page>
<figure confidence="0.286596">
Jurafsky Obituary
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.8988005">
beloved for his warmth, generosity, and patience. He is survived by his beloved wife
Lily Wong Fillmore, a retired Berkeley linguist and Education professor, their children
and grandchildren, and a wide community of fond former colleagues, students, and
collaborators, among whom I am proud to include myself.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.996575" genericHeader="abstract">
References
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.965927863636364">
Ackerman, Farrell, Paul Kay, and
Mary Catherine O’Connor. 2014.
Charles J. Fillmore. Language, 90(3).
Baker, Collin F., Charles J. Fillmore, and
John B. Lowe. 1998. The Berkeley
FrameNet project. In Proceedings of
ACL-COLING 1998, pages 86–90.
Bar-Hillel, Yehoshua. 1960. The present
status of automatic translation of
languages. Advances in computers,
1(1):91–163.
Bobrow, Daniel G., Ronald M. Kaplan,
Martin Kay, Donald A. Norman,
Henry Thompson, and Terry Winograd.
1977. GUS-1, a frame driven dialog
system. Artificial Intelligence,
8(2):155–173.
Bobrow, Daniel G. and Donald A. Norman.
1975. Some principles of memory
schemata. In Daniel G. Bobrow and
Allan Collins, editors, Representation
and Understanding. Academic Press.
</reference>
<bodyText confidence="0.943716049382716">
Bobrow, Daniel G. and Terry Winograd.
1977. An overview of KRL: A knowledge
representation language. Cognitive Science,
1:3–46.
Chambers, Nathanael and Dan Jurafsky.
2009. Unsupervised learning of narrative
schemas and their participants. In ACL
IJCNLP 2009.
Chambers, Nathanael and Dan Jurafsky.
2011. Template-based information
extraction without the templates.
In Proceedings of ACL 2011.
DeJong, Gerald F. 1982. An overview
of the FRUMP system. In Wendy G.
Lehnert and Martin H. Ringle,
editors, Strategies for Natural Language
Processing. Lawrence Erlbaum,
pages 149–176.
Fillmore, Charles J. 1962. Indirect object
constructions in English and the ordering
of transformations. Technical Report
Report No. 1, The Ohio State University
Research Foundation Project on Linguistic
Analysis.
Fillmore, Charles J. 1963. The position of
embedding transformations in a grammar.
Word, 19(2):208–231.
Fillmore, Charles J. 1965. Indirect Object
Constructions in English and the Ordering
of Transformations. Mouton.
Fillmore, Charles J. 1966. A proposal
concerning English prepositions. In
Francis P. Dinneen, editor,17th annual
Round Table., volume 17 of Monograph
Series on Language and Linguistics.
Georgetown University Press,
Washington D.C., pages 19–34.
Fillmore, Charles J. 1968. The case for
case. In Emmon W. Bach and Robert T.
Harms, editors, Universals in Linguistic
Theory. Holt, Rinehart &amp; Winston,
pages 1–88.
Fillmore, Charles J. 1971. Some problems
for case grammar. In R. J. O’Brien, editor,
22nd annual Round Table. Linguistics:
developments of the sixties – viewpoints of the
seventies, volume 24 of Monograph Series
on Language and Linguistics. Georgetown
University Press, Washington D.C.,
pages 35–56.
Fillmore, Charles J. 1975a. An alternative to
checklist theories of meaning. In BLS-75,
Berkeley, CA.
Fillmore, Charles J. 1975b. Lectures on deixis.
Indiana University Linguistics Club,
Bloomington, IN.
Fillmore, Charles J. 1976. Frame semantics
and the nature of language. In Annals
of the New York Academy of Sciences:
Conference on the Origin and Development
of Language and Speech, volume 280,
pages 20–32.
Fillmore, Charles J. 1977a. The case for case
reopened. In Peter Cole and Jerrold M.
Sadock, editors, Syntax and Semantics
Volume 8: Grammatical Relations.
Academic Press.
Fillmore, Charles J. 1977b. Scenes-and-frames
semantics. In Antonio Zampolli, editor,
Linguistic Structures Processing. North
Holland, pages 55–79.
Fillmore, Charles J. 1982. Frame semantics. In
Linguistics in the Morning Calm. Hanshin,
Seoul, pages 111–138. Linguistics Society
of Korea.
Fillmore, Charles J. 1985. Frames and the
semantics of understanding. Quaderni di
Semantica, VI(2):222–254.
Fillmore, Charles J. 1992. “Corpus
linguistics” vs. “computer-aided
armchair linguistics”. In Directions in
</bodyText>
<note confidence="0.34146">
Corpus Linguistics: Proceedings from
a 1991 Nobel Symposium on Corpus
</note>
<page confidence="0.987497">
729
</page>
<note confidence="0.620595">
Computational Linguistics Volume 40, Number 3
</note>
<reference confidence="0.908674416666667">
Linguistics, pages 35–66. Mouton de
Gruyter.
Fillmore, Charles J. 2003. Valency and
semantic roles: the concept of deep
structure case. In Vilmos ´Agel,
Ludwig M. Eichinger, Hans Werner
Eroms, Peter Hellwig, Hans J¨urgen
Heringer, and Henning Lobin, editors,
Dependenz und Valenz: Ein internationales
Handbuch der zeitgen¨ossischen Forschung.
Walter de Gruyter, chapter 36,
pages 457–475.
Fillmore, Charles J. 2012. Encounters with
language. Computational Linguistics,
38(4):701–718.
Fillmore, Charles J. and Beryl T. Atkins.
1991. Word meaning: Starting where
the MRDs stop. Invited talk at
ACL 1991.
Fillmore, Charles J. and Beryl T. Atkins.
1992. Towards a frame-based lexicon: The
semantics of RISK and its neighbors.
In Adrienne Lehrer and E. Feder
Kittay, editors, Frames, Fields, and
Contrasts. Lawrence Erlbaum,
pages 75–102.
Fillmore, Charles J. and Collin F. Baker.
2009. A frames approach to semantic
analysis. In Bernd Heine and Heiko
Narrog, editors, The Oxford Handbook of
Linguistic Analysis. Oxford University
Press, pages 313–340.
Fillmore, Charles J., Christopher R.
Johnson, and Miriam R. L. Petruck.
2003. Background to FrameNet.
International journal of lexicography,
16(3):235–250.
Fillmore, Charles J., Paul Kay, and
Mary Catherine O’Connor. 1988.
Regularity and idiomaticity in
grammatical constructions: The
case of Let Alone. Language,
64(3):501–538.
Gildea, Daniel and Daniel Jurafsky.
2000. Automatic labeling of semantic
roles. In ACL-00, pages 512–520,
Hong Kong.
Gildea, Daniel and Martha Palmer. 2002. The
necessity of syntactic parsing for predicate
argument recognition. In ACL-02,
Philadelphia, PA.
Goffman, Erving. 1974. Frame analysis: An
essay on the organization of experience.
Harvard University Press.
Hendrix, Gary G., Craig W. Thompson,
and Jonathan Slocum. 1973. Language
processing via canonical verbs and
semantic models. In Proceedings of
IJCAI-73.
Hymes, Dell. 1974. Ways of speaking.
In Richard Bauman and Joel Sherzer,
editors, Explorations in the ethnography of
speaking. Cambridge University Press,
pages 433–451.
Kipper, Karin, Hoa T. Dang, and Martha
Palmer. 2000. Class-based construction
of a verb lexicon. In AAAI/IAAI,
pages 691–696.
Kipper, Karin, Anna Korhonen, Neville
Ryant, and Martha Palmer. 2008. A
large-scale classification of English
verbs. Language Resources and Evaluation,
42(1):21–40.
Lakoff, George. 2010. Moral politics: How
liberals and conservatives think. University
of Chicago Press.
Lang, Joel and Mirella Lapata. 2014.
Similarity-driven semantic role induction
via graph partitioning. Computational
Linguistics, 40(3):633–669.
Levin, Beth. 1977. Mapping sentences
to case frames. Technical Report 167,
MIT AI Laboratory. AI Working
Paper 143.
</reference>
<bodyText confidence="0.878085333333333">
Liu, Ding and Daniel Gildea. 2010. Semantic
role features for machine translation.
In Proceedings of COLING 2010,
pages 716–724.
Lo, Chi-kiu, Karteek Addanki, Markus
Saers, and Dekai Wu. 2013. Improving
machine translation by training against
an automatic semantic frame based
evaluation metric. In Proceedings of
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.61869" genericHeader="categories and subject descriptors">
ACL 2013.
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.980328208333333">
Marcus, Mitchell P. 1980. A Theory of
Syntactic Recognition for Natural Language.
MIT Press.
M`arquez, Lluis, Xavier Carreras, Kenneth C
Litkowski, and Suzanne Stevenson. 2008.
Semantic role labeling: An introduction to
the special issue. Computational linguistics,
34(2):145–159.
Minsky, Marvin. 1974. A framework for
representing knowledge. Technical
Report 306, MIT AI Laboratory.
Memo 306.
Nash-Webber, Bonnie L. 1975. The role
of semantics in automatic speech
understanding. In Daniel G. Bobrow and
Allan Collins, editors, Representation
and Understanding. Academic Press,
pages 351–382.
Palmer, Martha, Daniel Gildea, and
Nianwen Xue. 2010. Semantic role
labeling. Synthesis Lectures on Human
Language Technologies, 3(1):1–103.
Palmer, Martha, Paul Kingsbury, and
Daniel Gildea. 2005. The proposition
</reference>
<page confidence="0.960204">
730
</page>
<figure confidence="0.396958">
Jurafsky Obituary
</figure>
<reference confidence="0.999638136363637">
bank: An annotated corpus of semantic
roles. Computational Linguistics,
31(1):71–106.
Schank, Roger C. and Robert P. Abelson.
1975. Scripts, plans, and knowledge. In
Proceedings of IJCAI-75, pages 151–157.
Schank, Roger C. and Robert P. Abelson.
1977. Scripts, Plans, Goals and
Understanding. Lawrence Erlbaum.
Shen, Dan and Mirella Lapata. 2007.
Using semantic roles to improve
question answering. In EMNLP-CoNLL,
pages 12–21.
Simmons, Robert F. 1973. Semantic
networks: Their computation and use
for understanding English sentences.
In Roger C. Schank and Kenneth Mark
Colby, editors, Computer Models of Thought
and Language. W.H. Freeman and Co.,
pages 61–113.
Surdeanu, Mihai, Massimiliano Ciaramita,
and Hugo Zaragoza. 2011. Learning to
rank answers to non-factoid questions
from web collections. Computational
Linguistics, 37(2):351–383.
Swier, R. and S. Stevenson. 2004.
Unsupervised semantic role labelling.
In EMNLP 2004, pages 95–102.
Tannen, Deborah. 1979. What’s in a frame?
Surface evidence for underlying
expectations. In Roy Freedle, editor,
New Directions in Discourse Processing.
Ablex, pages 137–181.
Tesni`ere, Lucien. 1959. ´El´ements de Syntaxe
Structurale. Librairie C. Klincksieck,
Paris.
Wilks, Yorick.1973. An artificial intelligence
approach to machine translation.
In Roger C. Schank and Kenneth Mark
Colby, editors, Computer Models of
Thought and Language. W.H. Freeman,
pages 114–151.
Winston, Patrick H. 1977. Artificial
Intelligence. Addison Wesley.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.998008">
731
</page>
</variant>
</algorithm>
<algorithm name="ParsHed" version="110505">
<variant no="0" confidence="0.000000">
<title confidence="0.99623">Obituary</title>
<author confidence="0.998732">Charles J Fillmore Dan Jurafsky</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.99964">Stanford University</affiliation>
<author confidence="0.808689">Charles J Fillmore died at his home in San Francisco on February</author>
<abstract confidence="0.984590284615384">cancer. He was 84 years old. Fillmore was one of the world’s pre-eminent scholars of lexical meaning and its relationship with context, grammar, corpora, and computation, and his work had an enormous impact on computational linguistics. His early theoretical work in the 1960s, 1970s, and 1980s on case grammar and then frame semantics significantly influenced computational linguistics, AI, and knowledge representation. More recent work in the last two decades on FrameNet, a computational lexicon and annotated corpus, influenced corpus linguistics and computational lexicography, and led to modern natural language understanding tasks like semantic role labeling. Fillmore was born and raised in St. Paul, Minnesota, and studied linguistics at the University of Minnesota. As an undergraduate he worked on a pre-computational Latin corpus linguistics project, alphabetizing index cards and building concordances. During his service in the Army in the early 1950s he was stationed for three years in Japan. After his service he became the first US soldier to be discharged locally in Japan, and stayed for three years studying Japanese. He supported himself by teaching English, pioneering a way to make ends meet that afterwards became popular with generations of young Americans abroad. In 1957 he moved back to the United States to attend graduate school at the University of Michigan. At Michigan, Fillmore worked on phonetics, phonology, and syntax, first in the American Structuralist tradition of developing what were called “discovery procedures” for linguistic analysis, algorithms for inducing phones or parts of speech. Discovery procedures were thought of as a methodological tool, a formal procedure that linguists could apply to data to discover linguistic structure, for example inducing parts of speech from the slots in “sentence frames” informed by the distribution of surrounding words. Like many linguistic graduate students of the period, he also worked partly on machine translation, and was interviewed at the time by Yehoshua Bar-Hillel, who was touring US machine translation laboratories in preparation for his famous report on the state of MT (Bar-Hillel 1960). in his graduate career, however, Fillmore read Noam Chomsky’s became an immediate proponent of the new transformational grammar. He graduated with his PhD in 1962 and moved to the linguistics department at Ohio State University. In his early work there Fillmore developed a number of early formal properties of generative grammar, such as the idea that rules would re-apply to representations in iterative stages called cycles (Fillmore 1963), a formal mechanism that still plays a role in modern theories of generative grammar. doi:10.1162/COLI a 00201 © 2014 Association for Computational Linguistics Computational Linguistics Volume 40, Number 3 But his greatest impact on computational linguistics came from the line of research began with his early work on grammar 1966, 1968, 1971, 1977a). Fillmore had become interested in argument structure by studying Lucien Tesni`ere’s de Syntaxe Structurale 1959) in which the term ‘dependency’ was introduced and the foundations were laid for dependency grammar. Like many transformational grammarians of the time, Fillmore began by trying to capture the relationships between distinct formal patterns with systematically related meanings; and he became interested in the different ways of expressing the object and recipient of transfer in sentences like “He gave a book to me” and “He gave me book” (Fillmore 1962, 1965), a phenomenon that became known as He then expanded to the more general goal of representing how the participants in an event are expressed syntactically, as in these two sentences about an event of a. The janitor will open the door with this key b. This key will open the door noticed that despite the differing syntactic structure, in both sentences the role of the the action and role of the and suggested that such abstract roles could constitute a shallow level of meaning representation. Following Tesni`ere’s terminology, Fillmore first referred to argument roles as 1966) but quickly switched to the term (see Fillmore (2003)) and proposed a universal list of semantic roles or cases (Agent, Patient, Instrument, etc.), that could be taken on by the arguments of predicates. Verbs would be listed in the lexicon with their ‘case frame’, the list of obligatory (or optional) case arguments. The idea that semantic roles could provide an intermediate level of semantic representation that could help map from syntactic parse structures to deeper, more fully-specified representations of meaning was quickly adopted in natural language processing, and systems for extracting case frames were created for machine translation (Wilks 1973), question-answering (Hendrix, Thompson, and Slocum 1973), spoken-language understanding (Nash-Webber 1975), and dialogue systems (Bobrow et al. 1977). General-purpose semantic role labelers were developed to map to case representations via ATNs (Simmons 1973) or, from parse trees, by using dictionaries with verb-specific case frames (Levin 1977; Marcus 1980). By 1977 case representation was widely used and taught in natural language processing and artificial intelligence, and was described as a standard component of natural language understanding in the edition of Winston’s (1977) textbook In 1971 Fillmore joined the linguistics faculty at the University of California, Berkeley, and by the mid-1970s he began to expand his ideas on case. He arrived at a more general model of semantic representation, one that expressed the background contexts or perspectives by which a word or a case role could be defined. He called this representation a and later described the intuition as follows: “The idea behind frame semantics is that speakers are aware of possibly quite complex situation types, packages of connected expectations, that go by various names—frames, schemas, scenarios, scripts, cultural narratives, memes—and the words in our language are understood with such frames as their presupposed background.” (Fillmore 2012, p. 712) 726 Jurafsky Obituary He described the name as coming from “the pre-transformationalist view of sentence as consisting of a frame and a substitution list,” but the word to be in the air for a suite of related notions proposed at about the same time by Minsky (1974), Hymes (1974), and Goffman (1974), as well as related notions with other names and Abelson 1975) and and Norman 1975) (see Tannen [1979] for a comparison). Fillmore was also influenced by the semantic field theorists and by a visit to the Yale AI lab where he took notice of the lists of slots and fillers used by early information extraction systems like DeJong (1982) and Schank and Abelson (1977). Fillmore’s version of this new idea—more linguistic than other manifestations, focusing on the way that words are associated with frames—was expressed in a series of papers starting in the mid-1970’s (Fillmore 1975a, 1976, 1977b, 1982, 1985). His example was the Commercial Event frame, in which a seller a buyer, the buyer thus goods that certain amount by the seller. The definition of each of these verbs sell, cost, pay, is interrelated by virtue of their joint association with a single kind of event or scenario. The meaning of each word draws in the entire frame, and by using (or hearing) the word, a language user necessarily activates the entire frame. As Fillmore put it: If I tell you that I bought a new pair of shoes, you do not know where I bought them or how much they cost, but you know, by virtue of the frame I have introduced into our discourse, that there have got to be answers to those questions. (Fillmore 1976, p. 29) also emphasized the way that frames could represent events, that verbs like different aspects of the same event, or that the differences between alternative senses of the same word might come from their drawing on different frames. Fillmore’s linguistic interpretation of frames influenced work in artificial intelligence on knowledge representation like KRL (Bobrow and Winograd 1977), and the perspective-taking aspect of frames had a strong influence on work on framing in linguistics and politics (Lakoff 2010). In 1988 Fillmore taught at the computational linguistics summer school in Pisa run by the late Antonio Zampolli and met the lexicographer Beryl T. Atkins. The two began collaboration to produce a frame description for the verb on corpus evidence (Fillmore and Atkins 1992). This work, including an invited talk at ACL 1991 (Fillmore and Atkins 1991), influenced the development of other projects in corpus-based lexical semantics (Kipper, Dang, and Palmer 2000; Kipper et al. 2008). Fillmore became interested in this idea that corpus linguistics, lexicography, and lexical semantics could fruitfully be combined (Fillmore 1992) and when he officially retired from UC Berkeley in 1995 he moved to the International Computer Science Institute (ICSI) in Berkeley (although still teaching at UC Berkeley part-time) and began work on the FrameNet project of computational corpus lexicography that combined his early ideas on semantic roles with his later work on frames and his recent interest in corpus lexicography. The idea of FrameNet was to build a large set of frames, each of which consisted of lists of constitutive roles or “frame elements”: sets of words that evoke the frame, grammatical information expressing how each frame element is realized in the sentence, and semantic relations between frames and between frame elements. Corpora were</abstract>
<note confidence="0.720999">annotated with the evoking words, frames, and frame elements (Baker, Fillmore, and Lowe 1998; Fillmore, Johnson, and Petruck 2003; Fillmore and Baker 2009). 727 Computational Linguistics Volume 40, Number 3</note>
<abstract confidence="0.990431425925926">Over the next 20 years until his death, Fillmore and his students and colleagues, especially under the direction of Collin Baker, proceeded to create the frames and handannotate the corpora. This period of his career was a productive and enjoyable one for Fillmore. In an interview for the ICSI Newsletter, he said “The happiest time of my career has been here at ICSI, where FrameNet has made it possible for me to work with a team of bright young people on a continuing basis doing work that I’ll never lose interest in.” The combination of rich linguistic annotation and corpus-based approach instantiated in FrameNet, together with the PropBank semantic-role-labeled corpus created soon afterwards by Martha Palmer and colleagues (Palmer, Kingsbury, and Gildea 2005), led to a revival of automatic approaches to semantic role labeling, first on FrameNet (Gildea and Jurafsky 2000) and then on PropBank data (Gildea and Palmer 2002, inter alia). The problem first addressed in the 1970s by hand-written rules was thus now generally recast as one of supervised machine learning. The resulting plethora of systems for performing automatic semantic role labeling (see the surveys in Palmer, Gildea, and Xue (2010) and M`arquez et al. (2008)) have been applied widely to improve the state of the art in tasks across NLP such as question answering (Shen and Lapata 2007; Surdeanu, Ciaramita, and Zaragoza 2011) and machine translation (Liu and Gildea 2010; Lo et al. 2013). Fillmore’s FrameNet project also led to the development of FrameNets for many other languages including Spanish, German, Japanese, Portuguese, Italian, and Chinese. And in a perhaps appropriate return to the discovery procedures that first inspired Fillmore, modern work has focused on ways to induce semantic roles from corpora without role annotation (Swier and Stevenson 2004; Chambers and Jurafsky 2009, 2011; Lang and Lapata 2014). In addition to his work in semantics, Fillmore had significant contributions to syntax and pragmatics, including the influential Santa Cruz Lectures on Deixis (Fillmore 1975b) and a long-standing research project in developing Construction Grammar, a theory—or perhaps more accurately family of theories—that represented a grammar as a collection of constructions, pairings of meaning, and form (Fillmore, Kay, and O’Connor 1988). He also contributed to the application of linguistics to other disciplines including cognitive science, education, and law. Ackerman, Kay, and O’Connor (2014) offer more discussion of these aspects of Fillmore’s work. Fillmore was much honored during his career; he was a fellow of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences, served as president of the Linguistic Society of America, was awarded an honorary doctorate from the University of Chicago, had festschrifts and conferences in his honor, received the ACL lifetime achievement award in 2012 (see the text of his acceptance speech in Fillmore [2012]) and, together with Collin Baker, the Antonio Zampolli Prize from ELRA in 2012. Nonetheless, he was unpretentious (universally referred to even by his undergraduates as “Chuck”), modest, embarrassed by compliments, and generally referred to himself light-heartedly as an Ordinary Working Linguist. His Minnesota background (he was Norwegian on his mother’s side) always led to Lake Wobegon comparisons, especially given his often bemused smile and wry deadpan wit. His colleague George Lakoff tells the story: “When he first came to Berkeley in 1971, he encountered a culture defined by the then-commonplace expression, ‘Let it all hang out.’ His response was to wear a button saying, ‘Tuck it all back in.’” Fillmore was also a favorite teacher and mentor who enjoyed working with what he often capitalized as “Young People”; and was deeply respected for his brilliance, careful attention to detail, and encyclopedic knowledge of language, and universally 728 Jurafsky Obituary beloved for his warmth, generosity, and patience. He is survived by his beloved wife Lily Wong Fillmore, a retired Berkeley linguist and Education professor, their children and grandchildren, and a wide community of fond former colleagues, students, and collaborators, among whom I am proud to include myself.</abstract>
<note confidence="0.812469">References Ackerman, Farrell, Paul Kay, and Mary Catherine O’Connor. 2014. J. Fillmore. 90(3). Baker, Collin F., Charles J. Fillmore, and John B. Lowe. 1998. The Berkeley</note>
<abstract confidence="0.944806666666667">project. In of pages 86–90. Bar-Hillel, Yehoshua. 1960. The present status of automatic translation of in 1(1):91–163.</abstract>
<author confidence="0.8354065">Daniel G Bobrow</author>
<author confidence="0.8354065">Ronald M Kaplan</author>
<author confidence="0.8354065">Martin Kay</author>
<author confidence="0.8354065">Donald A Norman</author>
<note confidence="0.8396446">Henry Thompson, and Terry Winograd. 1977. GUS-1, a frame driven dialog 8(2):155–173. Bobrow, Daniel G. and Donald A. Norman. 1975. Some principles of memory schemata. In Daniel G. Bobrow and Collins, editors, Academic Press. Bobrow, Daniel G. and Terry Winograd. 1977. An overview of KRL: A knowledge</note>
<abstract confidence="0.864364090909091">language. 1:3–46. Chambers, Nathanael and Dan Jurafsky. 2009. Unsupervised learning of narrative and their participants. In Chambers, Nathanael and Dan Jurafsky. 2011. Template-based information extraction without the templates. of ACL DeJong, Gerald F. 1982. An overview of the FRUMP system. In Wendy G.</abstract>
<author confidence="0.514132">Lehnert</author>
<author confidence="0.514132">Martin H Ringle</author>
<title confidence="0.475684">for Natural Language</title>
<author confidence="0.550998">Lawrence Erlbaum</author>
<note confidence="0.846778142857143">pages 149–176. Fillmore, Charles J. 1962. Indirect object constructions in English and the ordering of transformations. Technical Report Report No. 1, The Ohio State University Research Foundation Project on Linguistic Analysis. Fillmore, Charles J. 1963. The position of embedding transformations in a grammar. 19(2):208–231. Charles J. 1965. Object Constructions in English and the Ordering Mouton. Fillmore, Charles J. 1966. A proposal</note>
<abstract confidence="0.4993745">concerning English prepositions. In P. Dinneen, annual volume 17 of on Language and</abstract>
<affiliation confidence="0.992265">Georgetown University Press,</affiliation>
<address confidence="0.8843145">Washington D.C., pages 19–34. Fillmore, Charles J. 1968. The case for</address>
<author confidence="0.882411">In Emmon W Bach</author>
<author confidence="0.882411">T Robert</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.434238">editors, in Linguistic Holt, Rinehart &amp; Winston,</affiliation>
<note confidence="0.7347196">pages 1–88. Fillmore, Charles J. 1971. Some problems for case grammar. In R. J. O’Brien, editor, 22nd annual Round Table. Linguistics: developments of the sixties – viewpoints of the volume 24 of Series Language and Georgetown University Press, Washington D.C., pages 35–56. Fillmore, Charles J. 1975a. An alternative to</note>
<affiliation confidence="0.62033">theories of meaning. In</affiliation>
<address confidence="0.74158">Berkeley, CA.</address>
<author confidence="0.893899">Charles J b on</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.999962">Indiana University Linguistics Club,</affiliation>
<address confidence="0.992125">Bloomington, IN.</address>
<note confidence="0.72242996969697">Fillmore, Charles J. 1976. Frame semantics the nature of language. In of the New York Academy of Sciences: Conference on the Origin and Development Language and volume 280, pages 20–32. Fillmore, Charles J. 1977a. The case for case reopened. In Peter Cole and Jerrold M. editors, and Semantics 8: Grammatical Academic Press. Fillmore, Charles J. 1977b. Scenes-and-frames semantics. In Antonio Zampolli, editor, Structures North Holland, pages 55–79. Fillmore, Charles J. 1982. Frame semantics. In in the Morning Hanshin, Seoul, pages 111–138. Linguistics Society of Korea. Fillmore, Charles J. 1985. Frames and the of understanding. di VI(2):222–254. Fillmore, Charles J. 1992. “Corpus linguistics” vs. “computer-aided linguistics”. In in Corpus Linguistics: Proceedings from a 1991 Nobel Symposium on Corpus 729 Computational Linguistics Volume 40, Number 3 pages 35–66. Mouton de Gruyter. Fillmore, Charles J. 2003. Valency and semantic roles: the concept of deep</note>
<author confidence="0.778575666666667">In Vilmos ´Agel</author>
<author confidence="0.778575666666667">Ludwig M Eichinger</author>
<author confidence="0.778575666666667">Hans Werner Eroms</author>
<author confidence="0.778575666666667">Peter Hellwig</author>
<author confidence="0.778575666666667">Hans J¨urgen</author>
<email confidence="0.480597">Heringer,andHenningLobin,editors,</email>
<abstract confidence="0.828570846153846">Dependenz und Valenz: Ein internationales der zeitgen¨ossischen Walter de Gruyter, chapter 36, pages 457–475. Fillmore, Charles J. 2012. Encounters with 38(4):701–718. Fillmore, Charles J. and Beryl T. Atkins. 1991. Word meaning: Starting where the MRDs stop. Invited talk at ACL 1991. Fillmore, Charles J. and Beryl T. Atkins. 1992. Towards a frame-based lexicon: The semantics of RISK and its neighbors.</abstract>
<note confidence="0.524763666666667">In Adrienne Lehrer and E. Feder editors, Fields, and Lawrence Erlbaum, pages 75–102. Fillmore, Charles J. and Collin F. Baker. 2009. A frames approach to semantic</note>
<author confidence="0.309498">In Bernd Heine</author>
<author confidence="0.309498">Heiko</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.692193">editors, Oxford Handbook of Oxford University</affiliation>
<note confidence="0.950144066666667">Press, pages 313–340. Fillmore, Charles J., Christopher R. Johnson, and Miriam R. L. Petruck. 2003. Background to FrameNet. journal of 16(3):235–250. Fillmore, Charles J., Paul Kay, and Mary Catherine O’Connor. 1988. Regularity and idiomaticity in grammatical constructions: The of Let Alone. 64(3):501–538. Gildea, Daniel and Daniel Jurafsky. 2000. Automatic labeling of semantic In pages 512–520,</note>
<address confidence="0.3618535">Hong Kong. Gildea, Daniel and Martha Palmer. 2002. The</address>
<abstract confidence="0.498571909090909">necessity of syntactic parsing for predicate recognition. In Philadelphia, PA. Erving. 1974. analysis: An on the organization of Harvard University Press. Hendrix, Gary G., Craig W. Thompson, and Jonathan Slocum. 1973. Language processing via canonical verbs and models. In of Hymes, Dell. 1974. Ways of speaking.</abstract>
<author confidence="0.641526">In Richard Bauman</author>
<author confidence="0.641526">Joel Sherzer</author>
<degree confidence="0.560766">in the ethnography of</degree>
<affiliation confidence="0.983934">Cambridge University Press,</affiliation>
<note confidence="0.7575675">pages 433–451. Kipper, Karin, Hoa T. Dang, and Martha Palmer. 2000. Class-based construction a verb lexicon. In pages 691–696. Kipper, Karin, Anna Korhonen, Neville Ryant, and Martha Palmer. 2008. A large-scale classification of English Resources and 42(1):21–40.</note>
<author confidence="0.846489">politics How</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.8562475">and conservatives University of Chicago Press.</affiliation>
<address confidence="0.847468">Lang, Joel and Mirella Lapata. 2014.</address>
<abstract confidence="0.707711333333333">Similarity-driven semantic role induction graph partitioning. 40(3):633–669. Levin, Beth. 1977. Mapping sentences to case frames. Technical Report 167, MIT AI Laboratory. AI Working Paper 143. Liu, Ding and Daniel Gildea. 2010. Semantic role features for machine translation. of COLING pages 716–724. Lo, Chi-kiu, Karteek Addanki, Markus Saers, and Dekai Wu. 2013. Improving machine translation by training against an automatic semantic frame based</abstract>
<note confidence="0.431681333333333">metric. In of Mitchell P. 1980. Theory of Recognition for Natural MIT Press. M`arquez, Lluis, Xavier Carreras, Kenneth C Litkowski, and Suzanne Stevenson. 2008.</note>
</variant>
</algorithm>
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Farrell Ackerman</author>
<author>Paul Kay</author>
<author>Mary Catherine O’Connor</author>
</authors>
<date>2014</date>
<journal>Charles J. Fillmore. Language,</journal>
<volume>90</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<marker>Ackerman, Kay, O’Connor, 2014</marker>
<rawString>Ackerman, Farrell, Paul Kay, and Mary Catherine O’Connor. 2014. Charles J. Fillmore. Language, 90(3).</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Collin F Baker</author>
<author>Charles J Fillmore</author>
<author>John B Lowe</author>
</authors>
<title>The Berkeley FrameNet project.</title>
<date>1998</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of ACL-COLING</booktitle>
<pages>86--90</pages>
<marker>Baker, Fillmore, Lowe, 1998</marker>
<rawString>Baker, Collin F., Charles J. Fillmore, and John B. Lowe. 1998. The Berkeley FrameNet project. In Proceedings of ACL-COLING 1998, pages 86–90.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Yehoshua Bar-Hillel</author>
</authors>
<title>The present status of automatic translation of languages.</title>
<date>1960</date>
<booktitle>Advances in computers,</booktitle>
<pages>1--1</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="2337" citStr="Bar-Hillel 1960" startWordPosition="355" endWordPosition="356">nalysis, algorithms for inducing phones or parts of speech. Discovery procedures were thought of as a methodological tool, a formal procedure that linguists could apply to data to discover linguistic structure, for example inducing parts of speech from the slots in “sentence frames” informed by the distribution of surrounding words. Like many linguistic graduate students of the period, he also worked partly on machine translation, and was interviewed at the time by Yehoshua Bar-Hillel, who was touring US machine translation laboratories in preparation for his famous report on the state of MT (Bar-Hillel 1960). Early in his graduate career, however, Fillmore read Noam Chomsky’s Syntactic Structures and became an immediate proponent of the new transformational grammar. He graduated with his PhD in 1962 and moved to the linguistics department at Ohio State University. In his early work there Fillmore developed a number of early formal properties of generative grammar, such as the idea that rules would re-apply to representations in iterative stages called cycles (Fillmore 1963), a formal mechanism that still plays a role in modern theories of generative grammar. doi:10.1162/COLI a 00201 © 2014 Associ</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Bar-Hillel, 1960</marker>
<rawString>Bar-Hillel, Yehoshua. 1960. The present status of automatic translation of languages. Advances in computers, 1(1):91–163.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Daniel G Bobrow</author>
<author>Ronald M Kaplan</author>
<author>Martin Kay</author>
<author>Donald A Norman</author>
<author>Henry Thompson</author>
<author>Terry Winograd</author>
</authors>
<title>GUS-1, a frame driven dialog system.</title>
<date>1977</date>
<journal>Artificial Intelligence,</journal>
<volume>8</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<contexts>
<context position="5314" citStr="Bobrow et al. 1977" startWordPosition="803" endWordPosition="806">redicates. Verbs would be listed in the lexicon with their ‘case frame’, the list of obligatory (or optional) case arguments. The idea that semantic roles could provide an intermediate level of semantic representation that could help map from syntactic parse structures to deeper, more fully-specified representations of meaning was quickly adopted in natural language processing, and systems for extracting case frames were created for machine translation (Wilks 1973), question-answering (Hendrix, Thompson, and Slocum 1973), spoken-language understanding (Nash-Webber 1975), and dialogue systems (Bobrow et al. 1977). General-purpose semantic role labelers were developed to map to case representations via ATNs (Simmons 1973) or, from parse trees, by using dictionaries with verb-specific case frames (Levin 1977; Marcus 1980). By 1977 case representation was widely used and taught in natural language processing and artificial intelligence, and was described as a standard component of natural language understanding in the first edition of Winston’s (1977) textbook Artificial Intelligence. In 1971 Fillmore joined the linguistics faculty at the University of California, Berkeley, and by the mid-1970s he began </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Bobrow, Kaplan, Kay, Norman, Thompson, Winograd, 1977</marker>
<rawString>Bobrow, Daniel G., Ronald M. Kaplan, Martin Kay, Donald A. Norman, Henry Thompson, and Terry Winograd. 1977. GUS-1, a frame driven dialog system. Artificial Intelligence, 8(2):155–173.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Daniel G Bobrow</author>
<author>Donald A Norman</author>
</authors>
<title>Some principles of memory schemata.</title>
<date>1975</date>
<editor>In Daniel G. Bobrow and Allan Collins, editors, Representation and Understanding.</editor>
<publisher>Academic Press.</publisher>
<contexts>
<context position="6995" citStr="Bobrow and Norman 1975" startWordPosition="1062" endWordPosition="1065">s, schemas, scenarios, scripts, cultural narratives, memes—and the words in our language are understood with such frames as their presupposed background.” (Fillmore 2012, p. 712) 726 Jurafsky Obituary He described the name as coming from “the pre-transformationalist view of sentence structure as consisting of a frame and a substitution list,” but the word frame seemed to be in the air for a suite of related notions proposed at about the same time by Minsky (1974), Hymes (1974), and Goffman (1974), as well as related notions with other names like scripts (Schank and Abelson 1975) and schemata (Bobrow and Norman 1975) (see Tannen [1979] for a comparison). Fillmore was also influenced by the semantic field theorists and by a visit to the Yale AI lab where he took notice of the lists of slots and fillers used by early information extraction systems like DeJong (1982) and Schank and Abelson (1977). Fillmore’s version of this new idea—more linguistic than other manifestations, focusing on the way that words are associated with frames—was expressed in a series of papers starting in the mid-1970’s (Fillmore 1975a, 1976, 1977b, 1982, 1985). His motivating example was the Commercial Event frame, in which a seller </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Bobrow, Norman, 1975</marker>
<rawString>Bobrow, Daniel G. and Donald A. Norman. 1975. Some principles of memory schemata. In Daniel G. Bobrow and Allan Collins, editors, Representation and Understanding. Academic Press.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>Linguistics</author>
</authors>
<pages>35--66</pages>
<note>Mouton de Gruyter.</note>
<marker>Linguistics, </marker>
<rawString>Linguistics, pages 35–66. Mouton de Gruyter.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Charles J Fillmore</author>
</authors>
<title>Valency and semantic roles: the concept of deep structure case.</title>
<date>2003</date>
<booktitle>Dependenz und Valenz: Ein internationales Handbuch der zeitgen¨ossischen Forschung. Walter de Gruyter, chapter 36,</booktitle>
<pages>457--475</pages>
<editor>In Vilmos ´Agel, Ludwig M. Eichinger, Hans Werner Eroms, Peter Hellwig, Hans J¨urgen Heringer, and Henning Lobin, editors,</editor>
<contexts>
<context position="4556" citStr="Fillmore (2003)" startWordPosition="697" endWordPosition="698">are expressed syntactically, as in these two sentences about an event of opening: a. The janitor will open the door with this key b. This key will open the door Fillmore noticed that despite the differing syntactic structure, in both sentences key plays the role of the instrument of the action and door the role of the object, patient, or theme, and suggested that such abstract roles could constitute a shallow level of meaning representation. Following Tesni`ere’s terminology, Fillmore first referred to these argument roles as actants (Fillmore 1966) but quickly switched to the term case, (see Fillmore (2003)) and proposed a universal list of semantic roles or cases (Agent, Patient, Instrument, etc.), that could be taken on by the arguments of predicates. Verbs would be listed in the lexicon with their ‘case frame’, the list of obligatory (or optional) case arguments. The idea that semantic roles could provide an intermediate level of semantic representation that could help map from syntactic parse structures to deeper, more fully-specified representations of meaning was quickly adopted in natural language processing, and systems for extracting case frames were created for machine translation (Wil</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Fillmore, 2003</marker>
<rawString>Fillmore, Charles J. 2003. Valency and semantic roles: the concept of deep structure case. In Vilmos ´Agel, Ludwig M. Eichinger, Hans Werner Eroms, Peter Hellwig, Hans J¨urgen Heringer, and Henning Lobin, editors, Dependenz und Valenz: Ein internationales Handbuch der zeitgen¨ossischen Forschung. Walter de Gruyter, chapter 36, pages 457–475.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Charles J Fillmore</author>
</authors>
<title>Encounters with language.</title>
<date>2012</date>
<journal>Computational Linguistics,</journal>
<volume>38</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<contexts>
<context position="6541" citStr="Fillmore 2012" startWordPosition="987" endWordPosition="988">ideas on case. He arrived at a more general model of semantic representation, one that expressed the background contexts or perspectives by which a word or a case role could be defined. He called this new representation a frame, and later described the intuition as follows: “The idea behind frame semantics is that speakers are aware of possibly quite complex situation types, packages of connected expectations, that go by various names—frames, schemas, scenarios, scripts, cultural narratives, memes—and the words in our language are understood with such frames as their presupposed background.” (Fillmore 2012, p. 712) 726 Jurafsky Obituary He described the name as coming from “the pre-transformationalist view of sentence structure as consisting of a frame and a substitution list,” but the word frame seemed to be in the air for a suite of related notions proposed at about the same time by Minsky (1974), Hymes (1974), and Goffman (1974), as well as related notions with other names like scripts (Schank and Abelson 1975) and schemata (Bobrow and Norman 1975) (see Tannen [1979] for a comparison). Fillmore was also influenced by the semantic field theorists and by a visit to the Yale AI lab where he too</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Fillmore, 2012</marker>
<rawString>Fillmore, Charles J. 2012. Encounters with language. Computational Linguistics, 38(4):701–718.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Charles J Fillmore</author>
<author>Beryl T Atkins</author>
</authors>
<title>Word meaning: Starting where the MRDs stop. Invited talk at ACL</title>
<date>1991</date>
<contexts>
<context position="9237" citStr="Fillmore and Atkins 1991" startWordPosition="1437" endWordPosition="1440"> interpretation of frames influenced work in artificial intelligence on knowledge representation like KRL (Bobrow and Winograd 1977), and the perspective-taking aspect of frames had a strong influence on work on framing in linguistics and politics (Lakoff 2010). In 1988 Fillmore taught at the computational linguistics summer school in Pisa run by the late Antonio Zampolli and met the lexicographer Beryl T. Atkins. The two began a collaboration to produce a frame description for the verb risk based on corpus evidence (Fillmore and Atkins 1992). This work, including an invited talk at ACL 1991 (Fillmore and Atkins 1991), influenced the development of other projects in corpus-based lexical semantics (Kipper, Dang, and Palmer 2000; Kipper et al. 2008). Fillmore became interested in this idea that corpus linguistics, lexicography, and lexical semantics could fruitfully be combined (Fillmore 1992) and when he officially retired from UC Berkeley in 1995 he moved to the International Computer Science Institute (ICSI) in Berkeley (although still teaching at UC Berkeley part-time) and began work on the FrameNet project of computational corpus lexicography that combined his early ideas on semantic roles with his late</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Fillmore, Atkins, 1991</marker>
<rawString>Fillmore, Charles J. and Beryl T. Atkins. 1991. Word meaning: Starting where the MRDs stop. Invited talk at ACL 1991.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Charles J Fillmore</author>
<author>Beryl T Atkins</author>
</authors>
<title>Towards a frame-based lexicon: The semantics of RISK and its neighbors.</title>
<date>1992</date>
<booktitle>In Adrienne Lehrer</booktitle>
<pages>75--102</pages>
<editor>and E. Feder Kittay, editors, Frames, Fields, and Contrasts. Lawrence Erlbaum,</editor>
<contexts>
<context position="9160" citStr="Fillmore and Atkins 1992" startWordPosition="1424" endWordPosition="1427">word might come from their drawing on different frames. Fillmore’s linguistic interpretation of frames influenced work in artificial intelligence on knowledge representation like KRL (Bobrow and Winograd 1977), and the perspective-taking aspect of frames had a strong influence on work on framing in linguistics and politics (Lakoff 2010). In 1988 Fillmore taught at the computational linguistics summer school in Pisa run by the late Antonio Zampolli and met the lexicographer Beryl T. Atkins. The two began a collaboration to produce a frame description for the verb risk based on corpus evidence (Fillmore and Atkins 1992). This work, including an invited talk at ACL 1991 (Fillmore and Atkins 1991), influenced the development of other projects in corpus-based lexical semantics (Kipper, Dang, and Palmer 2000; Kipper et al. 2008). Fillmore became interested in this idea that corpus linguistics, lexicography, and lexical semantics could fruitfully be combined (Fillmore 1992) and when he officially retired from UC Berkeley in 1995 he moved to the International Computer Science Institute (ICSI) in Berkeley (although still teaching at UC Berkeley part-time) and began work on the FrameNet project of computational corp</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Fillmore, Atkins, 1992</marker>
<rawString>Fillmore, Charles J. and Beryl T. Atkins. 1992. Towards a frame-based lexicon: The semantics of RISK and its neighbors. In Adrienne Lehrer and E. Feder Kittay, editors, Frames, Fields, and Contrasts. Lawrence Erlbaum, pages 75–102.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Charles J Fillmore</author>
<author>Collin F Baker</author>
</authors>
<title>A frames approach to semantic analysis.</title>
<date>2009</date>
<booktitle>In Bernd Heine and Heiko Narrog, editors, The Oxford Handbook of Linguistic Analysis.</booktitle>
<pages>313--340</pages>
<publisher>Oxford University Press,</publisher>
<contexts>
<context position="10392" citStr="Fillmore and Baker 2009" startWordPosition="1612" endWordPosition="1615">ography that combined his early ideas on semantic roles with his later work on frames and his recent interest in corpus lexicography. The idea of FrameNet was to build a large set of frames, each of which consisted of lists of constitutive roles or “frame elements”: sets of words that evoke the frame, grammatical information expressing how each frame element is realized in the sentence, and semantic relations between frames and between frame elements. Corpora were annotated with the evoking words, frames, and frame elements (Baker, Fillmore, and Lowe 1998; Fillmore, Johnson, and Petruck 2003; Fillmore and Baker 2009). 727 Computational Linguistics Volume 40, Number 3 Over the next 20 years until his death, Fillmore and his students and colleagues, especially under the direction of Collin Baker, proceeded to create the frames and handannotate the corpora. This period of his career was a productive and enjoyable one for Fillmore. In an interview for the ICSI Newsletter, he said “The happiest time of my career has been here at ICSI, where FrameNet has made it possible for me to work with a team of bright young people on a continuing basis doing work that I’ll never lose interest in.” The combination of rich </context>
</contexts>
<marker>Fillmore, Baker, 2009</marker>
<rawString>Fillmore, Charles J. and Collin F. Baker. 2009. A frames approach to semantic analysis. In Bernd Heine and Heiko Narrog, editors, The Oxford Handbook of Linguistic Analysis. Oxford University Press, pages 313–340.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Charles J Fillmore</author>
<author>Christopher R Johnson</author>
<author>Miriam R L Petruck</author>
</authors>
<title>Background to FrameNet. International journal of lexicography,</title>
<date>2003</date>
<pages>16--3</pages>
<marker>Fillmore, Johnson, Petruck, 2003</marker>
<rawString>Fillmore, Charles J., Christopher R. Johnson, and Miriam R. L. Petruck. 2003. Background to FrameNet. International journal of lexicography, 16(3):235–250.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Charles J Fillmore</author>
<author>Paul Kay</author>
<author>Mary Catherine O’Connor</author>
</authors>
<title>Regularity and idiomaticity in grammatical constructions: The case of Let Alone.</title>
<date>1988</date>
<journal>Language,</journal>
<volume>64</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<marker>Fillmore, Kay, O’Connor, 1988</marker>
<rawString>Fillmore, Charles J., Paul Kay, and Mary Catherine O’Connor. 1988. Regularity and idiomaticity in grammatical constructions: The case of Let Alone. Language, 64(3):501–538.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Daniel Gildea</author>
<author>Daniel Jurafsky</author>
</authors>
<title>Automatic labeling of semantic roles.</title>
<date>2000</date>
<booktitle>In ACL-00,</booktitle>
<pages>512--520</pages>
<location>Hong Kong.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="11328" citStr="Gildea and Jurafsky 2000" startWordPosition="1761" endWordPosition="1764">lmore. In an interview for the ICSI Newsletter, he said “The happiest time of my career has been here at ICSI, where FrameNet has made it possible for me to work with a team of bright young people on a continuing basis doing work that I’ll never lose interest in.” The combination of rich linguistic annotation and corpus-based approach instantiated in FrameNet, together with the PropBank semantic-role-labeled corpus created soon afterwards by Martha Palmer and colleagues (Palmer, Kingsbury, and Gildea 2005), led to a revival of automatic approaches to semantic role labeling, first on FrameNet (Gildea and Jurafsky 2000) and then on PropBank data (Gildea and Palmer 2002, inter alia). The problem first addressed in the 1970s by hand-written rules was thus now generally recast as one of supervised machine learning. The resulting plethora of systems for performing automatic semantic role labeling (see the surveys in Palmer, Gildea, and Xue (2010) and M`arquez et al. (2008)) have been applied widely to improve the state of the art in tasks across NLP such as question answering (Shen and Lapata 2007; Surdeanu, Ciaramita, and Zaragoza 2011) and machine translation (Liu and Gildea 2010; Lo et al. 2013). Fillmore’s F</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Gildea, Jurafsky, 2000</marker>
<rawString>Gildea, Daniel and Daniel Jurafsky. 2000. Automatic labeling of semantic roles. In ACL-00, pages 512–520, Hong Kong.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Daniel Gildea</author>
<author>Martha Palmer</author>
</authors>
<title>The necessity of syntactic parsing for predicate argument recognition.</title>
<date>2002</date>
<booktitle>In ACL-02,</booktitle>
<location>Philadelphia, PA.</location>
<contexts>
<context position="11378" citStr="Gildea and Palmer 2002" startWordPosition="1770" endWordPosition="1773">id “The happiest time of my career has been here at ICSI, where FrameNet has made it possible for me to work with a team of bright young people on a continuing basis doing work that I’ll never lose interest in.” The combination of rich linguistic annotation and corpus-based approach instantiated in FrameNet, together with the PropBank semantic-role-labeled corpus created soon afterwards by Martha Palmer and colleagues (Palmer, Kingsbury, and Gildea 2005), led to a revival of automatic approaches to semantic role labeling, first on FrameNet (Gildea and Jurafsky 2000) and then on PropBank data (Gildea and Palmer 2002, inter alia). The problem first addressed in the 1970s by hand-written rules was thus now generally recast as one of supervised machine learning. The resulting plethora of systems for performing automatic semantic role labeling (see the surveys in Palmer, Gildea, and Xue (2010) and M`arquez et al. (2008)) have been applied widely to improve the state of the art in tasks across NLP such as question answering (Shen and Lapata 2007; Surdeanu, Ciaramita, and Zaragoza 2011) and machine translation (Liu and Gildea 2010; Lo et al. 2013). Fillmore’s FrameNet project also led to the development of Fra</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Gildea, Palmer, 2002</marker>
<rawString>Gildea, Daniel and Martha Palmer. 2002. The necessity of syntactic parsing for predicate argument recognition. In ACL-02, Philadelphia, PA.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Erving Goffman</author>
</authors>
<title>Frame analysis: An essay on the organization of experience.</title>
<date>1974</date>
<publisher>Harvard University Press.</publisher>
<contexts>
<context position="6873" citStr="Goffman (1974)" startWordPosition="1044" endWordPosition="1045">are of possibly quite complex situation types, packages of connected expectations, that go by various names—frames, schemas, scenarios, scripts, cultural narratives, memes—and the words in our language are understood with such frames as their presupposed background.” (Fillmore 2012, p. 712) 726 Jurafsky Obituary He described the name as coming from “the pre-transformationalist view of sentence structure as consisting of a frame and a substitution list,” but the word frame seemed to be in the air for a suite of related notions proposed at about the same time by Minsky (1974), Hymes (1974), and Goffman (1974), as well as related notions with other names like scripts (Schank and Abelson 1975) and schemata (Bobrow and Norman 1975) (see Tannen [1979] for a comparison). Fillmore was also influenced by the semantic field theorists and by a visit to the Yale AI lab where he took notice of the lists of slots and fillers used by early information extraction systems like DeJong (1982) and Schank and Abelson (1977). Fillmore’s version of this new idea—more linguistic than other manifestations, focusing on the way that words are associated with frames—was expressed in a series of papers starting in the mid-1</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Goffman, 1974</marker>
<rawString>Goffman, Erving. 1974. Frame analysis: An essay on the organization of experience. Harvard University Press.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Gary G Hendrix</author>
<author>Craig W Thompson</author>
<author>Jonathan Slocum</author>
</authors>
<title>Language processing via canonical verbs and semantic models.</title>
<date>1973</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of IJCAI-73.</booktitle>
<marker>Hendrix, Thompson, Slocum, 1973</marker>
<rawString>Hendrix, Gary G., Craig W. Thompson, and Jonathan Slocum. 1973. Language processing via canonical verbs and semantic models. In Proceedings of IJCAI-73.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Dell Hymes</author>
</authors>
<title>Ways of speaking.</title>
<date>1974</date>
<pages>433--451</pages>
<editor>In Richard Bauman and Joel Sherzer, editors,</editor>
<publisher>Cambridge University Press,</publisher>
<contexts>
<context position="6853" citStr="Hymes (1974)" startWordPosition="1041" endWordPosition="1042">at speakers are aware of possibly quite complex situation types, packages of connected expectations, that go by various names—frames, schemas, scenarios, scripts, cultural narratives, memes—and the words in our language are understood with such frames as their presupposed background.” (Fillmore 2012, p. 712) 726 Jurafsky Obituary He described the name as coming from “the pre-transformationalist view of sentence structure as consisting of a frame and a substitution list,” but the word frame seemed to be in the air for a suite of related notions proposed at about the same time by Minsky (1974), Hymes (1974), and Goffman (1974), as well as related notions with other names like scripts (Schank and Abelson 1975) and schemata (Bobrow and Norman 1975) (see Tannen [1979] for a comparison). Fillmore was also influenced by the semantic field theorists and by a visit to the Yale AI lab where he took notice of the lists of slots and fillers used by early information extraction systems like DeJong (1982) and Schank and Abelson (1977). Fillmore’s version of this new idea—more linguistic than other manifestations, focusing on the way that words are associated with frames—was expressed in a series of papers s</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Hymes, 1974</marker>
<rawString>Hymes, Dell. 1974. Ways of speaking. In Richard Bauman and Joel Sherzer, editors, Explorations in the ethnography of speaking. Cambridge University Press, pages 433–451.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Karin Kipper</author>
<author>Hoa T Dang</author>
<author>Martha Palmer</author>
</authors>
<title>Class-based construction of a verb lexicon. In</title>
<date>2000</date>
<booktitle>AAAI/IAAI,</booktitle>
<pages>691--696</pages>
<marker>Kipper, Dang, Palmer, 2000</marker>
<rawString>Kipper, Karin, Hoa T. Dang, and Martha Palmer. 2000. Class-based construction of a verb lexicon. In AAAI/IAAI, pages 691–696.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Karin Kipper</author>
<author>Anna Korhonen</author>
<author>Neville Ryant</author>
<author>Martha Palmer</author>
</authors>
<title>A large-scale classification of English verbs.</title>
<date>2008</date>
<journal>Language Resources and Evaluation,</journal>
<volume>42</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<contexts>
<context position="9369" citStr="Kipper et al. 2008" startWordPosition="1456" endWordPosition="1459">the perspective-taking aspect of frames had a strong influence on work on framing in linguistics and politics (Lakoff 2010). In 1988 Fillmore taught at the computational linguistics summer school in Pisa run by the late Antonio Zampolli and met the lexicographer Beryl T. Atkins. The two began a collaboration to produce a frame description for the verb risk based on corpus evidence (Fillmore and Atkins 1992). This work, including an invited talk at ACL 1991 (Fillmore and Atkins 1991), influenced the development of other projects in corpus-based lexical semantics (Kipper, Dang, and Palmer 2000; Kipper et al. 2008). Fillmore became interested in this idea that corpus linguistics, lexicography, and lexical semantics could fruitfully be combined (Fillmore 1992) and when he officially retired from UC Berkeley in 1995 he moved to the International Computer Science Institute (ICSI) in Berkeley (although still teaching at UC Berkeley part-time) and began work on the FrameNet project of computational corpus lexicography that combined his early ideas on semantic roles with his later work on frames and his recent interest in corpus lexicography. The idea of FrameNet was to build a large set of frames, each of wh</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Kipper, Korhonen, Ryant, Palmer, 2008</marker>
<rawString>Kipper, Karin, Anna Korhonen, Neville Ryant, and Martha Palmer. 2008. A large-scale classification of English verbs. Language Resources and Evaluation, 42(1):21–40.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>George Lakoff</author>
</authors>
<title>Moral politics: How liberals and conservatives think.</title>
<date>2010</date>
<publisher>University of Chicago Press.</publisher>
<contexts>
<context position="8873" citStr="Lakoff 2010" startWordPosition="1379" endWordPosition="1380">rs to those questions. (Fillmore 1976, p. 29) Fillmore also emphasized the way that frames could represent perspectives on events, such that verbs like sell or pay emphasize different aspects of the same event, or that the differences between alternative senses of the same word might come from their drawing on different frames. Fillmore’s linguistic interpretation of frames influenced work in artificial intelligence on knowledge representation like KRL (Bobrow and Winograd 1977), and the perspective-taking aspect of frames had a strong influence on work on framing in linguistics and politics (Lakoff 2010). In 1988 Fillmore taught at the computational linguistics summer school in Pisa run by the late Antonio Zampolli and met the lexicographer Beryl T. Atkins. The two began a collaboration to produce a frame description for the verb risk based on corpus evidence (Fillmore and Atkins 1992). This work, including an invited talk at ACL 1991 (Fillmore and Atkins 1991), influenced the development of other projects in corpus-based lexical semantics (Kipper, Dang, and Palmer 2000; Kipper et al. 2008). Fillmore became interested in this idea that corpus linguistics, lexicography, and lexical semantics c</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Lakoff, 2010</marker>
<rawString>Lakoff, George. 2010. Moral politics: How liberals and conservatives think. University of Chicago Press.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Joel Lang</author>
<author>Mirella Lapata</author>
</authors>
<title>Similarity-driven semantic role induction via graph partitioning.</title>
<date>2014</date>
<journal>Computational Linguistics,</journal>
<volume>40</volume>
<issue>3</issue>
<contexts>
<context position="12351" citStr="Lang and Lapata 2014" startWordPosition="1921" endWordPosition="1924">e of the art in tasks across NLP such as question answering (Shen and Lapata 2007; Surdeanu, Ciaramita, and Zaragoza 2011) and machine translation (Liu and Gildea 2010; Lo et al. 2013). Fillmore’s FrameNet project also led to the development of FrameNets for many other languages including Spanish, German, Japanese, Portuguese, Italian, and Chinese. And in a perhaps appropriate return to the discovery procedures that first inspired Fillmore, modern work has focused on ways to induce semantic roles from corpora without role annotation (Swier and Stevenson 2004; Chambers and Jurafsky 2009, 2011; Lang and Lapata 2014). In addition to his work in semantics, Fillmore had significant contributions to syntax and pragmatics, including the influential Santa Cruz Lectures on Deixis (Fillmore 1975b) and a long-standing research project in developing Construction Grammar, a theory—or perhaps more accurately family of theories—that represented a grammar as a collection of constructions, pairings of meaning, and form (Fillmore, Kay, and O’Connor 1988). He also contributed to the application of linguistics to other disciplines including cognitive science, education, and law. Ackerman, Kay, and O’Connor (2014) offer mo</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Lang, Lapata, 2014</marker>
<rawString>Lang, Joel and Mirella Lapata. 2014. Similarity-driven semantic role induction via graph partitioning. Computational Linguistics, 40(3):633–669.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Beth Levin</author>
</authors>
<title>Mapping sentences to case frames.</title>
<date>1977</date>
<tech>Technical Report 167,</tech>
<institution>MIT AI Laboratory.</institution>
<contexts>
<context position="5511" citStr="Levin 1977" startWordPosition="833" endWordPosition="834">resentation that could help map from syntactic parse structures to deeper, more fully-specified representations of meaning was quickly adopted in natural language processing, and systems for extracting case frames were created for machine translation (Wilks 1973), question-answering (Hendrix, Thompson, and Slocum 1973), spoken-language understanding (Nash-Webber 1975), and dialogue systems (Bobrow et al. 1977). General-purpose semantic role labelers were developed to map to case representations via ATNs (Simmons 1973) or, from parse trees, by using dictionaries with verb-specific case frames (Levin 1977; Marcus 1980). By 1977 case representation was widely used and taught in natural language processing and artificial intelligence, and was described as a standard component of natural language understanding in the first edition of Winston’s (1977) textbook Artificial Intelligence. In 1971 Fillmore joined the linguistics faculty at the University of California, Berkeley, and by the mid-1970s he began to expand his ideas on case. He arrived at a more general model of semantic representation, one that expressed the background contexts or perspectives by which a word or a case role could be define</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Levin, 1977</marker>
<rawString>Levin, Beth. 1977. Mapping sentences to case frames. Technical Report 167, MIT AI Laboratory. AI Working Paper 143.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Mitchell P Marcus</author>
</authors>
<title>A Theory of Syntactic Recognition for Natural Language.</title>
<date>1980</date>
<publisher>MIT Press.</publisher>
<contexts>
<context position="5525" citStr="Marcus 1980" startWordPosition="835" endWordPosition="836">that could help map from syntactic parse structures to deeper, more fully-specified representations of meaning was quickly adopted in natural language processing, and systems for extracting case frames were created for machine translation (Wilks 1973), question-answering (Hendrix, Thompson, and Slocum 1973), spoken-language understanding (Nash-Webber 1975), and dialogue systems (Bobrow et al. 1977). General-purpose semantic role labelers were developed to map to case representations via ATNs (Simmons 1973) or, from parse trees, by using dictionaries with verb-specific case frames (Levin 1977; Marcus 1980). By 1977 case representation was widely used and taught in natural language processing and artificial intelligence, and was described as a standard component of natural language understanding in the first edition of Winston’s (1977) textbook Artificial Intelligence. In 1971 Fillmore joined the linguistics faculty at the University of California, Berkeley, and by the mid-1970s he began to expand his ideas on case. He arrived at a more general model of semantic representation, one that expressed the background contexts or perspectives by which a word or a case role could be defined. He called t</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Marcus, 1980</marker>
<rawString>Marcus, Mitchell P. 1980. A Theory of Syntactic Recognition for Natural Language. MIT Press.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Lluis M`arquez</author>
<author>Xavier Carreras</author>
<author>Kenneth C Litkowski</author>
<author>Suzanne Stevenson</author>
</authors>
<title>Semantic role labeling: An introduction to the special issue.</title>
<date>2008</date>
<journal>Computational linguistics,</journal>
<volume>34</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<marker>M`arquez, Carreras, Litkowski, Stevenson, 2008</marker>
<rawString>M`arquez, Lluis, Xavier Carreras, Kenneth C Litkowski, and Suzanne Stevenson. 2008. Semantic role labeling: An introduction to the special issue. Computational linguistics, 34(2):145–159.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Marvin Minsky</author>
</authors>
<title>A framework for representing knowledge.</title>
<date>1974</date>
<tech>Technical Report 306,</tech>
<institution>MIT AI Laboratory. Memo 306.</institution>
<contexts>
<context position="6839" citStr="Minsky (1974)" startWordPosition="1039" endWordPosition="1040">semantics is that speakers are aware of possibly quite complex situation types, packages of connected expectations, that go by various names—frames, schemas, scenarios, scripts, cultural narratives, memes—and the words in our language are understood with such frames as their presupposed background.” (Fillmore 2012, p. 712) 726 Jurafsky Obituary He described the name as coming from “the pre-transformationalist view of sentence structure as consisting of a frame and a substitution list,” but the word frame seemed to be in the air for a suite of related notions proposed at about the same time by Minsky (1974), Hymes (1974), and Goffman (1974), as well as related notions with other names like scripts (Schank and Abelson 1975) and schemata (Bobrow and Norman 1975) (see Tannen [1979] for a comparison). Fillmore was also influenced by the semantic field theorists and by a visit to the Yale AI lab where he took notice of the lists of slots and fillers used by early information extraction systems like DeJong (1982) and Schank and Abelson (1977). Fillmore’s version of this new idea—more linguistic than other manifestations, focusing on the way that words are associated with frames—was expressed in a seri</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Minsky, 1974</marker>
<rawString>Minsky, Marvin. 1974. A framework for representing knowledge. Technical Report 306, MIT AI Laboratory. Memo 306.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Bonnie L Nash-Webber</author>
</authors>
<title>The role of semantics in automatic speech understanding.</title>
<date>1975</date>
<pages>351--382</pages>
<editor>In Daniel G. Bobrow and Allan Collins, editors, Representation and Understanding.</editor>
<publisher>Academic Press,</publisher>
<contexts>
<context position="5271" citStr="Nash-Webber 1975" startWordPosition="798" endWordPosition="799">t could be taken on by the arguments of predicates. Verbs would be listed in the lexicon with their ‘case frame’, the list of obligatory (or optional) case arguments. The idea that semantic roles could provide an intermediate level of semantic representation that could help map from syntactic parse structures to deeper, more fully-specified representations of meaning was quickly adopted in natural language processing, and systems for extracting case frames were created for machine translation (Wilks 1973), question-answering (Hendrix, Thompson, and Slocum 1973), spoken-language understanding (Nash-Webber 1975), and dialogue systems (Bobrow et al. 1977). General-purpose semantic role labelers were developed to map to case representations via ATNs (Simmons 1973) or, from parse trees, by using dictionaries with verb-specific case frames (Levin 1977; Marcus 1980). By 1977 case representation was widely used and taught in natural language processing and artificial intelligence, and was described as a standard component of natural language understanding in the first edition of Winston’s (1977) textbook Artificial Intelligence. In 1971 Fillmore joined the linguistics faculty at the University of Californi</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Nash-Webber, 1975</marker>
<rawString>Nash-Webber, Bonnie L. 1975. The role of semantics in automatic speech understanding. In Daniel G. Bobrow and Allan Collins, editors, Representation and Understanding. Academic Press, pages 351–382.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Martha Palmer</author>
<author>Daniel Gildea</author>
<author>Nianwen Xue</author>
</authors>
<date>2010</date>
<booktitle>Semantic role labeling. Synthesis Lectures on Human Language Technologies,</booktitle>
<pages>3--1</pages>
<marker>Palmer, Gildea, Xue, 2010</marker>
<rawString>Palmer, Martha, Daniel Gildea, and Nianwen Xue. 2010. Semantic role labeling. Synthesis Lectures on Human Language Technologies, 3(1):1–103.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Martha Palmer</author>
<author>Paul Kingsbury</author>
<author>Daniel Gildea</author>
</authors>
<title>The proposition bank: An annotated corpus of semantic roles.</title>
<date>2005</date>
<journal>Computational Linguistics,</journal>
<volume>31</volume>
<issue>1</issue>
<marker>Palmer, Kingsbury, Gildea, 2005</marker>
<rawString>Palmer, Martha, Paul Kingsbury, and Daniel Gildea. 2005. The proposition bank: An annotated corpus of semantic roles. Computational Linguistics, 31(1):71–106.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Roger C Schank</author>
<author>Robert P Abelson</author>
</authors>
<title>Scripts, plans, and knowledge.</title>
<date>1975</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of IJCAI-75,</booktitle>
<pages>151--157</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="6957" citStr="Schank and Abelson 1975" startWordPosition="1056" endWordPosition="1059">tations, that go by various names—frames, schemas, scenarios, scripts, cultural narratives, memes—and the words in our language are understood with such frames as their presupposed background.” (Fillmore 2012, p. 712) 726 Jurafsky Obituary He described the name as coming from “the pre-transformationalist view of sentence structure as consisting of a frame and a substitution list,” but the word frame seemed to be in the air for a suite of related notions proposed at about the same time by Minsky (1974), Hymes (1974), and Goffman (1974), as well as related notions with other names like scripts (Schank and Abelson 1975) and schemata (Bobrow and Norman 1975) (see Tannen [1979] for a comparison). Fillmore was also influenced by the semantic field theorists and by a visit to the Yale AI lab where he took notice of the lists of slots and fillers used by early information extraction systems like DeJong (1982) and Schank and Abelson (1977). Fillmore’s version of this new idea—more linguistic than other manifestations, focusing on the way that words are associated with frames—was expressed in a series of papers starting in the mid-1970’s (Fillmore 1975a, 1976, 1977b, 1982, 1985). His motivating example was the Comm</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Schank, Abelson, 1975</marker>
<rawString>Schank, Roger C. and Robert P. Abelson. 1975. Scripts, plans, and knowledge. In Proceedings of IJCAI-75, pages 151–157.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Roger C Schank</author>
<author>Robert P Abelson</author>
</authors>
<title>Scripts, Plans, Goals and Understanding. Lawrence Erlbaum.</title>
<date>1977</date>
<contexts>
<context position="7277" citStr="Schank and Abelson (1977)" startWordPosition="1111" endWordPosition="1114">nce structure as consisting of a frame and a substitution list,” but the word frame seemed to be in the air for a suite of related notions proposed at about the same time by Minsky (1974), Hymes (1974), and Goffman (1974), as well as related notions with other names like scripts (Schank and Abelson 1975) and schemata (Bobrow and Norman 1975) (see Tannen [1979] for a comparison). Fillmore was also influenced by the semantic field theorists and by a visit to the Yale AI lab where he took notice of the lists of slots and fillers used by early information extraction systems like DeJong (1982) and Schank and Abelson (1977). Fillmore’s version of this new idea—more linguistic than other manifestations, focusing on the way that words are associated with frames—was expressed in a series of papers starting in the mid-1970’s (Fillmore 1975a, 1976, 1977b, 1982, 1985). His motivating example was the Commercial Event frame, in which a seller sells goods to a buyer, the buyer thus buying the goods that cost a certain amount by paying a price charged by the seller. The definition of each of these verbs (buy, sell, cost, pay, charge), is interrelated by virtue of their joint association with a single kind of event or scen</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Schank, Abelson, 1977</marker>
<rawString>Schank, Roger C. and Robert P. Abelson. 1977. Scripts, Plans, Goals and Understanding. Lawrence Erlbaum.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Dan Shen</author>
<author>Mirella Lapata</author>
</authors>
<title>Using semantic roles to improve question answering.</title>
<date>2007</date>
<booktitle>In EMNLP-CoNLL,</booktitle>
<pages>12--21</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="11811" citStr="Shen and Lapata 2007" startWordPosition="1841" endWordPosition="1844">sbury, and Gildea 2005), led to a revival of automatic approaches to semantic role labeling, first on FrameNet (Gildea and Jurafsky 2000) and then on PropBank data (Gildea and Palmer 2002, inter alia). The problem first addressed in the 1970s by hand-written rules was thus now generally recast as one of supervised machine learning. The resulting plethora of systems for performing automatic semantic role labeling (see the surveys in Palmer, Gildea, and Xue (2010) and M`arquez et al. (2008)) have been applied widely to improve the state of the art in tasks across NLP such as question answering (Shen and Lapata 2007; Surdeanu, Ciaramita, and Zaragoza 2011) and machine translation (Liu and Gildea 2010; Lo et al. 2013). Fillmore’s FrameNet project also led to the development of FrameNets for many other languages including Spanish, German, Japanese, Portuguese, Italian, and Chinese. And in a perhaps appropriate return to the discovery procedures that first inspired Fillmore, modern work has focused on ways to induce semantic roles from corpora without role annotation (Swier and Stevenson 2004; Chambers and Jurafsky 2009, 2011; Lang and Lapata 2014). In addition to his work in semantics, Fillmore had signifi</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Shen, Lapata, 2007</marker>
<rawString>Shen, Dan and Mirella Lapata. 2007. Using semantic roles to improve question answering. In EMNLP-CoNLL, pages 12–21.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Robert F Simmons</author>
</authors>
<title>Semantic networks: Their computation and use for understanding English sentences.</title>
<date>1973</date>
<booktitle>Computer Models of Thought and Language. W.H. Freeman and Co.,</booktitle>
<pages>61--113</pages>
<editor>In Roger C. Schank and Kenneth Mark Colby, editors,</editor>
<contexts>
<context position="5424" citStr="Simmons 1973" startWordPosition="820" endWordPosition="821">rguments. The idea that semantic roles could provide an intermediate level of semantic representation that could help map from syntactic parse structures to deeper, more fully-specified representations of meaning was quickly adopted in natural language processing, and systems for extracting case frames were created for machine translation (Wilks 1973), question-answering (Hendrix, Thompson, and Slocum 1973), spoken-language understanding (Nash-Webber 1975), and dialogue systems (Bobrow et al. 1977). General-purpose semantic role labelers were developed to map to case representations via ATNs (Simmons 1973) or, from parse trees, by using dictionaries with verb-specific case frames (Levin 1977; Marcus 1980). By 1977 case representation was widely used and taught in natural language processing and artificial intelligence, and was described as a standard component of natural language understanding in the first edition of Winston’s (1977) textbook Artificial Intelligence. In 1971 Fillmore joined the linguistics faculty at the University of California, Berkeley, and by the mid-1970s he began to expand his ideas on case. He arrived at a more general model of semantic representation, one that expressed</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Simmons, 1973</marker>
<rawString>Simmons, Robert F. 1973. Semantic networks: Their computation and use for understanding English sentences. In Roger C. Schank and Kenneth Mark Colby, editors, Computer Models of Thought and Language. W.H. Freeman and Co., pages 61–113.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Mihai Surdeanu</author>
<author>Massimiliano Ciaramita</author>
<author>Hugo Zaragoza</author>
</authors>
<title>Learning to rank answers to non-factoid questions from web collections.</title>
<date>2011</date>
<journal>Computational Linguistics,</journal>
<volume>37</volume>
<issue>2</issue>
<marker>Surdeanu, Ciaramita, Zaragoza, 2011</marker>
<rawString>Surdeanu, Mihai, Massimiliano Ciaramita, and Hugo Zaragoza. 2011. Learning to rank answers to non-factoid questions from web collections. Computational Linguistics, 37(2):351–383.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>R Swier</author>
<author>S Stevenson</author>
</authors>
<title>Unsupervised semantic role labelling.</title>
<date>2004</date>
<booktitle>In EMNLP</booktitle>
<pages>95--102</pages>
<contexts>
<context position="12294" citStr="Swier and Stevenson 2004" startWordPosition="1912" endWordPosition="1915"> et al. (2008)) have been applied widely to improve the state of the art in tasks across NLP such as question answering (Shen and Lapata 2007; Surdeanu, Ciaramita, and Zaragoza 2011) and machine translation (Liu and Gildea 2010; Lo et al. 2013). Fillmore’s FrameNet project also led to the development of FrameNets for many other languages including Spanish, German, Japanese, Portuguese, Italian, and Chinese. And in a perhaps appropriate return to the discovery procedures that first inspired Fillmore, modern work has focused on ways to induce semantic roles from corpora without role annotation (Swier and Stevenson 2004; Chambers and Jurafsky 2009, 2011; Lang and Lapata 2014). In addition to his work in semantics, Fillmore had significant contributions to syntax and pragmatics, including the influential Santa Cruz Lectures on Deixis (Fillmore 1975b) and a long-standing research project in developing Construction Grammar, a theory—or perhaps more accurately family of theories—that represented a grammar as a collection of constructions, pairings of meaning, and form (Fillmore, Kay, and O’Connor 1988). He also contributed to the application of linguistics to other disciplines including cognitive science, educat</context>
</contexts>
<marker>Swier, Stevenson, 2004</marker>
<rawString>Swier, R. and S. Stevenson. 2004. Unsupervised semantic role labelling. In EMNLP 2004, pages 95–102.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Deborah Tannen</author>
</authors>
<title>What’s in a frame? Surface evidence for underlying expectations. In</title>
<date>1979</date>
<booktitle>New Directions in Discourse Processing. Ablex,</booktitle>
<pages>137--181</pages>
<editor>Roy Freedle, editor,</editor>
<marker>Tannen, 1979</marker>
<rawString>Tannen, Deborah. 1979. What’s in a frame? Surface evidence for underlying expectations. In Roy Freedle, editor, New Directions in Discourse Processing. Ablex, pages 137–181.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Lucien Tesni`ere</author>
</authors>
<title>El´ements de Syntaxe Structurale. Librairie C. Klincksieck,</title>
<date>1959</date>
<location>Paris.</location>
<marker>Tesni`ere, 1959</marker>
<rawString>Tesni`ere, Lucien. 1959. ´El´ements de Syntaxe Structurale. Librairie C. Klincksieck, Paris.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>Yorick 1973 Wilks</author>
</authors>
<title>An artificial intelligence approach to machine translation.</title>
<booktitle>Computer Models of Thought</booktitle>
<pages>114--151</pages>
<editor>In Roger C. Schank and Kenneth Mark Colby, editors,</editor>
<marker>Wilks, </marker>
<rawString>Wilks, Yorick.1973. An artificial intelligence approach to machine translation. In Roger C. Schank and Kenneth Mark Colby, editors, Computer Models of Thought and Language. W.H. Freeman, pages 114–151.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Patrick H Winston</author>
</authors>
<title>Artificial Intelligence.</title>
<date>1977</date>
<publisher>Addison Wesley.</publisher>
<marker>Winston, 1977</marker>
<rawString>Winston, Patrick H. 1977. Artificial Intelligence. Addison Wesley.</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>