<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="SectLabel" version="110505">
<variant no="0" confidence="0.008489">
<title confidence="0.803552">
Book Reviews
Semantic Relations Between Nominals
</title>
<author confidence="0.812507">
Vivi Nastase1, Preslav Nakov2, Diarmuid O´ S´eaghdha3, and Stan Szpakowicz4
</author>
<reference confidence="0.1969098">
(1FBK, Trento; 2QCRI, Qatar Foundation; 3University of Cambridge; 4University
of Ottawa)
Morgan &amp; Claypool (Synthesis Lectures on Human Language Technologies, edited by
Graeme Hirst, volume 19), 2013, xvii+124 pp; paperbound, ISBN 978-1-60845-979-7,
$40.00; e-book, ISBN 978-1-60845-980-3, $30.00 or by subscription
</reference>
<figure confidence="0.713508333333333">
Reviewed by
Lucy Vanderwende
Microsoft Research
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.999636571428571">
Understanding noun compounds is the challenge that drew me to study computational
linguistics. Think about how just two words, side by side, evoke a whole story: cacao
seeds evokes the tree on which the cacao seeds grow, and to understand cacao powder
we need to also imagine the seeds of the cacao tree that are crushed to powder. What
conjures up these concepts of tree and grow, and seeds and crush, which are not explicitly
present in the written word but are essential for our complete understanding of the
compounds? The mechanisms by which we make sense of noun compounds can
illuminate how we understand language more generally. And because the human mind
is so wily as to provide interpretations even when we do not ask it to, I have always
found it useful to study these phenomena of language on the computer, because the
computer surely does not (yet) have the type of knowledge that must be brought to bear
on the problem. If you find these phenomena equally intriguing and puzzling, then
you will find this book by Nastase, Nakov, O´ S´eaghdga, and Szpakowicz a wonderful
summary of past research efforts and a good introduction to the current methods for
analyzing semantic relations.
To be clear, this book is not only about noun compounds, but explores all types of
relations that can hold between what is expressed linguistically as nominal. Such nomi-
nals include entities (e.g., Godiva, Belgium) as well as nominals that refer to events (culti-
vation, roasting) and nominals with complex structure (delicious milk chocolate).1 In doing
so, describing the different semantic relations between chocolate in the 20th century and
chocolate in Belgium is within the scope of this book. This is a wise choice as there are then
some linguistic cues that will help define and narrow the types of semantic relations
(e.g., the prepositions above). Noun compounds are degenerate in the sense that there
are few if any overt linguistic cues as to the semantic relations between the nominals.
The book has three main chapters: an introduction to the various relation schemas
that have been used in the past to describe the nominal relations, an overview of meth-
ods for extracting semantic relations with supervision, and an overview of methods
for extracting semantic relations with little or no supervision. The preface promises a
</bodyText>
<footnote confidence="0.5206514">
1 Examples are drawn from the Introduction of Semantic Relations Between Nominals. The examples with
reference to cacao and chocolate make for a sweet introduction.
doi:10.1162/COLI r 00187
© 2014 Association for Computational Linguistics
Computational Linguistics Volume 40, Number 2
</footnote>
<bodyText confidence="0.99961123255814">
very brief chapter summing up the lessons learned and makes good on that promise as
Chapter 5 is very brief indeed.
It was a pleasure to be reminded of de Saussure’s characterization of the two foun-
dational types of relations: syntagmatic relations, which hold between words present in
the text, and paradigmatic relations, the associations of the text words to the broader
context (i.e., to words not in the text). The syntagmatic relations are then introduced
to us as the predicates in logic, taking one or more nominal arguments, or as the
labeled arcs that connect concepts, making the notion of semantic relations accessible to
people with differing backgrounds in computer science. What follows is “a menagerie
of relation schemata,” Section 2.2, where approximately eight different relation sets are
inventoried, an admirably comprehensive overview of the past decades of research in
this area.2 Whereas the authors acknowledge that from the NLP perspective, “[the aim]
is to select the most useful representation for a particular application” (page 12), no
examples are provided that demonstrate the impact of selecting one representation over
another. Thus, although the overview is of great value to a reader wishing to familiarize
themselves with the topic, the advanced reader will be left with the impression that the
authors do not know how to select from among the relation sets either.
When data labeled with semantic relations is available, supervised models can be
used. This scenario is explored in detail in Chapter 3. An overview of the data resources
available is followed by a brief discussion of the types of features often employed in
learning. This, and the next chapter, are clearly intended for readers with some famil-
iarity with machine learning who may not be as familiar with the full sweep of models
available. In particular, the organization of the material provides good entry points
where the reader can find plentiful references if they are curious about the approach.
The summary sections are very good reviews and would suffice to get a general idea
of how the task of extracting semantic relations can be approached. In particular, in
Section 3.5, the authors provide useful points to consider for navigating the myriad
possibilities of models and resources.
When no labeled data is available, a wider set of paradigms for extracting semantic
relations needs to be explored (in Chapter 4). These range from manually authored pat-
terns (Hearst 1992, inter alia) for extracting predetermined relation types, to identifying
novel relations with open relation extraction. OpenIE learns relations as expressed by
verbs or prepositions using sophisticated algorithms to determine when the verbs or
prepositions express the same or different relation type (Lin and Pantel 2001, inter alia).
These paradigms are well described in this chapter and, once again, the authors provide
plentiful information that invites the reader to go into greater depth wherever their in-
terests lie, with the odd exception that the authors steer the reader away from any ap-
proach that uses parsing, claiming that “deeper processing (e.g., syntactic parsing) is
altogether infeasible on a Web scale” (page 79, passim). We know that Google is pars-
ing the Web already (Petrov and McDonald 2012) and parsing is becoming orders-of-
magnitude faster (Canny et al., 2013), so the reader would be well advised to stay open to
the possibilities. Parsing was demonstrated to be crucial for extracting higher-order se-
mantic relations such as Location and Purpose (Montemagni and Vanderwende 1992).3
</bodyText>
<footnote confidence="0.986237166666667">
2 Readers may also wish to know about the project NomBank (Meyers et al., 2004), which is not included
in this chapter.
3 Coincidentally, this paper was presented in the same session as Marti Hearst’s paper at COLING 1992;
note the page numbers in the References. At the time, however, very few institutions had access to a
broad-coverage parser, but I suspect that parsing and features derived from parsing will soon become
commonplace.
</footnote>
<page confidence="0.992024">
516
</page>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.9904">
Book Reviews
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999807875">
In the end, the authors note that “relation extraction is not an end task, but its
purpose is to build resources to be used by other NLP and AI applications” (page 80).
And the application is what will determine which set of relations is appropriate, which
will in turn determine the best approach for extracting such semantic relations, whether
through supervised or unsupervised means. This book provides a wonderfully com-
prehensive overview of the choices that a practitioner makes today. I wish there was a
last chapter cataloguing NLP and AI applications that use the semantic relations, but
perhaps I can look forward to that in the next edition.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.993329" genericHeader="abstract">
References
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.999207707317073">
Canny, J., D. Hall, and D. Klein. 2013.
A multi-teraflop constituency parser using
GPUs. In Proceedings of the 2013 Conference
on Empirical Methods in Natural Language
Processing, pages 1,898–1,907, Seattle, WA.
Hearst, Marti 1992. Automatic acquisition
of hyponyms from large text corpora.
In Proceedings of the 15th International
Conference on Computational Linguistics
(COLING), pages 539–545, Nantes.
Lin, Dekang and Patrick Pantel. 2001.
Discovery of inference rules for
question-answering. Natural Language
Engineering, 7(4):343–360.
Meyers, A., R. Reeves, C. Macleod,
R. Szekely, V. Zielinska, B. Young, and
R. Grishman. 2004. The NomBank Project:
An interim report. In Proceedings of the
HLT-NAACL 2004 Workshop: Frontiers in
Corpus Annotation.
Montemagni, Simonetta and Lucy
Vanderwende. 1992. Structural patterns
vs. string patterns for extracting
semantic information from dictionaries.
In Proceedings of the Fourteenth International
Conference on Computational Linguistics
(COLING), pages 546–552, Nantes.
Petrov, Slav and Ryan McDonald. 2012.
Overview of the 2012 Shared Task on
Parsing the Web. In Notes of the First
Workshop on Syntactic Analysis of
Non-Canonical Language (SANCL),
Montreal.
This book review was edited by Pierre Isabelle.
Lucy Vanderwende is a Senior Researcher at Microsoft Corporation. Her thesis is titled “The
Analysis of Noun Sequences using Semantic Information extracted from On-Line Dictionaries”
(1996, Georgetown University). The research was continued in the MindNet project (Richardson,
Dolan and Vanderwende 1998). She continues to be fascinated by semantic relations and
works in the area of information extraction from biomedical text and on probabilistic frame-
induction (Cheung, Poon and Vanderwende 2013). Vanderwende’s address is: One Microsoft
Way, Redmond, WA 98052 USA; e-mail: lucyv@microsoft.com.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.996866">
517
</page>
</variant>
</algorithm>
<algorithm name="ParsHed" version="110505">
<variant no="0" confidence="0.085268">
<title confidence="0.99396">Book Reviews Semantic Relations Between Nominals</title>
<author confidence="0.932996">Preslav Diarmuid O´and Stan</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.751323">Trento; Qatar Foundation; of Cambridge; of Ottawa</affiliation>
<author confidence="0.8084205">xvii pp</author>
<author confidence="0.8084205">ISBN paperbound</author>
<keyword confidence="0.309139">40.00; e-book, ISBN 978-1-60845-980-3, $30.00 or by subscription</keyword>
<note confidence="0.91274">Reviewed by</note>
<author confidence="0.990921">Lucy Vanderwende</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.990693">Microsoft Research</affiliation>
<abstract confidence="0.972319846153846">Understanding noun compounds is the challenge that drew me to study computational Think about how just two words, side by side, evoke a whole story: the tree on which the cacao seeds grow, and to understand powder we need to also imagine the seeds of the cacao tree that are crushed to powder. What up these concepts of and which are not explicitly present in the written word but are essential for our complete understanding of the compounds? The mechanisms by which we make sense of noun compounds can illuminate how we understand language more generally. And because the human mind is so wily as to provide interpretations even when we do not ask it to, I have always found it useful to study these phenomena of language on the computer, because the computer surely does not (yet) have the type of knowledge that must be brought to bear on the problem. If you find these phenomena equally intriguing and puzzling, then you will find this book by Nastase, Nakov, O´ S´eaghdga, and Szpakowicz a wonderful</abstract>
</variant>
</algorithm>
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="false">
<title>2QCRI, Qatar Foundation; 3University of Cambridge; 4University of Ottawa</title>
<marker></marker>
<rawString>(1FBK, Trento; 2QCRI, Qatar Foundation; 3University of Cambridge; 4University of Ottawa)</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<authors>
<author>Morgan</author>
<author>Claypool</author>
</authors>
<title>Synthesis Lectures on Human Language Technologies, edited by Graeme Hirst,</title>
<volume>19</volume>
<note>pp; paperbound, ISBN 978-1-60845-979-7, $40.00; e-book, ISBN 978-1-60845-980-3, $30.00 or by subscription</note>
<marker>Morgan, Claypool, </marker>
<rawString>Morgan &amp; Claypool (Synthesis Lectures on Human Language Technologies, edited by Graeme Hirst, volume 19), 2013, xvii+124 pp; paperbound, ISBN 978-1-60845-979-7, $40.00; e-book, ISBN 978-1-60845-980-3, $30.00 or by subscription</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>J Canny</author>
<author>D Hall</author>
<author>D Klein</author>
</authors>
<title>A multi-teraflop constituency parser using GPUs.</title>
<date>2013</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 2013 Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing,</booktitle>
<pages>1--898</pages>
<location>Seattle, WA.</location>
<marker>Canny, Hall, Klein, 2013</marker>
<rawString>Canny, J., D. Hall, and D. Klein. 2013. A multi-teraflop constituency parser using GPUs. In Proceedings of the 2013 Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing, pages 1,898–1,907, Seattle, WA.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Marti Hearst</author>
</authors>
<title>Automatic acquisition of hyponyms from large text corpora.</title>
<date>1992</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the 15th International Conference on Computational Linguistics (COLING),</booktitle>
<pages>539--545</pages>
<location>Nantes.</location>
<marker>Hearst, 1992</marker>
<rawString>Hearst, Marti 1992. Automatic acquisition of hyponyms from large text corpora. In Proceedings of the 15th International Conference on Computational Linguistics (COLING), pages 539–545, Nantes.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Dekang Lin</author>
<author>Patrick Pantel</author>
</authors>
<title>Discovery of inference rules for question-answering.</title>
<date>2001</date>
<journal>Natural Language Engineering,</journal>
<volume>7</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<marker>Lin, Pantel, 2001</marker>
<rawString>Lin, Dekang and Patrick Pantel. 2001. Discovery of inference rules for question-answering. Natural Language Engineering, 7(4):343–360.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>A Meyers</author>
<author>R Reeves</author>
<author>C Macleod</author>
<author>R Szekely</author>
<author>V Zielinska</author>
<author>B Young</author>
<author>R Grishman</author>
</authors>
<title>The NomBank Project: An interim report.</title>
<date>2004</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the HLT-NAACL</booktitle>
<marker>Meyers, Reeves, Macleod, Szekely, Zielinska, Young, Grishman, 2004</marker>
<rawString>Meyers, A., R. Reeves, C. Macleod, R. Szekely, V. Zielinska, B. Young, and R. Grishman. 2004. The NomBank Project: An interim report. In Proceedings of the HLT-NAACL 2004 Workshop: Frontiers in Corpus Annotation.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Simonetta Montemagni</author>
<author>Lucy Vanderwende</author>
</authors>
<title>Structural patterns vs. string patterns for extracting semantic information from dictionaries.</title>
<date>1992</date>
<booktitle>In Proceedings of the Fourteenth International Conference on Computational Linguistics (COLING),</booktitle>
<pages>546--552</pages>
<location>Nantes.</location>
<marker>Montemagni, Vanderwende, 1992</marker>
<rawString>Montemagni, Simonetta and Lucy Vanderwende. 1992. Structural patterns vs. string patterns for extracting semantic information from dictionaries. In Proceedings of the Fourteenth International Conference on Computational Linguistics (COLING), pages 546–552, Nantes.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>Slav Petrov</author>
<author>Ryan McDonald</author>
</authors>
<title>Overview of the 2012 Shared Task on Parsing the Web.</title>
<date>2012</date>
<booktitle>In Notes of the First Workshop on Syntactic Analysis of Non-Canonical Language (SANCL),</booktitle>
<location>Montreal.</location>
<marker>Petrov, McDonald, 2012</marker>
<rawString>Petrov, Slav and Ryan McDonald. 2012. Overview of the 2012 Shared Task on Parsing the Web. In Notes of the First Workshop on Syntactic Analysis of Non-Canonical Language (SANCL), Montreal.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="false">
<title>This book review was edited by Pierre Isabelle. Lucy Vanderwende is a Senior Researcher at Microsoft Corporation. Her thesis is titled “The Analysis of Noun Sequences using Semantic Information extracted from On-Line Dictionaries”</title>
<date>1996</date>
<institution>Georgetown University).</institution>
<location>Redmond, WA 98052 USA;</location>
<note>e-mail: lucyv@microsoft.com.</note>
<marker>1996</marker>
<rawString>This book review was edited by Pierre Isabelle. Lucy Vanderwende is a Senior Researcher at Microsoft Corporation. Her thesis is titled “The Analysis of Noun Sequences using Semantic Information extracted from On-Line Dictionaries” (1996, Georgetown University). The research was continued in the MindNet project (Richardson, Dolan and Vanderwende 1998). She continues to be fascinated by semantic relations and works in the area of information extraction from biomedical text and on probabilistic frameinduction (Cheung, Poon and Vanderwende 2013). Vanderwende’s address is: One Microsoft Way, Redmond, WA 98052 USA; e-mail: lucyv@microsoft.com.</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>